<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<add>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/huber/publications.html</field>
<field name="title">Lehrstuhl Huber</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/huber/publications.html</field>
<field name="content">Lehrstuhl Huber Lehrstuhl Huber Internal | Search | About      Home  Events  People  Teaching  Research  Publications Journal articles, review articles and book chapters Talks  Contact         Department of Physics &amp;gt; LS Huber &amp;gt; AG Huber &amp;gt; Publications Journal articles, review articles and book chapters Michael Porer, Jean-Michel M?nard, and Rupert Huber Shot noise reduced terahertz detection via spectrally postfiltered electro-optic sampling Optics Letters 39, 2435-2438 (2014) H. Dachraoui, G. van der Laan, N. Müller, T. Milde, M. Porer, R. Manzke, R. Huber, S. Fritzsche and U. Heinzmann Mapping spin-orbit activated interchannel coupling EPL 106, 13001 (2014) O. Schubert, M. Hohenleutner, F. Langer, B. Urbanek, C. Lange, U. Huttner, D. Golde, T. Meier, M. Kira, S. W. Koch and R. Huber Sub-cycle control of terahertz high-harmonic generation by dynamical Bloch oscillations Nature Photon. 8, 119-123 (2014) T. L. Cocker and R. Huber A new twist on terahertz pulses Nature Photon. 7, 678-679 (2013) A. Pashkin, A. Sell, T. Kampfrath und R. Huber Electric and magnetic terahertz nonlinearities resolved on the sub-cycle scale New J. Phys. 15, 065003 (2013) O. Schubert, M. Eisele, V. Crozatier, N. Forget, D. Kaplan, and R. Huber Rapid-scan acousto-optical delay line with 34 kHz scan rate and 15 attosecond precision Optics Letters 38, 2907 (2013) P. Olbrich, C. Drexler, L. E. Golub, S. N. Danilov, V. A. Shalygin, R. Yakimova, S. Lara-Avila, S. Kubatkin, B. Redlich, R. Huber, and S.D. Ganichev Reststrahl band-assisted photocurrents in epitaxial graphene layers Phys. Rev. B 88, 245425 (2013) A. Pashkin, F. Junginger, B. Mayer, C. Schmidt, O. Schubert, D. Brida, R. Huber, and A. Leitenstorfer Quantum Physics with Ultrabroadband and Intense Terahertz Pulses IEEE Journal of Selected Topics in Quantum Electronics 19, 8401608 (2013) F. Junginger, B. Mayer, C. Schmidt, O. Schubert, S. M?hrlein, A. Leitenstorfer, R. Huber, and A. Pashkin Non-perturbative interband response of a bulk InSb semiconductor driven off-resonantly by terahertz electromagnetic few-cycle pulses Phys. Rev. Lett. 109, 147403 (2012) K. W. Kim, A. Pashkin, H. Sch?fer, M. Beyer, M. Porer, T. Wolf, C. Bernhard, J. Demsar, R. Huber, and A. Leitenstorfer Ultrafast transient generation of spin-density-wave order in the normal state of BaFe2As2 driven by coherent lattice vibrations Nature Materials 11, 497 (2012) M. Porer, J.-M. Menard, A. Leitenstorfer, R. Huber, R. Degl'Innocenti, S. Zanotto, G. Biasiol, L. Sorba, and A. Tredicucci, Nonadiabatic Splitting of a Photonic Bandstructure: Ultrastrong Light-matter Coupling and Slow-down of Light Physical Review B 85, 081302(R) (2012) R. Huber Photonics: Terahertz collisions Nature 483, 545-546 (2012) O. Schubert, C. Riek, F. Junginger, A. Sell, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Ultrashort pulse characterization with a terahertz streak camera Optics Letters 36, 4458 (2011) R. Huber, A. A. Anappara, G. Günter, A. Sell, S. De Liberato, C. Ciuti, G. Biasiol, L. Sorba, A. Tredicucci, and A. Leitenstorfer Switching ultrastrong light-matter coupling on a subcycle scale J. Appl. Phys. 109, 102418 (2011) A. Pashkin, C.Kübler, H. Ehrke, R. Lopez, A. Halabica, R. F. Haglund, Jr., R. Huber, and A. Leitenstorfer Ultrafast Insulator-Metal Phase Transition in VO2 Studied by Multiterahertz Spectroscopy Physical Review B 83, 195120 (2011) G. Krauss, D. Fehrenbacher, D. Brida, C. Riek, A. Sell, R. Huber und A. Leitenstorfer All-passive phase locking of a compact Er:fiber laser system Opt. Lett. 36, 540 (2011) G. Klatt, B. Surrer, D. Stephan, O. Schubert, M. Fischer, J. Faist, A. Leitenstorfer, R. Huber, and T. Dekorsy Photo-Dember terahertz emitter excited with an Er:fiber laser Appl. Phys. Lett. 98, 021114 (2011) T. Kampfrath, A. Sell, G. Klatt, A. Pashkin, S. Mährlein, T. Dekorsy, M. Wolf, M. Fiebig, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Coherent terahertz control of antiferromagnetic spin waves Nature Photonics 5, 31 (2011) This work has been featured in a News and Views Article by Junichiro Kono Spintronics: Coherent terahertz control Nature Photonics 5, 5 (2011) F. Junginger, A. Sell, O. Schubert, B. Mayer, D. Brida, M. Marangoni, G. Cerullo, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Single-cycle multiterahertz transients with peak fields above 10 MV/cm Optics Letters 35, 2645 (2010) A. Pashkin, M. Porer, M. Beyer, K. W. Kim, A. Dubroka, C. Bernhard, X. Yao, Y. Dagan, R. Hackl, A. Erb, J. Demsar, R. Huber, and A. Leitenstorfer Femtosecond Response of Quasiparticles and Phonons in Superconducting YBCO Studied by Wideband Terahertz Spectroscopy Physical Review Letters 105, 067001 (2010) This work has been featured in a Viewpoint in Physics by U. Bovensiepen A real-time view of elementary excitations in high-Tc superconductors Viewpoint in Physics 3, 63 (2010) G. Krauss, S. Lohss, T. Hanke, A. Sell, S. Eggert, R. Huber, and A. Leitenstorfer Synthesis of a single cycle of light with compact erbium-doped fibre technology Nature Photonics 4, 33 (2010) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science G. Günter, A. A. Anappara, J. Hees, A. Sell, G. Biasiol, L. Sorba, S. De Liberato, C. Ciuti, A. Tredicucci, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Sub-cycle switch-on of ultrastrong light-matter interaction Nature 458, 178 (2009) This work has been featured in a News and Views Article by Claire Gmachl Quantum optoelectronics: Swift switch of the strong Nature 458, 157 (2009) A. Sell, G. Krauss, R. Scheu, R. Huber, and A. Leitenstorfer 8-fs pulses from a compact Er:fiber system: quantitative modelling and experimental implementation Optics Express 17, 1070 (2009) F. Adler, F. Sotier, D. Träutlein, A. Sell, K. Moutzouris, R. Huber, and A. Leitenstorfer Widely Tunable Femtosecond Lasers and Applications in M. Kimura (ed.), Fiber Lasers: Research, Technology and Applications, Nova Science Publishers (2009) A. Sell, R. Scheu, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Field-resolved detection of phase-locked infrared transients tunable from 55 to 107 THz from an Er:fiber laser system Applied Physics Letters 93, 251107 (2008) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science A. Sell, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Phase-locked generation and field-resolved detection of widely tunable terahertz pulses with amplitudes exceeding 100 MV/cm Optics Letters 33, 2767 (2008) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science S. Leinß, T. Kampfrath, K. v. Volkmann, M. Wolf, J. T. Steiner, M. Kira, S. W. Koch, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Terahertz coherent control of optically dark paraexcitons in Cu2O Physical Review Letters 101, 246401 (2008) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science R. Huber, B. A. Schmid, R. A. Kaindl, and D. S. Chemla Femtosecond THz Studies of Intra-Excitonic Transitions physica status solidi (b) 245, 1041 (2008) F. Adler, A. Sell, F. Sotier, R. Huber, and A. Leitenstorfer Attosecond relative timing jitter and 13 fs tunable pulses from a two-branch femtosecond Er:fiber laser Optics Letters 32, 3504 (2007) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science C. Kübler, H. Ehrke, R. Huber, R. Lopez, A. Halabica, R. F. Haglund, Jr., and A. Leitenstorfer Coherent Structural Dynamics and Electronic Correlations during an Ultrafast Insulator-to-Metal Phase Transition in VO2 Physical Review Letters 99, 116401 (2007) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Nanoscale Science and Technology T. Zentgraf, R. Huber, N. C. Nielsen, D. S. Chemla, and R. Kaindl Ultrabroadband 50-130 THz pulses generated via phase-matched difference frequency mixing in LiIO3 Optics Express 15, 5775 (2007) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science R. Huber, B. A. Schmid, Y.-R. Shen, D. S. Chemla, R. A. Kaindl Stimulated THz Emission from Internal Exciton Transitions in Cu2O Physical Review Letters 96, 017402 (2006) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science J. van Tilborg, C. B. Schroeder, C. V. Filip. Cs. Toth, C. G. R. Geddes, G. Fubiani, R. Huber, R. A. Kaindl, E. Esarey, and W. P. Leemans Temporal Characterization of Femtosecond Laser-Plasma-Accelerated Electron Bunches using THz Radiation Physical Review Letters 96, 014801 (2006) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science R. Huber, R. A. Kaindl, B. A. Schmid, and D. S. Chemla Broadband THz study of excitonic resonances in the high-density regime in GaAs/AlxGa1-xAs quantum wells Physical Review B 72, 161314(R) (2005), also in cond-mat/0508082 This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science R. Huber, C. Kübler, Q. T. Vu, H. Haug, S. Tübel, F. Köhler, M.-C. Amann, and A. Leitenstorfer Femtosecond formation of phonon-plasmon coupled modes in InP: ultrabroadband THz experiment and quantum kinetic theory Physical Review Letters 94, 027401 (2005) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science C. Kübler, R. Huber, and A. Leitenstorfer (invited article) Ultrabroadband terahertz pulses: generation and field-resolved detection Semicond. Sci. Technol., 20, pp. 128 - 133 (2005) C. Kübler, R. Huber, S. Tübel and A. Leitenstorfer Ultrabroadband detection of multi-THz field transients with GaSe electro-optic sensors: approaching the near infrared Applied Physics Letters 85, 3360 (2004) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science NEWSFLASH in LaserFocusWorld M. Betz, R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm, A. Leitenstorfer, P. Gartner, L. Banyai, and H. Haug Ultrafast Formation of Quasiparticles in Semiconductors: How Bare Charges Get Dressed in K. Morawetz (ed.), Nonequilibrium Physics at Short Time Scales: Formation of Correlations, pp. 231 - 250, Springer (2004) A. Leitenstorfer, R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm How fast do charged particles get dressed? physica status solidi (b) 238, Issue 3,455 (2003) R. Huber, F. Adler, A. Leitenstorfer, M. Beutter, P. Baum, and E. Riedle 12 fs pulses from a cw-pumped 200 nJ Ti:sapphire amplifier at a variable repetition rate of up to 4 MHz Optics Letters 28, 2118 (2003) R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm, A. Leitenstorfer Watching bare charges get dressed in an ultrabroadband THz experiment "Ultrafast Phenomena XIII", eds. R.D. Miller, M.M. Murnane, N.F. Scherer, A.M. Weiner, (Springer Series in Chemical Physics 71, 2003) pp. 365 ? 367 B. Averbough, R. Huber, K.W. Cheah, Y.R. Shen, G.G. Qin, Z.C. Ma, and W.H. Zong Luminescence studies of a Si/SiO2 superlattice J. Appl. Phys. 92, 3564 (2002) R. Sammynaiken, S.J. Naftel, T.K. Sham, K.W. Cheah, B. Averbough, R. Huber, Y.R. Shen, G.G. Qin, Z.C. Ma, and W.H. Zong Structure and electronic properties of SiO2/Si multilayer superlattices: Si K edge and L3/2 edge x-ray absorption fine structure study J. Appl. Phys. 92, 3000 (2002) R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm, and A. Leitenstorfer Femtosecond Buildup of a Many-Body Resonance Observed via Two-Dimensional THz Time-Domain Spectroscopy phys. stat. sol. (b) 234, No. 1, 207 (2002) COVERSTORY R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm, M. Bichler, G. Abstreiter and A. Leitenstorfer How many-particle interactions develop after ultrafast excitation of an electron-hole plasma Nature 414, 286 (2001) A. Brodschelm, F. Tauser, R. Huber, J. Y. Sohn, A. Leitenstorfer Amplitude and Phase Resolved Detection of Tunable Femtosecond Pulses with Frequency Components beyond 100 THz "Ultrafast Phenomena XII", eds. T. Elsaesser, S. Mukhamel, M. M. Murnane, N. F. Scherer (Springer Series in Chemical Physics 66, Berlin, 2000), pp. 215 - 217 R. Huber, A. Brodschelm, F. Tauser, and A. Leitenstorfer Generation and field-resolved detection of femtosecond electromagnetic pulses tunable up to 41 THz Appl. Phys. Lett. 76, 3191 (2000) Invited and contributed talks at international conferences R. Huber Nonadiabatic control of intersubband cavity polaritons (Invited Talk) 14th International Conference on Modulated Semiconductor Structures (MSS14), to be jointly held with EP2DS18 in Kobe, Japan (July 19-24, 2009) R. Huber Switch-on of ultrastrong light-matter interaction faster than a cycle of light (Invited Talk) Conference on lasers and electro-optics - European quantum electronics conference (CLEO Europe - EQEC 2009), to be held in Munich, Germany (June 14-19, 2009) R. Huber Ultra-intense THz source and extreme THz nonlinearities in condensed matter (Invited Talk) Conference on lasers and electro-optics CLEO/IQEC 2009, to be held in Baltimore, USA (May 31-June 5, 2009) R. Huber Terahertz nonlinear optics of semiconductor systems (Invited Talk) Trends in Nanoscience 2009, to be held in Kloster Irsee, Germany (February 28 - March 4, 2009) R. Huber et al. Femtosecond solid state physics with ultra-intense THz fields (Invited Talk) International Workshop of the Special Research Program ADLIS (Advanced Light Sources), to be held in Munich, Germany (March 2-4, 2009) R. Huber High-field terahertz physics in the non-perturbative regime (Invited Talk) International Workshop on Nonequilibrium Nanostructures, Dresden, Germany (December 1-6, 2008) A. Sell, S. Leinß, J. Hees, G. Günter, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Femtosecond solid state physics with ultrabroadband THz pulses (Invited Talk) EOS Topical Meeting on Terahertz Science and Technology, Paris, France (September 29 - October 2, 2008) R. Huber THz coherent control and cavity QED in semiconductors (Invited Talk) International Conference on Correlation Effects in Radiation Fields, Rostock, Germany (September 8 ? 10, 2008) S. Leinß, T. Kampfrath, K. v. Volkmann, D. Fröhlich, M. Wolf, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Terahertz nonlinear control of optically dark excitons in Cu2O (Invited Talk) 8th International Conference on Excitonic Processes in Condensed Matter (EXCON?08), Kyoto, Japan (June 22-27, 2008) T. Kampfrath, S. Leinß, K. v. Volkmann, M. Wolf, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Terahertz Nonlinear Response and Coherent Quantum Control of Dark Excitons in Cu2O Conference on Ultrafast Phenomena 2008, UP08, Stresa, Italy (June 8-13, 2008) G. Günter, A. A. Anappara, J. Hees, S. Leinß, L. Sorba, G. Biasiol, A. Tredicucci, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Femtosecond Buildup of Ultrastrong Light-Matter Interaction Conference on Ultrafast Phenomena 2008, UP08, Stresa, Italy (June 8-13, 2008) R. Huber, C. Kübler, H. Ehrke, R. Lopez, A. Halabica, R. F. Haglund, and A. Leitenstorfer THz Slow Motion of an Ultrafast Insulator-Metal Transition in VO2: Coherent Structural Dynamics and Electronic Correlations Conference on Ultrafast Phenomena 2008, UP08, Stresa, Italy (June 8-13, 2008) A. Sell, R. Scheu, R. Huber, and A. Leitenstorfer Intense THz Pulses and 11-fs Electro-optic Sampling with a Multi-Branch Er:fiber/Ti:sapphire Hybrid Amplifier Conference on Ultrafast Phenomena 2008, UP08, Stresa, Italy (June 8-13, 2008) A. Sell, R. Scheu, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Two-branch Er:fiber laser for 11 fs tunable pulses with attosecond relative timing jitter CLEO/QELS 2008, San Jose, USA (May 4-9, 2008) S. Leinß, T. Kampfrath, K. v. Volkmann, M. Wolf, D. Fröhlich, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Terahertz Coherent Control of the Internal Quantum State of Dark Excitons in Cu2O CLEO/QELS 2008, San Jose, USA (May 4-9, 2008) R. Huber Ultrabroadband THz Studies of Correlated Electrons: From Excitons to Insulator-Metal Transitions (Invited Talk) Academy Colloquium ?TeraHertz Science?, Amsterdam, Netherlands (June 14-16, 2007) R. Huber, B. A. Schmid, R. A. Kaindl, and D. S. Chemla Femtosecond terahertz studies of excitons (Invited Talk) International Quantum Electronics Conference (CLEO Europe / IQEC 2007), Munich, Germany (June 17-22, 2007) R. Huber Broadband and ultrabroadband THz probes of photoexcited electron-hole systems in semiconductors (Invited Talk) Seminar and Workshop on ?Non-Equilibrium Dynamics in Interacting Systems?, Max-Planck-Institut für Physik komplexer Systeme, Dresden, Germany (April 18 - May 5, 2006) C. Kübler, H. Ehrke, R. Huber, A. Leitenstorfer, R. Lopez, A. Halabica, and R. F. Haglund Jr. Ultrafast Conductivity and Lattice Dynamics of Insulator-Metal Phase Transition in VO2 Studied via Multi-Terahertz Spectroscopy Joint 31st International Conference on Infrared and Millimeter Waves and 14th International Conference on Terahertz Technology (IRMMW-THz2006), Shanghai, China (September 18-22, 2006) R. Huber, C. Kübler, S. Tübel, and A. Leitenstorfer Femtosecond buildup of phonon-plasmon coupling in photoexcited InP observed by ultrabroadband THz probe (Invited Talk), SPIE Photonic West?06 International Symposium on ?Ultrafast Phenomena in Semiconductors and Nanostructures?, to be held at San Jose, CA (Jan. 21-26, 2006) R. Huber, R. A. Kaindl, B. A. Schmid, D. S. Chemla Broadband THz spectroscopy of resonantly excited high-density exciton gas QUELS 2005, Baltimore (May 22-27, 2005), to appear in: ?Trends in Optics and Photonics? C. Kübler, R. Huber, S. Tübel, F. Köhler, M.-C. Amann, and A. Leitenstorfer Ultrafast Formation of Coupled Phonon-Plasmon Modes in InP Observed with Femtosecond Terahertz Spectroscopy 14th International Conference on Nonequilibrium Carrier Dynamics in Semiconductors (HCIS 14), Chicago, Illinois, USA (July 24-29, 2005) R. Huber, R. A. Kaindl, B. A. Schmid, D. S. Chemla Broadband THz spectroscopy of high-density exciton gas APS March Meeting, Los Angeles (March 21-25, 2005), to appear in: ?Bulletin of the American Physical Society? R. Huber, C. Kübler, and A. Leitenstorfer Femtosecond Buildup of Phonon-Plasmon Mixed Modes in Polar Semiconductors Investigated via Single-Cycle Multi-THz Spectroscopy Invited Keynote TH6.1, Joint 29th International Conference on Infrared and Millimeter Waves (IRMMW 2004) and 12th IEEE International Conference on Terahertz Electronics (THz 2004), Karlsruhe, Germany (September 27-October 1, 2004) R. Huber, C. Kübler, S. Tübel, A. Leitenstorfer Ultrabroadband THz Technology and Applications in Femtosecond Semiconductor Physics, (Invited Talk), Quantum Electronics and Photonics, QEP-16, Glasgow, (September 6-9, 2004) R. Huber, C. Kübler, S. Tübel, A. Brodschelm, F. Köhler, R. Meyer, M.-C. Amann, and A. Leitenstorfer Femtosecond formation of phonon-plasmon coupled modes studied by ultrabroadband THz spectroscopy Ultrafast Phenomena XIV, Niigata, Japan, (July 25-30, 2004) , in: ?Ultrafast Phenomena XIV?, eds. T. Kobayashi, T. Okada, T. Kobayashi, K. Nelson, S. De Silvesti, (Springer Series in Chemical Physics, Vol. 79, Berlin, 2004), pp.729-731 C. Kübler, R. Huber, S. Tübel, and A. Leitenstorfer Ultrabroadband detection of multi-THz field transients with GaSe electro-optic sensors Ultrafast Phenomena XIV, Niigata, Japan, (July 25-30, 2004) , in: ?Ultrafast Phenomena XIV?, eds. T. Kobayashi, T. Okada, T. Kobayashi, K. Nelson, S. De Silvesti, (Springer Series in Chemical Physics, Vol. 79, Berlin, 2004), pp. 753-755 R. Huber, C. Kübler, S. Tübel, A. Leitenstorfer Femtosecond dynamics of a photoexcited phonon-plasmon system (Invited Talk), Workshop on Quantum Heterostructures and THz Electronics, Regensburg, (February 05, 2004) R. Huber, Florian Tauser, Andreas Brodschelm, and Alfred Leitenstorfer Ultrafast Buildup of a Many-Body Resonance after Femtosecond Excitation of an Electron-Hole Plasma in GaAs in B. Kramer (ed.), Advances in Solid State Physics 43, pp. 341 - 350, Springer (2004) R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm, M. Bichler, G. Abstreiter, and A. Leitenstorfer Ultrafast formation of many-particle interactions in a photoexcited electron-hole plasma (Invited Talk), Photonics West, Optoelectronics 2003, Ultrafast Phenomena in Semiconductors VII, San Jose (January 25-31, 2003), in press R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm, A. Leitenstorfer Watching bare charges get dressed in an ultrabroadband THz experiment, Phenomena XIII, Vancouver (May 12-17, 2002) in: "Ultrafast Phenomena XIII", eds. R.D. Miller, M.M. Murnane, N.F. Scherer, A.M. Weiner, (Springer Series in Chemical Physics 71, 2003) pp. 365 ? 367 F. Tauser, R. Huber, A. Brodschelm, M. Bichler, G. Abstreiter, and A. Leitenstorfer Femtosecond buildup of screening and collective effects in photoexcited GaAs: How bare charges get dressed (Invited Talk), 26th International Conference on the Physics in Semiconductors (ICPS 2002), Edinburgh, Scotland (July 29 - August 2, 2002), in press R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm, M. Bichler, G. Abstreiter, and A. Leitenstorfer Nonlinear multi-THz spectroscopy: femtosecond buildup of collective effects in an electron-hole plasma EQUONT Euroconference, EQUONT euroconference on "Ultrafast Processes in Solid State Nanostructures", Les Houches, France (April 21-26, 2002) R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm, and A. Leitenstorfer Ultrafast formation of plasmon-phonon hybrid modes in photoexcited GaAs (Invited Talk), Workshop on Quantum Heterostructures and THz Electronics, Regensburg, (January 17, 2002) A. Leitenstorfer, R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm, M. Bichler, G. Abstreiter Femtosecond buildup of Coulomb screening in a photoexcited electron-hole plasma 12th International Conference on Nonequilibrium Carrier Dynamics in Semiconductors (HCIS-12), Santa Fe, USA (August 27 - 31, 2001) in: Physica B 314, 248 (2002) R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm and A. Leitenstorfer Femtosecond buildup of Coulomb screening in photoexcited GaAs probed via ultrabroadband THz spectroscopy International Conference on Dynamical Processes in Excited States of Solids, DPC?01, Lyon, France (July 1-4, 2001) in: Journal of Luminescence 94&amp;95, 555 (2001) A. Brodschelm, F. Tauser, R. Huber, J. Y. Sohn, A. Leitenstorfer Amplitude and Phase Resolved Detection of Tunable Femtosecond Pulses with Frequency Components beyond 100 THz Ultrafast Phenomena XII, Charleston (2000) in: "Ultrafast Phenomena XII", eds. T. Elsaesser, S. Mukhamel, M. M. Murnane, N. F. Scherer (Springer Series in Chemical Physics 66, Berlin, 2000), pp. 215 ? 217 F. Tauser, R. Huber, A. Brodschelm, and A. Leitenstorfer Fully Coherent Generation and Detection of Tunable Femtosecond Pulses approaching the NIR ITW 2000, Sandbjerg Castle, Denmark (17-19 September 2000) Last modified: 10.04.2014 by Webmaster</field>
<field name="important">Lehrstuhl Huber Lehrstuhl Huber Internal | Search | About      Home  Events  People  Teaching  Research  Publications Journal articles, review articles and book chapters Talks  Contact         Department of Physics &amp;gt; LS Huber &amp;gt; AG Huber &amp;gt; Publications Journal articles, review articles and book chapters Michael Porer, Jean-Michel M?nard, and Rupert Huber Shot noise reduced terahertz detection via spectrally postfiltered electro-optic sampling Optics Letters 39, 2435-2438 (2014) H. Dachraoui, G. van der Laan, N. Müller, T. Milde, M. Porer, R. Manzke, R. Huber, S. Fritzsche and U. Heinzmann Mapping spin-orbit activated interchannel coupling EPL 106, 13001 (2014) O. Schubert, M. Hohenleutner, F. Langer, B. Urbanek, C. Lange, U. Huttner, D. Golde, T. Meier, M. Kira, S. W. Koch and R. Huber Sub-cycle control of terahertz high-harmonic generation by dynamical Bloch oscillations Nature Photon. 8, 119-123 (2014) T. L. Cocker and R. Huber A new twist on terahertz pulses Nature Photon. 7, 678-679 (2013) A. Pashkin, A. Sell, T. Kampfrath und R. Huber Electric and magnetic terahertz nonlinearities resolved on the sub-cycle scale New J. Phys. 15, 065003 (2013) O. Schubert, M. Eisele, V. Crozatier, N. Forget, D. Kaplan, and R. Huber Rapid-scan acousto-optical delay line with 34 kHz scan rate and 15 attosecond precision Optics Letters 38, 2907 (2013) P. Olbrich, C. Drexler, L. E. Golub, S. N. Danilov, V. A. Shalygin, R. Yakimova, S. Lara-Avila, S. Kubatkin, B. Redlich, R. Huber, and S.D. Ganichev Reststrahl band-assisted photocurrents in epitaxial graphene layers Phys. Rev. B 88, 245425 (2013) A. Pashkin, F. Junginger, B. Mayer, C. Schmidt, O. Schubert, D. Brida, R. Huber, and A. Leitenstorfer Quantum Physics with Ultrabroadband and Intense Terahertz Pulses IEEE Journal of Selected Topics in Quantum Electronics 19, 8401608 (2013) F. Junginger, B. Mayer, C. Schmidt, O. Schubert, S. M?hrlein, A. Leitenstorfer, R. Huber, and A. Pashkin Non-perturbative interband response of a bulk InSb semiconductor driven off-resonantly by terahertz electromagnetic few-cycle pulses Phys. Rev. Lett. 109, 147403 (2012) K. W. Kim, A. Pashkin, H. Sch?fer, M. Beyer, M. Porer, T. Wolf, C. Bernhard, J. Demsar, R. Huber, and A. Leitenstorfer Ultrafast transient generation of spin-density-wave order in the normal state of BaFe2As2 driven by coherent lattice vibrations Nature Materials 11, 497 (2012) M. Porer, J.-M. Menard, A. Leitenstorfer, R. Huber, R. Degl'Innocenti, S. Zanotto, G. Biasiol, L. Sorba, and A. Tredicucci, Nonadiabatic Splitting of a Photonic Bandstructure: Ultrastrong Light-matter Coupling and Slow-down of Light Physical Review B 85, 081302(R) (2012) R. Huber Photonics: Terahertz collisions Nature 483, 545-546 (2012) O. Schubert, C. Riek, F. Junginger, A. Sell, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Ultrashort pulse characterization with a terahertz streak camera Optics Letters 36, 4458 (2011) R. Huber, A. A. Anappara, G. Günter, A. Sell, S. De Liberato, C. Ciuti, G. Biasiol, L. Sorba, A. Tredicucci, and A. Leitenstorfer Switching ultrastrong light-matter coupling on a subcycle scale J. Appl. Phys. 109, 102418 (2011) A. Pashkin, C.Kübler, H. Ehrke, R. Lopez, A. Halabica, R. F. Haglund, Jr., R. Huber, and A. Leitenstorfer Ultrafast Insulator-Metal Phase Transition in VO2 Studied by Multiterahertz Spectroscopy Physical Review B 83, 195120 (2011) G. Krauss, D. Fehrenbacher, D. Brida, C. Riek, A. Sell, R. Huber und A. Leitenstorfer All-passive phase locking of a compact Er:fiber laser system Opt. Lett. 36, 540 (2011) G. Klatt, B. Surrer, D. Stephan, O. Schubert, M. Fischer, J. Faist, A. Leitenstorfer, R. Huber, and T. Dekorsy Photo-Dember terahertz emitter excited with an Er:fiber laser Appl. Phys. Lett. 98, 021114 (2011) T. Kampfrath, A. Sell, G. Klatt, A. Pashkin, S. Mährlein, T. Dekorsy, M. Wolf, M. Fiebig, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Coherent terahertz control of antiferromagnetic spin waves Nature Photonics 5, 31 (2011) This work has been featured in a News and Views Article by Junichiro Kono Spintronics: Coherent terahertz control Nature Photonics 5, 5 (2011) F. Junginger, A. Sell, O. Schubert, B. Mayer, D. Brida, M. Marangoni, G. Cerullo, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Single-cycle multiterahertz transients with peak fields above 10 MV/cm Optics Letters 35, 2645 (2010) A. Pashkin, M. Porer, M. Beyer, K. W. Kim, A. Dubroka, C. Bernhard, X. Yao, Y. Dagan, R. Hackl, A. Erb, J. Demsar, R. Huber, and A. Leitenstorfer Femtosecond Response of Quasiparticles and Phonons in Superconducting YBCO Studied by Wideband Terahertz Spectroscopy Physical Review Letters 105, 067001 (2010) This work has been featured in a Viewpoint in Physics by U. Bovensiepen A real-time view of elementary excitations in high-Tc superconductors Viewpoint in Physics 3, 63 (2010) G. Krauss, S. Lohss, T. Hanke, A. Sell, S. Eggert, R. Huber, and A. Leitenstorfer Synthesis of a single cycle of light with compact erbium-doped fibre technology Nature Photonics 4, 33 (2010) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science G. Günter, A. A. Anappara, J. Hees, A. Sell, G. Biasiol, L. Sorba, S. De Liberato, C. Ciuti, A. Tredicucci, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Sub-cycle switch-on of ultrastrong light-matter interaction Nature 458, 178 (2009) This work has been featured in a News and Views Article by Claire Gmachl Quantum optoelectronics: Swift switch of the strong Nature 458, 157 (2009) A. Sell, G. Krauss, R. Scheu, R. Huber, and A. Leitenstorfer 8-fs pulses from a compact Er:fiber system: quantitative modelling and experimental implementation Optics Express 17, 1070 (2009) F. Adler, F. Sotier, D. Träutlein, A. Sell, K. Moutzouris, R. Huber, and A. Leitenstorfer Widely Tunable Femtosecond Lasers and Applications in M. Kimura (ed.), Fiber Lasers: Research, Technology and Applications, Nova Science Publishers (2009) A. Sell, R. Scheu, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Field-resolved detection of phase-locked infrared transients tunable from 55 to 107 THz from an Er:fiber laser system Applied Physics Letters 93, 251107 (2008) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science A. Sell, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Phase-locked generation and field-resolved detection of widely tunable terahertz pulses with amplitudes exceeding 100 MV/cm Optics Letters 33, 2767 (2008) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science S. Leinß, T. Kampfrath, K. v. Volkmann, M. Wolf, J. T. Steiner, M. Kira, S. W. Koch, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Terahertz coherent control of optically dark paraexcitons in Cu2O Physical Review Letters 101, 246401 (2008) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science R. Huber, B. A. Schmid, R. A. Kaindl, and D. S. Chemla Femtosecond THz Studies of Intra-Excitonic Transitions physica status solidi (b) 245, 1041 (2008) F. Adler, A. Sell, F. Sotier, R. Huber, and A. Leitenstorfer Attosecond relative timing jitter and 13 fs tunable pulses from a two-branch femtosecond Er:fiber laser Optics Letters 32, 3504 (2007) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science C. Kübler, H. Ehrke, R. Huber, R. Lopez, A. Halabica, R. F. Haglund, Jr., and A. Leitenstorfer Coherent Structural Dynamics and Electronic Correlations during an Ultrafast Insulator-to-Metal Phase Transition in VO2 Physical Review Letters 99, 116401 (2007) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Nanoscale Science and Technology T. Zentgraf, R. Huber, N. C. Nielsen, D. S. Chemla, and R. Kaindl Ultrabroadband 50-130 THz pulses generated via phase-matched difference frequency mixing in LiIO3 Optics Express 15, 5775 (2007) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science R. Huber, B. A. Schmid, Y.-R. Shen, D. S. Chemla, R. A. Kaindl Stimulated THz Emission from Internal Exciton Transitions in Cu2O Physical Review Letters 96, 017402 (2006) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science J. van Tilborg, C. B. Schroeder, C. V. Filip. Cs. Toth, C. G. R. Geddes, G. Fubiani, R. Huber, R. A. Kaindl, E. Esarey, and W. P. Leemans Temporal Characterization of Femtosecond Laser-Plasma-Accelerated Electron Bunches using THz Radiation Physical Review Letters 96, 014801 (2006) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science R. Huber, R. A. Kaindl, B. A. Schmid, and D. S. Chemla Broadband THz study of excitonic resonances in the high-density regime in GaAs/AlxGa1-xAs quantum wells Physical Review B 72, 161314(R) (2005), also in cond-mat/0508082 This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science R. Huber, C. Kübler, Q. T. Vu, H. Haug, S. Tübel, F. Köhler, M.-C. Amann, and A. Leitenstorfer Femtosecond formation of phonon-plasmon coupled modes in InP: ultrabroadband THz experiment and quantum kinetic theory Physical Review Letters 94, 027401 (2005) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science C. Kübler, R. Huber, and A. Leitenstorfer (invited article) Ultrabroadband terahertz pulses: generation and field-resolved detection Semicond. Sci. Technol., 20, pp. 128 - 133 (2005) C. Kübler, R. Huber, S. Tübel and A. Leitenstorfer Ultrabroadband detection of multi-THz field transients with GaSe electro-optic sensors: approaching the near infrared Applied Physics Letters 85, 3360 (2004) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science NEWSFLASH in LaserFocusWorld M. Betz, R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm, A. Leitenstorfer, P. Gartner, L. Banyai, and H. Haug Ultrafast Formation of Quasiparticles in Semiconductors: How Bare Charges Get Dressed in K. Morawetz (ed.), Nonequilibrium Physics at Short Time Scales: Formation of Correlations, pp. 231 - 250, Springer (2004) A. Leitenstorfer, R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm How fast do charged particles get dressed? physica status solidi (b) 238, Issue 3,455 (2003) R. Huber, F. Adler, A. Leitenstorfer, M. Beutter, P. Baum, and E. Riedle 12 fs pulses from a cw-pumped 200 nJ Ti:sapphire amplifier at a variable repetition rate of up to 4 MHz Optics Letters 28, 2118 (2003) R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm, A. Leitenstorfer Watching bare charges get dressed in an ultrabroadband THz experiment "Ultrafast Phenomena XIII", eds. R.D. Miller, M.M. Murnane, N.F. Scherer, A.M. Weiner, (Springer Series in Chemical Physics 71, 2003) pp. 365 ? 367 B. Averbough, R. Huber, K.W. Cheah, Y.R. Shen, G.G. Qin, Z.C. Ma, and W.H. Zong Luminescence studies of a Si/SiO2 superlattice J. Appl. Phys. 92, 3564 (2002) R. Sammynaiken, S.J. Naftel, T.K. Sham, K.W. Cheah, B. Averbough, R. Huber, Y.R. Shen, G.G. Qin, Z.C. Ma, and W.H. Zong Structure and electronic properties of SiO2/Si multilayer superlattices: Si K edge and L3/2 edge x-ray absorption fine structure study J. Appl. Phys. 92, 3000 (2002) R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm, and A. Leitenstorfer Femtosecond Buildup of a Many-Body Resonance Observed via Two-Dimensional THz Time-Domain Spectroscopy phys. stat. sol. (b) 234, No. 1, 207 (2002) COVERSTORY R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm, M. Bichler, G. Abstreiter and A. Leitenstorfer How many-particle interactions develop after ultrafast excitation of an electron-hole plasma Nature 414, 286 (2001) A. Brodschelm, F. Tauser, R. Huber, J. Y. Sohn, A. Leitenstorfer Amplitude and Phase Resolved Detection of Tunable Femtosecond Pulses with Frequency Components beyond 100 THz "Ultrafast Phenomena XII", eds. T. Elsaesser, S. Mukhamel, M. M. Murnane, N. F. Scherer (Springer Series in Chemical Physics 66, Berlin, 2000), pp. 215 - 217 R. Huber, A. Brodschelm, F. Tauser, and A. Leitenstorfer Generation and field-resolved detection of femtosecond electromagnetic pulses tunable up to 41 THz Appl. Phys. Lett. 76, 3191 (2000) Invited and contributed talks at international conferences R. Huber Nonadiabatic control of intersubband cavity polaritons (Invited Talk) 14th International Conference on Modulated Semiconductor Structures (MSS14), to be jointly held with EP2DS18 in Kobe, Japan (July 19-24, 2009) R. Huber Switch-on of ultrastrong light-matter interaction faster than a cycle of light (Invited Talk) Conference on lasers and electro-optics - European quantum electronics conference (CLEO Europe - EQEC 2009), to be held in Munich, Germany (June 14-19, 2009) R. Huber Ultra-intense THz source and extreme THz nonlinearities in condensed matter (Invited Talk) Conference on lasers and electro-optics CLEO/IQEC 2009, to be held in Baltimore, USA (May 31-June 5, 2009) R. Huber Terahertz nonlinear optics of semiconductor systems (Invited Talk) Trends in Nanoscience 2009, to be held in Kloster Irsee, Germany (February 28 - March 4, 2009) R. Huber et al. Femtosecond solid state physics with ultra-intense THz fields (Invited Talk) International Workshop of the Special Research Program ADLIS (Advanced Light Sources), to be held in Munich, Germany (March 2-4, 2009) R. Huber High-field terahertz physics in the non-perturbative regime (Invited Talk) International Workshop on Nonequilibrium Nanostructures, Dresden, Germany (December 1-6, 2008) A. Sell, S. Leinß, J. Hees, G. Günter, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Femtosecond solid state physics with ultrabroadband THz pulses (Invited Talk) EOS Topical Meeting on Terahertz Science and Technology, Paris, France (September 29 - October 2, 2008) R. Huber THz coherent control and cavity QED in semiconductors (Invited Talk) International Conference on Correlation Effects in Radiation Fields, Rostock, Germany (September 8 ? 10, 2008) S. Leinß, T. Kampfrath, K. v. Volkmann, D. Fröhlich, M. Wolf, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Terahertz nonlinear control of optically dark excitons in Cu2O (Invited Talk) 8th International Conference on Excitonic Processes in Condensed Matter (EXCON?08), Kyoto, Japan (June 22-27, 2008) T. Kampfrath, S. Leinß, K. v. Volkmann, M. Wolf, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Terahertz Nonlinear Response and Coherent Quantum Control of Dark Excitons in Cu2O Conference on Ultrafast Phenomena 2008, UP08, Stresa, Italy (June 8-13, 2008) G. Günter, A. A. Anappara, J. Hees, S. Leinß, L. Sorba, G. Biasiol, A. Tredicucci, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Femtosecond Buildup of Ultrastrong Light-Matter Interaction Conference on Ultrafast Phenomena 2008, UP08, Stresa, Italy (June 8-13, 2008) R. Huber, C. Kübler, H. Ehrke, R. Lopez, A. Halabica, R. F. Haglund, and A. Leitenstorfer THz Slow Motion of an Ultrafast Insulator-Metal Transition in VO2: Coherent Structural Dynamics and Electronic Correlations Conference on Ultrafast Phenomena 2008, UP08, Stresa, Italy (June 8-13, 2008) A. Sell, R. Scheu, R. Huber, and A. Leitenstorfer Intense THz Pulses and 11-fs Electro-optic Sampling with a Multi-Branch Er:fiber/Ti:sapphire Hybrid Amplifier Conference on Ultrafast Phenomena 2008, UP08, Stresa, Italy (June 8-13, 2008) A. Sell, R. Scheu, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Two-branch Er:fiber laser for 11 fs tunable pulses with attosecond relative timing jitter CLEO/QELS 2008, San Jose, USA (May 4-9, 2008) S. Leinß, T. Kampfrath, K. v. Volkmann, M. Wolf, D. Fröhlich, A. Leitenstorfer, and R. Huber Terahertz Coherent Control of the Internal Quantum State of Dark Excitons in Cu2O CLEO/QELS 2008, San Jose, USA (May 4-9, 2008) R. Huber Ultrabroadband THz Studies of Correlated Electrons: From Excitons to Insulator-Metal Transitions (Invited Talk) Academy Colloquium ?TeraHertz Science?, Amsterdam, Netherlands (June 14-16, 2007) R. Huber, B. A. Schmid, R. A. Kaindl, and D. S. Chemla Femtosecond terahertz studies of excitons (Invited Talk) International Quantum Electronics Conference (CLEO Europe / IQEC 2007), Munich, Germany (June 17-22, 2007) R. Huber Broadband and ultrabroadband THz probes of photoexcited electron-hole systems in semiconductors (Invited Talk) Seminar and Workshop on ?Non-Equilibrium Dynamics in Interacting Systems?, Max-Planck-Institut für Physik komplexer Systeme, Dresden, Germany (April 18 - May 5, 2006) C. Kübler, H. Ehrke, R. Huber, A. Leitenstorfer, R. Lopez, A. Halabica, and R. F. Haglund Jr. Ultrafast Conductivity and Lattice Dynamics of Insulator-Metal Phase Transition in VO2 Studied via Multi-Terahertz Spectroscopy Joint 31st International Conference on Infrared and Millimeter Waves and 14th International Conference on Terahertz Technology (IRMMW-THz2006), Shanghai, China (September 18-22, 2006) R. Huber, C. Kübler, S. Tübel, and A. Leitenstorfer Femtosecond buildup of phonon-plasmon coupling in photoexcited InP observed by ultrabroadband THz probe (Invited Talk), SPIE Photonic West?06 International Symposium on ?Ultrafast Phenomena in Semiconductors and Nanostructures?, to be held at San Jose, CA (Jan. 21-26, 2006) R. Huber, R. A. Kaindl, B. A. Schmid, D. S. Chemla Broadband THz spectroscopy of resonantly excited high-density exciton gas QUELS 2005, Baltimore (May 22-27, 2005), to appear in: ?Trends in Optics and Photonics? C. Kübler, R. Huber, S. Tübel, F. Köhler, M.-C. Amann, and A. Leitenstorfer Ultrafast Formation of Coupled Phonon-Plasmon Modes in InP Observed with Femtosecond Terahertz Spectroscopy 14th International Conference on Nonequilibrium Carrier Dynamics in Semiconductors (HCIS 14), Chicago, Illinois, USA (July 24-29, 2005) R. Huber, R. A. Kaindl, B. A. Schmid, D. S. Chemla Broadband THz spectroscopy of high-density exciton gas APS March Meeting, Los Angeles (March 21-25, 2005), to appear in: ?Bulletin of the American Physical Society? R. Huber, C. Kübler, and A. Leitenstorfer Femtosecond Buildup of Phonon-Plasmon Mixed Modes in Polar Semiconductors Investigated via Single-Cycle Multi-THz Spectroscopy Invited Keynote TH6.1, Joint 29th International Conference on Infrared and Millimeter Waves (IRMMW 2004) and 12th IEEE International Conference on Terahertz Electronics (THz 2004), Karlsruhe, Germany (September 27-October 1, 2004) R. Huber, C. Kübler, S. Tübel, A. Leitenstorfer Ultrabroadband THz Technology and Applications in Femtosecond Semiconductor Physics, (Invited Talk), Quantum Electronics and Photonics, QEP-16, Glasgow, (September 6-9, 2004) R. Huber, C. Kübler, S. Tübel, A. Brodschelm, F. Köhler, R. Meyer, M.-C. Amann, and A. Leitenstorfer Femtosecond formation of phonon-plasmon coupled modes studied by ultrabroadband THz spectroscopy Ultrafast Phenomena XIV, Niigata, Japan, (July 25-30, 2004) , in: ?Ultrafast Phenomena XIV?, eds. T. Kobayashi, T. Okada, T. Kobayashi, K. Nelson, S. De Silvesti, (Springer Series in Chemical Physics, Vol. 79, Berlin, 2004), pp.729-731 C. Kübler, R. Huber, S. Tübel, and A. Leitenstorfer Ultrabroadband detection of multi-THz field transients with GaSe electro-optic sensors Ultrafast Phenomena XIV, Niigata, Japan, (July 25-30, 2004) , in: ?Ultrafast Phenomena XIV?, eds. T. Kobayashi, T. Okada, T. Kobayashi, K. Nelson, S. De Silvesti, (Springer Series in Chemical Physics, Vol. 79, Berlin, 2004), pp. 753-755 R. Huber, C. Kübler, S. Tübel, A. Leitenstorfer Femtosecond dynamics of a photoexcited phonon-plasmon system (Invited Talk), Workshop on Quantum Heterostructures and THz Electronics, Regensburg, (February 05, 2004) R. Huber, Florian Tauser, Andreas Brodschelm, and Alfred Leitenstorfer Ultrafast Buildup of a Many-Body Resonance after Femtosecond Excitation of an Electron-Hole Plasma in GaAs in B. Kramer (ed.), Advances in Solid State Physics 43, pp. 341 - 350, Springer (2004) R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm, M. Bichler, G. Abstreiter, and A. Leitenstorfer Ultrafast formation of many-particle interactions in a photoexcited electron-hole plasma (Invited Talk), Photonics West, Optoelectronics 2003, Ultrafast Phenomena in Semiconductors VII, San Jose (January 25-31, 2003), in press R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm, A. Leitenstorfer Watching bare charges get dressed in an ultrabroadband THz experiment, Phenomena XIII, Vancouver (May 12-17, 2002) in: "Ultrafast Phenomena XIII", eds. R.D. Miller, M.M. Murnane, N.F. Scherer, A.M. Weiner, (Springer Series in Chemical Physics 71, 2003) pp. 365 ? 367 F. Tauser, R. Huber, A. Brodschelm, M. Bichler, G. Abstreiter, and A. Leitenstorfer Femtosecond buildup of screening and collective effects in photoexcited GaAs: How bare charges get dressed (Invited Talk), 26th International Conference on the Physics in Semiconductors (ICPS 2002), Edinburgh, Scotland (July 29 - August 2, 2002), in press R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm, M. Bichler, G. Abstreiter, and A. Leitenstorfer Nonlinear multi-THz spectroscopy: femtosecond buildup of collective effects in an electron-hole plasma EQUONT Euroconference, EQUONT euroconference on "Ultrafast Processes in Solid State Nanostructures", Les Houches, France (April 21-26, 2002) R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm, and A. Leitenstorfer Ultrafast formation of plasmon-phonon hybrid modes in photoexcited GaAs (Invited Talk), Workshop on Quantum Heterostructures and THz Electronics, Regensburg, (January 17, 2002) A. Leitenstorfer, R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm, M. Bichler, G. Abstreiter Femtosecond buildup of Coulomb screening in a photoexcited electron-hole plasma 12th International Conference on Nonequilibrium Carrier Dynamics in Semiconductors (HCIS-12), Santa Fe, USA (August 27 - 31, 2001) in: Physica B 314, 248 (2002) R. Huber, F. Tauser, A. Brodschelm and A. Leitenstorfer Femtosecond buildup of Coulomb screening in photoexcited GaAs probed via ultrabroadband THz spectroscopy International Conference on Dynamical Processes in Excited States of Solids, DPC?01, Lyon, France (July 1-4, 2001) in: Journal of Luminescence 94&amp;95, 555 (2001) A. Brodschelm, F. Tauser, R. Huber, J. Y. Sohn, A. Leitenstorfer Amplitude and Phase Resolved Detection of Tunable Femtosecond Pulses with Frequency Components beyond 100 THz Ultrafast Phenomena XII, Charleston (2000) in: "Ultrafast Phenomena XII", eds. T. Elsaesser, S. Mukhamel, M. M. Murnane, N. F. Scherer (Springer Series in Chemical Physics 66, Berlin, 2000), pp. 215 ? 217 F. Tauser, R. Huber, A. Brodschelm, and A. Leitenstorfer Fully Coherent Generation and Detection of Tunable Femtosecond Pulses approaching the NIR ITW 2000, Sandbjerg Castle, Denmark (17-19 September 2000) Last modified: 10.04.2014 by Webmaster</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/huber/research.html</field>
<field name="title">Lehrstuhl Huber</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/huber/research.html</field>
<field name="content">Lehrstuhl Huber Lehrstuhl Huber Internal | Search | About      Home  Events  People  Teaching  Research Non-adiabatic light-matter coupling Quantum electronics THz nonlinear optics  Publications  Contact         Department of Physics &amp;gt; LS Huber &amp;gt; AG Huber &amp;gt; Research Ultrafast quantum dynamics and photonics Our scientific focus is set on ultrafast phenomena dominating the physics of solids, molecules and custom tailored nanostructures. We aim to understand and control the microscopic interplay between elementary degrees of freedom and exploit this knowledge to design quantum systems with novel functionalities. As the essential tool box, we conceive highly intense sources of ultrashort phase-locked laser pulses as well as field-sensitive detectors for the entire infrared and terahertz window of the electromagnetic spectrum. Similarly to an extreme slow motion camera, this technology allows us to capture and control elementary quantum dynamics on the femtosecond scale (1 fs = 1015 s). In particular, the availability of record-intense and ultrashort electric and magnetic field transients allows us to study matter under unprecedented high-field conditions and reach an extremely non-adiabatic limit of light-matter interaction. Exciting new pathways to quantum electronics, quantum optics and quantum electrodynamics have been opened. Our current list of projects includes: Ultrastrong and non-adiabatic light-matter coupling Quantum electronics of strongly correlated materials Terahertz nonlinear optics Femtosecond photonics Please, take a look at our publications for a comprehensive overview over our latest results. Last modified: 22.02.2011 by Webmaster</field>
<field name="important">Lehrstuhl Huber Lehrstuhl Huber Internal | Search | About      Home  Events  People  Teaching  Research Non-adiabatic light-matter coupling Quantum electronics THz nonlinear optics  Publications  Contact         Department of Physics &amp;gt; LS Huber &amp;gt; AG Huber &amp;gt; Research Ultrafast quantum dynamics and photonics Our scientific focus is set on ultrafast phenomena dominating the physics of solids, molecules and custom tailored nanostructures. We aim to understand and control the microscopic interplay between elementary degrees of freedom and exploit this knowledge to design quantum systems with novel functionalities. As the essential tool box, we conceive highly intense sources of ultrashort phase-locked laser pulses as well as field-sensitive detectors for the entire infrared and terahertz window of the electromagnetic spectrum. Similarly to an extreme slow motion camera, this technology allows us to capture and control elementary quantum dynamics on the femtosecond scale (1 fs = 1015 s). In particular, the availability of record-intense and ultrashort electric and magnetic field transients allows us to study matter under unprecedented high-field conditions and reach an extremely non-adiabatic limit of light-matter interaction. Exciting new pathways to quantum electronics, quantum optics and quantum electrodynamics have been opened. Our current list of projects includes: Ultrastrong and non-adiabatic light-matter coupling Quantum electronics of strongly correlated materials Terahertz nonlinear optics Femtosecond photonics Please, take a look at our publications for a comprehensive overview over our latest results. Last modified: 22.02.2011 by Webmaster</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/huber/ruperthuber.html</field>
<field name="title">Lehrstuhl Huber</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/huber/ruperthuber.html</field>
<field name="content">Lehrstuhl Huber Lehrstuhl Huber Internal | Search | About      Home  Events  People Our group Open positions Alumni  Teaching  Research  Publications  Contact         Department of Physics &amp;gt; LS Huber &amp;gt; AG Huber &amp;gt; People &amp;gt; Rupert Huber Prof. Dr. rer. nat. Rupert Huber Office PHY 2.1.18 Phone +49 941 943-2070, 2071 Fax +49 941 943-4223 e-Mail rupert.huberphysik.uni-regensburg.de Postal address Institut für Experimentelle und Angewandte Physik Universität Regensburg Universitätsstraße 31 93053 Regensburg Germany Academic career 1994 - 1999 Studies of physics at Technische Universität München (TUM), Munich, Germany, and UC Berkeley, California, USA, Diploma of Physics from TUM 2000 Guest scientist at Hong Kong Baptist University, Hong Kong, China 2001 - 2003 Graduation at the Department of Physics at TUM (E11, Prof. A. Laubereau) 2004 Postdoc at the Department of Physics at TUM 2004 - 2006 Alexander von Humboldt Fellow (Feodor Lynen Program) with Daniel Chemla's group at Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory and UC Berkeley, California, USA 2007 - 2010 Emmy Noether group leader at University of Konstanz (Chair of Prof. A. Leitenstorfer) since 2010 Chair for experimental and applied physics, University of Regensburg Prizes and honors 1994 - 2000 Fellowship for "highly talented students", by the State of Bavaria 2004 - 2006 Feodor-Lynen Fellowship of the Alexander von Humboldt Foundation (AvH) since 2007 Emmy-Noether Fellowship of the German Research Foundation (DFG) 2008 European THz Young Investigator Award 2008 of the European Optical Society 2009 Rudolf Kaiser Prize 2009 2012 ERC Starting Grant List of selected publications For a list of the most important publications by Rupert Huber, please, see menu item Publications. Last modified: 22.02.2011 by Webmaster</field>
<field name="important">Lehrstuhl Huber Lehrstuhl Huber Internal | Search | About      Home  Events  People Our group Open positions Alumni  Teaching  Research  Publications  Contact         Department of Physics &amp;gt; LS Huber &amp;gt; AG Huber &amp;gt; People &amp;gt; Rupert Huber Prof. Dr. rer. nat. Rupert Huber Office PHY 2.1.18 Phone +49 941 943-2070, 2071 Fax +49 941 943-4223 e-Mail rupert.huberphysik.uni-regensburg.de Postal address Institut für Experimentelle und Angewandte Physik Universität Regensburg Universitätsstraße 31 93053 Regensburg Germany Academic career 1994 - 1999 Studies of physics at Technische Universität München (TUM), Munich, Germany, and UC Berkeley, California, USA, Diploma of Physics from TUM 2000 Guest scientist at Hong Kong Baptist University, Hong Kong, China 2001 - 2003 Graduation at the Department of Physics at TUM (E11, Prof. A. Laubereau) 2004 Postdoc at the Department of Physics at TUM 2004 - 2006 Alexander von Humboldt Fellow (Feodor Lynen Program) with Daniel Chemla's group at Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory and UC Berkeley, California, USA 2007 - 2010 Emmy Noether group leader at University of Konstanz (Chair of Prof. A. Leitenstorfer) since 2010 Chair for experimental and applied physics, University of Regensburg Prizes and honors 1994 - 2000 Fellowship for "highly talented students", by the State of Bavaria 2004 - 2006 Feodor-Lynen Fellowship of the Alexander von Humboldt Foundation (AvH) since 2007 Emmy-Noether Fellowship of the German Research Foundation (DFG) 2008 European THz Young Investigator Award 2008 of the European Optical Society 2009 Rudolf Kaiser Prize 2009 2012 ERC Starting Grant List of selected publications For a list of the most important publications by Rupert Huber, please, see menu item Publications. Last modified: 22.02.2011 by Webmaster</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/huber/teaching.html</field>
<field name="title">Lehrstuhl Huber</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/huber/teaching.html</field>
<field name="content">Lehrstuhl Huber Lehrstuhl Huber Internal | Search | About      Home  Events  People  Teaching Struktur der Materie I Nichtlineare Optik Statistische Physik und Festkörperphysik Programmieren in C und C++ Technische EDV Bernhard Hess-Dozentur  Research  Publications  Contact         Department of Physics &amp;gt; LS Huber &amp;gt; AG Huber &amp;gt; Teaching Sommersemester 2014 Struktur der Materie I (Huber) Struktur der Materie IIa (Festkörperphysik) für LA Gy mit Übungen(Schuh) Elektronik für LA (Schuh/Wünsch) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Molekularstrahlepitaxie (Bougeard/Schuh) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Ultrakurzzeitphysik (Huber) Wintersemester 2013/2014 Integrierter Kurs II: Statistische Physik und Festkörperphysik (Grifoni/Huber) Elektronik für LA (Schuh/Wünsch) Technische EDV: Regelung, Messdatenerfassung, Digitale Signalverarbeitung (Schuh/Wünsch) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Molekularstrahlepitaxie (Bougeard/Schuh) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Ultrakurzzeitphysik (Huber) Sommersemester 2013 Struktur der Materie I (Huber) Struktur der Materie IIa (Festkörperphysik) für LA Gy mit Übungen (Schuh) Elektronik für LA (Schuh/Wünsch) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Molekularstrahlepitaxie (Bougeard/Schuh) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Ultrakurzzeitphysik (Huber) Wintersemester 2012/2013 Nichtlineare Optik (Huber) Programmieren in C und C++ (Schuh) Technische EDV: Regelung, Messdatenerfassung, Digitale Signalverarbeitung (Schuh/Wünsch) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Molekularstrahlepitaxie (Bougeard/Schuh) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Ultrakurzzeitphysik (Huber) Sommersemester 2012 Struktur der Materie I (Huber) Programmieren in C und C++ (Schuh) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Molekularstrahlepitaxie (Bougeard/Schuh) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Ultrakurzzeitphysik (Huber) Wintersemester 2011/2012 Integrierter Kurs II: Statistische Physik und Festkörperphysik (Grifoni/Huber) Programmieren in C und C++ (Schuh) Technische EDV: Regelung, Messdatenerfassung, Digitale Signalverarbeitung (Schuh/Wünsch) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Molekularstrahlepitaxie (Bougeard/Schuh) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Ultrakurzzeitphysik (Huber) Sommersemester 2011 Struktur der Materie I (Huber) ?Spektroskopie und Photonik mit Femtosekunden-Lasern: Von den Grundlagen über Terahertz-Strahlung bis zu ultraschnellen nano-optischen Schaltern? (Kampfrath) Programmieren in C und C++ (Schuh) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Molekularstrahlepitaxie (Bougeard/Schuh) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Ultrakurzzeitphysik (Huber) Last modified: 12.02.2014 by Webmaster</field>
<field name="important">Lehrstuhl Huber Lehrstuhl Huber Internal | Search | About      Home  Events  People  Teaching Struktur der Materie I Nichtlineare Optik Statistische Physik und Festkörperphysik Programmieren in C und C++ Technische EDV Bernhard Hess-Dozentur  Research  Publications  Contact         Department of Physics &amp;gt; LS Huber &amp;gt; AG Huber &amp;gt; Teaching Sommersemester 2014 Struktur der Materie I (Huber) Struktur der Materie IIa (Festkörperphysik) für LA Gy mit Übungen(Schuh) Elektronik für LA (Schuh/Wünsch) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Molekularstrahlepitaxie (Bougeard/Schuh) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Ultrakurzzeitphysik (Huber) Wintersemester 2013/2014 Integrierter Kurs II: Statistische Physik und Festkörperphysik (Grifoni/Huber) Elektronik für LA (Schuh/Wünsch) Technische EDV: Regelung, Messdatenerfassung, Digitale Signalverarbeitung (Schuh/Wünsch) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Molekularstrahlepitaxie (Bougeard/Schuh) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Ultrakurzzeitphysik (Huber) Sommersemester 2013 Struktur der Materie I (Huber) Struktur der Materie IIa (Festkörperphysik) für LA Gy mit Übungen (Schuh) Elektronik für LA (Schuh/Wünsch) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Molekularstrahlepitaxie (Bougeard/Schuh) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Ultrakurzzeitphysik (Huber) Wintersemester 2012/2013 Nichtlineare Optik (Huber) Programmieren in C und C++ (Schuh) Technische EDV: Regelung, Messdatenerfassung, Digitale Signalverarbeitung (Schuh/Wünsch) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Molekularstrahlepitaxie (Bougeard/Schuh) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Ultrakurzzeitphysik (Huber) Sommersemester 2012 Struktur der Materie I (Huber) Programmieren in C und C++ (Schuh) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Molekularstrahlepitaxie (Bougeard/Schuh) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Ultrakurzzeitphysik (Huber) Wintersemester 2011/2012 Integrierter Kurs II: Statistische Physik und Festkörperphysik (Grifoni/Huber) Programmieren in C und C++ (Schuh) Technische EDV: Regelung, Messdatenerfassung, Digitale Signalverarbeitung (Schuh/Wünsch) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Molekularstrahlepitaxie (Bougeard/Schuh) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Ultrakurzzeitphysik (Huber) Sommersemester 2011 Struktur der Materie I (Huber) ?Spektroskopie und Photonik mit Femtosekunden-Lasern: Von den Grundlagen über Terahertz-Strahlung bis zu ultraschnellen nano-optischen Schaltern? (Kampfrath) Programmieren in C und C++ (Schuh) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Molekularstrahlepitaxie (Bougeard/Schuh) Seminar zu speziellen Fragen der Ultrakurzzeitphysik (Huber) Last modified: 12.02.2014 by Webmaster</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/huber/tylercocker.html</field>
<field name="title">Lehrstuhl Huber</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/huber/tylercocker.html</field>
<field name="content">Lehrstuhl Huber Lehrstuhl Huber Internal | Search | About      Home  Events  People Our group Open positions Alumni  Teaching  Research  Publications  Contact         Department of Physics &amp;gt; LS Huber &amp;gt; AG Huber &amp;gt; People &amp;gt; Tyler Cocker Dr. Tyler Cocker Office PHY 2.1.10 Phone +49 941 943-2067 Fax +49 941 943-4223 e-Mail tyler.cockerphysik.uni-regensburg.de Postal address Institut für Experimentelle und Angewandte Physik Universität Regensburg Universitätsstraße 31 93053 Regensburg Germany Academic career September 2002 - May 2006 Bachelor of Science, Honours Physics with distinction, Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Victoria, British Columbia, Canada September 2006 - July 2012 Doctor of Philosophy in Physics, University of Alberta, Alberta, Canada Thesis title: Exploring conductivity in nanomaterials with terahertz pulses Advisor: Prof. Frank A. Hegmann Since September 2012 Postdoctoral researcher with Prof. Rupert Huber Since September 2013 Alexander von Humboldt Fellow hosted by Prof. Rupert Huber List of selected publications J. M. LaForge, T. L. Cocker, A. L. Beaudry, K. Cui, R. T. Tucker, M. T. Taschuk, F. A. Hegmann, and M. J. Brett Conductivity control of as-grown branched indium tin oxide nanowire networks Nanotechnology 25, 035701 (2014) T. L. Cocker and R. Huber A new twist on terahertz pulses Nature Photon. 7, 678-679 (2013) T. L. Cocker, V. Jelic, M. Gupta, S. J. Molesky, J. A. J. Burgess, G. De Los Reyes, L. V. Titova, Y. Y. Tsui, M. R. Freeman, and F. A. Hegmann An ultrafast terahertz scanning tunnelling microscope Nature Photon. 7, 620 (2013) T. L. Cocker, L. V. Titova, S. Fourmaux, G. Holloway, H.-C. Bandulet, D. Brassard, J.-C. Kieffer, M. A. El Khakani, and F. A. Hegmann Phase diagram of the ultrafast photoinduced insulator-metal phase transition in vanadium dioxide Phys. Rev. B 85, 155120 (2012) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science L. V. Titova, T. L. Cocker, D. G. Cooke, X. Wang, A. Meldrum, and F. A. Hegmann Ultrafast percolative transport dynamics in silicon nanocrystal films Phys. Rev. B 83, 085403 (2011) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science T. L. Cocker, L. V. Titova, S. Fourmaux, H.-C. Bandulet, D. Brassard, J.-C. Kieffer, M. A. El Khakani, and F. A. Hegmann Terahertz conductivity of the metal-insulator transition in a nanogranular VO2 film Appl. Phys. Lett. 97, 221905 (2010) G. Sharma, L. Razzari, F. H. Su, F. Blanchard, A. Ayesheshim, T. L. Cocker, L. V. Titova, T. Ozaki, J.-C. Kieffer, R. Morandotti, M. Reid, and F. A. Hegmann Time-resolved terahertz spectroscopy of free carrier nonlinear dynamics in semiconductors IEEE Photonics Journal 2, 578 (2010) F. H. Su, F. Blanchard, G. Sharma, L. Razzari, A. Ayesheshim, T. L. Cocker, L. V. Titova, T. Ozaki, J.-C. Kieffer, R. Morandotti, M. Reid, and F. A. Hegmann Terahertz pulse induced intervalley scattering in photoexcited GaAs Opt. Express 17, 9620 (2009) Last modified: 19.12.2013 by Webmaster</field>
<field name="important">Lehrstuhl Huber Lehrstuhl Huber Internal | Search | About      Home  Events  People Our group Open positions Alumni  Teaching  Research  Publications  Contact         Department of Physics &amp;gt; LS Huber &amp;gt; AG Huber &amp;gt; People &amp;gt; Tyler Cocker Dr. Tyler Cocker Office PHY 2.1.10 Phone +49 941 943-2067 Fax +49 941 943-4223 e-Mail tyler.cockerphysik.uni-regensburg.de Postal address Institut für Experimentelle und Angewandte Physik Universität Regensburg Universitätsstraße 31 93053 Regensburg Germany Academic career September 2002 - May 2006 Bachelor of Science, Honours Physics with distinction, Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Victoria, British Columbia, Canada September 2006 - July 2012 Doctor of Philosophy in Physics, University of Alberta, Alberta, Canada Thesis title: Exploring conductivity in nanomaterials with terahertz pulses Advisor: Prof. Frank A. Hegmann Since September 2012 Postdoctoral researcher with Prof. Rupert Huber Since September 2013 Alexander von Humboldt Fellow hosted by Prof. Rupert Huber List of selected publications J. M. LaForge, T. L. Cocker, A. L. Beaudry, K. Cui, R. T. Tucker, M. T. Taschuk, F. A. Hegmann, and M. J. Brett Conductivity control of as-grown branched indium tin oxide nanowire networks Nanotechnology 25, 035701 (2014) T. L. Cocker and R. Huber A new twist on terahertz pulses Nature Photon. 7, 678-679 (2013) T. L. Cocker, V. Jelic, M. Gupta, S. J. Molesky, J. A. J. Burgess, G. De Los Reyes, L. V. Titova, Y. Y. Tsui, M. R. Freeman, and F. A. Hegmann An ultrafast terahertz scanning tunnelling microscope Nature Photon. 7, 620 (2013) T. L. Cocker, L. V. Titova, S. Fourmaux, G. Holloway, H.-C. Bandulet, D. Brassard, J.-C. Kieffer, M. A. El Khakani, and F. A. Hegmann Phase diagram of the ultrafast photoinduced insulator-metal phase transition in vanadium dioxide Phys. Rev. B 85, 155120 (2012) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science L. V. Titova, T. L. Cocker, D. G. Cooke, X. Wang, A. Meldrum, and F. A. Hegmann Ultrafast percolative transport dynamics in silicon nanocrystal films Phys. Rev. B 83, 085403 (2011) This publication has been selected for the Virtual Journal of Ultrafast Science T. L. Cocker, L. V. Titova, S. Fourmaux, H.-C. Bandulet, D. Brassard, J.-C. Kieffer, M. A. El Khakani, and F. A. Hegmann Terahertz conductivity of the metal-insulator transition in a nanogranular VO2 film Appl. Phys. Lett. 97, 221905 (2010) G. Sharma, L. Razzari, F. H. Su, F. Blanchard, A. Ayesheshim, T. L. Cocker, L. V. Titova, T. Ozaki, J.-C. Kieffer, R. Morandotti, M. Reid, and F. A. Hegmann Time-resolved terahertz spectroscopy of free carrier nonlinear dynamics in semiconductors IEEE Photonics Journal 2, 578 (2010) F. H. Su, F. Blanchard, G. Sharma, L. Razzari, A. Ayesheshim, T. L. Cocker, L. V. Titova, T. Ozaki, J.-C. Kieffer, R. Morandotti, M. Reid, and F. A. Hegmann Terahertz pulse induced intervalley scattering in photoexcited GaAs Opt. Express 17, 9620 (2009) Last modified: 19.12.2013 by Webmaster</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/institute_e.phtml</field>
<field name="title">Physics ? Research ? Institutes and Chairs</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/institute_e.phtml</field>
<field name="content">Physics ? Research ? Institutes and Chairs Physics ? Research ? Institutes and Chairs Institutes and Chairs I. Faculty of the Institute of Theoretical Physics Chair Professor Braun Vladimir Braun Quantum field theory and quantum chromodynamics Tilo Wettig Lattice quantum chromodynamics, QCD on a Chip Falk Bruckmann Lattice quantum chromodynamics and solitons Chair Professor Grifoni Milena Grifoni Quantum transport and dissipation Thomas Niehaus Light Matter Interaction in Nanostructures John Schliemann Spin dynamics in semiconductor nanostructures, spintronics Chair Professor Richter Klaus Richter, Jens Siewert Complex quantum systems Jaroslav Fabian Spintronics Tobias Kramer Quantum dynamics in mesoscopic and atomic Systems Chair Professor Schäfer Andreas Schäfer Quantum chromodynamics and hadron physics Gunnar Bali Lattice QCD and Hadron Physics Dirk Pleiter Lattice quantum chromodynamics and Supercomputing Professor Morgenstern Ingo Morgenstern Superconductivity, optimization of industrial processes II. Faculty of the Institute of Experimental and Applied Physics Chair Professor Back Christian Back Magnetism, magneto-electronics Josef Zweck Electron microscopy Chair Professor Giessibl Franz J. Giessibl Atomic Force Microscopy Jascha Repp Scanning tunneling microscopy Chair Prof. Lupton John Lupton Organic semiconductors, optical nanostructures Christian Schüller Optical spectroscopy on semiconductor quantum structures Tobias Korn Spin and charge carrier dynamics in semiconductors, optical spectroscopy Chair Professor Huber Rupert Huber Ultrafast quantum physics and photonics Dominique Bougeard Low Dimensional Semiconductor Systems Chair Professor Weiss Dieter Weiss Semiconducting nanostructures Christoph Strunk Mesoscopic systems Andreas Hüttel Carbon Nanotube Transport and Nanomechanics Jonathan Eroms Graphene Professor Ganichev Sergey Ganichev Terahertz Physics III. Didactics of Physics Prof. Rincke IV. Natural science and technics Prof. Göhring   Legal Notice Last modified: 12 th May, 2014 by Webmaster</field>
<field name="important">Physics ? Research ? Institutes and Chairs Physics ? Research ? Institutes and Chairs Institutes and Chairs I. Faculty of the Institute of Theoretical Physics Chair Professor Braun Vladimir Braun Quantum field theory and quantum chromodynamics Tilo Wettig Lattice quantum chromodynamics, QCD on a Chip Falk Bruckmann Lattice quantum chromodynamics and solitons Chair Professor Grifoni Milena Grifoni Quantum transport and dissipation Thomas Niehaus Light Matter Interaction in Nanostructures John Schliemann Spin dynamics in semiconductor nanostructures, spintronics Chair Professor Richter Klaus Richter, Jens Siewert Complex quantum systems Jaroslav Fabian Spintronics Tobias Kramer Quantum dynamics in mesoscopic and atomic Systems Chair Professor Schäfer Andreas Schäfer Quantum chromodynamics and hadron physics Gunnar Bali Lattice QCD and Hadron Physics Dirk Pleiter Lattice quantum chromodynamics and Supercomputing Professor Morgenstern Ingo Morgenstern Superconductivity, optimization of industrial processes II. Faculty of the Institute of Experimental and Applied Physics Chair Professor Back Christian Back Magnetism, magneto-electronics Josef Zweck Electron microscopy Chair Professor Giessibl Franz J. Giessibl Atomic Force Microscopy Jascha Repp Scanning tunneling microscopy Chair Prof. Lupton John Lupton Organic semiconductors, optical nanostructures Christian Schüller Optical spectroscopy on semiconductor quantum structures Tobias Korn Spin and charge carrier dynamics in semiconductors, optical spectroscopy Chair Professor Huber Rupert Huber Ultrafast quantum physics and photonics Dominique Bougeard Low Dimensional Semiconductor Systems Chair Professor Weiss Dieter Weiss Semiconducting nanostructures Christoph Strunk Mesoscopic systems Andreas Hüttel Carbon Nanotube Transport and Nanomechanics Jonathan Eroms Graphene Professor Ganichev Sergey Ganichev Terahertz Physics III. Didactics of Physics Prof. Rincke IV. Natural science and technics Prof. Göhring   Legal Notice Last modified: 12 th May, 2014 by Webmaster</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/keller/h.html</field>
<field name="title">menue</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/keller/h.html</field>
<field name="content">menue menue</field>
<field name="important">menue menue</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/keller/leer.html</field>
<field name="title"></field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/keller/leer.html</field>
<field name="content"> </field>
<field name="important"> </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/keller/p.html</field>
<field name="title">menue</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/keller/p.html</field>
<field name="content">menue menue</field>
<field name="important">menue menue</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/kramer/</field>
<field name="title">Welcome</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/kramer/</field>
<field name="content">Welcome Welcome Language: de | en Institut für Theoretische Physik I Universität Regensburg Emmy Noether Gruppe Quantendynamik Menu: Research Blog Have a look at our research blog with posts about GPU computing semiclassics Hall effect and more Welcome at the research group ?Quantumdynamics? at the Institute for theoretical physics, Universität Regensburg, Germany. Starting in April 2013, I will relocate to Berlin. Please update your links to the new homepage at quantumdynamics.de of Dr. Tobias Kramer, Institut für Physik, Humboldt Universität zu Berlin. Copyright © 2009 Tobias Kramer | Generated by webgen | Design by Andreas Viklund</field>
<field name="important">Welcome Welcome Language: de | en Institut für Theoretische Physik I Universität Regensburg Emmy Noether Gruppe Quantendynamik Menu: Research Blog Have a look at our research blog with posts about GPU computing semiclassics Hall effect and more Welcome at the research group ?Quantumdynamics? at the Institute for theoretical physics, Universität Regensburg, Germany. Starting in April 2013, I will relocate to Berlin. Please update your links to the new homepage at quantumdynamics.de of Dr. Tobias Kramer, Institut für Physik, Humboldt Universität zu Berlin. Copyright © 2009 Tobias Kramer | Generated by webgen | Design by Andreas Viklund</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/kramer/publications.html</field>
<field name="title">Publications</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/kramer/publications.html</field>
<field name="content">Publications Publications Language: de | en Institut für Theoretische Physik I Universität Regensburg Emmy Noether Gruppe Quantendynamik Menu: Welcome Group Research Transport through nanostructures Photosynthesis Interacting many-body systems Atom laser Photoionisation Mathematical Physics Time in QM Collaborations Lectures Meetings Where to meet us? Conference 2007 Time-Dependent Phenomena in Quantum Mechanics Publications Links Research Blog Have a look at our research blog with posts about GPU computing semiclassics Hall effect and more Preprints Publications (article and arxiv versions may differ slightly) [36] Exciton Dynamics Lab for Light-Harvesting Complexes (GPU-HEOM) C. Kreisbeck and T. Kramer Public online tool at nanohub.org tool open access nanohub [35] Interacting electrons in a magnetic field: mapping quantum mechanics to a classical ersatz-system T. Kramer AIP Conference Proceedings, 1488, 394 (2012) article arxiv NASA [34] Long-Lived Electronic Coherence in Dissipative Exciton-Dynamics of Light-Harvesting Complexes C. Kreisbeck, T. Kramer Journal of Physical Chemistry Letters, 3, 2828 (2012) article arxiv NASA [33] Modelling of Oscillations in Two-Dimensional Echo-Spectra of the Fenna-Matthews-Olson Complex B.Hein, C. Kreisbeck, T. Kramer, M. Rodríguez New Journal of Physics, 14, 023018 (2012) article Open Access NASA [32] Comment on ?Screening model of metallic nonideal contacts in the integer quantized Hall regime? T. Kramer, V. Krueckl, E. Heller, and R. Parrott Phys. Rev. B, 84, 197301 (2011) article arxiv NASA [31] Spectra of harmonium in a magnetic field using an initial value representation of the semiclassical propagator F. Grossmann, T. Kramer J. Phys. A: Math. Theor., 44, 445309 (2011) article arxiv NASA [30] Fluctuations in the spectra of open few-body systems J. Eiglsperger, T. Kramer, J. Madroñero New Journal of Physics, 13, 063033 (2011) article Open Access NASA [29] High-performance solution of hierarchical equations of motions for studying energy-transfer in light-harvesting complexes C. Kreisbeck, T. Kramer, M. Rodríguez, B.Hein Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation, 7, 2166 (2011) article arxiv NASA [28] Time dependent approach to transport and scattering in atomic and mesoscopic systems T. Kramer AIP Conf. Proc., 1334, 142 (2011) article arxiv NASA [27] Two interacting electrons in a magnetic field: comparison of semiclassical, quantum, and variational solutions T. Kramer AIP Conf. Proc., 1323, 178 (2010) article arxiv NASA [26] Phase shifts and phase pi-jumps in four-terminal waveguide Aharonov-Bohm interferometers C. Kreisbeck, T. Kramer, S. Buchholz, S. Fischer, U. Kunze, D. Reuter, A. Wieck Phys. Rev. B, 82, 165329 (2010) article arxiv NASA [25] Self-consistent calculation of electric potentials in Hall devices T. Kramer, V. Krueckl, E. Heller, and R. Parrott Phys. Rev. B, 81, 205306 (2010) article arxiv NASA [24] Wave packet approach to transport in mesoscopic systems T. Kramer, C. Kreisbeck, and V. Krueckl Physica Scripta, 82, 038101 (2010) article arxiv NASA [23] Theory of the quantum Hall effect in finite graphene devices T. Kramer, C. Kreisbeck, V. Krueckl, E. Heller, R. Parrott, and C.-T. Liang Phys. Rev. B, 81, 081410(R) (2010) article arxiv NASA [22] Revivals of quantum wave-packets in graphene V. Krueckl and T. Kramer New Journal of Physics, 11, 093010 (2009) [Open Access] article arxiv NASA [21] Use of Lambert?s Theorem for the n-Dimensional Coulomb Problem V. Kanellopoulos, M. Kleber, and T. Kramer Phys. Rev. A, 80, 012101 (2009) article arxiv NASA [20] Quasiperiodic propagation in time of some classical/quantum systems: Nielsen?s conserved quantity and Floquet properties P. Kramer, T. Kramer, and V.I. Man?ko Physica Scripta, 79, 055006 (2009) article arxiv NASA [19] An efficient and accurate method to obtain the energy-dependent Green function for general potentials T. Kramer, E. Heller, and R. Parrott J. Phys.: Conference Series, 99 012010 (2008) Open Access article arxiv NASA [18] Imaging Magnetic Focusing of Coherent Electron Waves K. Aidala, R. Parrott, T. Kramer, R. Westervelt, E. Heller, M. Hanson, and A. Gossard Nature Physics, 3, 464-468 (2007) article arxiv NASA [17] New mathematical tools for quantum technology C. Bracher, M. Kleber, and T. Kramer Mathematics of Quantum Computation and Technology, edited by G. Chen, L. Kauffman, S. Lomonaco, Chapman and Hill/CRC (2007) book arxiv NASA [16] Quantum theory of an atom laser originating from a Bose-Einstein condensate or a Fermi gas in the presence of gravity T. Kramer and M. Rodríguez Phys. Rev. A, 74, 013611-1-13 (2006) article arxiv NASA [15] Landau level broadening without disorder, non-integer plateaus without interactions ? an alternative model of the quantum Hall effect T. Kramer Revista Mexicana de Física S, 52, 49-55 (2006) article arxiv NASA [14] Electron dynamics in parallel electric and magnetic fields C. Bracher, T. Kramer, and J. Delos Phys. Rev. A, 73, 062114-1-21 (2006) article arxiv NASA [13] A heuristic quantum theory of the integer quantum Hall effect T. Kramer International Journal of Modern Physics B, 20, 1243-1260 (2006) article arxiv NASA [12] The photoelectric effect in external fields C. Bracher, J. Delos, V. Kanellopoulos, M. Kleber, and T. Kramer Physics Letters A, 317, 62-66 (2005) article arxiv NASA [11] Transient effects in two channel interactions and an application to the behaviour of a time-dependent shutter T. Kramer and M. Moshinsky Revista Mexicana de Física, 51, 407-414 (2005) article Open Access NASA [10] Tunnelling out of a time-dependent well T. Kramer and M. Moshinsky J. Phys. A, 38, 5993-6003 (2005), AMS Review MR2167958 article arxiv NASA [9] Electron drift orbits in crossed electromagnetic fields and the quantum Hall effect T. Kramer Group theoretical methods in physics. Institute of Physics Conference Series Number 185., Edited by G.S. Pogosyan, L.E. Vicent and K.B. Wolf, Cocoyoc, Mexico, pp. 353-358 (2004) book arxiv NASA [8] Propagation in crossed magnetic and electric fields: The quantum source approach T. Kramer and C. Bracher Symmetries in Science XI, Edited by B. Gruber, G. Marmo, and N. Yoshinaga, Kluwer, Dordrecht (2004) book arxiv NASA [7] Matter waves from localized quantum sources T. Kramer Squeezed States and Uncertainty Relations, Edited by H. Moya-Cessa et al., pp. 210-217, Rinton Press, Princeton, NJ (2003) book arxiv NASA [6] Electron propagation in crossed magnetic and electric fields T. Kramer, C. Bracher, and M. Kleber J. Opt. B: Quantum Semiclass. Opt., 6, 21-27 (2004) article arxiv NASA [5] Observed photodetachment in parallel electric and magnetic fields J.N. Yukich, T. Kramer, and C. Bracher Phys. Rev. A, 68, 033412-1-8 (2003) article arxiv NASA [4] Ballistic matter waves with angular momentum: Exact solutions and applications C. Bracher, T. Kramer, and M. Kleber Phys. Rev. A, 67, 043601 (2003) article arxiv NASA [3] Matter waves from quantum sources in a force field T. Kramer, C. Bracher, and M. Kleber J. Phys. A: Math. Gen., 35, 8361 (2002) article arxiv NASA [2] Four-path interference and uncertainty principle in photodetachment microscopy T. Kramer, C. Bracher, and M. Kleber Europhys. Lett., 56, 471 (2001) article arxiv NASA [1] Exact electron states in 1d (quasi-) periodic arrays of delta-potentials P. Kramer and T. Kramer From quasicrystals to more complex systems: Les Houches School (1998) book arxiv   NASA Diplom and Doctoral Thesis [T2] Matter waves from quantum sources in a force field T. Kramer Technische Universität München, Germany (2003) thesis [T1] Quantum ballistic motion in electric and magnetic fields T. Kramer Technische Universität München, Germany (2000) unpublished Some publications in Nature [N2] Making the move from physics to finance T. Kramer and A. Wilson Nature, 425, 11 September 2003, pp. 220-221 article [N1] Aid workers fear impending disaster in Basra Q. Schiermeier and T. Kramer Nature, 422, 3 April 2003, p. 459 article Copyright © 2009 Tobias Kramer | Generated by webgen | Design by Andreas Viklund</field>
<field name="important">Publications Publications Language: de | en Institut für Theoretische Physik I Universität Regensburg Emmy Noether Gruppe Quantendynamik Menu: Welcome Group Research Transport through nanostructures Photosynthesis Interacting many-body systems Atom laser Photoionisation Mathematical Physics Time in QM Collaborations Lectures Meetings Where to meet us? Conference 2007 Time-Dependent Phenomena in Quantum Mechanics Publications Links Research Blog Have a look at our research blog with posts about GPU computing semiclassics Hall effect and more Preprints Publications (article and arxiv versions may differ slightly) [36] Exciton Dynamics Lab for Light-Harvesting Complexes (GPU-HEOM) C. Kreisbeck and T. Kramer Public online tool at nanohub.org tool open access nanohub [35] Interacting electrons in a magnetic field: mapping quantum mechanics to a classical ersatz-system T. Kramer AIP Conference Proceedings, 1488, 394 (2012) article arxiv NASA [34] Long-Lived Electronic Coherence in Dissipative Exciton-Dynamics of Light-Harvesting Complexes C. Kreisbeck, T. Kramer Journal of Physical Chemistry Letters, 3, 2828 (2012) article arxiv NASA [33] Modelling of Oscillations in Two-Dimensional Echo-Spectra of the Fenna-Matthews-Olson Complex B.Hein, C. Kreisbeck, T. Kramer, M. Rodríguez New Journal of Physics, 14, 023018 (2012) article Open Access NASA [32] Comment on ?Screening model of metallic nonideal contacts in the integer quantized Hall regime? T. Kramer, V. Krueckl, E. Heller, and R. Parrott Phys. Rev. B, 84, 197301 (2011) article arxiv NASA [31] Spectra of harmonium in a magnetic field using an initial value representation of the semiclassical propagator F. Grossmann, T. Kramer J. Phys. A: Math. Theor., 44, 445309 (2011) article arxiv NASA [30] Fluctuations in the spectra of open few-body systems J. Eiglsperger, T. Kramer, J. Madroñero New Journal of Physics, 13, 063033 (2011) article Open Access NASA [29] High-performance solution of hierarchical equations of motions for studying energy-transfer in light-harvesting complexes C. Kreisbeck, T. Kramer, M. Rodríguez, B.Hein Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation, 7, 2166 (2011) article arxiv NASA [28] Time dependent approach to transport and scattering in atomic and mesoscopic systems T. Kramer AIP Conf. Proc., 1334, 142 (2011) article arxiv NASA [27] Two interacting electrons in a magnetic field: comparison of semiclassical, quantum, and variational solutions T. Kramer AIP Conf. Proc., 1323, 178 (2010) article arxiv NASA [26] Phase shifts and phase pi-jumps in four-terminal waveguide Aharonov-Bohm interferometers C. Kreisbeck, T. Kramer, S. Buchholz, S. Fischer, U. Kunze, D. Reuter, A. Wieck Phys. Rev. B, 82, 165329 (2010) article arxiv NASA [25] Self-consistent calculation of electric potentials in Hall devices T. Kramer, V. Krueckl, E. Heller, and R. Parrott Phys. Rev. B, 81, 205306 (2010) article arxiv NASA [24] Wave packet approach to transport in mesoscopic systems T. Kramer, C. Kreisbeck, and V. Krueckl Physica Scripta, 82, 038101 (2010) article arxiv NASA [23] Theory of the quantum Hall effect in finite graphene devices T. Kramer, C. Kreisbeck, V. Krueckl, E. Heller, R. Parrott, and C.-T. Liang Phys. Rev. B, 81, 081410(R) (2010) article arxiv NASA [22] Revivals of quantum wave-packets in graphene V. Krueckl and T. Kramer New Journal of Physics, 11, 093010 (2009) [Open Access] article arxiv NASA [21] Use of Lambert?s Theorem for the n-Dimensional Coulomb Problem V. Kanellopoulos, M. Kleber, and T. Kramer Phys. Rev. A, 80, 012101 (2009) article arxiv NASA [20] Quasiperiodic propagation in time of some classical/quantum systems: Nielsen?s conserved quantity and Floquet properties P. Kramer, T. Kramer, and V.I. Man?ko Physica Scripta, 79, 055006 (2009) article arxiv NASA [19] An efficient and accurate method to obtain the energy-dependent Green function for general potentials T. Kramer, E. Heller, and R. Parrott J. Phys.: Conference Series, 99 012010 (2008) Open Access article arxiv NASA [18] Imaging Magnetic Focusing of Coherent Electron Waves K. Aidala, R. Parrott, T. Kramer, R. Westervelt, E. Heller, M. Hanson, and A. Gossard Nature Physics, 3, 464-468 (2007) article arxiv NASA [17] New mathematical tools for quantum technology C. Bracher, M. Kleber, and T. Kramer Mathematics of Quantum Computation and Technology, edited by G. Chen, L. Kauffman, S. Lomonaco, Chapman and Hill/CRC (2007) book arxiv NASA [16] Quantum theory of an atom laser originating from a Bose-Einstein condensate or a Fermi gas in the presence of gravity T. Kramer and M. Rodríguez Phys. Rev. A, 74, 013611-1-13 (2006) article arxiv NASA [15] Landau level broadening without disorder, non-integer plateaus without interactions ? an alternative model of the quantum Hall effect T. Kramer Revista Mexicana de Física S, 52, 49-55 (2006) article arxiv NASA [14] Electron dynamics in parallel electric and magnetic fields C. Bracher, T. Kramer, and J. Delos Phys. Rev. A, 73, 062114-1-21 (2006) article arxiv NASA [13] A heuristic quantum theory of the integer quantum Hall effect T. Kramer International Journal of Modern Physics B, 20, 1243-1260 (2006) article arxiv NASA [12] The photoelectric effect in external fields C. Bracher, J. Delos, V. Kanellopoulos, M. Kleber, and T. Kramer Physics Letters A, 317, 62-66 (2005) article arxiv NASA [11] Transient effects in two channel interactions and an application to the behaviour of a time-dependent shutter T. Kramer and M. Moshinsky Revista Mexicana de Física, 51, 407-414 (2005) article Open Access NASA [10] Tunnelling out of a time-dependent well T. Kramer and M. Moshinsky J. Phys. A, 38, 5993-6003 (2005), AMS Review MR2167958 article arxiv NASA [9] Electron drift orbits in crossed electromagnetic fields and the quantum Hall effect T. Kramer Group theoretical methods in physics. Institute of Physics Conference Series Number 185., Edited by G.S. Pogosyan, L.E. Vicent and K.B. Wolf, Cocoyoc, Mexico, pp. 353-358 (2004) book arxiv NASA [8] Propagation in crossed magnetic and electric fields: The quantum source approach T. Kramer and C. Bracher Symmetries in Science XI, Edited by B. Gruber, G. Marmo, and N. Yoshinaga, Kluwer, Dordrecht (2004) book arxiv NASA [7] Matter waves from localized quantum sources T. Kramer Squeezed States and Uncertainty Relations, Edited by H. Moya-Cessa et al., pp. 210-217, Rinton Press, Princeton, NJ (2003) book arxiv NASA [6] Electron propagation in crossed magnetic and electric fields T. Kramer, C. Bracher, and M. Kleber J. Opt. B: Quantum Semiclass. Opt., 6, 21-27 (2004) article arxiv NASA [5] Observed photodetachment in parallel electric and magnetic fields J.N. Yukich, T. Kramer, and C. Bracher Phys. Rev. A, 68, 033412-1-8 (2003) article arxiv NASA [4] Ballistic matter waves with angular momentum: Exact solutions and applications C. Bracher, T. Kramer, and M. Kleber Phys. Rev. A, 67, 043601 (2003) article arxiv NASA [3] Matter waves from quantum sources in a force field T. Kramer, C. Bracher, and M. Kleber J. Phys. A: Math. Gen., 35, 8361 (2002) article arxiv NASA [2] Four-path interference and uncertainty principle in photodetachment microscopy T. Kramer, C. Bracher, and M. Kleber Europhys. Lett., 56, 471 (2001) article arxiv NASA [1] Exact electron states in 1d (quasi-) periodic arrays of delta-potentials P. Kramer and T. Kramer From quasicrystals to more complex systems: Les Houches School (1998) book arxiv   NASA Diplom and Doctoral Thesis [T2] Matter waves from quantum sources in a force field T. Kramer Technische Universität München, Germany (2003) thesis [T1] Quantum ballistic motion in electric and magnetic fields T. Kramer Technische Universität München, Germany (2000) unpublished Some publications in Nature [N2] Making the move from physics to finance T. Kramer and A. Wilson Nature, 425, 11 September 2003, pp. 220-221 article [N1] Aid workers fear impending disaster in Basra Q. Schiermeier and T. Kramer Nature, 422, 3 April 2003, p. 459 article Copyright © 2009 Tobias Kramer | Generated by webgen | Design by Andreas Viklund</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/kreitmeier/</field>
<field name="title">Dr. S. Kreitmeier</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/kreitmeier/</field>
<field name="content">Dr. S. Kreitmeier   Dr. S. Kreitmeier  Prof. Dr. Stefan N. Kreitmeier E-Mail: Stefan.Kreitmeier@physik.uni-regensburg.de Phone: +49 941 943 2322 Fax: +49 941 943 2400 Universit?t Regensburg Institut f?r Experimentelle und Angewandte Physik D-93040 Regensburg, Germany Meine Hauptaufgabe an der Universität Regensburg ist seit einiger Zeit das Schutzrechte-Management Meine früheren Forschungen finden sich unter: Computersimulationen Experimentelles Veröffentlichungen Zur Polymer-Homepage</field>
<field name="important">Dr. S. Kreitmeier   Dr. S. Kreitmeier  Prof. Dr. Stefan N. Kreitmeier E-Mail: Stefan.Kreitmeier@physik.uni-regensburg.de Phone: +49 941 943 2322 Fax: +49 941 943 2400 Universit?t Regensburg Institut f?r Experimentelle und Angewandte Physik D-93040 Regensburg, Germany Meine Hauptaufgabe an der Universität Regensburg ist seit einiger Zeit das Schutzrechte-Management Meine früheren Forschungen finden sich unter: Computersimulationen Experimentelles Veröffentlichungen Zur Polymer-Homepage</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/kreitmeier/veroeffentlichungen.html</field>
<field name="title">Veröffentlichungen von Prof. Dr. S. Kreitmeier</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/kreitmeier/veroeffentlichungen.html</field>
<field name="content">Veröffentlichungen von Prof. Dr. S. Kreitmeier  Veröffentlichungen von Prof. Dr. S. Kreitmeier Veröffentlichungen 1. D. Göritz, J. Kemmerer, S. Kreitmeier, R. Rossbacher Annealing effects in high modulus polyethylene Coll. &amp; Poly. Sci., 261, (1983), 631 2. S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Network properties of mixtures of protonated and deuterated polyethylene Coll. &amp; Poly. Sci., 266, (1988), 235 3. S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz A new model of inhomogeneous deformation used for craze formation Makoromol. Chem., Macromol. Symp., 41, (1991), 253 4. S. Kreitmeier, M. Wittkop, D. Göritz Computer simulation of coil deformation J. Comp. Phys., 112, (1994), 267 5. W. Niedermeier, J. Stierstorfer, S. Kreitmeier, O. Metz, D. Göritz Morphological investigations on carbon black particles by atomic force microscopy Rubber Chem. &amp; Techn., 67, (1994), 148 6. M. Wittkop, J.U. Sommer, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Monte Carlo simulations of a single polymer chain under an external force in two and three dimensions Phys. Rev. E, 49, (1994), 5472 7. W. Niedermeier, H. Raab, J. Stierstorfer, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz The microstructure of carbon black investigated by atomic force microscopy Kautschuk Gummi Kunststoffe, 47, (1994), 799 8. S. N. Kreitmeier, G. L. Liang, D. W. Noid, B. Wunderlich Molecular dynamics simulations of macroscopic vibrations on cooling of superheated polyethylene crystals Polymer International, 36, (1995), 155 9. S. Kreitmeier, M. Wittkop, D. Göritz Computer simulations of energetic and conformational changes in polymer systems Makoromol. Chem.: Macromol. Symp., 100, (1995), 181 10. S. N. Kreitmeier, G. L. Liang, D. W. Noid, B. Wunderlich Molecular dynamics simulations of the temperature dependence of lattice parameters of paraffin crystals during cooling J. Chem. Soc. Faraday Trans., 91, (1995), 2601 11. M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz On the deformation of hard elastic polymers - applicability of the coil-strand transition model Acta Polymerica, 46, (1995), 319 12. W. Niedermeier, H. Raab, P. Maier, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Using lateral force and force modulation to image filled elastomers Kautschuk Gummi Kunststoffe, 48, (1995), 611 13. B. Wunderlich, S. N. Kreitmeier Defects in polymer crystals MRS Bulletin, 20 (1995), 17 14. S. Kreitmeier, M. Wittkop, T. Wagner, D. Göritz, R. Zietz Investigations of hard elastic polypropylene with respect to the coil-strand transtion model Coll. &amp; Polym. Sci., 273, (1995), 1008 15. M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Monte Carlo Simulations of a single polymer chain under extension above and below the Theta-temperature Phys. Rev. E, 53, (1996), 838 16. M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz The distribution function of a single polymer chain with excluded volume in two and three dimensions: A Monte Carlo study J. Chem. Phys., 104, (1996), 351 17. M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz The collapse transition of a single polymer chain in two and three dimensions: A Monte Carlo study J. Chem. Phys., 104, (1996), 3373 18. M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Deformation of a single polymer chain in two dimensions above and below the Theta-temperature: A Monte Carlo study Comput. Polymer Sci., 5, (1995), 187 19. M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Computer simulations on energetic and entropic changes of a single chain under extension J. Chem. Soc. Faraday Trans., 92, (1996), 1375 20. S.N. Kreitmeier, D. W. Noid, B.G. Sumpter Quantum-Monte-Carlo simulations on linear chains Macromol. Theory Simul., 5, (1996), 365 21. S. N. Kreitmeier, G. L. Liang, D. W. Noid, B. G. Sumpter Thermal analysis via molecular dynamics simulation J. Therm. Anal., 46, (1996), 853 22. M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Swelling of subchains with excluded volume in two and three dimensions: A Monte Carlo study Macromolecules, 29, (1996), 4754 23. M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Monte Carlo simulations of the dynamics of single polymer chains above and below the Theta-temperature Comput. &amp; Theo. Polymer Sci., 6, (1996), 41 24. M. Wittkop, T. Hölzl, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz A Monte Carlo study of the glass transition in three dimensional polymer melts J. Non-Cryst. Solids, 201, (1996), 199 25. B. Wunderlich, A. Boller, I. Okazaki, S. Kreitmeier Linearity, steady state, and complex heat capacity in modulated differential scanning calorimetry Thermochimica Acta, 282/283, (1996), 143 26. D. Göritz, S. Kreitmeier, M. Wittkop Micromechanism of the deformation process of macromolecular systems, J. Macromol. Sci.-Phys., B35, (1996), 615 27. B. Wunderlich, A. Boller, I. Okazaki, S. Kreitmeier Modulated differential scanning calorimetry in the glass transition region, II J. Therm. Anal., 47, (1996), 1013 28. W. Gottstein, S. Kreitmeier, M. Wittkop, D. Göritz, F. Gotsis Monte Carlo simulations of a single polymer chain on rough surfaces Polymer, 38, (1997), 1607 29. Th. Hölzl, M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Uniaxial deformation of bridging polymer systems: A Monte Carlo study J. Chem. Phys., 106, (1997), 7792 30. S. Kreitmeier, M. Wittkop, H. L. Trautenberg, T. Hölzl, D. Göritz Large-scale simulations on polymer melts J. Comput. Phys., 133, (1997), 181 31. Th. Hölzl, M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, H.-L. Trautenberg, D. Göritz Structural aspects of the glass transition in three-dimensional polymer melts J. Chem. Soc. Faraday Trans., 93, (1997), 2185 32. Ch. Hagn, M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, H.-L. Trautenberg, Th. Hölzl, D. Göritz The creation and spatial structure of end-linked bimodal polymer networks: A Monte-Carlo study Polym. Gels &amp; Network, 5, (1997), 327 33. A. Michel, S. Kreitmeier Molecular dynamics simulation of the collapse transition of a single polymer chain Comput. &amp; Theo. Polymer Sci, 7, (1998), 113 34. W. Michalke, S. Kreitmeier Quantum-Monte-Carlo simulations of polyethylene European Phys. J. B, 4, (1998), 469 35. J. Fröhlich, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Surface characterization of carbon blacks Kautschuk Gummi Kunststoffe, 51, (1998), 370 36. S. Kreitmeier, M. Wittkop, D. Göritz Computer simulations on the cyclic deformation of a single chain above and below the Theta-temperature Phys. Rev. E, 59, (1999), 1982 37. Th. Hölzl, C. Mesner, M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, S. Kain, D. Göritz Monte Carlo studies on the deformation behaviour of glassy model systems Comput. &amp; Theo. Polym. Sci., 9, (1999), 99 38. A. Michel, S. Kreitmeier, B. Wunderlich Molecular dynamics simulations of the adsorption of single chains on surfaces Springer Proceedings in Physics, 85, (2000), 228 39. S. Kreitmeier Equilibrium and non-equilibrium effects of a single polymer chain during cyclic deformation: A Monte Carlo study J. Chem. Phys., 112, (2000), 6925 40. R. Androsch, I. Moon, S. Kreitmeier, B. Wunderlich Determination of heat capacity with a sawtooth-type, power compensated temperature-modulated DSC Thermochim. Acta, 357-358, (2000), 267 41. Th. Lanzl, J. Ludwig, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz A modified method in dieelectric reearch of carbon black rubber compounds Kautschuk Gummi Kunststoffe, 53, (2000), 638 42. S. Kreitmeier, J. Böhm, D. Göritz Towards a new material law for elastomers: Part I Kautschuk Gummi Kunststoffe, 53, (2000), 716 43. M. Lang, W. Michalke, S. Kreitmeier Optimized decomposition of simulated polymer networks into meshes Macromol. Theo. Simul., 10, (2001), 204 44. M. Lang, W. Michalke, S. Kreitmeier A statistical model for the length distribution of meshes in a polymer network J. Chem. Phys., 114, (2001), 7627 45. W. Michalke, M. Lang, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Simulations on the number of entanglements of a polymer network using knot theory Phys. Rev. E, 64, (2001), 012801 46. W. Michalke, S. Kreitmeier, M. Lang, A. Buchner, D. Göritz Monte-Carlo simulations of end-linked bimodal polymer networks: part II Comput. &amp; Theo. Polym. Sci., 11, (2001), 459 47. A. Michel, S. Kreitmeier Adsorption of a single polymer chain on a surface: a molecular dynamics simulation J. Polym. Sci. B: Polym. Phys., 39, (2001), 2333 48. A. Michel, D. Göritz, S. Kreitmeier Molecular Dynamics simulation study - Localization and multi-flip effects in a single polymer chain on a surface'' Kautschuk Gummi Kunststoffe, 55, (2002), 447 49. M. Wacha, S. Kreitmeier Monte Carlo studies on the deformation behavior of entangled polymer chains'' Macromol. Theo. Simul. 11, (2002), 438 50. W. Michalke, M. Lang, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Comparison of topological properties between end-linked and statistically cross-linked polymer networks J. Chem. Phys. 117, (2002), 6300 51. M. Lang, W. Michalke, S. Kreitmeier Analysis of trapped entanglements in polymer networks J. Comput. Phys., 185, (2003), 549 52. M. Lang, D. Göritz, S. Kreitmeier Length of subchains and chain ends in cross-linked polymer networks Macromolecules, 36, (2003), 4464 53. M. Lang, D. Göritz, S. Kreitmeier The effect of spatially inhomogeneous mixing of polymer and cross-links for end-linked polymer networks in Constitutive Models for Rubber III, Busfeld &amp; Muhr (eds), Swets &amp; Zeitlinger, Lisse, (2003), 195 54. M. Lang, M. Malinowski, D. Göntner, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Computer simulation of structure and conductivity in carbon black filled elastomers in Filler Reinforcement of Rubbers (IOM Communications, 1 Carlton House Terrace, London, 2004) 55. M. Lang, W. Michalke, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Entanglements in Polymer Networks Kautschuk Gummi Kunststoffe, 58(2005), 179 56. M. Lang, D. Göritz, S. Kreitmeier Intra-Molecular Reactions in End-Linked Polymer Networks and Linear (Co)Polymerizations Macromolecules, 38, (2005), 2515 57. M. Lang, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Trapped Entanglements in Polymer Networks Rubber Chem. Tech., 80, (2007), 873 Zu Dr. Stefan Kreitmeier Homepage Zur Polymer-Homepage</field>
<field name="important">Veröffentlichungen von Prof. Dr. S. Kreitmeier  Veröffentlichungen von Prof. Dr. S. Kreitmeier Veröffentlichungen 1. D. Göritz, J. Kemmerer, S. Kreitmeier, R. Rossbacher Annealing effects in high modulus polyethylene Coll. &amp; Poly. Sci., 261, (1983), 631 2. S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Network properties of mixtures of protonated and deuterated polyethylene Coll. &amp; Poly. Sci., 266, (1988), 235 3. S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz A new model of inhomogeneous deformation used for craze formation Makoromol. Chem., Macromol. Symp., 41, (1991), 253 4. S. Kreitmeier, M. Wittkop, D. Göritz Computer simulation of coil deformation J. Comp. Phys., 112, (1994), 267 5. W. Niedermeier, J. Stierstorfer, S. Kreitmeier, O. Metz, D. Göritz Morphological investigations on carbon black particles by atomic force microscopy Rubber Chem. &amp; Techn., 67, (1994), 148 6. M. Wittkop, J.U. Sommer, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Monte Carlo simulations of a single polymer chain under an external force in two and three dimensions Phys. Rev. E, 49, (1994), 5472 7. W. Niedermeier, H. Raab, J. Stierstorfer, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz The microstructure of carbon black investigated by atomic force microscopy Kautschuk Gummi Kunststoffe, 47, (1994), 799 8. S. N. Kreitmeier, G. L. Liang, D. W. Noid, B. Wunderlich Molecular dynamics simulations of macroscopic vibrations on cooling of superheated polyethylene crystals Polymer International, 36, (1995), 155 9. S. Kreitmeier, M. Wittkop, D. Göritz Computer simulations of energetic and conformational changes in polymer systems Makoromol. Chem.: Macromol. Symp., 100, (1995), 181 10. S. N. Kreitmeier, G. L. Liang, D. W. Noid, B. Wunderlich Molecular dynamics simulations of the temperature dependence of lattice parameters of paraffin crystals during cooling J. Chem. Soc. Faraday Trans., 91, (1995), 2601 11. M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz On the deformation of hard elastic polymers - applicability of the coil-strand transition model Acta Polymerica, 46, (1995), 319 12. W. Niedermeier, H. Raab, P. Maier, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Using lateral force and force modulation to image filled elastomers Kautschuk Gummi Kunststoffe, 48, (1995), 611 13. B. Wunderlich, S. N. Kreitmeier Defects in polymer crystals MRS Bulletin, 20 (1995), 17 14. S. Kreitmeier, M. Wittkop, T. Wagner, D. Göritz, R. Zietz Investigations of hard elastic polypropylene with respect to the coil-strand transtion model Coll. &amp; Polym. Sci., 273, (1995), 1008 15. M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Monte Carlo Simulations of a single polymer chain under extension above and below the Theta-temperature Phys. Rev. E, 53, (1996), 838 16. M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz The distribution function of a single polymer chain with excluded volume in two and three dimensions: A Monte Carlo study J. Chem. Phys., 104, (1996), 351 17. M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz The collapse transition of a single polymer chain in two and three dimensions: A Monte Carlo study J. Chem. Phys., 104, (1996), 3373 18. M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Deformation of a single polymer chain in two dimensions above and below the Theta-temperature: A Monte Carlo study Comput. Polymer Sci., 5, (1995), 187 19. M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Computer simulations on energetic and entropic changes of a single chain under extension J. Chem. Soc. Faraday Trans., 92, (1996), 1375 20. S.N. Kreitmeier, D. W. Noid, B.G. Sumpter Quantum-Monte-Carlo simulations on linear chains Macromol. Theory Simul., 5, (1996), 365 21. S. N. Kreitmeier, G. L. Liang, D. W. Noid, B. G. Sumpter Thermal analysis via molecular dynamics simulation J. Therm. Anal., 46, (1996), 853 22. M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Swelling of subchains with excluded volume in two and three dimensions: A Monte Carlo study Macromolecules, 29, (1996), 4754 23. M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Monte Carlo simulations of the dynamics of single polymer chains above and below the Theta-temperature Comput. &amp; Theo. Polymer Sci., 6, (1996), 41 24. M. Wittkop, T. Hölzl, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz A Monte Carlo study of the glass transition in three dimensional polymer melts J. Non-Cryst. Solids, 201, (1996), 199 25. B. Wunderlich, A. Boller, I. Okazaki, S. Kreitmeier Linearity, steady state, and complex heat capacity in modulated differential scanning calorimetry Thermochimica Acta, 282/283, (1996), 143 26. D. Göritz, S. Kreitmeier, M. Wittkop Micromechanism of the deformation process of macromolecular systems, J. Macromol. Sci.-Phys., B35, (1996), 615 27. B. Wunderlich, A. Boller, I. Okazaki, S. Kreitmeier Modulated differential scanning calorimetry in the glass transition region, II J. Therm. Anal., 47, (1996), 1013 28. W. Gottstein, S. Kreitmeier, M. Wittkop, D. Göritz, F. Gotsis Monte Carlo simulations of a single polymer chain on rough surfaces Polymer, 38, (1997), 1607 29. Th. Hölzl, M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Uniaxial deformation of bridging polymer systems: A Monte Carlo study J. Chem. Phys., 106, (1997), 7792 30. S. Kreitmeier, M. Wittkop, H. L. Trautenberg, T. Hölzl, D. Göritz Large-scale simulations on polymer melts J. Comput. Phys., 133, (1997), 181 31. Th. Hölzl, M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, H.-L. Trautenberg, D. Göritz Structural aspects of the glass transition in three-dimensional polymer melts J. Chem. Soc. Faraday Trans., 93, (1997), 2185 32. Ch. Hagn, M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, H.-L. Trautenberg, Th. Hölzl, D. Göritz The creation and spatial structure of end-linked bimodal polymer networks: A Monte-Carlo study Polym. Gels &amp; Network, 5, (1997), 327 33. A. Michel, S. Kreitmeier Molecular dynamics simulation of the collapse transition of a single polymer chain Comput. &amp; Theo. Polymer Sci, 7, (1998), 113 34. W. Michalke, S. Kreitmeier Quantum-Monte-Carlo simulations of polyethylene European Phys. J. B, 4, (1998), 469 35. J. Fröhlich, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Surface characterization of carbon blacks Kautschuk Gummi Kunststoffe, 51, (1998), 370 36. S. Kreitmeier, M. Wittkop, D. Göritz Computer simulations on the cyclic deformation of a single chain above and below the Theta-temperature Phys. Rev. E, 59, (1999), 1982 37. Th. Hölzl, C. Mesner, M. Wittkop, S. Kreitmeier, S. Kain, D. Göritz Monte Carlo studies on the deformation behaviour of glassy model systems Comput. &amp; Theo. Polym. Sci., 9, (1999), 99 38. A. Michel, S. Kreitmeier, B. Wunderlich Molecular dynamics simulations of the adsorption of single chains on surfaces Springer Proceedings in Physics, 85, (2000), 228 39. S. Kreitmeier Equilibrium and non-equilibrium effects of a single polymer chain during cyclic deformation: A Monte Carlo study J. Chem. Phys., 112, (2000), 6925 40. R. Androsch, I. Moon, S. Kreitmeier, B. Wunderlich Determination of heat capacity with a sawtooth-type, power compensated temperature-modulated DSC Thermochim. Acta, 357-358, (2000), 267 41. Th. Lanzl, J. Ludwig, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz A modified method in dieelectric reearch of carbon black rubber compounds Kautschuk Gummi Kunststoffe, 53, (2000), 638 42. S. Kreitmeier, J. Böhm, D. Göritz Towards a new material law for elastomers: Part I Kautschuk Gummi Kunststoffe, 53, (2000), 716 43. M. Lang, W. Michalke, S. Kreitmeier Optimized decomposition of simulated polymer networks into meshes Macromol. Theo. Simul., 10, (2001), 204 44. M. Lang, W. Michalke, S. Kreitmeier A statistical model for the length distribution of meshes in a polymer network J. Chem. Phys., 114, (2001), 7627 45. W. Michalke, M. Lang, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Simulations on the number of entanglements of a polymer network using knot theory Phys. Rev. E, 64, (2001), 012801 46. W. Michalke, S. Kreitmeier, M. Lang, A. Buchner, D. Göritz Monte-Carlo simulations of end-linked bimodal polymer networks: part II Comput. &amp; Theo. Polym. Sci., 11, (2001), 459 47. A. Michel, S. Kreitmeier Adsorption of a single polymer chain on a surface: a molecular dynamics simulation J. Polym. Sci. B: Polym. Phys., 39, (2001), 2333 48. A. Michel, D. Göritz, S. Kreitmeier Molecular Dynamics simulation study - Localization and multi-flip effects in a single polymer chain on a surface'' Kautschuk Gummi Kunststoffe, 55, (2002), 447 49. M. Wacha, S. Kreitmeier Monte Carlo studies on the deformation behavior of entangled polymer chains'' Macromol. Theo. Simul. 11, (2002), 438 50. W. Michalke, M. Lang, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Comparison of topological properties between end-linked and statistically cross-linked polymer networks J. Chem. Phys. 117, (2002), 6300 51. M. Lang, W. Michalke, S. Kreitmeier Analysis of trapped entanglements in polymer networks J. Comput. Phys., 185, (2003), 549 52. M. Lang, D. Göritz, S. Kreitmeier Length of subchains and chain ends in cross-linked polymer networks Macromolecules, 36, (2003), 4464 53. M. Lang, D. Göritz, S. Kreitmeier The effect of spatially inhomogeneous mixing of polymer and cross-links for end-linked polymer networks in Constitutive Models for Rubber III, Busfeld &amp; Muhr (eds), Swets &amp; Zeitlinger, Lisse, (2003), 195 54. M. Lang, M. Malinowski, D. Göntner, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Computer simulation of structure and conductivity in carbon black filled elastomers in Filler Reinforcement of Rubbers (IOM Communications, 1 Carlton House Terrace, London, 2004) 55. M. Lang, W. Michalke, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Entanglements in Polymer Networks Kautschuk Gummi Kunststoffe, 58(2005), 179 56. M. Lang, D. Göritz, S. Kreitmeier Intra-Molecular Reactions in End-Linked Polymer Networks and Linear (Co)Polymerizations Macromolecules, 38, (2005), 2515 57. M. Lang, S. Kreitmeier, D. Göritz Trapped Entanglements in Polymer Networks Rubber Chem. Tech., 80, (2007), 873 Zu Dr. Stefan Kreitmeier Homepage Zur Polymer-Homepage</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/krey/pubkrey.html</field>
<field name="title">Publications of the group of Krey, Uwe</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/krey/pubkrey.html</field>
<field name="content">Publications of the group of Krey, Uwe Publications of the group of Krey, Uwe PUBLIKATIONEN und PREPRINTS der ehem. Arbeitsgruppe Krey: 1.) PREPRINTS sind (z.B. mit dem Autor-Suchwort Krey unter der Rubrik all years) auf dem 'Cornell-Preprint-Server': http://arXiv.org/find/cond-mat zu finden. (Bitte das blaue Feld anklicken !) 2.) PUBLIKATIONEN sind (nach Anklicken aller passenden PHYSIK-JAHRG?NGE (vor start search) und dann z.B. mit dem Autor-Suchwort Krey-U*) zu finden unter: http:// .../webspirs/... customer=ubRegensburg (= INSPEC) (Bitte das blaue Feld anklicken ! Ab ca. 1995 sind die Ver?ffentlichungen meist auch als preprints vorhanden)</field>
<field name="important">Publications of the group of Krey, Uwe Publications of the group of Krey, Uwe PUBLIKATIONEN und PREPRINTS der ehem. Arbeitsgruppe Krey: 1.) PREPRINTS sind (z.B. mit dem Autor-Suchwort Krey unter der Rubrik all years) auf dem 'Cornell-Preprint-Server': http://arXiv.org/find/cond-mat zu finden. (Bitte das blaue Feld anklicken !) 2.) PUBLIKATIONEN sind (nach Anklicken aller passenden PHYSIK-JAHRG?NGE (vor start search) und dann z.B. mit dem Autor-Suchwort Krey-U*) zu finden unter: http:// .../webspirs/... customer=ubRegensburg (= INSPEC) (Bitte das blaue Feld anklicken ! Ab ca. 1995 sind die Ver?ffentlichungen meist auch als preprints vorhanden)</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/krey/ue6Ess02.html</field>
<field name="title">ue6Ess02.html</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/krey/ue6Ess02.html</field>
<field name="content">ue6Ess02.html ue6Ess02.html &amp;gt; # EXERCISES ON THEOR. PH. II (ELECTRODYNAMICS and OPTICS) &amp;gt; # Prof. Dr.U. Krey, Univ. Regensburg, Juan-Diego Urbina, Rainer H?llinger; summer 2002, file 6 &amp;gt; # Topics: Alternating currents (impedances); MAPLE (a typical 'MAPLE worksheet') &amp;gt; #------------------------------------------------------------------------ &amp;gt; # Problem 11 : Complex impedance ; resonance effects &amp;gt; #------------------------------------------------------------------------ &amp;gt; # Consider a serial RLC circuit composed (i) of an Ohmic resistance R, &amp;gt; # (ii) a capacitive resistance (plate) with capacity C &amp;gt; # and (iii) an inductive resistance (solenoid) with inductivity L. &amp;gt; # This circuit forms the load attached &amp;gt; # to the poles of an alternating voltage generator, with the generator voltage U~(t) := U_0 * cos ( w*t) &amp;gt; # (U_0=220 Volt = amplitude of the generator voltage; w = 2*Pi*f = circular frequency; &amp;gt; # f = 50 Hz). For the current through the RLC serial load &amp;gt; # we thus obtain I(t) = I_0 * cos ( w*t-alpha), with &amp;gt; # I_0/U_0 = 1/sqrt(R^2+(w*L-1/(w*C))^2) #( = 1/|RR|, 1/abs(RR), current resonance) and &amp;gt; # alpha = arctan( ( w*L-1/(w*C) ) /R) #( = arctan (Im(RR)/Re(RR), phase resonance), &amp;gt; # with the complex ac resistance (impedance) RR := R + I*(w*L-1/(w*C)). I is the 'imaginary unit' (I^2=-1), whereas II is the current. &amp;gt; # Basic part, A: &amp;gt; # Please calculate and plot the current and phase resonance curves &amp;gt; # for various values of the Ohmic resistance R for C=1 Farad and L=1 Henry as a function of the &amp;gt; # reduced frequency w_red := w/w_0, with the resonance frequency w_0 :=1/sqrt{L*C} &amp;gt; # Solution (proposal, in mksA units): &amp;gt; ## R1 := 0.2; R2 := 0.1 ; R3 := 0.05;#(Ohm). (With the execution here and below the twofold '##' symbols should be deleted !!) &amp;gt; # &amp;gt; ## L := 1; #(Henry) &amp;gt; ## C := 1; #(Farad) &amp;gt; ## f1(w):= 1/ sqrt( R1*R1 +(w*L-1/(w*C))^2);  f2(w):= 1/sqrt( R2*R2 + (w*L-1/(w*C))^2);   f3(w):= 1/sqrt(R3*R3+(w*L-1/(w*C))^2); &amp;gt; # In units of Hz the frequency w is equal to w_red &amp;gt; ## plot ( { f1(w),f2(w),f3(w)} , w=0 .. 2); &amp;gt; ## alpha1(w) := arctan ( (w*L-1/(w*C))/R1 ); alpha2(w) := arctan ( (w*L-1/(w*C))/R2 );alpha3(w) := arctan ( (w*L-1/(w*C))/R3 ); &amp;gt; ## plot ( {alpha1(w), alpha2(w), alpha3(w)}, w = 0 .. 2 ); &amp;gt; # Phase resonance : For the resonance frequency (w=w_red=1) &amp;gt; # current and voltage are exactly 'in phase'; for lower frequencies &amp;gt; # the current is ahead of the voltage, alpha ? 0; for higher frequencies &amp;gt; # the current is behind the voltage (alpha ? 0) &amp;gt; # &amp;gt; # Second part, B: Please exploit systematically the possibility to calculate with complex numbers ( z:=x+I*y; Re(z);...; abs(z) ) &amp;gt; # Third part, C: Please try similar calculations (e.g., by variation of the complex quantities RR, UU, II etc.) &amp;gt; # for at least one further load, which is obtained from R , I*w*L und 1/(I*w*C) - [I is the imaginary unit, whereas II is the current] - &amp;gt; # by the formation of parallel or mixed circuits or with additional mutual inductivities (transformer). &amp;gt; # (In the last case, we have on the one hand for the complex input voltage of the transformer the result (UU_Tr)^(1)=I*w*L_{12}*(II)^(2), &amp;gt; # on the other hand the output voltage of the transformer is (UU_Tr)^(2)= - I*w*L_{21}*(II)^(1) = [R_2+I*(w*L_2-1/(w*C_2))]*(II)^(2). &amp;gt; # Altogether, with L_{12}=L_{21} : (RR)^(1)(w) =(UU)_~/(II)^(1) = R+I*(w*L-1/(w*C)) + w^2*L_{12}^2 /[R_2+I*(w*L_2-1/(w*C_2))] ) &amp;gt; #------------------------------------------------------------ &amp;gt; # Problem 12) Potential lines: 3d contour plots &amp;gt; #------------------------------------------------------------ &amp;gt; # The electrostatic potential of a positive point charge Q in vacuo &amp;gt; # at a distance Dx=1 to the l.h.s. in front of (!) a metal plane (y-z-plane at x=0) and the oppositely charged induced (fictitious) &amp;gt; # mirror image at the same distance to the r.h.s. (!) of that plane &amp;gt; # is (apart from a factor Q/(4*pi*eps_0)) in the plane z=0 given by : &amp;gt; # &amp;gt; ## Phi := (x,y) -&amp;gt; 1/(sqrt((x+1)^2+y^2))-1/(sqrt((x-1)^2+y^2)) ; &amp;gt; # &amp;gt; # The equipotential lines of this potential are obtained with : &amp;gt; # &amp;gt; ## plot3d( Phi, -2..2, -1..1 , view = -4..4, axes=box, style=patchcontour ); &amp;gt; # ( x-values between -2 and +2, y-values between -1 and +1; Phi-values between -4 and +4 ) &amp;gt; ########################################################################### &amp;gt; # ( You can rotate the plot and export it into Word or TeX documents ! ) &amp;gt; # &amp;gt; # First task: Produce similar plots for different potentials, e.g. for the &amp;gt; # potential of a constant electrostatic field which is deformed by a metallic sphere &amp;gt; # ( respectively of the analogous case of a current flow vec(j), with vec(j) ~ vec(E) ) : &amp;gt; ## Phii := (x,y) -&amp;gt; if x^2+y^2 &amp;gt; 1 then x * ( 1 - 1/(sqrt(x*x+y*y))^3 ) else 0 fi ; &amp;gt; # &amp;gt; ## plot3d( Phii , -3 .. 3 , -2 ..2, axes=box, style=patchcontour ); &amp;gt; ######################## ######################## ########################</field>
<field name="important">ue6Ess02.html ue6Ess02.html &amp;gt; # EXERCISES ON THEOR. PH. II (ELECTRODYNAMICS and OPTICS) &amp;gt; # Prof. Dr.U. Krey, Univ. Regensburg, Juan-Diego Urbina, Rainer H?llinger; summer 2002, file 6 &amp;gt; # Topics: Alternating currents (impedances); MAPLE (a typical 'MAPLE worksheet') &amp;gt; #------------------------------------------------------------------------ &amp;gt; # Problem 11 : Complex impedance ; resonance effects &amp;gt; #------------------------------------------------------------------------ &amp;gt; # Consider a serial RLC circuit composed (i) of an Ohmic resistance R, &amp;gt; # (ii) a capacitive resistance (plate) with capacity C &amp;gt; # and (iii) an inductive resistance (solenoid) with inductivity L. &amp;gt; # This circuit forms the load attached &amp;gt; # to the poles of an alternating voltage generator, with the generator voltage U~(t) := U_0 * cos ( w*t) &amp;gt; # (U_0=220 Volt = amplitude of the generator voltage; w = 2*Pi*f = circular frequency; &amp;gt; # f = 50 Hz). For the current through the RLC serial load &amp;gt; # we thus obtain I(t) = I_0 * cos ( w*t-alpha), with &amp;gt; # I_0/U_0 = 1/sqrt(R^2+(w*L-1/(w*C))^2) #( = 1/|RR|, 1/abs(RR), current resonance) and &amp;gt; # alpha = arctan( ( w*L-1/(w*C) ) /R) #( = arctan (Im(RR)/Re(RR), phase resonance), &amp;gt; # with the complex ac resistance (impedance) RR := R + I*(w*L-1/(w*C)). I is the 'imaginary unit' (I^2=-1), whereas II is the current. &amp;gt; # Basic part, A: &amp;gt; # Please calculate and plot the current and phase resonance curves &amp;gt; # for various values of the Ohmic resistance R for C=1 Farad and L=1 Henry as a function of the &amp;gt; # reduced frequency w_red := w/w_0, with the resonance frequency w_0 :=1/sqrt{L*C} &amp;gt; # Solution (proposal, in mksA units): &amp;gt; ## R1 := 0.2; R2 := 0.1 ; R3 := 0.05;#(Ohm). (With the execution here and below the twofold '##' symbols should be deleted !!) &amp;gt; # &amp;gt; ## L := 1; #(Henry) &amp;gt; ## C := 1; #(Farad) &amp;gt; ## f1(w):= 1/ sqrt( R1*R1 +(w*L-1/(w*C))^2);  f2(w):= 1/sqrt( R2*R2 + (w*L-1/(w*C))^2);   f3(w):= 1/sqrt(R3*R3+(w*L-1/(w*C))^2); &amp;gt; # In units of Hz the frequency w is equal to w_red &amp;gt; ## plot ( { f1(w),f2(w),f3(w)} , w=0 .. 2); &amp;gt; ## alpha1(w) := arctan ( (w*L-1/(w*C))/R1 ); alpha2(w) := arctan ( (w*L-1/(w*C))/R2 );alpha3(w) := arctan ( (w*L-1/(w*C))/R3 ); &amp;gt; ## plot ( {alpha1(w), alpha2(w), alpha3(w)}, w = 0 .. 2 ); &amp;gt; # Phase resonance : For the resonance frequency (w=w_red=1) &amp;gt; # current and voltage are exactly 'in phase'; for lower frequencies &amp;gt; # the current is ahead of the voltage, alpha ? 0; for higher frequencies &amp;gt; # the current is behind the voltage (alpha ? 0) &amp;gt; # &amp;gt; # Second part, B: Please exploit systematically the possibility to calculate with complex numbers ( z:=x+I*y; Re(z);...; abs(z) ) &amp;gt; # Third part, C: Please try similar calculations (e.g., by variation of the complex quantities RR, UU, II etc.) &amp;gt; # for at least one further load, which is obtained from R , I*w*L und 1/(I*w*C) - [I is the imaginary unit, whereas II is the current] - &amp;gt; # by the formation of parallel or mixed circuits or with additional mutual inductivities (transformer). &amp;gt; # (In the last case, we have on the one hand for the complex input voltage of the transformer the result (UU_Tr)^(1)=I*w*L_{12}*(II)^(2), &amp;gt; # on the other hand the output voltage of the transformer is (UU_Tr)^(2)= - I*w*L_{21}*(II)^(1) = [R_2+I*(w*L_2-1/(w*C_2))]*(II)^(2). &amp;gt; # Altogether, with L_{12}=L_{21} : (RR)^(1)(w) =(UU)_~/(II)^(1) = R+I*(w*L-1/(w*C)) + w^2*L_{12}^2 /[R_2+I*(w*L_2-1/(w*C_2))] ) &amp;gt; #------------------------------------------------------------ &amp;gt; # Problem 12) Potential lines: 3d contour plots &amp;gt; #------------------------------------------------------------ &amp;gt; # The electrostatic potential of a positive point charge Q in vacuo &amp;gt; # at a distance Dx=1 to the l.h.s. in front of (!) a metal plane (y-z-plane at x=0) and the oppositely charged induced (fictitious) &amp;gt; # mirror image at the same distance to the r.h.s. (!) of that plane &amp;gt; # is (apart from a factor Q/(4*pi*eps_0)) in the plane z=0 given by : &amp;gt; # &amp;gt; ## Phi := (x,y) -&amp;gt; 1/(sqrt((x+1)^2+y^2))-1/(sqrt((x-1)^2+y^2)) ; &amp;gt; # &amp;gt; # The equipotential lines of this potential are obtained with : &amp;gt; # &amp;gt; ## plot3d( Phi, -2..2, -1..1 , view = -4..4, axes=box, style=patchcontour ); &amp;gt; # ( x-values between -2 and +2, y-values between -1 and +1; Phi-values between -4 and +4 ) &amp;gt; ########################################################################### &amp;gt; # ( You can rotate the plot and export it into Word or TeX documents ! ) &amp;gt; # &amp;gt; # First task: Produce similar plots for different potentials, e.g. for the &amp;gt; # potential of a constant electrostatic field which is deformed by a metallic sphere &amp;gt; # ( respectively of the analogous case of a current flow vec(j), with vec(j) ~ vec(E) ) : &amp;gt; ## Phii := (x,y) -&amp;gt; if x^2+y^2 &amp;gt; 1 then x * ( 1 - 1/(sqrt(x*x+y*y))^3 ) else 0 fi ; &amp;gt; # &amp;gt; ## plot3d( Phii , -3 .. 3 , -2 ..2, axes=box, style=patchcontour ); &amp;gt; ######################## ######################## ########################</field>
</doc>

</add>