<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<add>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Biochemie2/www/locat.html</field>
<field name="title">Research Overview of the Sterner Lab</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Biochemie2/www/locat.html</field>
<field name="content">Research Overview of the Sterner Lab Home Research People More ...   City Map of Regensburg See below for a map of the university campus The above image as PDF-file Please see also this city map     University Campus  BCII is located on the first floor of building BIO 4       </field>
<field name="important">Research Overview of the Sterner Lab Home Research People More ...   City Map of Regensburg See below for a map of the university campus The above image as PDF-file Please see also this city map     University Campus  BCII is located on the first floor of building BIO 4       </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Biochemie2/www/more.html</field>
<field name="title">more ....</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Biochemie2/www/more.html</field>
<field name="content">more .... Location Research People Home         Here you find online material for our bioinformatics course.      </field>
<field name="important">more .... Location Research People Home         Here you find online material for our bioinformatics course.      </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Biochemie2/www/project_1.html</field>
<field name="title">Enzyme engineering [R. Sterner]</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Biochemie2/www/project_1.html</field>
<field name="content">Enzyme engineering [R. Sterner] Research Home People More ...   Enzyme engineering [R. Sterner] Technical advances during the last decade have enabled researchers to modify at will the properties of many naturally occurring enzymes. These approaches have also facilitated the generation of stabilised enzymes with increased turnover numbers and altered substrate- and stereo-selectivities to be used in industrial processes. Up to now, the most impressive results in enzyme design have been obtained by directed evolution. In this two-step approach random mutagenesis is used to create large enzyme repertoires, from which optimised variants are then isolated using either selection or screening techniques. In contrast to directed evolution, the alternative approach of rational enzyme design requires a detailed knowledge of a specific enzyme structure and catalytic mechanism. Although occasionally successful, rational design approaches often fail, due to a limited understanding of the subtle interplay among amino acid side chains within an enzyme active site. Recent results suggest that this bottleneck toward the acquisition of tailored enzymes can be overcome by applying sophisticated computational methods. We have used directed evolution to establish the activity of phosphoriboslyanthranilate isomerase (TrpF) on the natural (ba)8-barrel scaffolds of ProFAR isomerase (HisA) and imidazoleglycerol phosphate synthase (HisF). Since only few mutations were necessary for the activity switch, our results suggest that TrpF, HisA and HisF have evolved from a common ancestor by a series of gene duplication and fusion events. Moreover, we have used random mutagenesis and selection in vivo to increase the low catalytic activity of a thermostable dimeric anthranilate phosphoribosyl transferase at room temperature. The turnover number of the best mutant was increased 40-fold compared to the wild-type enzyme, due to an increased product release rate. Moreover, we have used rational design to generate a fully active monomeric variant of this enzyme by replacing hydrophobic residues at the protein interface with negatively charged ones. Enzyme engineering by directed evolution  </field>
<field name="important">Enzyme engineering [R. Sterner] Research Home People More ...   Enzyme engineering [R. Sterner] Technical advances during the last decade have enabled researchers to modify at will the properties of many naturally occurring enzymes. These approaches have also facilitated the generation of stabilised enzymes with increased turnover numbers and altered substrate- and stereo-selectivities to be used in industrial processes. Up to now, the most impressive results in enzyme design have been obtained by directed evolution. In this two-step approach random mutagenesis is used to create large enzyme repertoires, from which optimised variants are then isolated using either selection or screening techniques. In contrast to directed evolution, the alternative approach of rational enzyme design requires a detailed knowledge of a specific enzyme structure and catalytic mechanism. Although occasionally successful, rational design approaches often fail, due to a limited understanding of the subtle interplay among amino acid side chains within an enzyme active site. Recent results suggest that this bottleneck toward the acquisition of tailored enzymes can be overcome by applying sophisticated computational methods. We have used directed evolution to establish the activity of phosphoriboslyanthranilate isomerase (TrpF) on the natural (ba)8-barrel scaffolds of ProFAR isomerase (HisA) and imidazoleglycerol phosphate synthase (HisF). Since only few mutations were necessary for the activity switch, our results suggest that TrpF, HisA and HisF have evolved from a common ancestor by a series of gene duplication and fusion events. Moreover, we have used random mutagenesis and selection in vivo to increase the low catalytic activity of a thermostable dimeric anthranilate phosphoribosyl transferase at room temperature. The turnover number of the best mutant was increased 40-fold compared to the wild-type enzyme, due to an increased product release rate. Moreover, we have used rational design to generate a fully active monomeric variant of this enzyme by replacing hydrophobic residues at the protein interface with negatively charged ones. Enzyme engineering by directed evolution  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Biochemie2/www/project_2.html</field>
<field name="title">Enzyme evolution [R. Sterner]</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Biochemie2/www/project_2.html</field>
<field name="content">Enzyme evolution [R. Sterner] Research Home People More ...   Enzyme evolution [R. Sterner] It is plausible to assume that the highly efficient and specific contemporary enzymes have evolved from less sophisticated precursors. We are studying this process for the (ba)8-barrels enzymes ProFAR isomerase (HisA) and imidazole glycerol phosphate synthase (HisF). They possess a striking internal two-fold symmetry. The pairs of N-terminal halves (designated HisA-N and HisF-N), which consist of the first four (ba) units, and the pairs of C-terminal halves (designated HisA-C and HisF-C), which consist of the last four (ba) units, display sequence identities between 16 and 26 % and rmsd values of their main-chain non-hydrogen atoms between 1.4 and 2.1 ?. When produced separately, the half-barrels HisF-N and HisF-C are homodimeric proteins with native secondary and tertiary structures, but without measurable catalytic activity. When co-expressed in vivo or refolded together in vitro, the two proteins assemble to a catalytically fully active HisF-NC heterodimer. It was concluded that both HisF and HisA are composed of two structural domains, namely the corresponding N- and C-terminal half-barrels. These results suggest an evolutionary scenario according to which a primordial gene encoding a (ba)4-half-barrel as subunit of a homodimeric enzyme was duplicated and fused to yield a monomeric, ancestral (ba)8-barrel, which might have been the precursor of contemporary (ba)8-barrel enzymes. These postulated evolutionary events were reconstructed experimentally by generating new (ba)8-barrels from existing (ba)4-half-barrels. To this end, HisF-C was duplicated, fused and optimised to yield the stable and monomeric HisF-C***C barrel, whose X-ray structure could be solved at high resolution. Moreover, the N- and C-terminal half-barrels of HisA and HisF were fused crosswise to yield the chimeric HisAF and HisFA proteins. Using a combination of random mutagenesis and selection in vivo, high catalytic activity was established on the HisAF scaffold. The results show that stable and catalytically active (ba)8-barrels can be assembled in the laboratory by fusing, mixing and matching of (ba)4-half-barrels. Similar events might have occurred in the course of natural evolution. Generation of an artificial (ba)8-barrel from two identical (ba)4-barrels  </field>
<field name="important">Enzyme evolution [R. Sterner] Research Home People More ...   Enzyme evolution [R. Sterner] It is plausible to assume that the highly efficient and specific contemporary enzymes have evolved from less sophisticated precursors. We are studying this process for the (ba)8-barrels enzymes ProFAR isomerase (HisA) and imidazole glycerol phosphate synthase (HisF). They possess a striking internal two-fold symmetry. The pairs of N-terminal halves (designated HisA-N and HisF-N), which consist of the first four (ba) units, and the pairs of C-terminal halves (designated HisA-C and HisF-C), which consist of the last four (ba) units, display sequence identities between 16 and 26 % and rmsd values of their main-chain non-hydrogen atoms between 1.4 and 2.1 ?. When produced separately, the half-barrels HisF-N and HisF-C are homodimeric proteins with native secondary and tertiary structures, but without measurable catalytic activity. When co-expressed in vivo or refolded together in vitro, the two proteins assemble to a catalytically fully active HisF-NC heterodimer. It was concluded that both HisF and HisA are composed of two structural domains, namely the corresponding N- and C-terminal half-barrels. These results suggest an evolutionary scenario according to which a primordial gene encoding a (ba)4-half-barrel as subunit of a homodimeric enzyme was duplicated and fused to yield a monomeric, ancestral (ba)8-barrel, which might have been the precursor of contemporary (ba)8-barrel enzymes. These postulated evolutionary events were reconstructed experimentally by generating new (ba)8-barrels from existing (ba)4-half-barrels. To this end, HisF-C was duplicated, fused and optimised to yield the stable and monomeric HisF-C***C barrel, whose X-ray structure could be solved at high resolution. Moreover, the N- and C-terminal half-barrels of HisA and HisF were fused crosswise to yield the chimeric HisAF and HisFA proteins. Using a combination of random mutagenesis and selection in vivo, high catalytic activity was established on the HisAF scaffold. The results show that stable and catalytically active (ba)8-barrels can be assembled in the laboratory by fusing, mixing and matching of (ba)4-half-barrels. Similar events might have occurred in the course of natural evolution. Generation of an artificial (ba)8-barrel from two identical (ba)4-barrels  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Biochemie2/www/project_3.html</field>
<field name="title">Multi-enzyme Complexes [R. Sterner]</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Biochemie2/www/project_3.html</field>
<field name="content">Multi-enzyme Complexes [R. Sterner] Research Home People More ...   Multi-enzyme Complexes [R. Sterner] Glutamine amidotransferases are a family of enzymes, whose members contain two active sites that are often located on two different polypeptide chains. The glutaminase subunit hydrolyses glutamine to glutamate and ammonia, which is added to a specific acceptor substrate at the active site of the synthase subunit. There are two important questions regarding the mechanism of glutamine amidotransferases: How are the activities at the two active sites coordinated? How is nascent ammonia transferred from the glutaminase to the synthase subunit without getting in contact with bulk water? We are investigating these questions using imidazole glycerol phosphate (ImGP) synthase from Thermotoga maritima, which is a key metabolic enzyme that links histidine and purine biosynthesis. ImGP synthase consists of a complex of the glutaminase subunit HisH and the synthase subunit HisF, which has the (ba)8-barrel fold. A combination of biochemical investigations and X-ray crystallography revealed that glutamine hydrolysis at HisH is induced by ammonia consumption at the active site of HisF to which it migrates through a long bi-partite channel that comprises the interior of the b-barrel of HisF. The ImGP synthase  </field>
<field name="important">Multi-enzyme Complexes [R. Sterner] Research Home People More ...   Multi-enzyme Complexes [R. Sterner] Glutamine amidotransferases are a family of enzymes, whose members contain two active sites that are often located on two different polypeptide chains. The glutaminase subunit hydrolyses glutamine to glutamate and ammonia, which is added to a specific acceptor substrate at the active site of the synthase subunit. There are two important questions regarding the mechanism of glutamine amidotransferases: How are the activities at the two active sites coordinated? How is nascent ammonia transferred from the glutaminase to the synthase subunit without getting in contact with bulk water? We are investigating these questions using imidazole glycerol phosphate (ImGP) synthase from Thermotoga maritima, which is a key metabolic enzyme that links histidine and purine biosynthesis. ImGP synthase consists of a complex of the glutaminase subunit HisH and the synthase subunit HisF, which has the (ba)8-barrel fold. A combination of biochemical investigations and X-ray crystallography revealed that glutamine hydrolysis at HisH is induced by ammonia consumption at the active site of HisF to which it migrates through a long bi-partite channel that comprises the interior of the b-barrel of HisF. The ImGP synthase  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Biochemie2/www/publications.html</field>
<field name="title">Publications</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Biochemie2/www/publications.html</field>
<field name="content">Publications     Location Home Research More ...   Selected publications since 2000 Original research articles 2014 - 2013 Peterhoff, D., Beer, B., Rajendran, C., Kumpula, E.P., Kapetaniou, E., Guldan, H., Wierenga, R.K., Sterner, R. &amp; Babinger, P. (2014). A comprehensive analysis of the geranylgeranylglyceryl phosphate synthase enzyme family identifies novel members and reveals mechanisms of substrate specificity and quaternary structure organization. Mol. Microbiol. 92, 885-899. Sommer, B., Waege, I., P?llmann, D., Seitz, T., Thomm, M., Sterner, R. &amp; Hausner, W. (2014). Activation of a chimeric Rpb5/RpoH subunit using library selection. PLoS One 9, e87485. Reisinger, B.,  Kuzmanovic, N., L?ffler, P., Merkl, R., K?nig, B. &amp; Sterner, R. (2014). Expoiting protein symmetry to design light-controllable enzyme inhibitors. Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. 53, 595-598. Reisinger, B.,  Sperl, J., Holinski, A., Schmid, V., Rajendran, C., Carstensen, L., Schlee, S., Blanquart, S., Merkl, R. &amp; Sterner, R. (2014). Evidence for the existence of elaborate enzyme complexes in the paleoarchean era. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 136, 122-129. Janda, J. O., Meier, A. &amp; Merkl, R. (2013). CLIPS-4D: a classifier that distinguishes structurally and functionally important residue-positions based on sequence and 3D data. Bioinformatics 29, 3029-3035. Sperl, J. M., Rohweder, B., Rajendran, C. &amp; Sterner, R. (2013). Establishing catalytic activity on an artificial (??)8-barrel protein designed from identical half-barrels. FEBS Lett. 587, 2798-2805. Meier, M.M., Rajendran, C., Malisi, C., Fox, N.G., Xu, C., Schlee, S., Barondeau, D.P. Hoecker, B., Sterner, R. &amp; Raushel, F.M. (2013). Molecular engineering of organophosphate hydrolysis activity from a weak promiscuous lactonase template. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 135, 11670-11677. Hauptmann, J., Dueck, A., Harlander, S., Pfaff, J., Merkl, R. &amp; Meister, G. (2013). Turning catalytically inactive human Argonaute proteins into active slicer enzymes. Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol. 20, 814-817. Schlee, S., Dietrich, S., Kurcon, T., Delaney, P., Goodey, N.M. &amp; Sterner, R. (2013). Kinetic mechanism of indole-3-glycerol phosphate synthase. Biochemistry 52, 132-142.   2012 - 2011 List, F., Vega, M. C., Razeto, A., Haeger, M. C., Sterner, R. &amp; Wilmanns, M. (2012). Catalysis uncoupling in a glutamine amidotransferase bienzyme by unblocking the glutaminase active site. Chem. Biol. 19, 1589-1599. Reisinger, B.,  Bocola, M., List, F., Claren, J., Rajendran, C. &amp; Sterner, R. (2012). A sugar isomerization reaction established on various (??)8 -barrel scaffolds is based on substrate-assisted catalysis. Protein Eng. Des. Sel. 11, 751-760. Carstensen, L., Sperl, J. M., Bocola, M., List, F., Schmid, F. X. &amp; Sterner, R. (2012). Conservation of the folding mechanism between designed primordial (??)8-barrel proteins and their modern descendant. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 134, 12786-12791. Dietrich, S., Borst, N., Schlee, S., Schneider, D., Janda, J. O., Sterner, R. &amp; Merkl, R. (2012). Experimental assessment of the importance of amino acid positions identified by an entropy-based correlation analysis of multiple sequence alignments. Biochemistry 51, 5633-5641. Peterhoff, D., Zellner, H., Gudan, H., Merkl, R., Sterner, R. &amp; Babinger, P. (2012).  Dimerization determines substrate specificity of a bacterial prenyltransferase. ChemBioChem 13, 1297-1303. Evran, S., Telefoncu, A. &amp; Sterner, R. (2012). Directed evolution of (??)8-barrel enzymes: establishing phosphoribosylanthranilate isomerisation activity on the scaffold of the tryptophan synthase ?-subunit. Protein Eng. Des. Sel. 25, 285-293. Craig, D. B., Schwab, T. &amp; Sterner, R. (2012). Random mutagenesis suggests that sequence errors are not a major cause of variation in the activity of individual molecules of ?-galactosidase. Biochem. Cell Biol. 90, 540-547. Carstensen, L., Zold?k, G., Schmid, F. X. &amp; Sterner, R. (2012). Folding mechanism of an extremely thermostable (??)8-barrel enzyme: a high kinetic barrier protects the protein from denaturation. Biochemistry 51, 3420-3432. List, F., Bocola, M., Haeger, M. C. &amp; Sterner, R. (2012). Constitutively active glutaminase variants provide insights into the activation mechanism of anthranilate synthase. Biochemistry 51, 2812-2818. Guldan, H., Matysik, F. M., Bocola, M., Sterner, R. &amp; Babinger, P. (2011). Functional assignment of an enzyme that catalyzes the synthesis of an archaea-type ether lipid in bacteria. Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. Engl. 50, 8188-8191. Fischer, A., Seitz, T., Lochner, A., Sterner, R., Merkl, R. &amp; Bocola, M. (2011). A fast and precise approach for computational saturation mutagenesis and its experimental validation by using an artificial (??)8-barrel protein. ChemBioChem 12, 1544-1550. Schwab, T. &amp; Sterner, R. (2011). Stabilization of a metabolic enzyme by library selection in Thermus thermophilus. ChemBioChem  12, 1581-1588.   2010 - 2009 Ehrmann, A., Richter, K., Busch, F., Reimann, J., Albers, S.V. &amp; Sterner, R. (2010). Ligand-inducted formation of a transient tryptophan synthase complex with ??? subunit stoichiometry. Biochemistry 49, 10842-10853. Mandach, C. &amp; Merkl R. (2010) Genes optimized by evolution for accurate and fast translation encode in Archaea and Bacteria a braod and characteristic spectrum of protein functions. BMC Genomics 11, 617. Seitz, T., Thoma, R., Schoch, G.A., Stihle, M., Benz, J., D'Arcy, B., Wiget, A., Ruf, A., Hennig, M. &amp; Sterner, R. (2010). Enhancing the stability and solubility of the glucocorticoid receptor ligand-binding domain by high-throughput library screening. J. Mol. Biol. 403, 562-577. Liebold, C., List, F., Kalbitzer, H.R., Sterner, R. &amp; Brunner, E. (2010). The interaction of ammonia and xenon with the imidazole glycerol phosphate synthase from Thermotoga maritima as detected by NMR spectroscopy.  Protein Sci. 19, 1774-1782. Richter, M., Bosnali, M., Carstensen, L., Seitz, T., Durchschlag, H., Blanquart, S., Merkl, R. &amp; Sterner, R. (2010). Computational and experimental evidence for the evolution of a (??)8-barrel protein from an ancestral quarter-barrel stabilised by disulfide bonds.  J. Mol. Biol. 398, 763-773. Drzewiecki, K., Angelov, A., Ballschmiter, M. Tiefenbach, K.-J., Sterner, R. &amp; Liebl, W. (2010) Hyperthermostable acetyl xylan esterase. Microbial Biotechnol. 3, 84-92. Merkl R, Wiezer A. (2009) GO4genome: A prokaryotic phylogeny based on genome organization. J. Mol. Evol. 68, 550-562. Schlee, S., Deuss, M., Bruning, M., Ivens, A., Schwab, T., Hellmann, N., Mayans, O. &amp; Sterner, R. (2009). Activation of anthranilate phosphoribosyl transferase from Sulfolobus solfataricus by removal of Mg-inhibition and acceleration of product release. Biochemistry 48, 5199-5209. Claren, J., Malisi, C., H?cker, B. &amp; Sterner, R. (2009). Establishing wild-type levels of catalytic activity on natural and artificial (??)8-barrel protein scaffolds.  Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 106, 3704-3709. Xiang, D. F., Kolb, P., Meier, M. M., Fedorov, E. V., Fedorov, A. A., Sterner, R., Almo S. C., Shoichet, B. K. &amp; Raushel, F. M. (2009). Functional annotation and three-dimensional structure of Dr0930 from Deinococcus radiodurans: A close relative of phosphotriesterase in the amidohydrolase family. Biochemistry 48, 2237-2247. Fischer, A., Enkler, N., Neudert, G., Bocola, M., Sterner, R. &amp; Merkl, R. (2009). TransCent: Computational enzyme design by transferring active sites and considering constraints relevant for catalysis. BMC Bioinformatics 10, 54. H?cker, B., Lochner, A., Seitz, T., Claren, J. &amp; Sterner, R. (2009). High-resolution crystal structure of an artificial (??)8-barrel protein designed from identical half-barrels.  Biochemistry 48, 1145-1147.   2008 - 2006 Guldan, H., Sterner, R. &amp; Babinger, P. (2008). Identification and Characterization of a Bacterial Glycerol-1-phosphate Dehydrogenase: Ni2+ -Dependent AraM from Bacillus subtilis. Biochemistry 47, 7376-7384. Merkl, R. &amp; Zwick, M. (2008). H2r:Identification of evolutionary important residues by means of an entropy based analysis of multiple sequence alignments. BMC Bioinformatics 9, 151. Reetz, M. T., Rentzsch, M., Pletsch, A., Taglieber, A., Hollmann, F., Mondi?re, R. J. G., Dickmann, N., H?cker, B., Cerrone, S., Haeger, M. C. &amp; Sterner, R. (2008). A Robust Protein Host for Anchoring Chelating Ligands and Organocatalysts. ChemBioChem 9, 552-564. Schwab, T., Skegro, D., Mayans, O. &amp; Sterner, R. (2008). A rationally designed monomeric variant of anthranilate phosphoribosyltransferase from Sulfolobus solfataricus is as active as the dimeric wild-type enzyme but less thermostable. J. Mol. Biol. 376, 506-516. Seitz, T., Bocola, M., Claren, J. &amp; Sterner, R. (2007). Stabilization of a (??)8-Barrel Protein Designed from Identical Half Barrels. J. Mol. Biol. 372, 114-129. Merkl, R. (2007). Modelling the evolution of the archeal tryptophan synthase. BMC Evol Biol. 7, 59. Merkl, R. (2006). AMIGOS: a method for the inspection of genomic organisation or structure and its application to characterise conserved gene arrangements. In Silico Biol. 6, 281-306. Waack, S., Keller, O., Asper, R., Brodag, T., Damm, C., Fricke, W. F., Surovcik, K., Meinicke, P. &amp; Merkl, R. (2006). Score-based prediction of genomic islands in prokaryotic genomes using hidden Markov models. BMC Bioinformatics 7, 142. Merkl, R. (2006). A comparative categorization of protein function encoded in bacterial or archeal genomic islands. J Mol Evol. 62, 1-14. Leopoldseder, S., Hettwer, S. &amp; Sterner, R. (2006). Evolution of Multi-Enzyme Complexes: The Case of Tryptophan Synthase. Biochemistry 45, 14111-14119. Marino, M., Deuss, M., Svergun, D., Konarev, P., Sterner, R. &amp; Mayans, O. (2006). Structural and Mutational Analysis of Substrate Complexation by Anthranilate Phosphoribosyltransferase from Sulfolobus solfataricus. J. Biol. Chem. 281, 21410-21421.   2005 - 2003 Schneider, B., Kn?chel, T., Darimont, B., Hennig, M., Dietrich, S., Babinger, K., Kirschner, K. &amp; Sterner, R. (2005). Role of the N-terminal Extension of the (??)8-Barrel Enzyme Indole-3-Glycerol Phosphate Synthase for its Fold, Stability and Catalytic Activity. Biochemistry 44, 16405-16412. Vega, C., Zou, P., Fernandez, F., Murphy, G., Sterner, R., Popov, A. &amp; Wilmanns, M. (2005). Regulation of the hetero-octameric ATP phosphoribosyl transferase complex from Thermotoga maritima by a tRNA-synthetase-like subunit. Mol. Microbiol. 55, 675-686. Wiezer, A. &amp; Merkl, R. (2005). A comparative categorization of gene flux in diverse microbial species. Genomics 86, 462-475. H?cker, B., Claren, J. &amp; Sterner, R. (2004). Mimicking enzyme evolution by generating new (??)8-barrels from (??)4-half-barrels. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 101, 16448-16453. Thiemann, V., D?nges, C., Prowe, S., Sterner, R. &amp; Antranikian, G. (2004). Characterisation of a thermoalkali-stable cyclodextrin glycosyltransferase from the anaerobic thermoalkaliphilic bacterium Anaerobranca gottschalkii. Arch. Microbiol. 182, 226-235. Leopoldseder, S., Claren, J., J?rgens, C. &amp; Sterner, R. (2004). Interconverting the catalytic activities of (??)8-barrel enzymes from different metabolic pathways: sequence requirements and molecular analysis. J. Mol. Biol. 337, 871-879. Meinicke, P., Tech, M., Morgenstern, B. &amp; Merkl, R. (2004). Oligo kernels for datamining on biological sequences: a case study on prokaryotic translation initiation sites. BMC Bioinformatics 5, 169. Veith, B., Herzberg, C., Steckel, S., Feesche, J., Maurer, K. H., Ehrenreich, P., B?umer, S., Henne, A., Liesegang, H., Merkl, R., Ehrenreich, A. &amp; Gottschalk, G. (2004). The complete genome sequence of Bacillus licheniformis DSM13, an organism with great industrial potential. J Mol Microbiol Biotechnol. 7, 204-211. Merkl, R. (2004). SIGI: score-based identification of genomic islands. BMC Bioinformatics 5, 22. Henne, A., Br?ggemann, H., Raasch, C., Wiezer, A., Hartsch, T., Liesegang, H., Johann, A., Lienard, T., Gohl, O., Martinez-Arias, R., Jacobi, C., Starkuviene, V., Schlenczeck, S., Dencker, S., Huber, R., Klenk, H. P., Kramer W., Merkl, R., Gottschalk, G., &amp; Fritz, H.J.(2004). The genome sequence of the extreme thermophile Thermus thermophilus. Nat. Biotechnol. 22, 547-553. Helmstaedt, K., Heinrich, G., Merkl, R. &amp; Braus, G. H. (2004). Chorismate mutase of Thermus thermophilus is a monofunctional AroH class enzyme inhibited by tyrosine. Arch Microbiol. 181, 195-203. Tech, M. &amp; Merkl, R. (2003). YACOP: Enhanced gene prediction obtained by a combination of existing methods. In Silico Biol. 3, 441-451. Merkl, R. (2003). A survey of codon and amino acid frequency bias in microbial genomes focusing on translational efficiency. J Mol Evol. 57, 453-466. Wiezer, A. &amp; Merkl, R. (2003). secureBLAST. In Silico Biol. 3, 405-409. Bruggemann, H., Baumer, S., Fricke, W. F., Wiezer, A., Liesegang, H., Decker, I., Herzber, C., Martinez-Arias, R., Merkl, R., Henne, A. &amp; Gottschalk, G. (2003). The genome sequence of Clostridium tetani, the causative agent of tetanus disease. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 100, 1316-1321.   2002 - 2000 Henn-Sax, M., Thoma, R., Schmidt, S., Hennig, M., Kirschner, K. &amp; Sterner, R. (2002). Two (??)8-barrel enzymes of histidine and tryptophan biosynthesis have similar reaction mechanisms and common strategies for protecting their labile substrates. Biochemistry 41, 12032-12042. Hettwer, S. &amp; Sterner, R. (2002). A novel tryptophan synthase ?-subunit from the hyperthermophile Thermotoga maritima: quaternary structure, steady-state kinetics, and putative physiological role. J. Biol. Chem. 277, 8194-8201. Douangamath, A., Walker, M., Beismann-Driemeyer, S., Vega-Fernandez, M.C., Sterner, S. &amp; Wilmanns, M. (2002). Structural evidence for ammonia tunnelling across the (??)8-barrel of the imidazole glycerol phosphate synthase bienzyme complex. Structure 10, 185-193. H?cker, B., Schmidt, S. &amp; Sterner, R. (2002). A common evolutionary origin of two elementary enzyme folds. FEBS letters 510, 133-135. Larbig, K. D., Christmann, A., Johann, A., Klockgether, J., Hartsch, T., Merkl, R., Wiehlmann, L., Fritz, H. J. &amp; T?mmler, B. (2002). Gene islands integrated into tRNA(Gly) genes confer genome diversity on a Pseudomonas aeruginosa clone. J Bacteriol. 184, 6665-6680. Deppenmeier, U., Johann, A., Hartsch, T., Merkl, R., Schmitz, R. A., Martinez-Arias, R., Henne, A., Wiezer, A., B?umer, S., Jacobi, C., Br?ggemann, H., Lienard, T., Christmann, A., B?meke, M., Steckel, S., Bhattacharyya, A., Lykidis, A., Overbeek, R., Klenk, H. P., Gunsalus, R. P., Fritz, H. J. &amp; Gottschalk, G. (2002). The genome of Methanosarcina mazei: evidence for lateral gene transfer between bacteria and archaea. J Mol Microbiol Biotechnol. 4, 453-461. Beismann-Driemeyer, S. &amp; Sterner, R. (2001). Imidazole glycerol phosphate synthase from Thermotoga maritima: Quaternary structure, steady-state kinetics and reaction mechanism of the bi-enzyme complex. J. Biol. Chem. 276, 20387-20996. H?cker, B., Beismann-Driemeyer, S., Hettwer, S., Lustig, A. &amp; Sterner, R. (2001). Dissection of a (??)8-barrel enzyme into two folded halves. Nat. Struct. Biol. 8, 32-36. Lang, D., Thoma, R., Henn-Sax, M., Sterner, R. &amp; Wilmanns, M. (2000). Structural evidence for evolution of the  ?/? barrel scaffold by gene duplication and fusion. Science 289, 1546-1550. J?rgens, C., Strom, A., Wegener, D., Hettwer, S., Wilmanns, M. &amp; Sterner, R. (2000). Directed evolution of a (??)8-barrel enzyme to catalyze related reactions in two different metabolic pathways. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 97, 9925-9930. Thoma, R., Hennig, M., Sterner, R. &amp; Kirschner, K. (2000). Structure and function of mutationally generated monomers of dimeric phosphoribosylanthranilate isomerase from Thermotoga maritima. Structure 8, 265-276.   Reviews List, F., Sterner, R. &amp; Wilmanns, M. (2011). Related (??)8-barrel proteins in histidine and tryptophan biosynthesis: a paradigm to study enzyme evolution. ChemBioChem 12, 1487-1494. Sterner, R. &amp; Brunner, E. The relationship between catalytic activity, structural flexibility and conformational stability as deduced from the analysis of mesophilic - thermophilic enzyme pairs and protein engineering studies. In: F. Robb et al., eds., Thermophiles - Biology and Technology at High Temperatures, CRC Press, Boca Raton, London, New York, pp. 25-38, 2008. Sterner, R. &amp; H?cker, B. (2005). Catalytic versatility , stability, and evolution of the (??)8-barrel enzyme fold. Chemical Reviews 105, 4038-4055. Jaenicke, R. &amp; Sterner, R. Life at high temperatures. In: M. Dworkin et al., eds., The Procaryotes: An Evolving Electronic Resource for the Microbiological Community, 3rd edition (Latest update release 3.9, March 2002), New York, Springer-Verlag, 2000. Sterner, R. &amp; Liebl, W. (2001). Thermophilic Adaptation of Proteins. Crit. Rev. Biochem. Mol. Biol. 63, 39-106. Sterner, R., Merz, A., Thoma, R. &amp; Kirschner, K. (2001). Phosphoribosyl anthranilate isomerase and indoleglycerol phosphate synthase: tryptophan biosynthetic enzymes from Thermotoga maritima. Meth. Enzymol. 331, 270-280. Sterner, R. (2001). 4Fe-4S ferredoxin from Thermotoga maritima. Meth. Enzymol. 334, 23-30. H?cker, B., J?rgens, C., Wilmanns, M. &amp; Sterner, R. (2001). Stability, catalytic versatility and evolution of the (??)8-barrel fold. Curr. Opin. Biotechnol. 12, 376-381. Henn-Sax, M., H?cker, B., Wilmanns, M. &amp; Sterner, R. (2001). Divergent evolution of (??)8-barrel enzymes. Biol. Chem. 382, 1315-1317.   Meeting reports, book reviews,  guest editorials Sterner, R. (2011). Directed evolution: a powerful approach to optimising and understanding enzymes. ChemBioChem 12, 1439-1440. Sterner, R., Merkl, R. &amp; Raushel, F.M. (2008). Computational Design of Enzymes. Chem. Biol. 5, 421-423. Sterner, R. &amp; Skerra, A. (2007). Design von Enzymen und anderen Proteinen: Einblicke aus Natur, Labor und Computersimulationen. Biospektrum 07, 814. Sterner, R. &amp; Schmid, F.X. (2004). De novo design of an enzyme. Science 304, 1916-1917. Schmid, F.X. &amp; Sterner, R. (2004). Protein Design. ChemBioChem 5, 143-144. Jaenicke, R. &amp; Sterner, R. (2003). Protein Design at the Crossroads of Biotechnology, Chemistry, Theory, and Evolution. Futura 18, 5-10. Jaenicke, R. &amp; Sterner, R. (2003). Protein Design at the Crossroads of Biotechnology, Chemistry, Theory, and Evolution. Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. 42, 140-142. Sterner, R. (2003). Book Review: Directed Molecular Evolution of Proteins or How to Improve Enzymes for Biocatalysis. Edited by S. Brakmann and K. Johnsson. ChemBioChem 4, 119.      </field>
<field name="important">Publications     Location Home Research More ...   Selected publications since 2000 Original research articles 2014 - 2013 Peterhoff, D., Beer, B., Rajendran, C., Kumpula, E.P., Kapetaniou, E., Guldan, H., Wierenga, R.K., Sterner, R. &amp; Babinger, P. (2014). A comprehensive analysis of the geranylgeranylglyceryl phosphate synthase enzyme family identifies novel members and reveals mechanisms of substrate specificity and quaternary structure organization. Mol. Microbiol. 92, 885-899. Sommer, B., Waege, I., P?llmann, D., Seitz, T., Thomm, M., Sterner, R. &amp; Hausner, W. (2014). Activation of a chimeric Rpb5/RpoH subunit using library selection. PLoS One 9, e87485. Reisinger, B.,  Kuzmanovic, N., L?ffler, P., Merkl, R., K?nig, B. &amp; Sterner, R. (2014). Expoiting protein symmetry to design light-controllable enzyme inhibitors. Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. 53, 595-598. Reisinger, B.,  Sperl, J., Holinski, A., Schmid, V., Rajendran, C., Carstensen, L., Schlee, S., Blanquart, S., Merkl, R. &amp; Sterner, R. (2014). Evidence for the existence of elaborate enzyme complexes in the paleoarchean era. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 136, 122-129. Janda, J. O., Meier, A. &amp; Merkl, R. (2013). CLIPS-4D: a classifier that distinguishes structurally and functionally important residue-positions based on sequence and 3D data. Bioinformatics 29, 3029-3035. Sperl, J. M., Rohweder, B., Rajendran, C. &amp; Sterner, R. (2013). Establishing catalytic activity on an artificial (??)8-barrel protein designed from identical half-barrels. FEBS Lett. 587, 2798-2805. Meier, M.M., Rajendran, C., Malisi, C., Fox, N.G., Xu, C., Schlee, S., Barondeau, D.P. Hoecker, B., Sterner, R. &amp; Raushel, F.M. (2013). Molecular engineering of organophosphate hydrolysis activity from a weak promiscuous lactonase template. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 135, 11670-11677. Hauptmann, J., Dueck, A., Harlander, S., Pfaff, J., Merkl, R. &amp; Meister, G. (2013). Turning catalytically inactive human Argonaute proteins into active slicer enzymes. Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol. 20, 814-817. Schlee, S., Dietrich, S., Kurcon, T., Delaney, P., Goodey, N.M. &amp; Sterner, R. (2013). Kinetic mechanism of indole-3-glycerol phosphate synthase. Biochemistry 52, 132-142.   2012 - 2011 List, F., Vega, M. C., Razeto, A., Haeger, M. C., Sterner, R. &amp; Wilmanns, M. (2012). Catalysis uncoupling in a glutamine amidotransferase bienzyme by unblocking the glutaminase active site. Chem. Biol. 19, 1589-1599. Reisinger, B.,  Bocola, M., List, F., Claren, J., Rajendran, C. &amp; Sterner, R. (2012). A sugar isomerization reaction established on various (??)8 -barrel scaffolds is based on substrate-assisted catalysis. Protein Eng. Des. Sel. 11, 751-760. Carstensen, L., Sperl, J. M., Bocola, M., List, F., Schmid, F. X. &amp; Sterner, R. (2012). Conservation of the folding mechanism between designed primordial (??)8-barrel proteins and their modern descendant. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 134, 12786-12791. Dietrich, S., Borst, N., Schlee, S., Schneider, D., Janda, J. O., Sterner, R. &amp; Merkl, R. (2012). Experimental assessment of the importance of amino acid positions identified by an entropy-based correlation analysis of multiple sequence alignments. Biochemistry 51, 5633-5641. Peterhoff, D., Zellner, H., Gudan, H., Merkl, R., Sterner, R. &amp; Babinger, P. (2012).  Dimerization determines substrate specificity of a bacterial prenyltransferase. ChemBioChem 13, 1297-1303. Evran, S., Telefoncu, A. &amp; Sterner, R. (2012). Directed evolution of (??)8-barrel enzymes: establishing phosphoribosylanthranilate isomerisation activity on the scaffold of the tryptophan synthase ?-subunit. Protein Eng. Des. Sel. 25, 285-293. Craig, D. B., Schwab, T. &amp; Sterner, R. (2012). Random mutagenesis suggests that sequence errors are not a major cause of variation in the activity of individual molecules of ?-galactosidase. Biochem. Cell Biol. 90, 540-547. Carstensen, L., Zold?k, G., Schmid, F. X. &amp; Sterner, R. (2012). Folding mechanism of an extremely thermostable (??)8-barrel enzyme: a high kinetic barrier protects the protein from denaturation. Biochemistry 51, 3420-3432. List, F., Bocola, M., Haeger, M. C. &amp; Sterner, R. (2012). Constitutively active glutaminase variants provide insights into the activation mechanism of anthranilate synthase. Biochemistry 51, 2812-2818. Guldan, H., Matysik, F. M., Bocola, M., Sterner, R. &amp; Babinger, P. (2011). Functional assignment of an enzyme that catalyzes the synthesis of an archaea-type ether lipid in bacteria. Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. Engl. 50, 8188-8191. Fischer, A., Seitz, T., Lochner, A., Sterner, R., Merkl, R. &amp; Bocola, M. (2011). A fast and precise approach for computational saturation mutagenesis and its experimental validation by using an artificial (??)8-barrel protein. ChemBioChem 12, 1544-1550. Schwab, T. &amp; Sterner, R. (2011). Stabilization of a metabolic enzyme by library selection in Thermus thermophilus. ChemBioChem  12, 1581-1588.   2010 - 2009 Ehrmann, A., Richter, K., Busch, F., Reimann, J., Albers, S.V. &amp; Sterner, R. (2010). Ligand-inducted formation of a transient tryptophan synthase complex with ??? subunit stoichiometry. Biochemistry 49, 10842-10853. Mandach, C. &amp; Merkl R. (2010) Genes optimized by evolution for accurate and fast translation encode in Archaea and Bacteria a braod and characteristic spectrum of protein functions. BMC Genomics 11, 617. Seitz, T., Thoma, R., Schoch, G.A., Stihle, M., Benz, J., D'Arcy, B., Wiget, A., Ruf, A., Hennig, M. &amp; Sterner, R. (2010). Enhancing the stability and solubility of the glucocorticoid receptor ligand-binding domain by high-throughput library screening. J. Mol. Biol. 403, 562-577. Liebold, C., List, F., Kalbitzer, H.R., Sterner, R. &amp; Brunner, E. (2010). The interaction of ammonia and xenon with the imidazole glycerol phosphate synthase from Thermotoga maritima as detected by NMR spectroscopy.  Protein Sci. 19, 1774-1782. Richter, M., Bosnali, M., Carstensen, L., Seitz, T., Durchschlag, H., Blanquart, S., Merkl, R. &amp; Sterner, R. (2010). Computational and experimental evidence for the evolution of a (??)8-barrel protein from an ancestral quarter-barrel stabilised by disulfide bonds.  J. Mol. Biol. 398, 763-773. Drzewiecki, K., Angelov, A., Ballschmiter, M. Tiefenbach, K.-J., Sterner, R. &amp; Liebl, W. (2010) Hyperthermostable acetyl xylan esterase. Microbial Biotechnol. 3, 84-92. Merkl R, Wiezer A. (2009) GO4genome: A prokaryotic phylogeny based on genome organization. J. Mol. Evol. 68, 550-562. Schlee, S., Deuss, M., Bruning, M., Ivens, A., Schwab, T., Hellmann, N., Mayans, O. &amp; Sterner, R. (2009). Activation of anthranilate phosphoribosyl transferase from Sulfolobus solfataricus by removal of Mg-inhibition and acceleration of product release. Biochemistry 48, 5199-5209. Claren, J., Malisi, C., H?cker, B. &amp; Sterner, R. (2009). Establishing wild-type levels of catalytic activity on natural and artificial (??)8-barrel protein scaffolds.  Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 106, 3704-3709. Xiang, D. F., Kolb, P., Meier, M. M., Fedorov, E. V., Fedorov, A. A., Sterner, R., Almo S. C., Shoichet, B. K. &amp; Raushel, F. M. (2009). Functional annotation and three-dimensional structure of Dr0930 from Deinococcus radiodurans: A close relative of phosphotriesterase in the amidohydrolase family. Biochemistry 48, 2237-2247. Fischer, A., Enkler, N., Neudert, G., Bocola, M., Sterner, R. &amp; Merkl, R. (2009). TransCent: Computational enzyme design by transferring active sites and considering constraints relevant for catalysis. BMC Bioinformatics 10, 54. H?cker, B., Lochner, A., Seitz, T., Claren, J. &amp; Sterner, R. (2009). High-resolution crystal structure of an artificial (??)8-barrel protein designed from identical half-barrels.  Biochemistry 48, 1145-1147.   2008 - 2006 Guldan, H., Sterner, R. &amp; Babinger, P. (2008). Identification and Characterization of a Bacterial Glycerol-1-phosphate Dehydrogenase: Ni2+ -Dependent AraM from Bacillus subtilis. Biochemistry 47, 7376-7384. Merkl, R. &amp; Zwick, M. (2008). H2r:Identification of evolutionary important residues by means of an entropy based analysis of multiple sequence alignments. BMC Bioinformatics 9, 151. Reetz, M. T., Rentzsch, M., Pletsch, A., Taglieber, A., Hollmann, F., Mondi?re, R. J. G., Dickmann, N., H?cker, B., Cerrone, S., Haeger, M. C. &amp; Sterner, R. (2008). A Robust Protein Host for Anchoring Chelating Ligands and Organocatalysts. ChemBioChem 9, 552-564. Schwab, T., Skegro, D., Mayans, O. &amp; Sterner, R. (2008). A rationally designed monomeric variant of anthranilate phosphoribosyltransferase from Sulfolobus solfataricus is as active as the dimeric wild-type enzyme but less thermostable. J. Mol. Biol. 376, 506-516. Seitz, T., Bocola, M., Claren, J. &amp; Sterner, R. (2007). Stabilization of a (??)8-Barrel Protein Designed from Identical Half Barrels. J. Mol. Biol. 372, 114-129. Merkl, R. (2007). Modelling the evolution of the archeal tryptophan synthase. BMC Evol Biol. 7, 59. Merkl, R. (2006). AMIGOS: a method for the inspection of genomic organisation or structure and its application to characterise conserved gene arrangements. In Silico Biol. 6, 281-306. Waack, S., Keller, O., Asper, R., Brodag, T., Damm, C., Fricke, W. F., Surovcik, K., Meinicke, P. &amp; Merkl, R. (2006). Score-based prediction of genomic islands in prokaryotic genomes using hidden Markov models. BMC Bioinformatics 7, 142. Merkl, R. (2006). A comparative categorization of protein function encoded in bacterial or archeal genomic islands. J Mol Evol. 62, 1-14. Leopoldseder, S., Hettwer, S. &amp; Sterner, R. (2006). Evolution of Multi-Enzyme Complexes: The Case of Tryptophan Synthase. Biochemistry 45, 14111-14119. Marino, M., Deuss, M., Svergun, D., Konarev, P., Sterner, R. &amp; Mayans, O. (2006). Structural and Mutational Analysis of Substrate Complexation by Anthranilate Phosphoribosyltransferase from Sulfolobus solfataricus. J. Biol. Chem. 281, 21410-21421.   2005 - 2003 Schneider, B., Kn?chel, T., Darimont, B., Hennig, M., Dietrich, S., Babinger, K., Kirschner, K. &amp; Sterner, R. (2005). Role of the N-terminal Extension of the (??)8-Barrel Enzyme Indole-3-Glycerol Phosphate Synthase for its Fold, Stability and Catalytic Activity. Biochemistry 44, 16405-16412. Vega, C., Zou, P., Fernandez, F., Murphy, G., Sterner, R., Popov, A. &amp; Wilmanns, M. (2005). Regulation of the hetero-octameric ATP phosphoribosyl transferase complex from Thermotoga maritima by a tRNA-synthetase-like subunit. Mol. Microbiol. 55, 675-686. Wiezer, A. &amp; Merkl, R. (2005). A comparative categorization of gene flux in diverse microbial species. Genomics 86, 462-475. H?cker, B., Claren, J. &amp; Sterner, R. (2004). Mimicking enzyme evolution by generating new (??)8-barrels from (??)4-half-barrels. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 101, 16448-16453. Thiemann, V., D?nges, C., Prowe, S., Sterner, R. &amp; Antranikian, G. (2004). Characterisation of a thermoalkali-stable cyclodextrin glycosyltransferase from the anaerobic thermoalkaliphilic bacterium Anaerobranca gottschalkii. Arch. Microbiol. 182, 226-235. Leopoldseder, S., Claren, J., J?rgens, C. &amp; Sterner, R. (2004). Interconverting the catalytic activities of (??)8-barrel enzymes from different metabolic pathways: sequence requirements and molecular analysis. J. Mol. Biol. 337, 871-879. Meinicke, P., Tech, M., Morgenstern, B. &amp; Merkl, R. (2004). Oligo kernels for datamining on biological sequences: a case study on prokaryotic translation initiation sites. BMC Bioinformatics 5, 169. Veith, B., Herzberg, C., Steckel, S., Feesche, J., Maurer, K. H., Ehrenreich, P., B?umer, S., Henne, A., Liesegang, H., Merkl, R., Ehrenreich, A. &amp; Gottschalk, G. (2004). The complete genome sequence of Bacillus licheniformis DSM13, an organism with great industrial potential. J Mol Microbiol Biotechnol. 7, 204-211. Merkl, R. (2004). SIGI: score-based identification of genomic islands. BMC Bioinformatics 5, 22. Henne, A., Br?ggemann, H., Raasch, C., Wiezer, A., Hartsch, T., Liesegang, H., Johann, A., Lienard, T., Gohl, O., Martinez-Arias, R., Jacobi, C., Starkuviene, V., Schlenczeck, S., Dencker, S., Huber, R., Klenk, H. P., Kramer W., Merkl, R., Gottschalk, G., &amp; Fritz, H.J.(2004). The genome sequence of the extreme thermophile Thermus thermophilus. Nat. Biotechnol. 22, 547-553. Helmstaedt, K., Heinrich, G., Merkl, R. &amp; Braus, G. H. (2004). Chorismate mutase of Thermus thermophilus is a monofunctional AroH class enzyme inhibited by tyrosine. Arch Microbiol. 181, 195-203. Tech, M. &amp; Merkl, R. (2003). YACOP: Enhanced gene prediction obtained by a combination of existing methods. In Silico Biol. 3, 441-451. Merkl, R. (2003). A survey of codon and amino acid frequency bias in microbial genomes focusing on translational efficiency. J Mol Evol. 57, 453-466. Wiezer, A. &amp; Merkl, R. (2003). secureBLAST. In Silico Biol. 3, 405-409. Bruggemann, H., Baumer, S., Fricke, W. F., Wiezer, A., Liesegang, H., Decker, I., Herzber, C., Martinez-Arias, R., Merkl, R., Henne, A. &amp; Gottschalk, G. (2003). The genome sequence of Clostridium tetani, the causative agent of tetanus disease. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 100, 1316-1321.   2002 - 2000 Henn-Sax, M., Thoma, R., Schmidt, S., Hennig, M., Kirschner, K. &amp; Sterner, R. (2002). Two (??)8-barrel enzymes of histidine and tryptophan biosynthesis have similar reaction mechanisms and common strategies for protecting their labile substrates. Biochemistry 41, 12032-12042. Hettwer, S. &amp; Sterner, R. (2002). A novel tryptophan synthase ?-subunit from the hyperthermophile Thermotoga maritima: quaternary structure, steady-state kinetics, and putative physiological role. J. Biol. Chem. 277, 8194-8201. Douangamath, A., Walker, M., Beismann-Driemeyer, S., Vega-Fernandez, M.C., Sterner, S. &amp; Wilmanns, M. (2002). Structural evidence for ammonia tunnelling across the (??)8-barrel of the imidazole glycerol phosphate synthase bienzyme complex. Structure 10, 185-193. H?cker, B., Schmidt, S. &amp; Sterner, R. (2002). A common evolutionary origin of two elementary enzyme folds. FEBS letters 510, 133-135. Larbig, K. D., Christmann, A., Johann, A., Klockgether, J., Hartsch, T., Merkl, R., Wiehlmann, L., Fritz, H. J. &amp; T?mmler, B. (2002). Gene islands integrated into tRNA(Gly) genes confer genome diversity on a Pseudomonas aeruginosa clone. J Bacteriol. 184, 6665-6680. Deppenmeier, U., Johann, A., Hartsch, T., Merkl, R., Schmitz, R. A., Martinez-Arias, R., Henne, A., Wiezer, A., B?umer, S., Jacobi, C., Br?ggemann, H., Lienard, T., Christmann, A., B?meke, M., Steckel, S., Bhattacharyya, A., Lykidis, A., Overbeek, R., Klenk, H. P., Gunsalus, R. P., Fritz, H. J. &amp; Gottschalk, G. (2002). The genome of Methanosarcina mazei: evidence for lateral gene transfer between bacteria and archaea. J Mol Microbiol Biotechnol. 4, 453-461. Beismann-Driemeyer, S. &amp; Sterner, R. (2001). Imidazole glycerol phosphate synthase from Thermotoga maritima: Quaternary structure, steady-state kinetics and reaction mechanism of the bi-enzyme complex. J. Biol. Chem. 276, 20387-20996. H?cker, B., Beismann-Driemeyer, S., Hettwer, S., Lustig, A. &amp; Sterner, R. (2001). Dissection of a (??)8-barrel enzyme into two folded halves. Nat. Struct. Biol. 8, 32-36. Lang, D., Thoma, R., Henn-Sax, M., Sterner, R. &amp; Wilmanns, M. (2000). Structural evidence for evolution of the  ?/? barrel scaffold by gene duplication and fusion. Science 289, 1546-1550. J?rgens, C., Strom, A., Wegener, D., Hettwer, S., Wilmanns, M. &amp; Sterner, R. (2000). Directed evolution of a (??)8-barrel enzyme to catalyze related reactions in two different metabolic pathways. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 97, 9925-9930. Thoma, R., Hennig, M., Sterner, R. &amp; Kirschner, K. (2000). Structure and function of mutationally generated monomers of dimeric phosphoribosylanthranilate isomerase from Thermotoga maritima. Structure 8, 265-276.   Reviews List, F., Sterner, R. &amp; Wilmanns, M. (2011). Related (??)8-barrel proteins in histidine and tryptophan biosynthesis: a paradigm to study enzyme evolution. ChemBioChem 12, 1487-1494. Sterner, R. &amp; Brunner, E. The relationship between catalytic activity, structural flexibility and conformational stability as deduced from the analysis of mesophilic - thermophilic enzyme pairs and protein engineering studies. In: F. Robb et al., eds., Thermophiles - Biology and Technology at High Temperatures, CRC Press, Boca Raton, London, New York, pp. 25-38, 2008. Sterner, R. &amp; H?cker, B. (2005). Catalytic versatility , stability, and evolution of the (??)8-barrel enzyme fold. Chemical Reviews 105, 4038-4055. Jaenicke, R. &amp; Sterner, R. Life at high temperatures. In: M. Dworkin et al., eds., The Procaryotes: An Evolving Electronic Resource for the Microbiological Community, 3rd edition (Latest update release 3.9, March 2002), New York, Springer-Verlag, 2000. Sterner, R. &amp; Liebl, W. (2001). Thermophilic Adaptation of Proteins. Crit. Rev. Biochem. Mol. Biol. 63, 39-106. Sterner, R., Merz, A., Thoma, R. &amp; Kirschner, K. (2001). Phosphoribosyl anthranilate isomerase and indoleglycerol phosphate synthase: tryptophan biosynthetic enzymes from Thermotoga maritima. Meth. Enzymol. 331, 270-280. Sterner, R. (2001). 4Fe-4S ferredoxin from Thermotoga maritima. Meth. Enzymol. 334, 23-30. H?cker, B., J?rgens, C., Wilmanns, M. &amp; Sterner, R. (2001). Stability, catalytic versatility and evolution of the (??)8-barrel fold. Curr. Opin. Biotechnol. 12, 376-381. Henn-Sax, M., H?cker, B., Wilmanns, M. &amp; Sterner, R. (2001). Divergent evolution of (??)8-barrel enzymes. Biol. Chem. 382, 1315-1317.   Meeting reports, book reviews,  guest editorials Sterner, R. (2011). Directed evolution: a powerful approach to optimising and understanding enzymes. ChemBioChem 12, 1439-1440. Sterner, R., Merkl, R. &amp; Raushel, F.M. (2008). Computational Design of Enzymes. Chem. Biol. 5, 421-423. Sterner, R. &amp; Skerra, A. (2007). Design von Enzymen und anderen Proteinen: Einblicke aus Natur, Labor und Computersimulationen. Biospektrum 07, 814. Sterner, R. &amp; Schmid, F.X. (2004). De novo design of an enzyme. Science 304, 1916-1917. Schmid, F.X. &amp; Sterner, R. (2004). Protein Design. ChemBioChem 5, 143-144. Jaenicke, R. &amp; Sterner, R. (2003). Protein Design at the Crossroads of Biotechnology, Chemistry, Theory, and Evolution. Futura 18, 5-10. Jaenicke, R. &amp; Sterner, R. (2003). Protein Design at the Crossroads of Biotechnology, Chemistry, Theory, and Evolution. Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. 42, 140-142. Sterner, R. (2003). Book Review: Directed Molecular Evolution of Proteins or How to Improve Enzymes for Biocatalysis. Edited by S. Brakmann and K. Johnsson. ChemBioChem 4, 119.      </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Biochemie2/www/staff.html</field>
<field name="title">People of Biochemistry II</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Biochemie2/www/staff.html</field>
<field name="content">People of Biochemistry II Location Research Home More ...       Tel (49)941-943-   Room   Email Address @biologie.uni-regensburg.de Prof. Dr. Reinhard Sterner 30 15 4.1.27 Reinhard.Sterner Claudia Pauer (Secretary) 30 04 4.1.26 Claudia.Pauer Dr. Helmut Durchschlag 30 41 4.1.01 Helmut.Durchschlag Prof. Dr. Rainer Merkl 30 86 4.1.25 Rainer.Merkl Dr. Patrick Babinger 16 34 4.1.05 Patrick.Babinger   Dr. Bettina Rohweder   33 39   4.1.02   Bettina.Rohweder Dr. Sandra Schlee 33 39 4.1.02 Sandra.Schlee   Dr. Heike St?er   33 39   4.1.02   Heike.Stueer Klaus-J?rgen Tiefenbach 30 40 4.1.31 Klaus-Juergen.Tiefenbach Laboratory assistants (Technische Assistentinnen) Christiane Endres 16 34 4.1.05 Christiane.Endres Sonja Fuchs 16 36 4.1.07 Sonja.Fuchs Hermine Reisner 16 34 4.1.05 Hermine.Reisner Jeannette Ueckert 33 39 4.1.02 Jeannette.Ueckert Graduate students (Doktoranden)   Florian Busch   16 36   4.1.07   Florian.Busch   Kristina Heyn   30 28   4.1.04   Kristina.Heyn   Alexandra Holinski   16 34   4.1.05   Alexandra.Holinski   Wolfgang Kaiser   16 34   4.1.04   Wolfgang.Kaiser   Mona Linde   16 34   4.1.05   Mona.Linde   Patrick L?ffler   30 28   4.1.04   Patrick.Loeffler   David Peterhoff   16 36   4.1.07   David.Peterhoff   Maximilian Plach   33 39   4.1.02   Maximilian.Plach   Bernd Reisinger   16 36   4.1.02   Bernd.Reisinger Undergraduates (Masterstudenten)   Michael Schupfner   16 36   4.1.07   Michael.Schupfner                 Alumni (Ehemalige des Lehrstuhls)    </field>
<field name="important">People of Biochemistry II Location Research Home More ...       Tel (49)941-943-   Room   Email Address @biologie.uni-regensburg.de Prof. Dr. Reinhard Sterner 30 15 4.1.27 Reinhard.Sterner Claudia Pauer (Secretary) 30 04 4.1.26 Claudia.Pauer Dr. Helmut Durchschlag 30 41 4.1.01 Helmut.Durchschlag Prof. Dr. Rainer Merkl 30 86 4.1.25 Rainer.Merkl Dr. Patrick Babinger 16 34 4.1.05 Patrick.Babinger   Dr. Bettina Rohweder   33 39   4.1.02   Bettina.Rohweder Dr. Sandra Schlee 33 39 4.1.02 Sandra.Schlee   Dr. Heike St?er   33 39   4.1.02   Heike.Stueer Klaus-J?rgen Tiefenbach 30 40 4.1.31 Klaus-Juergen.Tiefenbach Laboratory assistants (Technische Assistentinnen) Christiane Endres 16 34 4.1.05 Christiane.Endres Sonja Fuchs 16 36 4.1.07 Sonja.Fuchs Hermine Reisner 16 34 4.1.05 Hermine.Reisner Jeannette Ueckert 33 39 4.1.02 Jeannette.Ueckert Graduate students (Doktoranden)   Florian Busch   16 36   4.1.07   Florian.Busch   Kristina Heyn   30 28   4.1.04   Kristina.Heyn   Alexandra Holinski   16 34   4.1.05   Alexandra.Holinski   Wolfgang Kaiser   16 34   4.1.04   Wolfgang.Kaiser   Mona Linde   16 34   4.1.05   Mona.Linde   Patrick L?ffler   30 28   4.1.04   Patrick.Loeffler   David Peterhoff   16 36   4.1.07   David.Peterhoff   Maximilian Plach   33 39   4.1.02   Maximilian.Plach   Bernd Reisinger   16 36   4.1.02   Bernd.Reisinger Undergraduates (Masterstudenten)   Michael Schupfner   16 36   4.1.07   Michael.Schupfner                 Alumni (Ehemalige des Lehrstuhls)    </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/</field>
<field name="title">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/</field>
<field name="content">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Supervisors  Publications  Lectures  Scholarships    Intranet (+ misc. info)           Graduate College (GRK 640) "Sensory photoreceptors in natural and artificial systems"  University of Regensburg   The DFG Graduate College is an interdisciplinary internationally oriented enterprise for cooperative research and post graduate education, that brings together activities from biology, chemistry, medicine and physics. Students with academic education (Master or Diploma) in one of these fields, who would like to join this interdisciplinary project as PhD students or postdoc, are invited to apply for one of the 11 scholarships. Proficiency of the German language is not required.    webmaster                 </field>
<field name="important">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Supervisors  Publications  Lectures  Scholarships    Intranet (+ misc. info)           Graduate College (GRK 640) "Sensory photoreceptors in natural and artificial systems"  University of Regensburg   The DFG Graduate College is an interdisciplinary internationally oriented enterprise for cooperative research and post graduate education, that brings together activities from biology, chemistry, medicine and physics. Students with academic education (Master or Diploma) in one of these fields, who would like to join this interdisciplinary project as PhD students or postdoc, are invited to apply for one of the 11 scholarships. Proficiency of the German language is not required.    webmaster                 </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/count/sqrreview.php</field>
<field name="title">redirecting</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/count/sqrreview.php</field>
<field name="content">redirecting</field>
<field name="important">redirecting</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/dfg.html</field>
<field name="title">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/dfg.html</field>
<field name="content">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview   about this college   about the DFG   light and matter  Projects  Graduates  Supervisors  Publications  Lectures  Scholarships    Intranet (+ misc. info)           About the DFG: DFG is the central public funding organization for academic research in Germany. DFG is thus comparable to a Research Council (in British and western European terminology) or a (national) Research Foundation (in American and far eastern terminology).   Graduate College - What's that? Operating since 1990, the programme of Graduate Colleges has soon become one of the most competitive funding modes available in the DFG environment. It is designed to promote high-quality graduate (doctoral) studies through participation of graduate students recruited through country-wide calls in (often interdisciplinary) research programmes. Graduate students supported by the Graduate Colleges, who are autonomous in their selection of candidates, may be German or foreign nationals. The maximum funding period for a Graduate College has been set to nine years. The programme aims, inter alia, at shortening the average time for doctoration to three years after the first degree.  For further information see: http://www.dfg.de/english/              </field>
<field name="important">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview   about this college   about the DFG   light and matter  Projects  Graduates  Supervisors  Publications  Lectures  Scholarships    Intranet (+ misc. info)           About the DFG: DFG is the central public funding organization for academic research in Germany. DFG is thus comparable to a Research Council (in British and western European terminology) or a (national) Research Foundation (in American and far eastern terminology).   Graduate College - What's that? Operating since 1990, the programme of Graduate Colleges has soon become one of the most competitive funding modes available in the DFG environment. It is designed to promote high-quality graduate (doctoral) studies through participation of graduate students recruited through country-wide calls in (often interdisciplinary) research programmes. Graduate students supported by the Graduate Colleges, who are autonomous in their selection of candidates, may be German or foreign nationals. The maximum funding period for a Graduate College has been set to nine years. The programme aims, inter alia, at shortening the average time for doctoration to three years after the first degree.  For further information see: http://www.dfg.de/english/              </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/download/molbiolcourse/index.html</field>
<field name="title">Practical course</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/download/molbiolcourse/index.html</field>
<field name="content">Practical course Practical course on October 28th 2002 image ZIP archive dscn0001 800 X 600 71 KB dscn0002 800 X 600 46 KB dscn0003 800 X 600 67 KB dscn0004 800 X 600 61 KB dscn0005 800 X 600 62 KB dscn0006 800 X 600 85 KB dscn0007 800 X 600 62 KB dscn0008 800 X 600 73 KB dscn0009 800 X 600 63 KB dscn0010 800 X 600 56 KB dscn0011 800 X 600 69 KB dscn0012 800 X 600 74 KB dscn0013 800 X 600 55 KB dscn0014 800 X 600 57 KB dscn0015 800 X 600 82 KB dscn0016 800 X 600 75 KB dscn0017 800 X 600 77 KB dscn0018 800 X 600 57 KB dscn0019 800 X 600 59 KB dscn0020 800 X 600 53 KB dscn0021 800 X 600 79 KB dscn0022 800 X 600 83 KB dscn0023 800 X 600 79 KB dscn0024 800 X 600 89 KB This gallery created by trial version of Express Thumbnail Creator</field>
<field name="important">Practical course Practical course on October 28th 2002 image ZIP archive dscn0001 800 X 600 71 KB dscn0002 800 X 600 46 KB dscn0003 800 X 600 67 KB dscn0004 800 X 600 61 KB dscn0005 800 X 600 62 KB dscn0006 800 X 600 85 KB dscn0007 800 X 600 62 KB dscn0008 800 X 600 73 KB dscn0009 800 X 600 63 KB dscn0010 800 X 600 56 KB dscn0011 800 X 600 69 KB dscn0012 800 X 600 74 KB dscn0013 800 X 600 55 KB dscn0014 800 X 600 57 KB dscn0015 800 X 600 82 KB dscn0016 800 X 600 75 KB dscn0017 800 X 600 77 KB dscn0018 800 X 600 57 KB dscn0019 800 X 600 59 KB dscn0020 800 X 600 53 KB dscn0021 800 X 600 79 KB dscn0022 800 X 600 83 KB dscn0023 800 X 600 79 KB dscn0024 800 X 600 89 KB This gallery created by trial version of Express Thumbnail Creator</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/intra/Kostenz2008/Bilder_Kostenz_2008/index.html</field>
<field name="title">images</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/intra/Kostenz2008/Bilder_Kostenz_2008/index.html</field>
<field name="content">images Summer Meeting 2008 Impressions   image001.jpg   image002.jpg   image003.jpg   image004.jpg   image005.jpg   image006.jpg   image007.jpg   image008.jpg   image009.jpg   image010.jpg   image011.jpg   image012.jpg   image013.jpg   image014.jpg   image015.jpg   image016.jpg   image017.jpg   image018.jpg   image019.jpg  </field>
<field name="important">images Summer Meeting 2008 Impressions   image001.jpg   image002.jpg   image003.jpg   image004.jpg   image005.jpg   image006.jpg   image007.jpg   image008.jpg   image009.jpg   image010.jpg   image011.jpg   image012.jpg   image013.jpg   image014.jpg   image015.jpg   image016.jpg   image017.jpg   image018.jpg   image019.jpg  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/intra/Regen2004/Fotos1/Regen-Fotos1.html</field>
<field name="title">Summer Meeting Regen 2004 - Fotos2</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/intra/Regen2004/Fotos1/Regen-Fotos1.html</field>
<field name="content">Summer Meeting Regen 2004 - Fotos2 Summer Meeting Regen 2004 - Fotos2 Back to Homepage GCSP image001.jpg 214.28 KB image002.jpg 202.75 KB image003.jpg 210.27 KB image004.jpg 212.63 KB image005.jpg 212.72 KB image006.jpg 214.10 KB image007.jpg 48.90 KB image008.jpg 121.46 KB image009.jpg 130.56 KB image010.jpg 113.99 KB image011.jpg 104.91 KB image012.jpg 116.54 KB image013.jpg 131.30 KB image014.jpg 129.11 KB image015.jpg 138.20 KB image016.jpg 114.00 KB image017.jpg 112.98 KB image018.jpg 63.81 KB image019.jpg 191.32 KB image020.jpg 147.78 KB image021.jpg 164.84 KB image022.jpg 187.11 KB image023.jpg 134.77 KB image024.jpg 231.73 KB image025.jpg 178.53 KB image026.jpg 116.53 KB image027.jpg 242.67 KB image028.jpg 215.37 KB image029.jpg 104.38 KB image030.jpg 213.42 KB image031.jpg 91.32 KB image032.jpg 133.86 KB image033.jpg 158.12 KB image034.jpg 154.04 KB image035.jpg 155.07 KB image036.jpg 143.68 KB image037.jpg 132.83 KB image038.jpg 151.83 KB image039.jpg 128.69 KB image040.jpg 128.84 KB image041.jpg 143.21 KB image042.jpg 172.11 KB image043.jpg 100.29 KB image044.jpg 115.57 KB image045.jpg 116.95 KB Created by IrfanView</field>
<field name="important">Summer Meeting Regen 2004 - Fotos2 Summer Meeting Regen 2004 - Fotos2 Back to Homepage GCSP image001.jpg 214.28 KB image002.jpg 202.75 KB image003.jpg 210.27 KB image004.jpg 212.63 KB image005.jpg 212.72 KB image006.jpg 214.10 KB image007.jpg 48.90 KB image008.jpg 121.46 KB image009.jpg 130.56 KB image010.jpg 113.99 KB image011.jpg 104.91 KB image012.jpg 116.54 KB image013.jpg 131.30 KB image014.jpg 129.11 KB image015.jpg 138.20 KB image016.jpg 114.00 KB image017.jpg 112.98 KB image018.jpg 63.81 KB image019.jpg 191.32 KB image020.jpg 147.78 KB image021.jpg 164.84 KB image022.jpg 187.11 KB image023.jpg 134.77 KB image024.jpg 231.73 KB image025.jpg 178.53 KB image026.jpg 116.53 KB image027.jpg 242.67 KB image028.jpg 215.37 KB image029.jpg 104.38 KB image030.jpg 213.42 KB image031.jpg 91.32 KB image032.jpg 133.86 KB image033.jpg 158.12 KB image034.jpg 154.04 KB image035.jpg 155.07 KB image036.jpg 143.68 KB image037.jpg 132.83 KB image038.jpg 151.83 KB image039.jpg 128.69 KB image040.jpg 128.84 KB image041.jpg 143.21 KB image042.jpg 172.11 KB image043.jpg 100.29 KB image044.jpg 115.57 KB image045.jpg 116.95 KB Created by IrfanView</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/intra/Regen2004/Fotos2/Regen-Fotos2.html</field>
<field name="title">Summer Meeting Regen 2004 - Fotos2</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/intra/Regen2004/Fotos2/Regen-Fotos2.html</field>
<field name="content">Summer Meeting Regen 2004 - Fotos2 Summer Meeting Regen 2004 - Fotos2 Back to Homepage GCSP image001.jpg 91.85 KB image002.jpg 63.72 KB image003.jpg 68.11 KB image004.jpg 81.56 KB image005.jpg 64.55 KB image006.jpg 82.04 KB image007.jpg 98.99 KB image008.jpg 83.09 KB image009.jpg 78.08 KB image010.jpg 74.40 KB image011.jpg 67.15 KB image012.jpg 107.37 KB image013.jpg 110.34 KB image014.jpg 68.72 KB image015.jpg 66.79 KB image016.jpg 92.76 KB image017.jpg 89.01 KB image018.jpg 88.21 KB image019.jpg 86.34 KB image020.jpg 78.99 KB image021.jpg 91.98 KB image022.jpg 82.28 KB image023.jpg 81.02 KB image024.jpg 71.88 KB image025.jpg 75.29 KB image026.jpg 87.48 KB image027.jpg 81.62 KB image028.jpg 87.05 KB image029.jpg 82.37 KB image030.jpg 81.42 KB image031.jpg 79.20 KB image032.jpg 83.26 KB image033.jpg 84.81 KB image034.jpg 81.04 KB image035.jpg 82.87 KB image036.jpg 101.38 KB image037.jpg 86.23 KB image038.jpg 83.24 KB image039.jpg 96.21 KB image040.jpg 90.80 KB image041.jpg 126.64 KB image042.jpg 91.24 KB image043.jpg 117.53 KB image044.jpg 141.74 KB image045.jpg 131.15 KB image046.jpg 129.88 KB image047.jpg 138.46 KB image048.jpg 147.36 KB image049.jpg 138.32 KB image050.jpg 151.77 KB image051.jpg 149.26 KB image052.jpg 117.62 KB image053.jpg 79.36 KB image054.jpg 67.59 KB image055.jpg 80.49 KB image056.jpg 78.90 KB image057.jpg 85.35 KB image058.jpg 90.40 KB image059.jpg 86.67 KB image060.jpg 92.84 KB image061.jpg 90.69 KB image062.jpg 81.63 KB image063.jpg 80.74 KB image064.jpg 124.36 KB image065.jpg 98.70 KB image066.jpg 74.21 KB Created by IrfanView</field>
<field name="important">Summer Meeting Regen 2004 - Fotos2 Summer Meeting Regen 2004 - Fotos2 Back to Homepage GCSP image001.jpg 91.85 KB image002.jpg 63.72 KB image003.jpg 68.11 KB image004.jpg 81.56 KB image005.jpg 64.55 KB image006.jpg 82.04 KB image007.jpg 98.99 KB image008.jpg 83.09 KB image009.jpg 78.08 KB image010.jpg 74.40 KB image011.jpg 67.15 KB image012.jpg 107.37 KB image013.jpg 110.34 KB image014.jpg 68.72 KB image015.jpg 66.79 KB image016.jpg 92.76 KB image017.jpg 89.01 KB image018.jpg 88.21 KB image019.jpg 86.34 KB image020.jpg 78.99 KB image021.jpg 91.98 KB image022.jpg 82.28 KB image023.jpg 81.02 KB image024.jpg 71.88 KB image025.jpg 75.29 KB image026.jpg 87.48 KB image027.jpg 81.62 KB image028.jpg 87.05 KB image029.jpg 82.37 KB image030.jpg 81.42 KB image031.jpg 79.20 KB image032.jpg 83.26 KB image033.jpg 84.81 KB image034.jpg 81.04 KB image035.jpg 82.87 KB image036.jpg 101.38 KB image037.jpg 86.23 KB image038.jpg 83.24 KB image039.jpg 96.21 KB image040.jpg 90.80 KB image041.jpg 126.64 KB image042.jpg 91.24 KB image043.jpg 117.53 KB image044.jpg 141.74 KB image045.jpg 131.15 KB image046.jpg 129.88 KB image047.jpg 138.46 KB image048.jpg 147.36 KB image049.jpg 138.32 KB image050.jpg 151.77 KB image051.jpg 149.26 KB image052.jpg 117.62 KB image053.jpg 79.36 KB image054.jpg 67.59 KB image055.jpg 80.49 KB image056.jpg 78.90 KB image057.jpg 85.35 KB image058.jpg 90.40 KB image059.jpg 86.67 KB image060.jpg 92.84 KB image061.jpg 90.69 KB image062.jpg 81.63 KB image063.jpg 80.74 KB image064.jpg 124.36 KB image065.jpg 98.70 KB image066.jpg 74.21 KB Created by IrfanView</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/intra/chiemsee/chiemsee2003/index.html</field>
<field name="title">images</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/intra/chiemsee/chiemsee2003/index.html</field>
<field name="content">images Summer Meeting 2003 Impressions   image001.jpg   image002.jpg   image003.jpg   image004.jpg   image005.jpg   image006.jpg   image007.jpg   image008.jpg   image009.jpg   image010.jpg   image011.jpg   image012.jpg   image013.jpg   image014.jpg   image015.jpg   image016.jpg   image017.jpg   image018.jpg   image019.jpg   image020.jpg   image021.jpg   image022.jpg   image023.jpg   image024.jpg   image025.jpg   image026.jpg   image027.jpg   image028.jpg   image029.jpg   image030.jpg   image031.jpg   image032.jpg   image033.jpg   image034.jpg   image035.jpg   image036.jpg   image037.jpg   image038.jpg   image039.jpg   image040.jpg   image041.jpg   image042.jpg   image043.jpg   image044.jpg   image045.jpg   image046.jpg   image047.jpg   image048.jpg   image049.jpg   image050.jpg   image051.jpg   image052.jpg   image053.jpg   image054.jpg   image055.jpg   image056.jpg   image057.jpg   image058.jpg   image059.jpg   image060.jpg   image061.jpg   image062.jpg   image063.jpg   image064.jpg   image065.jpg   image066.jpg   image067.jpg   image068.jpg   image069.jpg   image070.jpg   image071.jpg   image072.jpg   image073.jpg   image074.jpg   image075.jpg   image076.jpg   image077.jpg   image078.jpg   image079.jpg   image080.jpg   image081.jpg   image082.jpg   image083.jpg   image084.jpg   image085.jpg   image086.jpg   image087.jpg   image088.jpg   image089.jpg   image090.jpg   image091.jpg   image092.jpg   image093.jpg   image094.jpg   image095.jpg   image096.jpg   image097.jpg   image098.jpg   image099.jpg   image100.jpg</field>
<field name="important">images Summer Meeting 2003 Impressions   image001.jpg   image002.jpg   image003.jpg   image004.jpg   image005.jpg   image006.jpg   image007.jpg   image008.jpg   image009.jpg   image010.jpg   image011.jpg   image012.jpg   image013.jpg   image014.jpg   image015.jpg   image016.jpg   image017.jpg   image018.jpg   image019.jpg   image020.jpg   image021.jpg   image022.jpg   image023.jpg   image024.jpg   image025.jpg   image026.jpg   image027.jpg   image028.jpg   image029.jpg   image030.jpg   image031.jpg   image032.jpg   image033.jpg   image034.jpg   image035.jpg   image036.jpg   image037.jpg   image038.jpg   image039.jpg   image040.jpg   image041.jpg   image042.jpg   image043.jpg   image044.jpg   image045.jpg   image046.jpg   image047.jpg   image048.jpg   image049.jpg   image050.jpg   image051.jpg   image052.jpg   image053.jpg   image054.jpg   image055.jpg   image056.jpg   image057.jpg   image058.jpg   image059.jpg   image060.jpg   image061.jpg   image062.jpg   image063.jpg   image064.jpg   image065.jpg   image066.jpg   image067.jpg   image068.jpg   image069.jpg   image070.jpg   image071.jpg   image072.jpg   image073.jpg   image074.jpg   image075.jpg   image076.jpg   image077.jpg   image078.jpg   image079.jpg   image080.jpg   image081.jpg   image082.jpg   image083.jpg   image084.jpg   image085.jpg   image086.jpg   image087.jpg   image088.jpg   image089.jpg   image090.jpg   image091.jpg   image092.jpg   image093.jpg   image094.jpg   image095.jpg   image096.jpg   image097.jpg   image098.jpg   image099.jpg   image100.jpg</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/intra/novehrady/impressions.html</field>
<field name="title">Graduate Summer School - Nove Hrady 2001!</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/intra/novehrady/impressions.html</field>
<field name="content">Graduate Summer School - Nove Hrady 2001!   Summer Meeting 2001 Impressions In order to download the images click right mouse button and choose  "Save Image as..."  The End</field>
<field name="important">Graduate Summer School - Nove Hrady 2001!   Summer Meeting 2001 Impressions In order to download the images click right mouse button and choose  "Save Image as..."  The End</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/intra/novehrady/impressions2.html</field>
<field name="title">Graduate Summer School - Nove Hrady 2001!</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/intra/novehrady/impressions2.html</field>
<field name="content">Graduate Summer School - Nove Hrady 2001!   Summer Meeting 2002 Impressions In order to download the images click right mouse button and choose  "Save Image as..."  cu next year</field>
<field name="important">Graduate Summer School - Nove Hrady 2001!   Summer Meeting 2002 Impressions In order to download the images click right mouse button and choose  "Save Image as..."  cu next year</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/intra/template.html</field>
<field name="title">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/intra/template.html</field>
<field name="content">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Supervisors  Lectures  Scholarships    Intranet             general html template This is a html file for download and modification. I will not give any support on any question. All links in this file are absolute (images appear and links work on the file downloaded to your computer).  How to publish your project: edit this file the way you want put it into a directory spelled "www" on your drive "G:\" rename the file to"proj_g_nnn.html ( g is the first letter of your given name, nnn the surname)  if you now hit the detail button (  ) on the present graduate page the browser will be redirected to the adress: http://www-nw.uni-regensburg.de/~dau1234...uni-regensburg.de/proj_t_nnn.html                                       </field>
<field name="important">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Supervisors  Lectures  Scholarships    Intranet             general html template This is a html file for download and modification. I will not give any support on any question. All links in this file are absolute (images appear and links work on the file downloaded to your computer).  How to publish your project: edit this file the way you want put it into a directory spelled "www" on your drive "G:\" rename the file to"proj_g_nnn.html ( g is the first letter of your given name, nnn the surname)  if you now hit the detail button (  ) on the present graduate page the browser will be redirected to the adress: http://www-nw.uni-regensburg.de/~dau1234...uni-regensburg.de/proj_t_nnn.html                                       </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ss2001.html</field>
<field name="title">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ss2001.html</field>
<field name="content">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Supervisors  Publications  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Guest lectures  -  Summer Term 2001 reverse chronological order Dr. Michael Salomon invited by Prof. Hegemann 11. Juli 2001 BIO 5.2.38, 17.00 s.t.  Photochemistry and Biochemistry of Phototropins     Dr. Michael Salomon Botanisches Institut Menzinger Straße 67 D-80638 München Tel.: ++49 89 17861-297 Fax.: ++49 89 17861-185 www: http://129.187.115.12/botphys/staff/ruediger/salomon-d.html e-mail: salomon@botanik.biologie.uni-muenchen.de Handout Prof. Dr. Thomas Carell invited by Prof. Daub 4. Juli 2001 BIO 5.2.38, 17.00 s.t. Light-induced DNA repair:  From model studies to electron transfer in DNA     Prof. Dr. Thomas Carell Fachbereich Chemie Philipps-Universität Marburg Hans-Meerwein Strasse D-35032 Marburg Tel.: ++49 6421 282 1534  Fax.: ++49 6421 282 2189 www: http://staff-www.uni-marburg.de/~carell/Thomas.html e-mail: carell@mailer.uni-marburg.de Handout Prof. Dr. Max Glasbeek invited by Prof. Yersin 20. Juni 2001 BIO 5.2.38, 17.00 s.t.  Barrierless Bond Twisting and Proton Transfer Dynamics Studied by Femtosecond Fluorescence Upconversion Spectroscopy     Prof. Dr Max Glasbeek 035-6942600 AQ, 01-01-84 Beethovenlaan 62 1411 HT Naarden Hoogleraar Fys. Chem. UvA, 020-5256996 e-mail: glasbeek@fys.chem.uva.nl Handout Prof. Dr. Dr. h.c. Michael Grätzel invited by Prof. Daub 19. Juni 2001 H47 Chemistry, 17.00 The Fascinating World of Nanocrystals - From the Lithium Battery to Dye-solar Cells     Prof. Dr. Dr. h.c. Michael Grätzel  Laboratory for Photonics and Interfaces Swiss Federal Institute of Technology,  CH-1015 Lausanne, Switzerland Tel: 0041 / 21 693-3112 Fax: 0041 / 21 693-6100 e-mail: michael.graetzel@epfl.ch   Prof. Dr. Dr. h.c. Michael Grätzel invited by Prof. Daub 18. Juni 2001 H47 Chemistry,  17.00 Molecular Electronics     Prof. Dr. Dr. h.c. Michael Grätzel  Laboratory for Photonics and Interfaces Swiss Federal Institute of Technology,  CH-1015 Lausanne, Switzerland Tel: 0041 / 21 693-3112 Fax: 0041 / 21 693-6100 e-mail: michael.graetzel@epfl.ch   Prof. Noboru Ono invited by Prof. Daub 13. Juni 2001 H47 Chemistry,  17.00 New Functional Dyes Based on Pyrroles Fused with Bicyclo Frameworks     Prof. Noboru Ono Department of Chemistry Faculty of Science Ehime University, Matsuyama 790-8577 Japan e-mail: ononbr@dpc.ehime-u.ac.jp Handout Prof. Dr. Paul E. Hardin invited by Dr. Stanewsky 23. May 2001 BIO 5.2.38, 17.00 s.t.  Mechanisms of central and peripheral clock function in Drosophila     Paul E. Hardin, Ph.D. Professor University of Houston Department of Biology and Biochemistry 369 Science &amp; Research Bldg II Houston, Texas  77204-5001 voice:  713-743-2652 fax:  713-743-2636 e-mail: phardin@uh.edu www: http://www.uh.edu/academics/nsm/Faculty/B&amp;B/print_phardin.htm Handout Dr. Eva Wolf invited by Dr. Stanewsky 25. April 2001 BIO 5.2.38, 17.00 s.t. Structural characterisation of biological clock proteins     Dr. Eva Wolf Max-Planck-Institut für molekulare Physiologie Abteilung Strukturelle Biologie Otto-Hahn-Straße 11 44227 Dortmund Phone: (+49 231) 133-2162/2187 Fax: (+49 231) 133-2699 www: http://www.mpi-dortmund.mpg.de/departments/dep1/wolf/index2.html e-mail:eva.wolf@mpi-dortmund.mpg.de Handout              </field>
<field name="important">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Supervisors  Publications  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Guest lectures  -  Summer Term 2001 reverse chronological order Dr. Michael Salomon invited by Prof. Hegemann 11. Juli 2001 BIO 5.2.38, 17.00 s.t.  Photochemistry and Biochemistry of Phototropins     Dr. Michael Salomon Botanisches Institut Menzinger Straße 67 D-80638 München Tel.: ++49 89 17861-297 Fax.: ++49 89 17861-185 www: http://129.187.115.12/botphys/staff/ruediger/salomon-d.html e-mail: salomon@botanik.biologie.uni-muenchen.de Handout Prof. Dr. Thomas Carell invited by Prof. Daub 4. Juli 2001 BIO 5.2.38, 17.00 s.t. Light-induced DNA repair:  From model studies to electron transfer in DNA     Prof. Dr. Thomas Carell Fachbereich Chemie Philipps-Universität Marburg Hans-Meerwein Strasse D-35032 Marburg Tel.: ++49 6421 282 1534  Fax.: ++49 6421 282 2189 www: http://staff-www.uni-marburg.de/~carell/Thomas.html e-mail: carell@mailer.uni-marburg.de Handout Prof. Dr. Max Glasbeek invited by Prof. Yersin 20. Juni 2001 BIO 5.2.38, 17.00 s.t.  Barrierless Bond Twisting and Proton Transfer Dynamics Studied by Femtosecond Fluorescence Upconversion Spectroscopy     Prof. Dr Max Glasbeek 035-6942600 AQ, 01-01-84 Beethovenlaan 62 1411 HT Naarden Hoogleraar Fys. Chem. UvA, 020-5256996 e-mail: glasbeek@fys.chem.uva.nl Handout Prof. Dr. Dr. h.c. Michael Grätzel invited by Prof. Daub 19. Juni 2001 H47 Chemistry, 17.00 The Fascinating World of Nanocrystals - From the Lithium Battery to Dye-solar Cells     Prof. Dr. Dr. h.c. Michael Grätzel  Laboratory for Photonics and Interfaces Swiss Federal Institute of Technology,  CH-1015 Lausanne, Switzerland Tel: 0041 / 21 693-3112 Fax: 0041 / 21 693-6100 e-mail: michael.graetzel@epfl.ch   Prof. Dr. Dr. h.c. Michael Grätzel invited by Prof. Daub 18. Juni 2001 H47 Chemistry,  17.00 Molecular Electronics     Prof. Dr. Dr. h.c. Michael Grätzel  Laboratory for Photonics and Interfaces Swiss Federal Institute of Technology,  CH-1015 Lausanne, Switzerland Tel: 0041 / 21 693-3112 Fax: 0041 / 21 693-6100 e-mail: michael.graetzel@epfl.ch   Prof. Noboru Ono invited by Prof. Daub 13. Juni 2001 H47 Chemistry,  17.00 New Functional Dyes Based on Pyrroles Fused with Bicyclo Frameworks     Prof. Noboru Ono Department of Chemistry Faculty of Science Ehime University, Matsuyama 790-8577 Japan e-mail: ononbr@dpc.ehime-u.ac.jp Handout Prof. Dr. Paul E. Hardin invited by Dr. Stanewsky 23. May 2001 BIO 5.2.38, 17.00 s.t.  Mechanisms of central and peripheral clock function in Drosophila     Paul E. Hardin, Ph.D. Professor University of Houston Department of Biology and Biochemistry 369 Science &amp; Research Bldg II Houston, Texas  77204-5001 voice:  713-743-2652 fax:  713-743-2636 e-mail: phardin@uh.edu www: http://www.uh.edu/academics/nsm/Faculty/B&amp;B/print_phardin.htm Handout Dr. Eva Wolf invited by Dr. Stanewsky 25. April 2001 BIO 5.2.38, 17.00 s.t. Structural characterisation of biological clock proteins     Dr. Eva Wolf Max-Planck-Institut für molekulare Physiologie Abteilung Strukturelle Biologie Otto-Hahn-Straße 11 44227 Dortmund Phone: (+49 231) 133-2162/2187 Fax: (+49 231) 133-2699 www: http://www.mpi-dortmund.mpg.de/departments/dep1/wolf/index2.html e-mail:eva.wolf@mpi-dortmund.mpg.de Handout              </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ss2003.html</field>
<field name="title">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ss2003.html</field>
<field name="content">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Publications  Supervisors  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Guest lectures  - Summer Term 2003 For this kind of lecture guest professors wil be invited. During the teaching terms we will have at least two guest lectures per month. The program will be composed under the guidance of the students.  The term Research Report is used for lectures given by the supervisors of the Graduate College. Topics, abstracts and handouts of past guest lectures can be found in the guest lecture archive . This page fitting to A4 papersize in width Prof. Dr. Josef Wachtveitl invited by Prof. Dr. P. Hegemann 30.04.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Speed limits in protein folding: Conformational dynamics in model peptides.       Institut f?r Physikalische und Theoretische Chemie Marie-Curie-Str. 11 60439 Frankfurt am Main wveitl@theochem.uni-frankfurt.de http://www.theochem.uni-frankfurt.de/femtochem/www/members/members.html   Handout Prof. Dr. G. Klug invited by Prof. Dr. G. Hauska 07.05.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Light regulation of photosynthesis genes in Rhodobacter       Institut für Mikrobiologie und Molekularbiologie Heinrich-Buff-Ring 26-32 35392 Giessen gabriele.klug@mikro.bio.uni-giessen.de http://www.uni-giessen.de/~gf1265   Handout Prof. Dr. D. Bryant invited by Prof. Dr. G. Hauska 08.05.2003 16.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Chlorobium tepidum: Genomics-Enabled Biochemical Genetics in an Anoxygenic Photoautotrophic Green Sulfur Bacterium       Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology The Pennsylvania State University dab14@psu.edu http://www.bmb.psu.edu/faculty/bryant/lab/   Prof. Dr. J. Golbeck invited by Prof. Dr. G. Hauska 28.05.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 A Comparison of the Bound and Unbound Structures of PsaC: Implications for the Assembly of Photosystem I       Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology 310 South Frear Laboratory Pennsylvania State University jhg5@psu.edu http://www.bmb.psu.edu/faculty/golbeck/golbeck.html   Prof. Dr. Petr Klan invited by Prof. Dr. B. König 04.06.2003 17.00 s.t.    H 46 Photochemical transformations in water ice       University Brno CZ   Prof. Dr. Schuhmann invited by Prof. Dr. J. Daub 18.06.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Microelectrochemistry ? from materials to biological applications       Anal. Chem. - Elektroanalytik &amp; Sensorik Ruhr-Universität Bochum D-44780 Bochum wolfgang.schuhmann@ruhr-uni-bochum.de http://www.ruhr-uni-bochum.de/elan   Handout Prof. Dr. Rouyers invited by Prof. Dr. C. Förster 02.07.2003 17.00 s.t.    H 46 Protein oscillations and photoreception in the Drosophila circadian clock         Summer School invited by PD. Dr. R. Stanewsky 20.07.2003 - 23.07.2003    Graduate College Summer School       Frauenchiemsee ralf.stanewsky@biologie.uni-regensburg.de http://www.uni-regensburg.de/GK/SP/lectures/workshops.html   Prof. Dr. Winslow Briggs invited by Prof. Dr. P. Hegemann 10.09.2003 17.00 s.t.    H 40 Phototropins: a new family of plant photoreceptors. (supported by Vielberth Foundation)       Carnegie Institution of Washington Stanford University California USA briggs@andrew2.stanford.edu http://carnegiedpb.stanford.edu/research/research_briggs.php   Dr. Aba Losi invited by Prof. Dr. A. Penzkofer 16.09.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 The bacterial counterparts of plants phototropins: photochemical properties - problems and perspectives       Deptartment of Physics University of Parma 43100 Parma ITALY losia@fis.unipr.it http://www.fis.unipr.it/home/losia/losiweb/index.htm   Dr. Shin-ichi Sasaki invited by Dr. G. Knör 17.09.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Receptor Design Towards Ion Sensing       Department of Bioscience and Biotechnology Ritsumeikan University Nojihigashi Kusatsu Shiga 525-8577 Japan            </field>
<field name="important">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Publications  Supervisors  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Guest lectures  - Summer Term 2003 For this kind of lecture guest professors wil be invited. During the teaching terms we will have at least two guest lectures per month. The program will be composed under the guidance of the students.  The term Research Report is used for lectures given by the supervisors of the Graduate College. Topics, abstracts and handouts of past guest lectures can be found in the guest lecture archive . This page fitting to A4 papersize in width Prof. Dr. Josef Wachtveitl invited by Prof. Dr. P. Hegemann 30.04.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Speed limits in protein folding: Conformational dynamics in model peptides.       Institut f?r Physikalische und Theoretische Chemie Marie-Curie-Str. 11 60439 Frankfurt am Main wveitl@theochem.uni-frankfurt.de http://www.theochem.uni-frankfurt.de/femtochem/www/members/members.html   Handout Prof. Dr. G. Klug invited by Prof. Dr. G. Hauska 07.05.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Light regulation of photosynthesis genes in Rhodobacter       Institut für Mikrobiologie und Molekularbiologie Heinrich-Buff-Ring 26-32 35392 Giessen gabriele.klug@mikro.bio.uni-giessen.de http://www.uni-giessen.de/~gf1265   Handout Prof. Dr. D. Bryant invited by Prof. Dr. G. Hauska 08.05.2003 16.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Chlorobium tepidum: Genomics-Enabled Biochemical Genetics in an Anoxygenic Photoautotrophic Green Sulfur Bacterium       Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology The Pennsylvania State University dab14@psu.edu http://www.bmb.psu.edu/faculty/bryant/lab/   Prof. Dr. J. Golbeck invited by Prof. Dr. G. Hauska 28.05.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 A Comparison of the Bound and Unbound Structures of PsaC: Implications for the Assembly of Photosystem I       Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology 310 South Frear Laboratory Pennsylvania State University jhg5@psu.edu http://www.bmb.psu.edu/faculty/golbeck/golbeck.html   Prof. Dr. Petr Klan invited by Prof. Dr. B. König 04.06.2003 17.00 s.t.    H 46 Photochemical transformations in water ice       University Brno CZ   Prof. Dr. Schuhmann invited by Prof. Dr. J. Daub 18.06.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Microelectrochemistry ? from materials to biological applications       Anal. Chem. - Elektroanalytik &amp; Sensorik Ruhr-Universität Bochum D-44780 Bochum wolfgang.schuhmann@ruhr-uni-bochum.de http://www.ruhr-uni-bochum.de/elan   Handout Prof. Dr. Rouyers invited by Prof. Dr. C. Förster 02.07.2003 17.00 s.t.    H 46 Protein oscillations and photoreception in the Drosophila circadian clock         Summer School invited by PD. Dr. R. Stanewsky 20.07.2003 - 23.07.2003    Graduate College Summer School       Frauenchiemsee ralf.stanewsky@biologie.uni-regensburg.de http://www.uni-regensburg.de/GK/SP/lectures/workshops.html   Prof. Dr. Winslow Briggs invited by Prof. Dr. P. Hegemann 10.09.2003 17.00 s.t.    H 40 Phototropins: a new family of plant photoreceptors. (supported by Vielberth Foundation)       Carnegie Institution of Washington Stanford University California USA briggs@andrew2.stanford.edu http://carnegiedpb.stanford.edu/research/research_briggs.php   Dr. Aba Losi invited by Prof. Dr. A. Penzkofer 16.09.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 The bacterial counterparts of plants phototropins: photochemical properties - problems and perspectives       Deptartment of Physics University of Parma 43100 Parma ITALY losia@fis.unipr.it http://www.fis.unipr.it/home/losia/losiweb/index.htm   Dr. Shin-ichi Sasaki invited by Dr. G. Knör 17.09.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Receptor Design Towards Ion Sensing       Department of Bioscience and Biotechnology Ritsumeikan University Nojihigashi Kusatsu Shiga 525-8577 Japan            </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ss2004.html</field>
<field name="title">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ss2004.html</field>
<field name="content">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Publications  Supervisors  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Past Guest lectures  - Summer Term 2004 For this kind of lecture guest professors wil be invited. During the teaching terms we will have at least two guest lectures per month. The program will be composed under the guidance of the students.  The term Research Report is used for lectures given by the supervisors of the Graduate College. Topics, abstracts and handouts of past guest lectures can be found in the guest lecture archive .This page fitting to A4 papersize in width Prof. Dr. W. Engelmann invited by Prof. Dr. C. F?rster 12.05.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 How to stop a biological clock by light: Point of singularity       Institut f?r Botanik Universit?t T?bingen mailto:wolfgang.engelmann@uni-tuebingen.de http://bioclox.bot.biologie.uni-tuebingen.de/   Dr. Ajayaghosh invited by Prof. Dr. J. Daub 26.05.2004 17.00 s.t.    CHE H46 Supramolecular Chemistry of Oligo(p-phenylenevinylene)s: A Novel Class of Functional Organogels       Regional Research Laboratory (CSIR) Trivandrum - India mailto:aajayaghosh@rediffmail.com   Handout Prof. Dr. Parker invited by Prof. Dr. B. K?nig 02.06.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Excitement in f block:metal complexes in action       Department of Chemistry University of Durham - England mailto:David.Parker@durham.ac.uk http://www.dur.ac.uk/chemistry/Staff/dp/dp.htm   Dr. Michael Heagy invited by Prof. Dr. J. Daub 23.06.2004 9.00 s.t.    CHE 12.0.16 Fluorescent Chemosensors for Carbohydrates: Bright Spies for Saccharides       Department of Chemistry New Mexiko Tech mailto:mheagy@nmt.edu http://www.nmt.edu/~chem/heagy/homepage.html   Dr. John Kennis invited by Prof. Dr. P. Hegemann 30.06.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Primary reactions of flavin-based photoreceptors       Dept. of Biophysics Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam Netherlands mailto:J.Kennis@few.vu.nl   Handout PD Dr. Alf Mews invited by Prof. Dr. S. Steinem 07.07.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Chemistry and photo physics of individual semiconductor nanocrystals       Institut f?r Physikalische Chemie der Universit?t Mainz Welderweg 11 - D-55099 Mainz mailto:alf.mews@uni-mainz.de http://www.uni-mainz.de/FB/Chemie/Basche/mews.html   Prof. Dr. Kohler invited by Prof. Dr. J. Daub 14.07.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Physical Chemistry of Chemical Oscillations       Institut f?r Analytische Chemie und Chemo- und Biosensorik Uni Regensburg mailto:Hans-Helmut.Kohler@chemie.uni-regensburg http://www-analytik.chemie.uni-regensburg.de/kohler/index.html   Handout Dr. Gayvoronsky invited by Prof. Dr. A. Penzkofer 14.07.2004 10.15    PHY 5.0.20 Application of nonlinear optical response for monitoring of nanoparticle TiO2 porous films photocatalytic activity       Institute of Physics NASU Kiev - Ukraine   Handout Prof. Dr. T. Bach invited by Prof. Dr. B. K?nig 21.07.2004 17.00 s.t.    CHE H46 Enantioselective Photochemical Reactions in Solution       Lehrstuhl f. Organische Chemie I TU M?nchen mailto:Thorsten.Bach@ch.tum.de http://webserver.fak-cbg.tu-muenchen.de/oc1/tbach/   Prof. Dr. T. Tsuboi invited by Prof. Dr. A. Penzkofer 04.08.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 White color electroluminescence of organic light emitting diode with phosphorescent PtOEP       Research Institute of Advanced Technology Faculty of Engineering Kyoto Sangyo University mailto:tsuboi@cc.kyoto-su.ac.jp http://www.kyoto-su.ac.jp/~tsuboi/main.html   Handout M. Grininger invited by Prof. Dr. J. Daub 05.08.2004 17.00 s.t.    CHE H46 Dodecin From the Structure to a Function       MPI f?r Biochemie Am Klopferspitz 18a 82152 Martinsried - Germany            </field>
<field name="important">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Publications  Supervisors  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Past Guest lectures  - Summer Term 2004 For this kind of lecture guest professors wil be invited. During the teaching terms we will have at least two guest lectures per month. The program will be composed under the guidance of the students.  The term Research Report is used for lectures given by the supervisors of the Graduate College. Topics, abstracts and handouts of past guest lectures can be found in the guest lecture archive .This page fitting to A4 papersize in width Prof. Dr. W. Engelmann invited by Prof. Dr. C. F?rster 12.05.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 How to stop a biological clock by light: Point of singularity       Institut f?r Botanik Universit?t T?bingen mailto:wolfgang.engelmann@uni-tuebingen.de http://bioclox.bot.biologie.uni-tuebingen.de/   Dr. Ajayaghosh invited by Prof. Dr. J. Daub 26.05.2004 17.00 s.t.    CHE H46 Supramolecular Chemistry of Oligo(p-phenylenevinylene)s: A Novel Class of Functional Organogels       Regional Research Laboratory (CSIR) Trivandrum - India mailto:aajayaghosh@rediffmail.com   Handout Prof. Dr. Parker invited by Prof. Dr. B. K?nig 02.06.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Excitement in f block:metal complexes in action       Department of Chemistry University of Durham - England mailto:David.Parker@durham.ac.uk http://www.dur.ac.uk/chemistry/Staff/dp/dp.htm   Dr. Michael Heagy invited by Prof. Dr. J. Daub 23.06.2004 9.00 s.t.    CHE 12.0.16 Fluorescent Chemosensors for Carbohydrates: Bright Spies for Saccharides       Department of Chemistry New Mexiko Tech mailto:mheagy@nmt.edu http://www.nmt.edu/~chem/heagy/homepage.html   Dr. John Kennis invited by Prof. Dr. P. Hegemann 30.06.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Primary reactions of flavin-based photoreceptors       Dept. of Biophysics Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam Netherlands mailto:J.Kennis@few.vu.nl   Handout PD Dr. Alf Mews invited by Prof. Dr. S. Steinem 07.07.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Chemistry and photo physics of individual semiconductor nanocrystals       Institut f?r Physikalische Chemie der Universit?t Mainz Welderweg 11 - D-55099 Mainz mailto:alf.mews@uni-mainz.de http://www.uni-mainz.de/FB/Chemie/Basche/mews.html   Prof. Dr. Kohler invited by Prof. Dr. J. Daub 14.07.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Physical Chemistry of Chemical Oscillations       Institut f?r Analytische Chemie und Chemo- und Biosensorik Uni Regensburg mailto:Hans-Helmut.Kohler@chemie.uni-regensburg http://www-analytik.chemie.uni-regensburg.de/kohler/index.html   Handout Dr. Gayvoronsky invited by Prof. Dr. A. Penzkofer 14.07.2004 10.15    PHY 5.0.20 Application of nonlinear optical response for monitoring of nanoparticle TiO2 porous films photocatalytic activity       Institute of Physics NASU Kiev - Ukraine   Handout Prof. Dr. T. Bach invited by Prof. Dr. B. K?nig 21.07.2004 17.00 s.t.    CHE H46 Enantioselective Photochemical Reactions in Solution       Lehrstuhl f. Organische Chemie I TU M?nchen mailto:Thorsten.Bach@ch.tum.de http://webserver.fak-cbg.tu-muenchen.de/oc1/tbach/   Prof. Dr. T. Tsuboi invited by Prof. Dr. A. Penzkofer 04.08.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 White color electroluminescence of organic light emitting diode with phosphorescent PtOEP       Research Institute of Advanced Technology Faculty of Engineering Kyoto Sangyo University mailto:tsuboi@cc.kyoto-su.ac.jp http://www.kyoto-su.ac.jp/~tsuboi/main.html   Handout M. Grininger invited by Prof. Dr. J. Daub 05.08.2004 17.00 s.t.    CHE H46 Dodecin From the Structure to a Function       MPI f?r Biochemie Am Klopferspitz 18a 82152 Martinsried - Germany            </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ss2005.html</field>
<field name="title">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ss2005.html</field>
<field name="content">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Publications  Supervisors  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Past Guest lectures  - Summer Term 2005 For this kind of lecture guest professors wil be invited. During the teaching terms we will have at least two guest lectures per month. The program will be composed under the guidance of the students.  The term Research Report is used for lectures given by the supervisors of the Graduate College. Topics, abstracts and handouts of past guest lectures can be found in the guest lecture archive . This page fitting to A4 papersize in width Prof. Ortwin Brede invited by Prof. G. Hauska 25.04.2005 17.15 h    H46 Pulse Radiolysis       Fakult?t f?r Chemie und Mineralogie Interdisziplin?re Arbeitsgruppe "Zeitaufgel?ste Spektroskopie" Permoserstr. 15 - D-04318 Leipzig brede@mpgag.uni-leipzig.de http://www.uni-leipzig.de/~mpgseite/iagmain.htm   Dr. Christian Wegener invited by Prof. Ch. F?rster 18.05.2005 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Acetylcholine might mediate light signals from larval photoreceptors to pacemaker clock neurons in Drosophila       Philipps-Universit?t Marburg Fachbereich Biologie - Tierphysiologie-Neurobiologie Karl-von-Frisch Str. - 35032 Marburg wegener@staff.uni-marburg.de http://www.staff.uni-marburg.de/~wegener/   Prof. W. Domcke invited by Prof. M. Sch?tz 25.05.2005 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Hydrogen bonds and concial intersections and photostability of the building blocks of life       Technical University of Munich - Department of Chemistry Chair of Theoretical Chemistry Lichtenbergstra?e 4 - D-85747 Garching Wolfgang.Domcke@ch.tum.de http://www.theo.chemie.tu-muenchen.de/   Prof. Dr. Wolfgang Zinth invited by Prof. A. Penzkofer 22.06.2005 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Primary Steps in Photosynthesis       Lehrstuhl fuer BioMolekulare Optik Ludwig-Maximilians-Universitaet Oettingerstr. 67 - D-80538 M?nchen wolfgang.zinth@physik.uni-muenchen.de http://www.bmo.physik.uni-muenchen.de/%7Ezinth/   Prof. Dr. Werner Blau invited by Prof. A. Penzkofer 29.06.2005 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Molecular Engineering and Photophysics of Disc-Shape Molecules       Department of Physics Trinity College Dublin Dublin 2 - Ireland wblau@tcd.ie http://www.tcd.ie/Physics/Molecular_Electronics/   Handout Prof. Alfred Batschauer invited by Prof. A. Penzkofer 13.07.2005 17.00 s.t.    PHY H34 The Role of Cryptochromes in Plant Development       Philipps-Universit?t Biology Plant Physiology/Photobiology Karl-von-Frisch-Str. 8 - D-35032 Marburg batschau@staff.uni-marburg.de http://www.staff.uni-marburg.de/~p_phys/BATSCHAU.DIR/index.htm   Prof. Dr. Taiju Tsuboi invited by Prof. A. Penzkofer 23.09.2005 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Transient electronic processes of phosphorescent organic light emitting diode materials under endothermic energy transfer from fluorescent host materials       Research Institue of Advanced Technology - Faculty of Engineering Kyoto Sangyo University Kamigamo - Kita-ku - Kyoto 603-8555 - JAPAN tsuboi@cc.kyoto-su.ac.jp   Handout Andy Wende invited by Dr. G. N?ll 28.09.2005 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Signal Transduction in the Halophilic Halobacterium salinarum upon Environmental Changes       MPI of Biochemistry - Dept. Membrane Biochemistry Am Klopferspitz 18 M?nchen - Germany wende@biochem.mpg.de http://www.biochem.mpg.de/oesterhelt/   Handout          </field>
<field name="important">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Publications  Supervisors  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Past Guest lectures  - Summer Term 2005 For this kind of lecture guest professors wil be invited. During the teaching terms we will have at least two guest lectures per month. The program will be composed under the guidance of the students.  The term Research Report is used for lectures given by the supervisors of the Graduate College. Topics, abstracts and handouts of past guest lectures can be found in the guest lecture archive . This page fitting to A4 papersize in width Prof. Ortwin Brede invited by Prof. G. Hauska 25.04.2005 17.15 h    H46 Pulse Radiolysis       Fakult?t f?r Chemie und Mineralogie Interdisziplin?re Arbeitsgruppe "Zeitaufgel?ste Spektroskopie" Permoserstr. 15 - D-04318 Leipzig brede@mpgag.uni-leipzig.de http://www.uni-leipzig.de/~mpgseite/iagmain.htm   Dr. Christian Wegener invited by Prof. Ch. F?rster 18.05.2005 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Acetylcholine might mediate light signals from larval photoreceptors to pacemaker clock neurons in Drosophila       Philipps-Universit?t Marburg Fachbereich Biologie - Tierphysiologie-Neurobiologie Karl-von-Frisch Str. - 35032 Marburg wegener@staff.uni-marburg.de http://www.staff.uni-marburg.de/~wegener/   Prof. W. Domcke invited by Prof. M. Sch?tz 25.05.2005 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Hydrogen bonds and concial intersections and photostability of the building blocks of life       Technical University of Munich - Department of Chemistry Chair of Theoretical Chemistry Lichtenbergstra?e 4 - D-85747 Garching Wolfgang.Domcke@ch.tum.de http://www.theo.chemie.tu-muenchen.de/   Prof. Dr. Wolfgang Zinth invited by Prof. A. Penzkofer 22.06.2005 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Primary Steps in Photosynthesis       Lehrstuhl fuer BioMolekulare Optik Ludwig-Maximilians-Universitaet Oettingerstr. 67 - D-80538 M?nchen wolfgang.zinth@physik.uni-muenchen.de http://www.bmo.physik.uni-muenchen.de/%7Ezinth/   Prof. Dr. Werner Blau invited by Prof. A. Penzkofer 29.06.2005 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Molecular Engineering and Photophysics of Disc-Shape Molecules       Department of Physics Trinity College Dublin Dublin 2 - Ireland wblau@tcd.ie http://www.tcd.ie/Physics/Molecular_Electronics/   Handout Prof. Alfred Batschauer invited by Prof. A. Penzkofer 13.07.2005 17.00 s.t.    PHY H34 The Role of Cryptochromes in Plant Development       Philipps-Universit?t Biology Plant Physiology/Photobiology Karl-von-Frisch-Str. 8 - D-35032 Marburg batschau@staff.uni-marburg.de http://www.staff.uni-marburg.de/~p_phys/BATSCHAU.DIR/index.htm   Prof. Dr. Taiju Tsuboi invited by Prof. A. Penzkofer 23.09.2005 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Transient electronic processes of phosphorescent organic light emitting diode materials under endothermic energy transfer from fluorescent host materials       Research Institue of Advanced Technology - Faculty of Engineering Kyoto Sangyo University Kamigamo - Kita-ku - Kyoto 603-8555 - JAPAN tsuboi@cc.kyoto-su.ac.jp   Handout Andy Wende invited by Dr. G. N?ll 28.09.2005 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Signal Transduction in the Halophilic Halobacterium salinarum upon Environmental Changes       MPI of Biochemistry - Dept. Membrane Biochemistry Am Klopferspitz 18 M?nchen - Germany wende@biochem.mpg.de http://www.biochem.mpg.de/oesterhelt/   Handout          </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ss2007.html</field>
<field name="title">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ss2007.html</field>
<field name="content">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Publications  Supervisors  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Past Guest lectures  - Summer Term 2007 For this kind of lecture guest professors wil be invited. During the teaching terms we will have at least two guest lectures per month. The program will be composed under the guidance of the students.  The term Research Report is used for lectures given by the supervisors of the Graduate College. Topics, abstracts and handouts of past guest lectures can be found in the guest lecture archive .This page fitting to A4 papersize in width PD. Dr. Roswitha Wiltschko invited by GK640 16.05.2007 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 "Magnetic orientation and perception in birds and other animals"       Zoologisches Institut der Johann Wolfgang Goethe-Universitaet in Frankfurt am Main mailto:wiltschko@zoology.uni-frankfurt.de http://www.bio.uni-frankfurt.de/akpoev   Handout Prof. Dr. Christoph Randler invited by GK MedChem/OC Kolloq. 22.06.2007 15.00 s.t.    H46 "Scientific talks and poster presentations"       Didaktik der Biologie Institut der Biologie I University of Leipzig randler@rz.uni-leipzig.de http://www.uni-leipzig.de/~instbota   Prof. Dr. Peter B?uerle invited by GDCh 25.06.2007 17.00 c.t.    H 46 "Functional Pi-Electron Materials for Organic Electronics and Solar Energy Conversion"       Institute of Organic Chemistry II and Advanced Materials University of Ulm D89081 Ulm mailto:peter.baeuerle@uni-ulm.de http://www.uni-ulm.de/oc2   Prof. Dr. Dirk Guldi invited by GDCh 02.07.2007 17.00 c.t.    H 46 "Nanotubes - Versatile Platform for Electron donor Acceptor Interactions"       Institut fuer Physikalische Chemie Universitt Erlangen D91058 - Erlangen mailto:guldi@chemie.uni-erlangen.de http://www.uni-erlangen.de/guldi   Prof. Dr. George I. Stegeman invited by GK640 26.09.2007 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 "The Dawn (Beginning of a New Day) of Discreteness and Periodicity in Optics"       College of Optics &amp; Photonics: CREOL &amp; FPCE University of Central Florida - P.O. Box 12700 P.O. Box 12700 - Orlando Fl 32816-2700 mailto:george@creol.ucf.edu http://www.biologie.hu-berlin.de/~expbp/   Handout          </field>
<field name="important">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Publications  Supervisors  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Past Guest lectures  - Summer Term 2007 For this kind of lecture guest professors wil be invited. During the teaching terms we will have at least two guest lectures per month. The program will be composed under the guidance of the students.  The term Research Report is used for lectures given by the supervisors of the Graduate College. Topics, abstracts and handouts of past guest lectures can be found in the guest lecture archive .This page fitting to A4 papersize in width PD. Dr. Roswitha Wiltschko invited by GK640 16.05.2007 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 "Magnetic orientation and perception in birds and other animals"       Zoologisches Institut der Johann Wolfgang Goethe-Universitaet in Frankfurt am Main mailto:wiltschko@zoology.uni-frankfurt.de http://www.bio.uni-frankfurt.de/akpoev   Handout Prof. Dr. Christoph Randler invited by GK MedChem/OC Kolloq. 22.06.2007 15.00 s.t.    H46 "Scientific talks and poster presentations"       Didaktik der Biologie Institut der Biologie I University of Leipzig randler@rz.uni-leipzig.de http://www.uni-leipzig.de/~instbota   Prof. Dr. Peter B?uerle invited by GDCh 25.06.2007 17.00 c.t.    H 46 "Functional Pi-Electron Materials for Organic Electronics and Solar Energy Conversion"       Institute of Organic Chemistry II and Advanced Materials University of Ulm D89081 Ulm mailto:peter.baeuerle@uni-ulm.de http://www.uni-ulm.de/oc2   Prof. Dr. Dirk Guldi invited by GDCh 02.07.2007 17.00 c.t.    H 46 "Nanotubes - Versatile Platform for Electron donor Acceptor Interactions"       Institut fuer Physikalische Chemie Universitt Erlangen D91058 - Erlangen mailto:guldi@chemie.uni-erlangen.de http://www.uni-erlangen.de/guldi   Prof. Dr. George I. Stegeman invited by GK640 26.09.2007 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 "The Dawn (Beginning of a New Day) of Discreteness and Periodicity in Optics"       College of Optics &amp; Photonics: CREOL &amp; FPCE University of Central Florida - P.O. Box 12700 P.O. Box 12700 - Orlando Fl 32816-2700 mailto:george@creol.ucf.edu http://www.biologie.hu-berlin.de/~expbp/   Handout          </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ss2008.html</field>
<field name="title">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ss2008.html</field>
<field name="content">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Publications  Supervisors  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Past Guest lectures  - Summer Term 2008 For this kind of lecture guest professors wil be invited. During the teaching terms we will have at least two guest lectures per month. The program will be composed under the guidance of the students.  The term Research Report is used for lectures given by the supervisors of the Graduate College. Topics, abstracts and handouts of past guest lectures can be found in the guest lecture archive . This page fitting to A4 papersize in width Prof. Dr. Walter Thiel invited by GDCh 02.06.2008 17.00 c.t.    CHE H46 Theoretische Untersuchungen zu enzymatischen Reaktionen       Max Planck Institut M?hlheim Germany thiel_at_mpi-muelheim.mpg.de http://www.mpi-muelheim.mpg.de/   Prof. Dr. Klaus M?llen invited by GDCh 16.06.2008 17.15    H 46 molecular electronics       Max-Planck-Institut f?r Polymerforschung Mainz Germany klaus.muellen_at_mpip-mainz.mpg.de http://www.mpip-mainz.mpg.de/www/pages/mitarbeiter/direktoren/?id=4   Prof. Dr. Rodolfo Costa invited by GC640 18.06.2008 17.00 s.t.    Bio 5.2.38 Natural behavioural rhythmicity in Drosophila       University Padua Italy costa_at_bio.unipd.it   Dr. Sven Rau invited by OC 02.07.2008 17.15    H 46 photocatalysis       University Jena Germany Sven.Rau[a]uni-jena.de http://www.chemie.uni-jena.de/institute/ac/rau/start.html   Prof. Dr. Taiju Tsuboi invited by GK640 27.08.2008 17.00    BIO 5.2.38 Energy transfer between phosphorescent organic molecule and fluorescent organic molecule       Faculty of Engineering - Kyoto Sangyo University Kyoto Japan tuboi_at_cc.kyoto-su.ac.jp http://www.kyoto-su.ac.jp/index-e.html   Handout          </field>
<field name="important">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Publications  Supervisors  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Past Guest lectures  - Summer Term 2008 For this kind of lecture guest professors wil be invited. During the teaching terms we will have at least two guest lectures per month. The program will be composed under the guidance of the students.  The term Research Report is used for lectures given by the supervisors of the Graduate College. Topics, abstracts and handouts of past guest lectures can be found in the guest lecture archive . This page fitting to A4 papersize in width Prof. Dr. Walter Thiel invited by GDCh 02.06.2008 17.00 c.t.    CHE H46 Theoretische Untersuchungen zu enzymatischen Reaktionen       Max Planck Institut M?hlheim Germany thiel_at_mpi-muelheim.mpg.de http://www.mpi-muelheim.mpg.de/   Prof. Dr. Klaus M?llen invited by GDCh 16.06.2008 17.15    H 46 molecular electronics       Max-Planck-Institut f?r Polymerforschung Mainz Germany klaus.muellen_at_mpip-mainz.mpg.de http://www.mpip-mainz.mpg.de/www/pages/mitarbeiter/direktoren/?id=4   Prof. Dr. Rodolfo Costa invited by GC640 18.06.2008 17.00 s.t.    Bio 5.2.38 Natural behavioural rhythmicity in Drosophila       University Padua Italy costa_at_bio.unipd.it   Dr. Sven Rau invited by OC 02.07.2008 17.15    H 46 photocatalysis       University Jena Germany Sven.Rau[a]uni-jena.de http://www.chemie.uni-jena.de/institute/ac/rau/start.html   Prof. Dr. Taiju Tsuboi invited by GK640 27.08.2008 17.00    BIO 5.2.38 Energy transfer between phosphorescent organic molecule and fluorescent organic molecule       Faculty of Engineering - Kyoto Sangyo University Kyoto Japan tuboi_at_cc.kyoto-su.ac.jp http://www.kyoto-su.ac.jp/index-e.html   Handout          </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ws2000-01.html</field>
<field name="title">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ws2000-01.html</field>
<field name="content">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Supervisors  Publications  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Guest lectures  -  Winter Term 2000-2001 reverse chronological order Prof. Dr. Silvia E. Braslavsky 24. January 2001. Determination of the time-resolved thermodynamic profile in senesory photoreceptors by photothermal methods.     Silvia E. Braslavsky Max-Planck-Institut für Strahlenchemie Postfach 10 13 65 D 45413 Mülheim an der Ruhr, Germany Tel: *49 (208) 306-3681 direct; -0 (switchboard) Fax: *49 (208) 306-3951 www: http://www.mpi-muelheim.mpg.de/mpistr_braslavsky.html e-mail: braslavskys@mpi-muelheim.mpg.de Handout Prof. Dr. Ladislav  Nedbal 17. January 2001. Kinetic Imaging of Plant Chlorophyll Fluorescence.     Ladislav Nedbal Laboratory of Applied Photobiology &amp; Bio-Imaging Institute of Landscape Ecology Zamek 136 CZ-37333 Nove Hrady Czech Republic email: nedbal@greentech.cz Handout Prof. Dr. J. Daub 10. January 2001 Research Report: Signaling" from a Chemist's View: Methods and Systems     www: http://www-oc.chemie.uni-regensburg.de/daub/index_d.html e-mail: joerg.daub@chemie.uni-regensburg.de   Prof. Dr. A. Penzkofer 13.December 2000 Research Report: Time-resolved linear and nonlinear optical spectroscopy on organic molecules and luminescent polymers     www: http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/maier/ e-mail: alfons.penzkofer@physik.uni-regensburg.de   Dr. Ralf Stanewsky 6.December 2000 Genetic and molecular dissection of the circadian system in the fruitfly Drosophila melanogaster     Dr. Ralf Stanewsky  Institut fuer Zoologie  Lehrstuhl fuer Entwicklungsbiologie  Universität Regensburg  93040 Regensburg  www: http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Schneuwly/Circadian/cir.htm e-mail: ralf.stanewsky@biologie.uni-regensburg.de Handout Prof. Dr. Volker Buß 29. November 2000 Rhodopsin - Challenge and Playground for Theoreticians     Prof. Ph. D. Volker Buß Gerhard-Mercator-Universität-GH-Duisburg FB6 / Theoretische Chemie Lotharstraße 1 D-47057 Duisburg www: http://www.theochem.uni-duisburg.de/THC/people/buss.html e-mail: theobuss@uni-duisburg.de Handout Prof. Russell G. Foster 21. November 2000 The photic regulation of the mammalian circadian system and other irradiance detection tasks.     Prof. Russell G. Foster Chair, Department of Integrative &amp; Molecular Neuroscience Division of Neuroscience &amp; Psychological Medicine Imperial College School of Medicine Charing Cross Hospital, Fulham Palace Road London, W6 8RF, UK www: http://www.med.ic.ac.uk/divisions/template_divisions_departments.asp?id=86 e-mail: r.foster@ic.ac.uk Handout Prof. Dr. Wolfgang Rettig 15. November 2000 Biaromatic photoreceptor systems with molecular photodiode behaviour   Prof. Dr. Wolfgang Rettig Inst. Phys. and Theor. Chemie  Humboldt-Univ. Berlin Bunsenstr. 1 D-10117 Berlin www: http://www.chemie.hu-berlin.de/physch/phys_ag/wr/index.html e-mail: rettig@chemie.hu-berlin.de Handout              </field>
<field name="important">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Supervisors  Publications  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Guest lectures  -  Winter Term 2000-2001 reverse chronological order Prof. Dr. Silvia E. Braslavsky 24. January 2001. Determination of the time-resolved thermodynamic profile in senesory photoreceptors by photothermal methods.     Silvia E. Braslavsky Max-Planck-Institut für Strahlenchemie Postfach 10 13 65 D 45413 Mülheim an der Ruhr, Germany Tel: *49 (208) 306-3681 direct; -0 (switchboard) Fax: *49 (208) 306-3951 www: http://www.mpi-muelheim.mpg.de/mpistr_braslavsky.html e-mail: braslavskys@mpi-muelheim.mpg.de Handout Prof. Dr. Ladislav  Nedbal 17. January 2001. Kinetic Imaging of Plant Chlorophyll Fluorescence.     Ladislav Nedbal Laboratory of Applied Photobiology &amp; Bio-Imaging Institute of Landscape Ecology Zamek 136 CZ-37333 Nove Hrady Czech Republic email: nedbal@greentech.cz Handout Prof. Dr. J. Daub 10. January 2001 Research Report: Signaling" from a Chemist's View: Methods and Systems     www: http://www-oc.chemie.uni-regensburg.de/daub/index_d.html e-mail: joerg.daub@chemie.uni-regensburg.de   Prof. Dr. A. Penzkofer 13.December 2000 Research Report: Time-resolved linear and nonlinear optical spectroscopy on organic molecules and luminescent polymers     www: http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/maier/ e-mail: alfons.penzkofer@physik.uni-regensburg.de   Dr. Ralf Stanewsky 6.December 2000 Genetic and molecular dissection of the circadian system in the fruitfly Drosophila melanogaster     Dr. Ralf Stanewsky  Institut fuer Zoologie  Lehrstuhl fuer Entwicklungsbiologie  Universität Regensburg  93040 Regensburg  www: http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Schneuwly/Circadian/cir.htm e-mail: ralf.stanewsky@biologie.uni-regensburg.de Handout Prof. Dr. Volker Buß 29. November 2000 Rhodopsin - Challenge and Playground for Theoreticians     Prof. Ph. D. Volker Buß Gerhard-Mercator-Universität-GH-Duisburg FB6 / Theoretische Chemie Lotharstraße 1 D-47057 Duisburg www: http://www.theochem.uni-duisburg.de/THC/people/buss.html e-mail: theobuss@uni-duisburg.de Handout Prof. Russell G. Foster 21. November 2000 The photic regulation of the mammalian circadian system and other irradiance detection tasks.     Prof. Russell G. Foster Chair, Department of Integrative &amp; Molecular Neuroscience Division of Neuroscience &amp; Psychological Medicine Imperial College School of Medicine Charing Cross Hospital, Fulham Palace Road London, W6 8RF, UK www: http://www.med.ic.ac.uk/divisions/template_divisions_departments.asp?id=86 e-mail: r.foster@ic.ac.uk Handout Prof. Dr. Wolfgang Rettig 15. November 2000 Biaromatic photoreceptor systems with molecular photodiode behaviour   Prof. Dr. Wolfgang Rettig Inst. Phys. and Theor. Chemie  Humboldt-Univ. Berlin Bunsenstr. 1 D-10117 Berlin www: http://www.chemie.hu-berlin.de/physch/phys_ag/wr/index.html e-mail: rettig@chemie.hu-berlin.de Handout              </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ws2001-02.html</field>
<field name="title">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ws2001-02.html</field>
<field name="content">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Supervisors  Publications  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Guest lectures  -  Winter Term 2001-2002 reverse chronological order Dr. Marcel Mayor, invited by Prof. Daub 28. February 2002 to be announced      Research Center Karlsruhe GmbH, Institut für Nanotechnologie Postfach 3640, Germany e-mail: marcel.mayor@int.fzk.de Handout Prof. Dr. Horst Kisch invited by Prof. Hauska 16. January 2002 Photoinduced charge separation on semiconductor powders - new ways for the chemical synthesis        Institut f?r Anorganische Chemie Universit?t Erlangen-N?rnberg Egerlandstra?e 1 D-91058 Erlangen Fax: +49 (9131) 85-27363 Tel: +49 (9131) 85-27363 e-mail: kisch@anorganik.chemie.uni-erlangen.de Dr. Knut Rurack, invited by Prof. Daub 9. January 2002 Bifunctional Molecular Reporters:  Approaches towards Multi-Mode Fluorescence Signaling.      Federal Institute for Materials Research and Testing (BAM), Richard-Willstaetter-Str. 11,  D-12489 Berlin, Germany Fon ++4930/8104 5576 Fax ++4930/8104 1137 (or ++4930/39731945) e-mail: knut.rurack@bam.de Handout Prof. Dr. Matthias Rögner invited by Prof. Hauska 12. December 2001 Structure, Funktion and Regulation of the Cytochrome b6f Komplex in the Cyanobacterium Synechocystis PCC 6803        Ruhr Universitauml;t Bochum Lehrstuhl für Biochemie der Pflanzen Fax: +49 (234) 32-1 43 22 Tel: +49 (234) 32-2 36 34 e-mail: matthias.roegner@ruhr-uni-bochum.de Handout Prof. Dr. Jadwiga M. Giebultowicz invited by Dr. Stanewsky 10. December 2001 Joint Seminar - Graduate College and Zoologisches Kolloquium Circadian clocks: from molecular mechanisms to physiological functions        Department of Entomology Oregon State University Handout Dr. Helmut Port invited by Prof. Daub 21. November 2001 Photoswitchable Intramolecular Transfer Processes Control by Structure and Environment?       Universit?t Stuttgart 3. Physikalisches Institut Pfaffenwaldring 57 70569 Stuttgart Tel: +49 (711) 685 - 5283, 5233 Fax: +49 (711) 685 - 5281 e-mail: H.Port@physik.uni-stuttgart.de Dr. Jörg Tittor invited by Prof. Hegemann 7. November 2001 Structure and Function of Archaeal Rhodopsins (Bacteriorhodopsin and Halorhodopsin )     MPI für Biochemie          </field>
<field name="important">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Supervisors  Publications  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Guest lectures  -  Winter Term 2001-2002 reverse chronological order Dr. Marcel Mayor, invited by Prof. Daub 28. February 2002 to be announced      Research Center Karlsruhe GmbH, Institut für Nanotechnologie Postfach 3640, Germany e-mail: marcel.mayor@int.fzk.de Handout Prof. Dr. Horst Kisch invited by Prof. Hauska 16. January 2002 Photoinduced charge separation on semiconductor powders - new ways for the chemical synthesis        Institut f?r Anorganische Chemie Universit?t Erlangen-N?rnberg Egerlandstra?e 1 D-91058 Erlangen Fax: +49 (9131) 85-27363 Tel: +49 (9131) 85-27363 e-mail: kisch@anorganik.chemie.uni-erlangen.de Dr. Knut Rurack, invited by Prof. Daub 9. January 2002 Bifunctional Molecular Reporters:  Approaches towards Multi-Mode Fluorescence Signaling.      Federal Institute for Materials Research and Testing (BAM), Richard-Willstaetter-Str. 11,  D-12489 Berlin, Germany Fon ++4930/8104 5576 Fax ++4930/8104 1137 (or ++4930/39731945) e-mail: knut.rurack@bam.de Handout Prof. Dr. Matthias Rögner invited by Prof. Hauska 12. December 2001 Structure, Funktion and Regulation of the Cytochrome b6f Komplex in the Cyanobacterium Synechocystis PCC 6803        Ruhr Universitauml;t Bochum Lehrstuhl für Biochemie der Pflanzen Fax: +49 (234) 32-1 43 22 Tel: +49 (234) 32-2 36 34 e-mail: matthias.roegner@ruhr-uni-bochum.de Handout Prof. Dr. Jadwiga M. Giebultowicz invited by Dr. Stanewsky 10. December 2001 Joint Seminar - Graduate College and Zoologisches Kolloquium Circadian clocks: from molecular mechanisms to physiological functions        Department of Entomology Oregon State University Handout Dr. Helmut Port invited by Prof. Daub 21. November 2001 Photoswitchable Intramolecular Transfer Processes Control by Structure and Environment?       Universit?t Stuttgart 3. Physikalisches Institut Pfaffenwaldring 57 70569 Stuttgart Tel: +49 (711) 685 - 5283, 5233 Fax: +49 (711) 685 - 5281 e-mail: H.Port@physik.uni-stuttgart.de Dr. Jörg Tittor invited by Prof. Hegemann 7. November 2001 Structure and Function of Archaeal Rhodopsins (Bacteriorhodopsin and Halorhodopsin )     MPI für Biochemie          </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ws2002-03.html</field>
<field name="title">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ws2002-03.html</field>
<field name="content">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Supervisors  Publications  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Guest lectures  -  Winter Term 2002-2003 reverse chronological order Dr. Anja Rosengarth invited by Prof. Dr. Steinem 21.08.2002 -23.08.2002 9.00-11.00    BIO 5.2.38 Principals of X-ray Crystallography: A practical approach       Departments of Molecular Biology &amp; Biochemistry University of California Irvine anja@bragg.bio.uci.edu http://anx12.bio.uci.edu/~hudel/lab/   Handout Dr. Anja Rosengarth invited by Prof. Dr. Steinem 26.08.2002 10.00    H 46 Elucidation of annexin1-induced membrane aggregation using X-ray crystallography       Departments of Molecular Biology &amp; Biochemistry University of California Irvine anja@bragg.bio.uci.edu http://anx12.bio.uci.edu/~hudel/lab/   Prof. Dr. S. Nakatsuji invited by Prof. Dr. J. Daub 23.09.2002 17.00 s.t.    H46 Development of novel organic spin systems based on aminoxyl radicals       Himeji Institute of Technology Kouto Jaqan nakatuji@sci.himeji-tech.ac.jp   Dr. V. Gayvoronsky invited by Prof. Dr. A. Penzkofer 01.10.2002 17.00 s.t.    PHY 5.0.20 Linear and Nonlinear Optical Properties of TiO 2 Nanocomposites       Institute of Physics National Academy of Sciences of Ukraine Kiev vlad@iop.kiev.ua http://www.iop.kiev.ua/   Handout Dr. Stefan Weber invited by Prof. Dr. Hegemann 16.10.2002 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Modern EPR-Studies on Photoactive DNA Repair Enzymes an Plant Blue Light Receptors       Institute of Experimental Physics Free University Berlin Arnimallee 14 14195 Berlin Stefan.Weber@physik.fu-berlin.de http://www.physik.fu-berlin.de/~webers/   Handout Prof. Ytian Lu invited by Prof. Dr. A. Penzkofer 06.11.2002 17.00 s.t.    PHY 5.0.21 Advances in Semiconductor Diode Array Lasers       Shanghai Institute of Optics and Fine Mechanics Academia Sinica 201800 Shanghai China http://www.siom.ac.cn/   Handout Dr. Rita Grandori invited by Prof. Dr. G. Hauska 13.11.2002 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Applications of mass spectrometry to protein studies       Johannes Kepler University Organische Chemie 4040 Linz Austria rita.grandori@jku.at http://www.orc.uni-linz.ac.at/   Handout Dr. Bernd Becker invited by Prof. Dr. P. Hegemann 27.11.2002 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Application of profiling techniques for the analysis of melanocytic tumors       Uni-Klinik Regensburg Abt. Dermatologie Franz-Joseph-Strauss-Allee 11 93052 Regensburg Bernd.Becker@klinik.uni-regensburg.de http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/Medizin/Dermatologie/d.htm   Handout Student Seminar invited by Prof. Dr. P. Hegemann 04.12.2002 15.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 New Perspectives of the Graduate college       thomas.schoedl@biologie.uni-regensburg.de   Handout Dr. Victor Sourjik invited by Prof. Dr. Schmitt 06.12.2002 14.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Using Fluorescence Resonance Energy Transfer (FRET) to Study Bacterial Behavior       Department of Molecular and Cellular Biology Harvard University USA   PD Dr. Martha Merrow invited by PD Dr. Stanewsky 11.12.2002 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Photoreception in Neurospora: more photoreceptor molecules than functions       Institute for Medical Psychology Ludwig-Maximilians-University Munich http://www.imp-muenchen.de/   Handout Prof. Gijsbertus TJ van der Horst invited by PD Dr. R. Stanewsky 18.12.2002 1 6.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Mammalian Photolyases and Cryptochroms afterwards Xmas get together       Department of Cell Biology and Genetics Erasmus Medical Center Rotterdam NL vanderhorst@gen.fgg.eur.nl   Handout   invited by Prof. Dr. Hegemann 14.01.2003 9.00 s.t.    PHY 5.0.21 D  F  G     C  o  l  l  o  q  u  i  u  m         Handout Dr. Hartmann Harz invited by Prof. Dr. Hauska 15.01.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Use of fluorescent indicators in microscopy       harz@biz.uni-muenchen.de http://www.biz.uni-muenchen.de   Roman Fedorov invited by Prof. Dr. P. Hegemann 22.01.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Crystal structures and molecular mechanism of a light induced signaling switch: the Phot-LOV1 domain from Chlamydomonas reinhardtii       roman.fedorov@mpi-dortmund.mpg.de   Handout Dr. Kirchhoff invited by Prof. Dr. C. Steinem 05.02.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Significance of the light harvesting complex II for the formation of supermoleculare protein arrangements in photosynthetic membranes       Institut f?r Botanik Schlo?garten 3 48149 M?nster Kirchhh@uni-muenster.de http://www.uni-muenster.de/Biologie/botanik/Botany.htm   Handout Prof. T. Tsuboi invited by Prof. Dr. A. Penzkofer 12.02.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Spin-triplet fluorescent molecules for organic electroluminescence display devices       Faculty of Engineering Kyoto Sangyo University Kamigamo Kita-ku Kyoto 603-8555 Japan tsuboi@cc.kyoto-su.ac.jp            </field>
<field name="important">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Supervisors  Publications  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Guest lectures  -  Winter Term 2002-2003 reverse chronological order Dr. Anja Rosengarth invited by Prof. Dr. Steinem 21.08.2002 -23.08.2002 9.00-11.00    BIO 5.2.38 Principals of X-ray Crystallography: A practical approach       Departments of Molecular Biology &amp; Biochemistry University of California Irvine anja@bragg.bio.uci.edu http://anx12.bio.uci.edu/~hudel/lab/   Handout Dr. Anja Rosengarth invited by Prof. Dr. Steinem 26.08.2002 10.00    H 46 Elucidation of annexin1-induced membrane aggregation using X-ray crystallography       Departments of Molecular Biology &amp; Biochemistry University of California Irvine anja@bragg.bio.uci.edu http://anx12.bio.uci.edu/~hudel/lab/   Prof. Dr. S. Nakatsuji invited by Prof. Dr. J. Daub 23.09.2002 17.00 s.t.    H46 Development of novel organic spin systems based on aminoxyl radicals       Himeji Institute of Technology Kouto Jaqan nakatuji@sci.himeji-tech.ac.jp   Dr. V. Gayvoronsky invited by Prof. Dr. A. Penzkofer 01.10.2002 17.00 s.t.    PHY 5.0.20 Linear and Nonlinear Optical Properties of TiO 2 Nanocomposites       Institute of Physics National Academy of Sciences of Ukraine Kiev vlad@iop.kiev.ua http://www.iop.kiev.ua/   Handout Dr. Stefan Weber invited by Prof. Dr. Hegemann 16.10.2002 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Modern EPR-Studies on Photoactive DNA Repair Enzymes an Plant Blue Light Receptors       Institute of Experimental Physics Free University Berlin Arnimallee 14 14195 Berlin Stefan.Weber@physik.fu-berlin.de http://www.physik.fu-berlin.de/~webers/   Handout Prof. Ytian Lu invited by Prof. Dr. A. Penzkofer 06.11.2002 17.00 s.t.    PHY 5.0.21 Advances in Semiconductor Diode Array Lasers       Shanghai Institute of Optics and Fine Mechanics Academia Sinica 201800 Shanghai China http://www.siom.ac.cn/   Handout Dr. Rita Grandori invited by Prof. Dr. G. Hauska 13.11.2002 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Applications of mass spectrometry to protein studies       Johannes Kepler University Organische Chemie 4040 Linz Austria rita.grandori@jku.at http://www.orc.uni-linz.ac.at/   Handout Dr. Bernd Becker invited by Prof. Dr. P. Hegemann 27.11.2002 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Application of profiling techniques for the analysis of melanocytic tumors       Uni-Klinik Regensburg Abt. Dermatologie Franz-Joseph-Strauss-Allee 11 93052 Regensburg Bernd.Becker@klinik.uni-regensburg.de http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/Medizin/Dermatologie/d.htm   Handout Student Seminar invited by Prof. Dr. P. Hegemann 04.12.2002 15.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 New Perspectives of the Graduate college       thomas.schoedl@biologie.uni-regensburg.de   Handout Dr. Victor Sourjik invited by Prof. Dr. Schmitt 06.12.2002 14.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Using Fluorescence Resonance Energy Transfer (FRET) to Study Bacterial Behavior       Department of Molecular and Cellular Biology Harvard University USA   PD Dr. Martha Merrow invited by PD Dr. Stanewsky 11.12.2002 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Photoreception in Neurospora: more photoreceptor molecules than functions       Institute for Medical Psychology Ludwig-Maximilians-University Munich http://www.imp-muenchen.de/   Handout Prof. Gijsbertus TJ van der Horst invited by PD Dr. R. Stanewsky 18.12.2002 1 6.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Mammalian Photolyases and Cryptochroms afterwards Xmas get together       Department of Cell Biology and Genetics Erasmus Medical Center Rotterdam NL vanderhorst@gen.fgg.eur.nl   Handout   invited by Prof. Dr. Hegemann 14.01.2003 9.00 s.t.    PHY 5.0.21 D  F  G     C  o  l  l  o  q  u  i  u  m         Handout Dr. Hartmann Harz invited by Prof. Dr. Hauska 15.01.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Use of fluorescent indicators in microscopy       harz@biz.uni-muenchen.de http://www.biz.uni-muenchen.de   Roman Fedorov invited by Prof. Dr. P. Hegemann 22.01.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Crystal structures and molecular mechanism of a light induced signaling switch: the Phot-LOV1 domain from Chlamydomonas reinhardtii       roman.fedorov@mpi-dortmund.mpg.de   Handout Dr. Kirchhoff invited by Prof. Dr. C. Steinem 05.02.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Significance of the light harvesting complex II for the formation of supermoleculare protein arrangements in photosynthetic membranes       Institut f?r Botanik Schlo?garten 3 48149 M?nster Kirchhh@uni-muenster.de http://www.uni-muenster.de/Biologie/botanik/Botany.htm   Handout Prof. T. Tsuboi invited by Prof. Dr. A. Penzkofer 12.02.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Spin-triplet fluorescent molecules for organic electroluminescence display devices       Faculty of Engineering Kyoto Sangyo University Kamigamo Kita-ku Kyoto 603-8555 Japan tsuboi@cc.kyoto-su.ac.jp            </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ws2003-04.html</field>
<field name="title">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ws2003-04.html</field>
<field name="content">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Publications  Supervisors  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Guest lectures  - Winter Term 2003/04 For this kind of lecture guest professors wil be invited. During the teaching terms we will have at least two guest lectures per month. The program will be composed under the guidance of the students.  The term Research Report is used for lectures given by the supervisors of the Graduate College. Topics, abstracts and handouts of past guest lectures can be found in the guest lecture archive . This page fitting to A4 papersize in width Prof. Dr. R. Diller invited by Prof. Dr. P. Hegemann 15.10.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Ultrafast IR Spectroscopy on Retinal binding Proteins       Fachbereich Physik Universität Kaiserslautern diller@physik.uni-kl.de http://www.uni-kl.de/   Handout Prof. Dr. G. Nagel invited by Prof. Dr. P. Hegemann 05.11.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Channelrhodopsins       Max-Planck-Institute of Biophysics Marie-Curie-Str. 15 60439 Frankfurt Main Georg.Nagel@mpibp-frankfurt.mpg.de http://www.mpibp-frankfurt.mpg.de/nagel/nagel.html   Handout Dr. Martin Engelhard invited by Prof. Dr. P. Hegemann 26.11.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 The Sensory Rhodopsin-HtrII Complex: From Retinal Isomerisation to Transducer Activation       MPI of Molecular Physiology Otto-Hahn-Stra?e 11 44227 Dortmund martin.engelhard@mpi-dortmund.mpg.de http://www.mpi-dortmund.mpg.de/departments/dep3/engelhard/index2.html   Handout Andr? Fiala invited by Prof. Dr. C. F?rster 03.12.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Optical calcium imaging of odorant representations in the Drosophila brain using genetically encoded cameleon       Biozentrum der Universit?t W?rzburg Am Hubland 97074 W?rzburg andre.fiala@biozentrum.uni-wuerzburg.de http://www.biozentrum.uni-wuerzburg.de/genetics/   Handout Prof. Dr. L.-O. Essen invited by Prof. Dr. P. Hegemann 10.12.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 How proteins adapt to salt: A structural view towards halophilicity       Department of Chemistry Philipps-University Marburg Hans-Meerwein-Strasse 35032 Marburg Germany essen@chemie.uni-marburg.de http://www.chemie.uni-marburg.de/~essen/essen_group.html   Prof. Dr. Yehuda Haas invited by Prof. Dr. B. Dick 17.12.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Why did Nature Choose Isomerization Around Double Bonds in Schiff Bases For the Primary Event in Vision?       Department of Physical Chemistry - Hebrew University Givat Ram Jerusalem 91904 yehuda@chem.ch.huji.ac.il http://chem.ch.huji.ac.il/employee/haas/ihaas.htm   Dr. Klaus Fendler invited by Prof. Dr. C. Steinem 21.01.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Electrical Experiments on Biological Enzymes: The Transport Mechanism of Cytochrome c Oxidase and Melibiose Permease       MPI fuer Biophysik Marie-Curie-Strasse 15 60439 Frankfurt/M klaus.fendler@mpibp-frankfurt.mpg.de http://www.mpibp-frankfurt.mpg.de/fendler/fendler.html   Prof. Norbert Dencher invited by Prof. Dr. C. Steinem 28.01.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Exploration of photon-energy conversion and photosignal transduction by biomembranes with flash absorption-spectroscopy &amp; AFM &amp; native gel electrophoresis       Technische Universit?t Darmstadt Institut f?r Biochemie - Abteilung f?r physikalische Biochemie Petersenstra?e 22 - D-64287 Darmstadt dencher@pop.tu-darmstadt.de http://www.chemie.tu-darmstadt.de/Fachgebiete/BC/AKDencher/index_de.html   Prof. Neil R. Branda invited by Prof. Dr. J. Daub 04.02.2004 17.00 s.t.    CHE H46 Molecular Switches to Control Structure and Function       Simon Fraser University Department of Chemistry Burnaby - Canada nbranda@sfu.ca http://css.sfu.ca/members/bio.cgi?MemberID=408   Prof. Alfred R. Holzwarth invited by Prof. Dr. A. Penzkofer 11.02.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Exciton dynamics in the chlorosomal antenna systems of green bacteria and model systems       Max-Planck-Institut f?r Bioanorganische Chemie P.O.Box 101365 D-45413 Muelheim a.d.Ruhr holzwarth@mpi-muehlheim.mpg.de http://www.mpi-muelheim.mpg.de/mpistr_holzwarth.html   Prof. Widmar Tanner invited by Prof. Dr. C. Steinem / Prof. Dr. G. Hauska 18.02.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 SUBCOMPARTMENTS OF BIOLOGICAL MEMBRANES (with a DVD-film of Aki Kusumi)       Uni Regensburg Lehrstuhl f?r Zellbiologie und Pflanzenphysiologie 93040 Regensburg widmar.tanner@biologie.uni-regensburg.de http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Botanik/Tanner/            </field>
<field name="important">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Publications  Supervisors  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Guest lectures  - Winter Term 2003/04 For this kind of lecture guest professors wil be invited. During the teaching terms we will have at least two guest lectures per month. The program will be composed under the guidance of the students.  The term Research Report is used for lectures given by the supervisors of the Graduate College. Topics, abstracts and handouts of past guest lectures can be found in the guest lecture archive . This page fitting to A4 papersize in width Prof. Dr. R. Diller invited by Prof. Dr. P. Hegemann 15.10.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Ultrafast IR Spectroscopy on Retinal binding Proteins       Fachbereich Physik Universität Kaiserslautern diller@physik.uni-kl.de http://www.uni-kl.de/   Handout Prof. Dr. G. Nagel invited by Prof. Dr. P. Hegemann 05.11.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Channelrhodopsins       Max-Planck-Institute of Biophysics Marie-Curie-Str. 15 60439 Frankfurt Main Georg.Nagel@mpibp-frankfurt.mpg.de http://www.mpibp-frankfurt.mpg.de/nagel/nagel.html   Handout Dr. Martin Engelhard invited by Prof. Dr. P. Hegemann 26.11.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 The Sensory Rhodopsin-HtrII Complex: From Retinal Isomerisation to Transducer Activation       MPI of Molecular Physiology Otto-Hahn-Stra?e 11 44227 Dortmund martin.engelhard@mpi-dortmund.mpg.de http://www.mpi-dortmund.mpg.de/departments/dep3/engelhard/index2.html   Handout Andr? Fiala invited by Prof. Dr. C. F?rster 03.12.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Optical calcium imaging of odorant representations in the Drosophila brain using genetically encoded cameleon       Biozentrum der Universit?t W?rzburg Am Hubland 97074 W?rzburg andre.fiala@biozentrum.uni-wuerzburg.de http://www.biozentrum.uni-wuerzburg.de/genetics/   Handout Prof. Dr. L.-O. Essen invited by Prof. Dr. P. Hegemann 10.12.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 How proteins adapt to salt: A structural view towards halophilicity       Department of Chemistry Philipps-University Marburg Hans-Meerwein-Strasse 35032 Marburg Germany essen@chemie.uni-marburg.de http://www.chemie.uni-marburg.de/~essen/essen_group.html   Prof. Dr. Yehuda Haas invited by Prof. Dr. B. Dick 17.12.2003 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Why did Nature Choose Isomerization Around Double Bonds in Schiff Bases For the Primary Event in Vision?       Department of Physical Chemistry - Hebrew University Givat Ram Jerusalem 91904 yehuda@chem.ch.huji.ac.il http://chem.ch.huji.ac.il/employee/haas/ihaas.htm   Dr. Klaus Fendler invited by Prof. Dr. C. Steinem 21.01.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Electrical Experiments on Biological Enzymes: The Transport Mechanism of Cytochrome c Oxidase and Melibiose Permease       MPI fuer Biophysik Marie-Curie-Strasse 15 60439 Frankfurt/M klaus.fendler@mpibp-frankfurt.mpg.de http://www.mpibp-frankfurt.mpg.de/fendler/fendler.html   Prof. Norbert Dencher invited by Prof. Dr. C. Steinem 28.01.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Exploration of photon-energy conversion and photosignal transduction by biomembranes with flash absorption-spectroscopy &amp; AFM &amp; native gel electrophoresis       Technische Universit?t Darmstadt Institut f?r Biochemie - Abteilung f?r physikalische Biochemie Petersenstra?e 22 - D-64287 Darmstadt dencher@pop.tu-darmstadt.de http://www.chemie.tu-darmstadt.de/Fachgebiete/BC/AKDencher/index_de.html   Prof. Neil R. Branda invited by Prof. Dr. J. Daub 04.02.2004 17.00 s.t.    CHE H46 Molecular Switches to Control Structure and Function       Simon Fraser University Department of Chemistry Burnaby - Canada nbranda@sfu.ca http://css.sfu.ca/members/bio.cgi?MemberID=408   Prof. Alfred R. Holzwarth invited by Prof. Dr. A. Penzkofer 11.02.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Exciton dynamics in the chlorosomal antenna systems of green bacteria and model systems       Max-Planck-Institut f?r Bioanorganische Chemie P.O.Box 101365 D-45413 Muelheim a.d.Ruhr holzwarth@mpi-muehlheim.mpg.de http://www.mpi-muelheim.mpg.de/mpistr_holzwarth.html   Prof. Widmar Tanner invited by Prof. Dr. C. Steinem / Prof. Dr. G. Hauska 18.02.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 SUBCOMPARTMENTS OF BIOLOGICAL MEMBRANES (with a DVD-film of Aki Kusumi)       Uni Regensburg Lehrstuhl f?r Zellbiologie und Pflanzenphysiologie 93040 Regensburg widmar.tanner@biologie.uni-regensburg.de http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Botanik/Tanner/            </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ws2004-05.html</field>
<field name="title">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ws2004-05.html</field>
<field name="content">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Publications  Supervisors  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Past Guest lectures  - Winter Term 2004-2005 For this kind of lecture guest professors wil be invited. During the teaching terms we will have at least two guest lectures per month. The program will be composed under the guidance of the students.  The term Research Report is used for lectures given by the supervisors of the Graduate College. Topics, abstracts and handouts of past guest lectures can be found in the guest lecture archive .This page fitting to A4 papersize in width Dr. Dieter Braun invited by Prof. Dr. C. Steinem 10.11.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 "LockIn Imaging of Membrane Potential and Reaction Kinetics and Movement of DNA by Temperature Gradients"       Dissipative Biosystems Ludwig-Maximilians-University Amalienstr. 54 - D-80799 M?nchen - Germany mailto:dieter.braun@physik.uni-muenchen.de http://www.dieterb.de/indexe.html   Prof. Dr. E. Riedle invited by Prof. Dr. J. Daub 24.11.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 New chemical dynamics seen with new ultrafast techniques       LS f. Biomolekulare Optik Universit?t M?nchen mailto:riedle@physik.uni-muenchen.de http://www.bmo.physik.uni-muenchen.de/~riedle/   Handout Prof. Dr. U. Nienhaus invited by Prof. Dr. C. Steinem 15.12.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Novel green and red and green/red fluorescent proteins from the GFP family       Abteilung f?r Biophysik Universit?t Ulm Albert-Einstein-Allee 11 - D-89081 Ulm mailto:uli@uiuc.edu http://www.uni-ulm.de/biophys/   Prof. Dr. C. Lambert invited by Prof. Dr. J. Daub 24.01.2005 17.00 c.t.    CHE H46 Applications of Triarylamines in Electron Transfer Processes       Institut f?r Organische Chemie Universit?t W?rzburg Am Hubland - D-97074 W?rzburg mailto:lambert@chemie.uni-wuerzburg.de http://www-organik.chemie.uni-wuerzburg.de/ak_lambe/main_frame.htm   Handout Prof. Dr. W. Junge invited by Prof. Dr. G. Hauska 26.01.2005 17.00 s.t.    CHE H46 "ATP Sythase: The Progress After Rotation Assays"       Division of Biophysics Department of Biology and Chemistry University of Osnabr?ck mailto:junge@uni-osnabrueck.de http://www.biologie.uni-osnabrueck.de/biophysik/Junge/index.html            </field>
<field name="important">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Publications  Supervisors  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Past Guest lectures  - Winter Term 2004-2005 For this kind of lecture guest professors wil be invited. During the teaching terms we will have at least two guest lectures per month. The program will be composed under the guidance of the students.  The term Research Report is used for lectures given by the supervisors of the Graduate College. Topics, abstracts and handouts of past guest lectures can be found in the guest lecture archive .This page fitting to A4 papersize in width Dr. Dieter Braun invited by Prof. Dr. C. Steinem 10.11.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 "LockIn Imaging of Membrane Potential and Reaction Kinetics and Movement of DNA by Temperature Gradients"       Dissipative Biosystems Ludwig-Maximilians-University Amalienstr. 54 - D-80799 M?nchen - Germany mailto:dieter.braun@physik.uni-muenchen.de http://www.dieterb.de/indexe.html   Prof. Dr. E. Riedle invited by Prof. Dr. J. Daub 24.11.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 New chemical dynamics seen with new ultrafast techniques       LS f. Biomolekulare Optik Universit?t M?nchen mailto:riedle@physik.uni-muenchen.de http://www.bmo.physik.uni-muenchen.de/~riedle/   Handout Prof. Dr. U. Nienhaus invited by Prof. Dr. C. Steinem 15.12.2004 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 Novel green and red and green/red fluorescent proteins from the GFP family       Abteilung f?r Biophysik Universit?t Ulm Albert-Einstein-Allee 11 - D-89081 Ulm mailto:uli@uiuc.edu http://www.uni-ulm.de/biophys/   Prof. Dr. C. Lambert invited by Prof. Dr. J. Daub 24.01.2005 17.00 c.t.    CHE H46 Applications of Triarylamines in Electron Transfer Processes       Institut f?r Organische Chemie Universit?t W?rzburg Am Hubland - D-97074 W?rzburg mailto:lambert@chemie.uni-wuerzburg.de http://www-organik.chemie.uni-wuerzburg.de/ak_lambe/main_frame.htm   Handout Prof. Dr. W. Junge invited by Prof. Dr. G. Hauska 26.01.2005 17.00 s.t.    CHE H46 "ATP Sythase: The Progress After Rotation Assays"       Division of Biophysics Department of Biology and Chemistry University of Osnabr?ck mailto:junge@uni-osnabrueck.de http://www.biologie.uni-osnabrueck.de/biophysik/Junge/index.html            </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ws2007-08.html</field>
<field name="title">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/guest-lectures-ws2007-08.html</field>
<field name="content">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Publications  Supervisors  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Past Guest lectures  - Winter Term 2007/2008 For this kind of lecture guest professors wil be invited. During the teaching terms we will have at least two guest lectures per month. The program will be composed under the guidance of the students.  The term Research Report is used for lectures given by the supervisors of the Graduate College. Topics, abstracts and handouts of past guest lectures can be found in the guest lecture archive . This page fitting to A4 papersize in width Prof. Dr. Torsten Fiebig invited by GK640 17.10.2007 17.15    Bio 5.2.38 "Biophotonics with ultrafast laser pulses - from basic research to medical applications"       Chemistry Departments Boston College U.S. torsten.fiebig.1_at_bc.edu http://www2.bc.edu/~fiebig/   Prof. Dr. Taiju Tsuboi invited by Prof. A. Penzkofer 24.10.2007 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 "Photophysics and Chemistry of Organic Materials used for Organic Light Emitting Diodes"       Faculty of Engineering - Kyoto Sangyo University Kamigamo - Kita-Ku Kyoto 603-8555 Japan tuboi_at_cc.kyoto-su.ac.jp   Handout Prof. Dr. Klaus M?llen invited by GDCh 05.11.2007 17.15    H46 "Molecular Electronics"       Max Planck Institute for Polymer Research Mainz klaus.muellen_at_mpip-mainz.mpg.de http://www.mpip-mainz.mpg.de/groups/muellen/director   Dr. Henrik Mouritsen invited by GK640 07.11.2007 17.15    Bio 5.2.38 "Bird Migration: The possible role of the visual system in sensing direction of the geomagnetic field"       Dept. Biology University of Oldenburg henrik.mouritsen_at_uni-oldenburg.de http://www.member.uni-oldenburg.de/henrik.mouritsen/5918.html   Dr. Dilip Joshi invited by Prof. C. F?rster 14.11.2007 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 "Altitude of origin affects the photic senisitivity of two Drosophila ananassae wild-type strains that live in the Himalaya"       Zoology Department Ahmednagar College Ahmednagar India dsjoshi_anr_sancharnet.in   Prof. Dr. Thomas Carell invited by GK640 05.12.2007 17.00 s.t.    H46 "Repair and Mutagenesis of UV-Induced DNA Photolesions"       Faculty for Chemistry and Pharmacy LMU Munich thomas.carell_at_cup.uni-muenchen.de http://www.cup.uni-muenchen.de/oc/carell   Prof. Dr. Christel Marian invited by GK640 16.01.2008 17.00 s.t.    Bio 5.2.38 "Intersystem Crossing in Flavins: A Quantum Chemical Investigation"       Institut f?r Theoretische Chemie Heinrich-Heine-Universit?t D?sseldorf Christel.Marian_at_uni-duesseldorf.de http://www.chemie.uni-duesseldorf.de/Faecher/Theochem   Dr. Radek Cibulka invited by GK640 17.01.2008 12.00 s.t.    H46 "Flavin based sulfoxidation catalysts"       Department of Organic Chemistry Prague Institute of Chemical Technology Prague - Czech Republic cibulkar_at_vscht.cz http://uoch.vscht.cz/en/index.htm   Prof. Dr. Reji Philip invited by GK640 22.02.2008 17.00 s.t.    Bio 5.2.38 Slow light experiments by coherent population oscillations       Optics group Raman Research Institute Bangalore India reji_at_rri.res.in http://www.rri.res.in/~reji/            </field>
<field name="important">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects  Graduates  Publications  Supervisors  Lectures    lectures &amp; seminars    guest lectures    guest lecture archive    workshops  Scholarships    Intranet           Past Guest lectures  - Winter Term 2007/2008 For this kind of lecture guest professors wil be invited. During the teaching terms we will have at least two guest lectures per month. The program will be composed under the guidance of the students.  The term Research Report is used for lectures given by the supervisors of the Graduate College. Topics, abstracts and handouts of past guest lectures can be found in the guest lecture archive . This page fitting to A4 papersize in width Prof. Dr. Torsten Fiebig invited by GK640 17.10.2007 17.15    Bio 5.2.38 "Biophotonics with ultrafast laser pulses - from basic research to medical applications"       Chemistry Departments Boston College U.S. torsten.fiebig.1_at_bc.edu http://www2.bc.edu/~fiebig/   Prof. Dr. Taiju Tsuboi invited by Prof. A. Penzkofer 24.10.2007 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 "Photophysics and Chemistry of Organic Materials used for Organic Light Emitting Diodes"       Faculty of Engineering - Kyoto Sangyo University Kamigamo - Kita-Ku Kyoto 603-8555 Japan tuboi_at_cc.kyoto-su.ac.jp   Handout Prof. Dr. Klaus M?llen invited by GDCh 05.11.2007 17.15    H46 "Molecular Electronics"       Max Planck Institute for Polymer Research Mainz klaus.muellen_at_mpip-mainz.mpg.de http://www.mpip-mainz.mpg.de/groups/muellen/director   Dr. Henrik Mouritsen invited by GK640 07.11.2007 17.15    Bio 5.2.38 "Bird Migration: The possible role of the visual system in sensing direction of the geomagnetic field"       Dept. Biology University of Oldenburg henrik.mouritsen_at_uni-oldenburg.de http://www.member.uni-oldenburg.de/henrik.mouritsen/5918.html   Dr. Dilip Joshi invited by Prof. C. F?rster 14.11.2007 17.00 s.t.    BIO 5.2.38 "Altitude of origin affects the photic senisitivity of two Drosophila ananassae wild-type strains that live in the Himalaya"       Zoology Department Ahmednagar College Ahmednagar India dsjoshi_anr_sancharnet.in   Prof. Dr. Thomas Carell invited by GK640 05.12.2007 17.00 s.t.    H46 "Repair and Mutagenesis of UV-Induced DNA Photolesions"       Faculty for Chemistry and Pharmacy LMU Munich thomas.carell_at_cup.uni-muenchen.de http://www.cup.uni-muenchen.de/oc/carell   Prof. Dr. Christel Marian invited by GK640 16.01.2008 17.00 s.t.    Bio 5.2.38 "Intersystem Crossing in Flavins: A Quantum Chemical Investigation"       Institut f?r Theoretische Chemie Heinrich-Heine-Universit?t D?sseldorf Christel.Marian_at_uni-duesseldorf.de http://www.chemie.uni-duesseldorf.de/Faecher/Theochem   Dr. Radek Cibulka invited by GK640 17.01.2008 12.00 s.t.    H46 "Flavin based sulfoxidation catalysts"       Department of Organic Chemistry Prague Institute of Chemical Technology Prague - Czech Republic cibulkar_at_vscht.cz http://uoch.vscht.cz/en/index.htm   Prof. Dr. Reji Philip invited by GK640 22.02.2008 17.00 s.t.    Bio 5.2.38 Slow light experiments by coherent population oscillations       Optics group Raman Research Institute Bangalore India reji_at_rri.res.in http://www.rri.res.in/~reji/            </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/printguestlectures.php</field>
<field name="title">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/lectures/printguestlectures.php</field>
<field name="content">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg Graduate College  "Sensory photoreceptors in natural and artificial systems"  GUEST LECTURES    </field>
<field name="important">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg Graduate College  "Sensory photoreceptors in natural and artificial systems"  GUEST LECTURES    </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/projects/announced-projects.php</field>
<field name="title">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/GK/SP/projects/announced-projects.php</field>
<field name="content">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects   current projects   announced projects  Graduates  Supervisors  Lectures  Publications  Scholarships    Intranet         [1] Membrane suspended nanocompartments as a new artificial membrane system for studying light-activated proton pumps and channels [2] Generation of flavoproteins with modified chromophores in vivo [3] Role of the compound eyes and extraretinal photoreceptors in synchronizing the activity rhythm of Drosophila melanogaster to light-dark (LD) cycles. [4] Biochemical studies on FAD derivates [5] In vitro characterisation of "Channelopsins" from Chlamydomonas reinhardtii [6] Photophysical and Photochemical Studies on Open-Chain Tetrapyrrole Complexes [7] Investigation of the photocycle of a plant photoreceptor by Quantum Chemical Calculations and Molecular Dynamics Simulations For detailed information about announced projects hit one of the links belowchoose number:   [1]   [2]   [3]   [4]   [5]   [6]   [7]    no project chosen how to apply ... (in general)        </field>
<field name="important">Graduate College - Sensory Photoreceptors - Regensburg    Overview  Projects   current projects   announced projects  Graduates  Supervisors  Lectures  Publications  Scholarships    Intranet         [1] Membrane suspended nanocompartments as a new artificial membrane system for studying light-activated proton pumps and channels [2] Generation of flavoproteins with modified chromophores in vivo [3] Role of the compound eyes and extraretinal photoreceptors in synchronizing the activity rhythm of Drosophila melanogaster to light-dark (LD) cycles. [4] Biochemical studies on FAD derivates [5] In vitro characterisation of "Channelopsins" from Chlamydomonas reinhardtii [6] Photophysical and Photochemical Studies on Open-Chain Tetrapyrrole Complexes [7] Investigation of the photocycle of a plant photoreceptor by Quantum Chemical Calculations and Molecular Dynamics Simulations For detailed information about announced projects hit one of the links belowchoose number:   [1]   [2]   [3]   [4]   [5]   [6]   [7]    no project chosen how to apply ... (in general)        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/archiv/archive.html</field>
<field name="title">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/archiv/archive.html</field>
<field name="content">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   What is ECN? Programme Committee Our Faculty Our Students News News Archive you are here: Home » About ECN » News » News Archive News Archive ECN V (2010-2012) Fifth Year of the Experimental and Clinical Neurosciences (ECN) Programme Download Programme 2010-2012 ECN course material via G.R.I.P.S. E-Learning-Plattform The invitation flyer for the ECN programme autumn 2011 Weekend seminar for the ECN-Students: At the crossroads of their studies, by Dominik Kraus ECN IV (2009-2011) ENB report from the ECN 2009 opening ceremony ENB interview with Claire Davis and Rebecca Robins on their motivation to join the ECN programme ECN III (2008-2010) Schloss Neufahrn February 27./28 Elite Master's Defence 2009: Photos from the two successful days Oct 3 - 4, 2008: Weekendseminar organized by Dr. Anton Beer and Prof. Mark Greenlee and held in Bavaria's Altmühltal. Report by Ada Tse and Erin Liu   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
<field name="important">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   What is ECN? Programme Committee Our Faculty Our Students News News Archive you are here: Home » About ECN » News » News Archive News Archive ECN V (2010-2012) Fifth Year of the Experimental and Clinical Neurosciences (ECN) Programme Download Programme 2010-2012 ECN course material via G.R.I.P.S. E-Learning-Plattform The invitation flyer for the ECN programme autumn 2011 Weekend seminar for the ECN-Students: At the crossroads of their studies, by Dominik Kraus ECN IV (2009-2011) ENB report from the ECN 2009 opening ceremony ENB interview with Claire Davis and Rebecca Robins on their motivation to join the ECN programme ECN III (2008-2010) Schloss Neufahrn February 27./28 Elite Master's Defence 2009: Photos from the two successful days Oct 3 - 4, 2008: Weekendseminar organized by Dr. Anton Beer and Prof. Mark Greenlee and held in Bavaria's Altmühltal. Report by Ada Tse and Erin Liu   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/comm.html</field>
<field name="title">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/comm.html</field>
<field name="content">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   What is ECN? Programme Committee Our Faculty Our Students News News Archive you are here: Home » About ECN » Programme Committee Programme Committee   Prof. Dr. Inga D. Neumann (Programme Director) Molecular and Behavioural Neuroendocrinology, Institute of Zoology University of Regensburg 93053 Regensburg Phone: 0941 943 3055 Fax: 0941 943 3052 homepage     Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly Developmental Neurobiology, Institute of Zoology University of Regensburg 93053 Regensburg Phone: 0941 943 3068 Fax: 0941 943 3325 homepage     Prof. Dr. Mark Greenlee Institute of Experimental Psychology University of Regensburg 93053 Regensburg Phone: 0941 943 3815 Fax: 0941 943 4496 homepage     Prof. Dr. Ulrich Bogdahn Dept. of Neurology, Medical Faculty University of Regensburg 93053 Regensburg Phone: 0941 941 3001 Fax: 0941 941 3005 homepage     Prof. Dr. Christian Wetzel Dept. of Psychiatry, Medical Faculty University of Regensburg 93053 Regensburg Phone:. 0941 941 2067 Fax: 0941 941 2068 homepage       home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
<field name="important">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   What is ECN? Programme Committee Our Faculty Our Students News News Archive you are here: Home » About ECN » Programme Committee Programme Committee   Prof. Dr. Inga D. Neumann (Programme Director) Molecular and Behavioural Neuroendocrinology, Institute of Zoology University of Regensburg 93053 Regensburg Phone: 0941 943 3055 Fax: 0941 943 3052 homepage     Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly Developmental Neurobiology, Institute of Zoology University of Regensburg 93053 Regensburg Phone: 0941 943 3068 Fax: 0941 943 3325 homepage     Prof. Dr. Mark Greenlee Institute of Experimental Psychology University of Regensburg 93053 Regensburg Phone: 0941 943 3815 Fax: 0941 943 4496 homepage     Prof. Dr. Ulrich Bogdahn Dept. of Neurology, Medical Faculty University of Regensburg 93053 Regensburg Phone: 0941 941 3001 Fax: 0941 941 3005 homepage     Prof. Dr. Christian Wetzel Dept. of Psychiatry, Medical Faculty University of Regensburg 93053 Regensburg Phone:. 0941 941 2067 Fax: 0941 941 2068 homepage       home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/contact.html</field>
<field name="title">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/contact.html</field>
<field name="content">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   Imprint you are here: Home » Contact Contact Before contacting us regarding the application process please check whether your questions can also be answered by the intensive information provided on our homepage. Please have a look at our application category first, especially at the FAQ's For e-mail requests please contact »   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
<field name="important">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   Imprint you are here: Home » Contact Contact Before contacting us regarding the application process please check whether your questions can also be answered by the intensive information provided on our homepage. Please have a look at our application category first, especially at the FAQ's For e-mail requests please contact »   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/ecn.html</field>
<field name="title">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/ecn.html</field>
<field name="content">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   What is ECN? Programme Committee Our Faculty Our Students News News Archive you are here: Home » About ECN » What is ECN? What is ECN? Our aim is to establish a highly specialised, internationally competitive, graduate degree for honours students in the area of Experimental and Clinical Neurosciences (ECN). The ECN-Programme is based on an interdisciplinary scientific network with emphasis on decoding the molecular, cellular and neuroendocrine mechanisms underlying neuropsychiatric disorders. The following key research areas are of central importance: molecular neurobiology (neuroplasticity, neurogenetics, neuronal signaling), behavioural and molecular neuroendocrinology (emotionality, social behaviour, cognition, early and adult life stress and correlation with molecular, cellular and neuroendocrine parameters, surgical approaches), Neuro-imaging/ functional magnetic resonance tomography. Graduate studies take place in a complementary and competitive environment. Didactic concepts include the participation at interactive lectures, seminars, journal clubs and tutorials, training of preparation of slide presentations, drafted manuscripts and research proposals. The graduate students acquire experimental skills according to the research profile of the selected participating research teams, qualifications with respect to experimental design and experimental procedures, statistical data analysis, and "laboratory management" as well as data presentations. ECN Video (in German) The ECN student Matthias Zunhammer presents the ECN Master's Programme as part of the Elite Network of Bavaria: News &amp; Events Students of the Programme 2010-2012: We are proud to announce that new students have been selected to join the ECN programme 2010-2012. Their names can be found here: Students   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
<field name="important">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   What is ECN? Programme Committee Our Faculty Our Students News News Archive you are here: Home » About ECN » What is ECN? What is ECN? Our aim is to establish a highly specialised, internationally competitive, graduate degree for honours students in the area of Experimental and Clinical Neurosciences (ECN). The ECN-Programme is based on an interdisciplinary scientific network with emphasis on decoding the molecular, cellular and neuroendocrine mechanisms underlying neuropsychiatric disorders. The following key research areas are of central importance: molecular neurobiology (neuroplasticity, neurogenetics, neuronal signaling), behavioural and molecular neuroendocrinology (emotionality, social behaviour, cognition, early and adult life stress and correlation with molecular, cellular and neuroendocrine parameters, surgical approaches), Neuro-imaging/ functional magnetic resonance tomography. Graduate studies take place in a complementary and competitive environment. Didactic concepts include the participation at interactive lectures, seminars, journal clubs and tutorials, training of preparation of slide presentations, drafted manuscripts and research proposals. The graduate students acquire experimental skills according to the research profile of the selected participating research teams, qualifications with respect to experimental design and experimental procedures, statistical data analysis, and "laboratory management" as well as data presentations. ECN Video (in German) The ECN student Matthias Zunhammer presents the ECN Master's Programme as part of the Elite Network of Bavaria: News &amp; Events Students of the Programme 2010-2012: We are proud to announce that new students have been selected to join the ECN programme 2010-2012. Their names can be found here: Students   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/faculty.html</field>
<field name="title">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/faculty.html</field>
<field name="content">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   What is ECN? Programme Committee Our Faculty Our Students News News Archive you are here: Home » About ECN » Our Faculty Our Faculty ECN Educators from Regensburg Other German ECN Educators International ECN Educators Our Faculty   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
<field name="important">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   What is ECN? Programme Committee Our Faculty Our Students News News Archive you are here: Home » About ECN » Our Faculty Our Faculty ECN Educators from Regensburg Other German ECN Educators International ECN Educators Our Faculty   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/faqs.html</field>
<field name="title">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/faqs.html</field>
<field name="content">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   Application &amp; Enrolment Required Documents Tuition Fees &amp; Costs of living FAQs you are here: Home » Who Should Attend? » FAQs FAQs Am I eligible for the ECN programme? Applicants are eligible if they hold a Bachelor degree, or equivalent, in biology, chemistry, medicine, psychology, or a closely related subject area. Also eligible to apply are students in the final year of their Bachelor, provided that the degree will be conferred prior to the MSc enrolment date. German applicants who do not hold a Bachelor degree must have successfully completed the "Vordiplom" or "Physikum" examinations in one of the subjects specified above, and must have completed two semesters of advanced-level courses ("Hauptstudium") by the date of enrolment in the MSc programme. What is the next application deadline for the ECN programme? Early application January 31st / late application March 15th 2013. What is the duration of the ECN programme? Three semesters (each semester lasts 6 months). When does the new ECN Programme start? The ECN programme starts each year in September. How many students will be selected for the programme per year? Up to a maximum of 20 students. What is the language of instruction? English. What are the English language requirements? Applicants who are not native speakers of the English language must demonstrate English proficiency by obtaining acceptable results in an internationally recognized test (e.g., TOEFL, IELTS, APIEL, CPE). Proof of higher education in English or of residence in an English-speaking country for a reasonable length of time may also be acceptable upon the decision of the Admissions Committee. Language skills may also be evaluated during the personal interviews of selected candidates, see » Application &amp; Enrolment. Are there German language requirements? There are no German language requirements. However, a German course will be offered to students of the ECN Programme. Is there an age limit for the application? The applicants' age should not exceed 26 years upon enrolment. Exceptions are possible only under particular circumstances, upon the decision of the Admissions Committee. Are there tuition fees? Yes, 114 Euro per semester. Where can I find the application forms? There are no official application forms, please send the required documents in paper form by mail as listed under » Application &amp; Enrolment To whom should I submit my application documents? Prof. Dr. Inga D. Neumann ECN-Programme University of Regensburg Germany Do I have to submit original documents for the application? Copies are sufficient, however, at the enrolment, original documents are necessary. Where can I find the examination regulations (Prüfungsordnung)? See » Application &amp; Enrolment Is the ECN Programme officially registered? The ECN Programme is a registered member of the Network of European Neuroscience Schools (NENS), see: Federation of European Neuroscience Societies. The NENS was founded in 2003 and represents over 130 european graduate schools and programmes.  Membership of NENS helps to ensure high quality standards across programmes and also provides a number of benefits for students within registered programmes including training stipends and participation in annual meetings. How can I organize housing, visa application, bank account, health insurance and immigration? After acceptance to the ECN Programme, you will receive all necessary information about registration at the University of Regensburg, housing, visa application, bank account, health insurance and immigration. Please contact the student counsellor for any further questions: elli.wunderlich@verwaltung.uni-regensburg.de page up     home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
<field name="important">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   Application &amp; Enrolment Required Documents Tuition Fees &amp; Costs of living FAQs you are here: Home » Who Should Attend? » FAQs FAQs Am I eligible for the ECN programme? Applicants are eligible if they hold a Bachelor degree, or equivalent, in biology, chemistry, medicine, psychology, or a closely related subject area. Also eligible to apply are students in the final year of their Bachelor, provided that the degree will be conferred prior to the MSc enrolment date. German applicants who do not hold a Bachelor degree must have successfully completed the "Vordiplom" or "Physikum" examinations in one of the subjects specified above, and must have completed two semesters of advanced-level courses ("Hauptstudium") by the date of enrolment in the MSc programme. What is the next application deadline for the ECN programme? Early application January 31st / late application March 15th 2013. What is the duration of the ECN programme? Three semesters (each semester lasts 6 months). When does the new ECN Programme start? The ECN programme starts each year in September. How many students will be selected for the programme per year? Up to a maximum of 20 students. What is the language of instruction? English. What are the English language requirements? Applicants who are not native speakers of the English language must demonstrate English proficiency by obtaining acceptable results in an internationally recognized test (e.g., TOEFL, IELTS, APIEL, CPE). Proof of higher education in English or of residence in an English-speaking country for a reasonable length of time may also be acceptable upon the decision of the Admissions Committee. Language skills may also be evaluated during the personal interviews of selected candidates, see » Application &amp; Enrolment. Are there German language requirements? There are no German language requirements. However, a German course will be offered to students of the ECN Programme. Is there an age limit for the application? The applicants' age should not exceed 26 years upon enrolment. Exceptions are possible only under particular circumstances, upon the decision of the Admissions Committee. Are there tuition fees? Yes, 114 Euro per semester. Where can I find the application forms? There are no official application forms, please send the required documents in paper form by mail as listed under » Application &amp; Enrolment To whom should I submit my application documents? Prof. Dr. Inga D. Neumann ECN-Programme University of Regensburg Germany Do I have to submit original documents for the application? Copies are sufficient, however, at the enrolment, original documents are necessary. Where can I find the examination regulations (Prüfungsordnung)? See » Application &amp; Enrolment Is the ECN Programme officially registered? The ECN Programme is a registered member of the Network of European Neuroscience Schools (NENS), see: Federation of European Neuroscience Societies. The NENS was founded in 2003 and represents over 130 european graduate schools and programmes.  Membership of NENS helps to ensure high quality standards across programmes and also provides a number of benefits for students within registered programmes including training stipends and participation in annual meetings. How can I organize housing, visa application, bank account, health insurance and immigration? After acceptance to the ECN Programme, you will receive all necessary information about registration at the University of Regensburg, housing, visa application, bank account, health insurance and immigration. Please contact the student counsellor for any further questions: elli.wunderlich@verwaltung.uni-regensburg.de page up     home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/impr.html</field>
<field name="title">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/impr.html</field>
<field name="content">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   Imprint you are here: Home » Contact » Imprint Imprint Diese Seite wurde erstellt von Anka Draganski (Klinik und Poliklinik für Neurologie). Bei Fragen bzw. Problemen bzgl. der technischen und optischen Gestaltung dieser Homepage wenden Sie sich bitte an : Webmaster Verantwortlich für den Inhalt dieser Seiten ist: Prof. Dr. Inga D. Neumann Molecular and Behavioural Neuroendocrinology Institute of Zoology University of Regensburg 93053 Regensburg Tel. +49 941 943 3055 Fax +49 941 943 3052 inga.neumann@biologie.uni-regensburg.de Bildnachweis: Bilder Hintergund (oben): I.Kleiter © Copyright Das Copyright aller hier veröffentlichten Texte, Bilder oder Logos liegt bei den Organisatoren des ECN oder (im Falle der Logos) beim jeweiligem Besitzer! Bevor sie Grafiken oder Texte von unseren Seiten kopieren, wenden Sie sich bitte an: inga.neumann@biologie.uni-regensburg.de Alle hier verwendeten Namen, Begriffe, Zeichen und Grafiken können Marken- oder Warenzeichen im Besitze ihrer rechtlichen Eigentümer sein. Die Rechte aller erwähnten und benutzten Marken- und Warenzeichen liegen ausschließlich bei deren Besitzern. Haftungsausschluss Mit dem Urteil vom 12. Mai 1998 - 312 O 85/98 - "Haftung für Links" hat das Landgericht (LG) Hamburg entschieden, dass man durch die Erstellung eines Links die Inhalte der gelinkten Seite ggf. mit zu verantworten hat. Dies kann - so das Gericht - nur dadurch verhindert werden, dass man sich ausdrücklich von diesen Inhalten distanziert. Hiermit distanzieren wir uns ausdrücklich von allen Inhalten aller gelinkten Seiten auf dieser Homepage und machen uns die die Inhalte, die auf solchen Sites oder Quellen zugänglich sind, nicht zu eigen und schließen jede Haftung oder Gewährleistung in Bezug auf diese aus. Diese Erklärung gilt für alle verfügbaren Links auf dieser Homepage sowie evtl. vorhandene Linklisten oder Foren, die zur Zeit aktiv sind und / oder aktiv werden. Sollte sich auf diesen Seiten ein Link zu einer externen Seite befinden, auf der von dritter Seite rechtswidrige Inhalte verbreitet werden, so wird auf einen entsprechenden Hinweis hin der Link zu einer derartigen Seite entfernt.   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster 2011 © University of Regensburg  </field>
<field name="important">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   Imprint you are here: Home » Contact » Imprint Imprint Diese Seite wurde erstellt von Anka Draganski (Klinik und Poliklinik für Neurologie). Bei Fragen bzw. Problemen bzgl. der technischen und optischen Gestaltung dieser Homepage wenden Sie sich bitte an : Webmaster Verantwortlich für den Inhalt dieser Seiten ist: Prof. Dr. Inga D. Neumann Molecular and Behavioural Neuroendocrinology Institute of Zoology University of Regensburg 93053 Regensburg Tel. +49 941 943 3055 Fax +49 941 943 3052 inga.neumann@biologie.uni-regensburg.de Bildnachweis: Bilder Hintergund (oben): I.Kleiter © Copyright Das Copyright aller hier veröffentlichten Texte, Bilder oder Logos liegt bei den Organisatoren des ECN oder (im Falle der Logos) beim jeweiligem Besitzer! Bevor sie Grafiken oder Texte von unseren Seiten kopieren, wenden Sie sich bitte an: inga.neumann@biologie.uni-regensburg.de Alle hier verwendeten Namen, Begriffe, Zeichen und Grafiken können Marken- oder Warenzeichen im Besitze ihrer rechtlichen Eigentümer sein. Die Rechte aller erwähnten und benutzten Marken- und Warenzeichen liegen ausschließlich bei deren Besitzern. Haftungsausschluss Mit dem Urteil vom 12. Mai 1998 - 312 O 85/98 - "Haftung für Links" hat das Landgericht (LG) Hamburg entschieden, dass man durch die Erstellung eines Links die Inhalte der gelinkten Seite ggf. mit zu verantworten hat. Dies kann - so das Gericht - nur dadurch verhindert werden, dass man sich ausdrücklich von diesen Inhalten distanziert. Hiermit distanzieren wir uns ausdrücklich von allen Inhalten aller gelinkten Seiten auf dieser Homepage und machen uns die die Inhalte, die auf solchen Sites oder Quellen zugänglich sind, nicht zu eigen und schließen jede Haftung oder Gewährleistung in Bezug auf diese aus. Diese Erklärung gilt für alle verfügbaren Links auf dieser Homepage sowie evtl. vorhandene Linklisten oder Foren, die zur Zeit aktiv sind und / oder aktiv werden. Sollte sich auf diesen Seiten ein Link zu einer externen Seite befinden, auf der von dritter Seite rechtswidrige Inhalte verbreitet werden, so wird auf einen entsprechenden Hinweis hin der Link zu einer derartigen Seite entfernt.   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster 2011 © University of Regensburg  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/news.html</field>
<field name="title">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/news.html</field>
<field name="content">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   What is ECN? Programme Committee Our Faculty Our Students News News Archive you are here: Home » About ECN » News News February 2012 ECN VI Weekend Seminar by Annemarie Wolff read report November 2011 Poster Award as a co-author for the ECN student Natalie Izurieta at 19th Conference of the German Sleep Society (DGSM) in Mannheim. view the poster September 26, 2011 Study Programme 2011-2013 is online now  Download Programme 2011-2013 September 19, 2011 9th G?ttingen Meeting of the German Neuroscience Society, March 2011:  A Big Success, by Aileen Rose Lo read article September 19, 2011 Neurizons Conference May 2011, by Isabell Gehring read article August 11, 2011 Noble Lindau! A Report from the 61st Nobel Laureate Meeting in Lindau by Natalie Izurieta read article January 1, 2011 Elite study programme "Experimental and Clinical Neurosciences" (ECN) - a success story read article   Older articles can be found in our News Archive NEWS ARCHIVE Older articles can be found in our » News Archive   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
<field name="important">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   What is ECN? Programme Committee Our Faculty Our Students News News Archive you are here: Home » About ECN » News News February 2012 ECN VI Weekend Seminar by Annemarie Wolff read report November 2011 Poster Award as a co-author for the ECN student Natalie Izurieta at 19th Conference of the German Sleep Society (DGSM) in Mannheim. view the poster September 26, 2011 Study Programme 2011-2013 is online now  Download Programme 2011-2013 September 19, 2011 9th G?ttingen Meeting of the German Neuroscience Society, March 2011:  A Big Success, by Aileen Rose Lo read article September 19, 2011 Neurizons Conference May 2011, by Isabell Gehring read article August 11, 2011 Noble Lindau! A Report from the 61st Nobel Laureate Meeting in Lindau by Natalie Izurieta read article January 1, 2011 Elite study programme "Experimental and Clinical Neurosciences" (ECN) - a success story read article   Older articles can be found in our News Archive NEWS ARCHIVE Older articles can be found in our » News Archive   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/news110811.html</field>
<field name="title">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/news110811.html</field>
<field name="content">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   What is ECN? Programme Committee Our Faculty Our Students News News Archive you are here: Home » About ECN » News Noble Lindau! A Report from the 61st Nobel Laureate Meeting in Lindau August 11, 2011 Nobel Prize winner Robert Huber from Munich, Germany (4th from right, front row) and young researchers at 61st Nobel Laureate Meeting in Lindau. It was a great honor for me to participate in the ?61st Nobel Laureate Meeting? dedicated to physiology/medicine which took place in Lindau, from 26th June to 2nd July. This meeting provided an environment for exchanging knowledge, experiences and ideas between 23 Nobel laureates and 567 young researchers from 77 countries. The goals of the meeting ?educate - inspire - connect? were accomplished through several academic and social activities. I started the week with a ?science breakfast? on a boat at the Lindau harbor. Once on board Nobel laureate Peter Agre and young researchers started a panel discussion with the topic ?one world, one health?. Every morning I attended the plenary lectures, regarding different topics including neuroscience. Some Nobel laureates presented lectures on their scientific work. For instance, Erwin Neher gave a lecture on ?signals and signaling mechanisms in the central nervous system?. Other Nobel laureates chose a more informal style and were talking about personal experiences in their scienctific daily life work. Oliver Smithies showed us pages of his lab notebooks. He explained how he invented gel electrophoresis and built up a homemade PCR machine. Every day after lunch we had ?parallel discussions?. This means that we had the chance to meet with our favorite morning lecturer in a relative small group to discuss with them their research and life experiences. Nobel Prize winner Peter Agre from USA (right) and ECN / ENB student Natalie Izurieta. For the entire week, I had the opportunity to meet many young researchers from all around the world and very different scientific backgrounds. During the afternoon breaks I met with some new friends for visiting the Picasso exhibition in the city museum or swimming in the lake or simply walking around the city. Every evening we had a dinner event. On monday it was a ?get-together? dinner with live music. I was lucky of share the table with Harold Kroto, who won the Nobel prize for the ?buckyball? - the spherical form of C60. On tuesday evening, I was invited by the ?Elite Network of Bavaria? (ENB) for a dinner with the Nobel laureate Robert Huber together with his wife and other 14 young researchers from the ENB. We found out that Huber was born in Munich. During the Bavarian evening on thursday, he surprised everyone when he did his speech wearing a ?Tracht?, the traditional Bavarian costume. The Bavarian evening was organized by the ENB. They offered a Bavarian dinner buffet and traditional Bavarian music and dance. On friday evening, we enjoyed the concert of the ?Verbier Festival Chamber Orchestra? at the city theater. On our last day, we had a boat trip to Mainau, where the closing panel discussion on "global health" took place. After lunch, we attended the exhibition ?discoveries 2011: health?, which consisted of 18 pavilions with interactive exhibitions of key issues in health and medical research. On our way back to Lindau, we enjoyed live music on the boat. Back at the Lindau harbor, there was an emotional farewell. The last ?good bye? to those who were leaving the island that day. Fortunately, I could meet up with some that still remained until the next day. Winning a Nobel prize is a dream for many, but sometimes it seems to be just a dream. Meeting and interacting with the Nobel Laureates and hearing about their work and personal experiences helped me to see them as real people. Moreover, it was also wonderful to meet so many young researchers from all over the world. Interdisciplinary work is the basis of research nowadays and in this meeting I had the opportunity to exchange ideas and built networks for the future. The Nobel Laureates Meeting in Lindau was an invaluable opportunity of great inspiration for my personal and professional development. back to "News"   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
<field name="important">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   What is ECN? Programme Committee Our Faculty Our Students News News Archive you are here: Home » About ECN » News Noble Lindau! A Report from the 61st Nobel Laureate Meeting in Lindau August 11, 2011 Nobel Prize winner Robert Huber from Munich, Germany (4th from right, front row) and young researchers at 61st Nobel Laureate Meeting in Lindau. It was a great honor for me to participate in the ?61st Nobel Laureate Meeting? dedicated to physiology/medicine which took place in Lindau, from 26th June to 2nd July. This meeting provided an environment for exchanging knowledge, experiences and ideas between 23 Nobel laureates and 567 young researchers from 77 countries. The goals of the meeting ?educate - inspire - connect? were accomplished through several academic and social activities. I started the week with a ?science breakfast? on a boat at the Lindau harbor. Once on board Nobel laureate Peter Agre and young researchers started a panel discussion with the topic ?one world, one health?. Every morning I attended the plenary lectures, regarding different topics including neuroscience. Some Nobel laureates presented lectures on their scientific work. For instance, Erwin Neher gave a lecture on ?signals and signaling mechanisms in the central nervous system?. Other Nobel laureates chose a more informal style and were talking about personal experiences in their scienctific daily life work. Oliver Smithies showed us pages of his lab notebooks. He explained how he invented gel electrophoresis and built up a homemade PCR machine. Every day after lunch we had ?parallel discussions?. This means that we had the chance to meet with our favorite morning lecturer in a relative small group to discuss with them their research and life experiences. Nobel Prize winner Peter Agre from USA (right) and ECN / ENB student Natalie Izurieta. For the entire week, I had the opportunity to meet many young researchers from all around the world and very different scientific backgrounds. During the afternoon breaks I met with some new friends for visiting the Picasso exhibition in the city museum or swimming in the lake or simply walking around the city. Every evening we had a dinner event. On monday it was a ?get-together? dinner with live music. I was lucky of share the table with Harold Kroto, who won the Nobel prize for the ?buckyball? - the spherical form of C60. On tuesday evening, I was invited by the ?Elite Network of Bavaria? (ENB) for a dinner with the Nobel laureate Robert Huber together with his wife and other 14 young researchers from the ENB. We found out that Huber was born in Munich. During the Bavarian evening on thursday, he surprised everyone when he did his speech wearing a ?Tracht?, the traditional Bavarian costume. The Bavarian evening was organized by the ENB. They offered a Bavarian dinner buffet and traditional Bavarian music and dance. On friday evening, we enjoyed the concert of the ?Verbier Festival Chamber Orchestra? at the city theater. On our last day, we had a boat trip to Mainau, where the closing panel discussion on "global health" took place. After lunch, we attended the exhibition ?discoveries 2011: health?, which consisted of 18 pavilions with interactive exhibitions of key issues in health and medical research. On our way back to Lindau, we enjoyed live music on the boat. Back at the Lindau harbor, there was an emotional farewell. The last ?good bye? to those who were leaving the island that day. Fortunately, I could meet up with some that still remained until the next day. Winning a Nobel prize is a dream for many, but sometimes it seems to be just a dream. Meeting and interacting with the Nobel Laureates and hearing about their work and personal experiences helped me to see them as real people. Moreover, it was also wonderful to meet so many young researchers from all over the world. Interdisciplinary work is the basis of research nowadays and in this meeting I had the opportunity to exchange ideas and built networks for the future. The Nobel Laureates Meeting in Lindau was an invaluable opportunity of great inspiration for my personal and professional development. back to "News"   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/pro_descr.html</field>
<field name="title">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/pro_descr.html</field>
<field name="content">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   Programme Features Lectures &amp; Courses Internships you are here: Home » Programme Description Programme Description Key Features of the International Master's Programme The University of Regensburg offers an International Master?s Programme in Experimental and Clinical Neurosciences Yearly admission of a maximum of 20 students after competitive selection procedures The curriculum is designed for outstanding students of biology, biochemistry, medicine or psychology with a bachelor degree, or equivalent, from German or foreign universities Duration of the programme: 3 semesters (2 semesters coursework and 6 months for a scientific project to acquire the Master of Science [in Neuroscience] degree) Interdisciplinary and highly specialized teaching programme in experimental and clinical neurosciences Participation of national and international experts of the field in teaching courses Intensive supervision during seminars and in methodology and project internships Interdisciplinary research projects Funding possible for 8-week project internships and the Master?s thesis in selected laboratories abroad Active participation in a summer school and one scientific conference Students can apply for a structured PhD Programme in Regensburg after the ECN-Programme: Regensburg International Graduate School of LIfe Sciences (RIgeL) The ECN Programme is a registered member of the Network of European Neuroscience Schools (NENS): Federation of European Neuroscience Societies. The NENS was founded in 2003 and represents over 130 european graduate schools and programmes.  Membership of NENS helps to ensure high quality standards across programmes and also provides a number of benefits for students within registered programmes including training stipends and participation in annual meetings. Deadlines for application Early application deadline and early selection: January 31, 2012 Late application deadline and second selection: March 15, 2012 Note: We give priority to those students who apply before January 31!   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
<field name="important">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   Programme Features Lectures &amp; Courses Internships you are here: Home » Programme Description Programme Description Key Features of the International Master's Programme The University of Regensburg offers an International Master?s Programme in Experimental and Clinical Neurosciences Yearly admission of a maximum of 20 students after competitive selection procedures The curriculum is designed for outstanding students of biology, biochemistry, medicine or psychology with a bachelor degree, or equivalent, from German or foreign universities Duration of the programme: 3 semesters (2 semesters coursework and 6 months for a scientific project to acquire the Master of Science [in Neuroscience] degree) Interdisciplinary and highly specialized teaching programme in experimental and clinical neurosciences Participation of national and international experts of the field in teaching courses Intensive supervision during seminars and in methodology and project internships Interdisciplinary research projects Funding possible for 8-week project internships and the Master?s thesis in selected laboratories abroad Active participation in a summer school and one scientific conference Students can apply for a structured PhD Programme in Regensburg after the ECN-Programme: Regensburg International Graduate School of LIfe Sciences (RIgeL) The ECN Programme is a registered member of the Network of European Neuroscience Schools (NENS): Federation of European Neuroscience Societies. The NENS was founded in 2003 and represents over 130 european graduate schools and programmes.  Membership of NENS helps to ensure high quality standards across programmes and also provides a number of benefits for students within registered programmes including training stipends and participation in annual meetings. Deadlines for application Early application deadline and early selection: January 31, 2012 Late application deadline and second selection: March 15, 2012 Note: We give priority to those students who apply before January 31!   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/reqdocs.html</field>
<field name="title">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/reqdocs.html</field>
<field name="content">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   Application &amp; Enrolment Required Documents Tuition Fees &amp; Costs of living FAQs you are here: Home » Who Should Attend? » Required Documents Required Documents Please send the required documents listed below: Application form - only required for non-German applicants Official Transcript / Record of Study: Detailed documentation of your academic coursework (list of courses attended, including grades and credits) Schoolleaving certificate Degrees: Certificates of relevant examinations (e.g., Bachelor or Master degree, Vordiplom, Physikum) Statement of Purpose: explanation of your intent to study Curriculum Vitae: including complete address, phone numbers and e-mail. Please enclose also a passport-sized photograph Financial Statement: explanation of how you plan to finance your studies (no proof of financial security is required at this time) Two Letters of Reference: Originally signed letters from two academic instructors including an evaluation of your academic experience, intellectual merit, and personality (in closed envelopes; preferably mailed to the coordination office directly) Proof of Proficiency in English: For German applicants the proof of a proficiency in english is included in the high-school certificate. Therefore, a language test is not necessary. Special remarks for non-German applicants: In addition to the documents listed above, international applicants have to hand in the following forms: Declaration of financial support Applicants from China, Vietnam and Mongolia: An APS certificate should be included to your application! For further information about the APS, please refer to your country of residence: China, Vietnam, Mongolia Applicants from Afghanistan, Cameroon, Georgia, Iran, Turkey, USA: Your documents (school leaving certificate and study certificates) will have to be checked by the Zeugnisanerkennungsstelle (office for recognition of academic certificates) in Munich. All documents must be submitted in English or German! Certified copies of official documents are not mandatory at the time of submission. However, certified copies of all relevant documents (e.g., diploma, transcripts) must be submitted upon acceptance to the programme. Documents can be certified, for example, by the dean's or registrar's office of your university, a German embassy or consulate, a branch of the German Academic Exchange Service (DAAD), a Goethe Institute, or a public notary. page up     home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
<field name="important">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   Application &amp; Enrolment Required Documents Tuition Fees &amp; Costs of living FAQs you are here: Home » Who Should Attend? » Required Documents Required Documents Please send the required documents listed below: Application form - only required for non-German applicants Official Transcript / Record of Study: Detailed documentation of your academic coursework (list of courses attended, including grades and credits) Schoolleaving certificate Degrees: Certificates of relevant examinations (e.g., Bachelor or Master degree, Vordiplom, Physikum) Statement of Purpose: explanation of your intent to study Curriculum Vitae: including complete address, phone numbers and e-mail. Please enclose also a passport-sized photograph Financial Statement: explanation of how you plan to finance your studies (no proof of financial security is required at this time) Two Letters of Reference: Originally signed letters from two academic instructors including an evaluation of your academic experience, intellectual merit, and personality (in closed envelopes; preferably mailed to the coordination office directly) Proof of Proficiency in English: For German applicants the proof of a proficiency in english is included in the high-school certificate. Therefore, a language test is not necessary. Special remarks for non-German applicants: In addition to the documents listed above, international applicants have to hand in the following forms: Declaration of financial support Applicants from China, Vietnam and Mongolia: An APS certificate should be included to your application! For further information about the APS, please refer to your country of residence: China, Vietnam, Mongolia Applicants from Afghanistan, Cameroon, Georgia, Iran, Turkey, USA: Your documents (school leaving certificate and study certificates) will have to be checked by the Zeugnisanerkennungsstelle (office for recognition of academic certificates) in Munich. All documents must be submitted in English or German! Certified copies of official documents are not mandatory at the time of submission. However, certified copies of all relevant documents (e.g., diploma, transcripts) must be submitted upon acceptance to the programme. Documents can be certified, for example, by the dean's or registrar's office of your university, a German embassy or consulate, a branch of the German Academic Exchange Service (DAAD), a Goethe Institute, or a public notary. page up     home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/st2011.html</field>
<field name="title">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/st2011.html</field>
<field name="content">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   What is ECN? Programme Committee Our Faculty Our Students News News Archive you are here: Home » Our Students » 2011-2013 2011-2013 Bauer, Angelika Germany Cárdenas Conejo Zugey, Elizabeth Mexico Dubinski, Daniel Russia Geis, Sandra Germany Itzhacki, Jacob Panama Kavalaklio?lu, Tulya Turkey Kobor, Ines Germany Lange, Raphael Germany Langgartner, Dominik Germany Ohli, Jasmin Germany Pimentel, Vanessa USA Symeonidou, Evangelia-Regkina Greece Welz, Tobias Germany Wolff, Annemarie Canada     Bauer, Angelika City and country of origin: Regensburg, Germany Educational Background: Bachelor of Science in Biology, University of Regensburg Bachelor thesis: "Role of mGluR7 in mediating maternal care and aggression in mice". Department of Animal Physiology and Neurobiology   Main scientific interests: Molecular and Cellular Neurosciences, in particular the molecular background of neurological disorders Neuroendocrinology Neuropharmacology : drugs, addiction and treatment of psychiatric disorders Future plans and objectives: Successfully finish the ECN programme Proceed to a PhD in a field of my scientific interests Constantly improve my technical skills and knowledge in science   page up   Cárdenas Conejo, Zugey Elizabeth City and Country of origin: Michoacán, México Educational background: 2004-2009 B.Sc in Biology, Bachelor Thesis on ?Descriptive study of the structural relationship between the neural lineage cells and  CD133 + cells in differentiated brain tumors?. 2001-2004 High School, Technical Study in ?Food technology and Biochemical Sciences?. Main scientific interests Brain tumors Stem Cells Signaling Pathways Regenerative Medicine Future Plans and objectives A successful graduation from the Clinical and Experimental Neurosciences Master Program, pursue with a PhD in the Cancer Stem Cell area. page up   Dubinski, Daniel City and country of origin: Moscow, Russian Federation Educational background: Medical studies, University of Regensburg Doctoral student, Department of Neurology, University of Regensburg International Master's Programme in Experimental and Clinical  Neurosciences Main scientific interests: Neurooncology (Tumor stemm cells, Tumorimmunology) Neurosurgery Neuropharmacology Neuroendocrinology Future plans and objectives: Finishing med-school, doctoral thesis and master thesis and starting a residency in Neurosurgery page up   Geis, Sandra City and country of origin: Schwandorf, Germany Educational background: B. Sc. in Biology at the Humboldt University of Berlin       Main scientific interests: Cognitive neuroscience Behavioural neuroscience Brain imaging techniques Psychiatric diseases Future plans and objectives: PhD in Neuroscience. page up   Itzhacki, Jacob City and country of origin: Panama Educational background: Doctor in Medicine, Facultad de Medicina, Universidad de Panama (2001-2008) Medical Internship (1st and 2nd cat), Ministerio de Salud, Panama (2008-2010)   Main scientific interests: Visual pathways Internal representation Philosophy of mind Identity Future plans and objectives Continued education through a PhD in Neurosciences, in pursuit of means to pave the way to understanding thought, consciousness. page up   Kavalaklio?lu, Tulya City and country of origin: Ankara, Turkey Educational background: Bachelor of Science: Bilkent University, Molecular Biology and Genetics     Main scientific interests Molecular and Cellular basis of learning and memory Genetic and epigenetic regulation of neurodegenerative diseases Application of recent advances in stem cell and cancer fields to Neural Science Future plans and objectives Ph.D. in Neuroscience page up   Kobor, Ines City and country of origin: Munich, Germany Educational background: B.sc. Biology, University of Regensburg (2008-2011) International Master?s Programme: ? Experimental and Clinical Neuroscience? (2011-2013)     Main scientific interest: Behavioural Neuroscience Molecular Mechanisms of neurological diseases Future plans and objectives: PhD in Neuroscience page up   Lange, Raphael City and country of origin: Guben, Germany Educational background: B. Sc. in Biology, University of Regensburg Bachelor thesis: The Influence of Prenatal Stress on the Vulnerability to Chronic Psychosocial Stress and Experimental Colitis in Adult Male Wistar Rats   Main scientific interests: Neuroendocrinology Functional MRI Neurodegenerative and neuropsychiatric diseases Future plans and objectives: PhD in Neuroscience page up   Langgartner, Dominik City and country of origin: Burghausen, Germany Educational background: B. Sc. in Biology, University of Regensburg Bachelor Thesis: Chronic stress-induced body-side specific shift in the main corticosterone secretagogue ? from ACTH to Oxytocin?   Main scientific interests Neuroendocrinology Neurodegenerative diseases Developmental neuroscience Future plans and objectives Complete the ECN Master?s Programme successfully Gain more knowledge and experience concerning neuro-scientific methods and techniques PhD in Neuroscience page up   Ohli, Jasmin City and country of origin: Altötting, Germany Educational background: Bachelor of Science in Biology at University of Regensburg     Main scientific interests: Neurodegenerative diseases Neuropharmacology Molecular and Behavioural Neuroendocrinology Futur plans and objectives: PhD in Neuroscience page up   Pimentel, Vanessa City and country of origin: Tampa, Florida: USA Educational background: Immunology, Developmental biology; Bachelor of Science in Biology from the University of South Florida     Main scientific interests: Neuropharmacology Behavioural neuroscience Osteopathic and Traditional Chinese medicine Futur plans and objectives Ph.D in Neuroscience and Doctor of Osteopathic medicine page up   Symeonidou, Evangelia-Regkina City and country of origin: Serres, Greece Educational background: B.Sc. in Biology, University of Regensburg Bachelor Thesis: ?Examination of Neuronal Mechanisms of Non-Declarative Memory with EEG in Humans?. Patient care traineeship at the neurosurgery department at the Clinical Centre of the University of Regensburg Main scientific interests: Memory formation Cognitive Neuroscience Neurodegenerative diseases Psychiatric diseases Future plans and objectives: Expand my knowledge in the field of Neuroscience during the ECN master?s program. Research internships in the fields of my interest. Pursue a PhD and career in Neuroscience. page up   Welz, Tobias City and country of origin: Regensburg, Germany Educational background: B.Sc. in Biology, University of Regensburg Bachelor thesis: Protein synthesis in the PVN as underlying mechanism for Oxytocin-induced anxiolysis     Main scientific interests: Molecular Neuroscience Neuropharmacology Neurodegenerative / Neurological diseases   Future plans and objectives After finishing the ECN I would like to start my PhD in Molecular Neuroscience. Afterwards the combination of both Molecular and Clinical Neuroscience or Neuropharmacology  are the most interesting research fields for me. page up   Wolff, Annemarie City and country of origin: Ottawa, Canada Educational background: Psychology/Neuroscience       Main scientific interests: Neurodegenerative and Psychiatric illnesses   Future plans and objectives Once I have completed my Master?s degree, I intend on pursuing a Ph.D. page up   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
<field name="important">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   What is ECN? Programme Committee Our Faculty Our Students News News Archive you are here: Home » Our Students » 2011-2013 2011-2013 Bauer, Angelika Germany Cárdenas Conejo Zugey, Elizabeth Mexico Dubinski, Daniel Russia Geis, Sandra Germany Itzhacki, Jacob Panama Kavalaklio?lu, Tulya Turkey Kobor, Ines Germany Lange, Raphael Germany Langgartner, Dominik Germany Ohli, Jasmin Germany Pimentel, Vanessa USA Symeonidou, Evangelia-Regkina Greece Welz, Tobias Germany Wolff, Annemarie Canada     Bauer, Angelika City and country of origin: Regensburg, Germany Educational Background: Bachelor of Science in Biology, University of Regensburg Bachelor thesis: "Role of mGluR7 in mediating maternal care and aggression in mice". Department of Animal Physiology and Neurobiology   Main scientific interests: Molecular and Cellular Neurosciences, in particular the molecular background of neurological disorders Neuroendocrinology Neuropharmacology : drugs, addiction and treatment of psychiatric disorders Future plans and objectives: Successfully finish the ECN programme Proceed to a PhD in a field of my scientific interests Constantly improve my technical skills and knowledge in science   page up   Cárdenas Conejo, Zugey Elizabeth City and Country of origin: Michoacán, México Educational background: 2004-2009 B.Sc in Biology, Bachelor Thesis on ?Descriptive study of the structural relationship between the neural lineage cells and  CD133 + cells in differentiated brain tumors?. 2001-2004 High School, Technical Study in ?Food technology and Biochemical Sciences?. Main scientific interests Brain tumors Stem Cells Signaling Pathways Regenerative Medicine Future Plans and objectives A successful graduation from the Clinical and Experimental Neurosciences Master Program, pursue with a PhD in the Cancer Stem Cell area. page up   Dubinski, Daniel City and country of origin: Moscow, Russian Federation Educational background: Medical studies, University of Regensburg Doctoral student, Department of Neurology, University of Regensburg International Master's Programme in Experimental and Clinical  Neurosciences Main scientific interests: Neurooncology (Tumor stemm cells, Tumorimmunology) Neurosurgery Neuropharmacology Neuroendocrinology Future plans and objectives: Finishing med-school, doctoral thesis and master thesis and starting a residency in Neurosurgery page up   Geis, Sandra City and country of origin: Schwandorf, Germany Educational background: B. Sc. in Biology at the Humboldt University of Berlin       Main scientific interests: Cognitive neuroscience Behavioural neuroscience Brain imaging techniques Psychiatric diseases Future plans and objectives: PhD in Neuroscience. page up   Itzhacki, Jacob City and country of origin: Panama Educational background: Doctor in Medicine, Facultad de Medicina, Universidad de Panama (2001-2008) Medical Internship (1st and 2nd cat), Ministerio de Salud, Panama (2008-2010)   Main scientific interests: Visual pathways Internal representation Philosophy of mind Identity Future plans and objectives Continued education through a PhD in Neurosciences, in pursuit of means to pave the way to understanding thought, consciousness. page up   Kavalaklio?lu, Tulya City and country of origin: Ankara, Turkey Educational background: Bachelor of Science: Bilkent University, Molecular Biology and Genetics     Main scientific interests Molecular and Cellular basis of learning and memory Genetic and epigenetic regulation of neurodegenerative diseases Application of recent advances in stem cell and cancer fields to Neural Science Future plans and objectives Ph.D. in Neuroscience page up   Kobor, Ines City and country of origin: Munich, Germany Educational background: B.sc. Biology, University of Regensburg (2008-2011) International Master?s Programme: ? Experimental and Clinical Neuroscience? (2011-2013)     Main scientific interest: Behavioural Neuroscience Molecular Mechanisms of neurological diseases Future plans and objectives: PhD in Neuroscience page up   Lange, Raphael City and country of origin: Guben, Germany Educational background: B. Sc. in Biology, University of Regensburg Bachelor thesis: The Influence of Prenatal Stress on the Vulnerability to Chronic Psychosocial Stress and Experimental Colitis in Adult Male Wistar Rats   Main scientific interests: Neuroendocrinology Functional MRI Neurodegenerative and neuropsychiatric diseases Future plans and objectives: PhD in Neuroscience page up   Langgartner, Dominik City and country of origin: Burghausen, Germany Educational background: B. Sc. in Biology, University of Regensburg Bachelor Thesis: Chronic stress-induced body-side specific shift in the main corticosterone secretagogue ? from ACTH to Oxytocin?   Main scientific interests Neuroendocrinology Neurodegenerative diseases Developmental neuroscience Future plans and objectives Complete the ECN Master?s Programme successfully Gain more knowledge and experience concerning neuro-scientific methods and techniques PhD in Neuroscience page up   Ohli, Jasmin City and country of origin: Altötting, Germany Educational background: Bachelor of Science in Biology at University of Regensburg     Main scientific interests: Neurodegenerative diseases Neuropharmacology Molecular and Behavioural Neuroendocrinology Futur plans and objectives: PhD in Neuroscience page up   Pimentel, Vanessa City and country of origin: Tampa, Florida: USA Educational background: Immunology, Developmental biology; Bachelor of Science in Biology from the University of South Florida     Main scientific interests: Neuropharmacology Behavioural neuroscience Osteopathic and Traditional Chinese medicine Futur plans and objectives Ph.D in Neuroscience and Doctor of Osteopathic medicine page up   Symeonidou, Evangelia-Regkina City and country of origin: Serres, Greece Educational background: B.Sc. in Biology, University of Regensburg Bachelor Thesis: ?Examination of Neuronal Mechanisms of Non-Declarative Memory with EEG in Humans?. Patient care traineeship at the neurosurgery department at the Clinical Centre of the University of Regensburg Main scientific interests: Memory formation Cognitive Neuroscience Neurodegenerative diseases Psychiatric diseases Future plans and objectives: Expand my knowledge in the field of Neuroscience during the ECN master?s program. Research internships in the fields of my interest. Pursue a PhD and career in Neuroscience. page up   Welz, Tobias City and country of origin: Regensburg, Germany Educational background: B.Sc. in Biology, University of Regensburg Bachelor thesis: Protein synthesis in the PVN as underlying mechanism for Oxytocin-induced anxiolysis     Main scientific interests: Molecular Neuroscience Neuropharmacology Neurodegenerative / Neurological diseases   Future plans and objectives After finishing the ECN I would like to start my PhD in Molecular Neuroscience. Afterwards the combination of both Molecular and Clinical Neuroscience or Neuropharmacology  are the most interesting research fields for me. page up   Wolff, Annemarie City and country of origin: Ottawa, Canada Educational background: Psychology/Neuroscience       Main scientific interests: Neurodegenerative and Psychiatric illnesses   Future plans and objectives Once I have completed my Master?s degree, I intend on pursuing a Ph.D. page up   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/tuition.html</field>
<field name="title">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/tuition.html</field>
<field name="content">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   Application &amp; Enrolment Required Documents Tuition Fees &amp; Costs of living FAQs you are here: Home » Who Should Attend? » Tuition Fees &amp; Costs of Living Tuition Fees &amp; Costs of Living Living Expenses: Living costs (including accommodation in a student dormitory and health insurance) in Regensburg range from Euro 600 to 1000 per month for a single person. Housing: Single rooms for students under 30 years of age are available in student dormitories administered by the Studentenwerk, University of Regensburg, with monthly rents starting at approximately Euro 150 and ranging up to Euro 250. A limited number of dormitory rooms are available through the program for accepted students. Housing request forms will be administered to all students in conjunction with the acceptance letter. The coordination office will, upon request, provide additional housing assistance for accepted students. Private housing is usually more expensive, but offers a wider range of options (e.g., flat-sharing). For detailed English-language information regarding both on- and off-campus housing possibilities in Regensburg, see the English Studentenwerk . Health Insurance: German health insurance is obligatory for all students who are not citizens of the European Union. Special public health insurance is available to all students under 30 years of age at low rates. This insurance covers the costs of normal medical treatment (including dental care) in Germany. The monthly payment is currently Euro 55,-. For more detailed information including a health insurance application form, see the English-language webpage of the Techniker Krankenkasse or visit the the English-language webpage of MAWISTA. Financial Aid / Scholarships : Students are advised to apply for financial support and/or scholarships through the appropriate granting institutions, such as their home country governments, German Academic Exchange Service DAAD or Alexander von Humbold Foundation.   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster 2011 © University of Regensburg  </field>
<field name="important">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   Application &amp; Enrolment Required Documents Tuition Fees &amp; Costs of living FAQs you are here: Home » Who Should Attend? » Tuition Fees &amp; Costs of Living Tuition Fees &amp; Costs of Living Living Expenses: Living costs (including accommodation in a student dormitory and health insurance) in Regensburg range from Euro 600 to 1000 per month for a single person. Housing: Single rooms for students under 30 years of age are available in student dormitories administered by the Studentenwerk, University of Regensburg, with monthly rents starting at approximately Euro 150 and ranging up to Euro 250. A limited number of dormitory rooms are available through the program for accepted students. Housing request forms will be administered to all students in conjunction with the acceptance letter. The coordination office will, upon request, provide additional housing assistance for accepted students. Private housing is usually more expensive, but offers a wider range of options (e.g., flat-sharing). For detailed English-language information regarding both on- and off-campus housing possibilities in Regensburg, see the English Studentenwerk . Health Insurance: German health insurance is obligatory for all students who are not citizens of the European Union. Special public health insurance is available to all students under 30 years of age at low rates. This insurance covers the costs of normal medical treatment (including dental care) in Germany. The monthly payment is currently Euro 55,-. For more detailed information including a health insurance application form, see the English-language webpage of the Techniker Krankenkasse or visit the the English-language webpage of MAWISTA. Financial Aid / Scholarships : Students are advised to apply for financial support and/or scholarships through the appropriate granting institutions, such as their home country governments, German Academic Exchange Service DAAD or Alexander von Humbold Foundation.   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster 2011 © University of Regensburg  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/who.html</field>
<field name="title">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_III/Zoologie/Elite/html/who.html</field>
<field name="content">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   Application &amp; Enrolment Required Documents Tuition Fees &amp; Costs of living FAQs you are here: Home » Application Who Should Attend? Applicants must hold a Bachelor degree, or equivalent, in biology, chemistry, medicine, psychology, or a closely related subject area. Also eligible to apply are students in the final year of their Bachelor, or equivalent, degree courses, provided that the degree will be conferred prior to the enrollment date within the MSc programme. Applicants who are not native speakers of the English language must demonstrate English proficiency by obtaining acceptable results in an internationally recognized test (e.g., TOEFL, IELTS, APIEL, CPE). Proof of higher education in English or a residence of reasonable length in an English-speaking country may also be acceptable upon the decision of the Admissions Committee. Language skills may also be evaluated during the personal interviews of selected candidates (see » Application &amp; Enrolment). page up     home | contact us | imprint | webmaster 2011 © University of Regensburg  </field>
<field name="important">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   Application &amp; Enrolment Required Documents Tuition Fees &amp; Costs of living FAQs you are here: Home » Application Who Should Attend? Applicants must hold a Bachelor degree, or equivalent, in biology, chemistry, medicine, psychology, or a closely related subject area. Also eligible to apply are students in the final year of their Bachelor, or equivalent, degree courses, provided that the degree will be conferred prior to the enrollment date within the MSc programme. Applicants who are not native speakers of the English language must demonstrate English proficiency by obtaining acceptable results in an internationally recognized test (e.g., TOEFL, IELTS, APIEL, CPE). Proof of higher education in English or a residence of reasonable length in an English-speaking country may also be acceptable upon the decision of the Admissions Committee. Language skills may also be evaluated during the personal interviews of selected candidates (see » Application &amp; Enrolment). page up     home | contact us | imprint | webmaster 2011 © University of Regensburg  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_IV/Pharmazie/PharmBio/dorn.html</field>
<field name="title">302 Found</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_IV/Pharmazie/PharmBio/dorn.html</field>
<field name="content">302 Found Found The document has moved here.</field>
<field name="important">302 Found Found The document has moved here.</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_IV/Pharmazie/PharmChem1/index.htm</field>
<field name="title">Lehrstuhl Pharmazeutische Chemie 1</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_IV/Pharmazie/PharmChem1/index.htm</field>
<field name="content">Lehrstuhl Pharmazeutische Chemie 1 Klicken Sie hier, falls die automatische Weiterleitung versagt.</field>
<field name="important">Lehrstuhl Pharmazeutische Chemie 1 Klicken Sie hier, falls die automatische Weiterleitung versagt.</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_IV/Pharmazie/buschauer/anreise_engl.htm</field>
<field name="title">How to reach us!</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_IV/Pharmazie/buschauer/anreise_engl.htm</field>
<field name="content">How to reach us! Institute of Pharmacy Students Emil-Fischer Grad.School GK 1910 MedChem DPhG GK 760 MedChem Contact Coworkers Open Positions Publications Research Report Directions Our research group is located in the building of the Faculty Chemistry and Pharmacy (see map) By car: From Nuremberg or Passau via A3: follow signs for Regensburg, take exit 'Klinikum/Universität' (A3) From Munich or Berlin via A 93: change to A3 at 'Autobahnkreuz Regensburg', direction Passau, then take 'Klinikum/Universität' (A3). (the university is located very close to A3; see map). By train: Arrival at Regensburg main station (Hauptbahnhof): - The university is located within 15-20 min walking distance (see map). - Taxi stand: in front of the station - Bus (Albertstraße, 2 min from station): take line 6 (direction Klinikum)   or line 11 (direction Burgweinting) to the University (bus stop 'Mensa'),   then follow the signs to the Chemistry/Pharmacy building (see map). By airplane: Arrival at Frankfurt/Main Int. Airport: take the train to Regensburg main station (Hauptbahnhof; see above). Trains for Regensburg are leaving every hour. Arrival at Munich Airport: take the bus shuttle to Freising main station, then take the train to Regensburg. Trains for Regensburg are leaving from Freising every hour. As an alternative you can book the Airport Shuttle. Arrival at Nuremberg Airport: take the subway or the bus to Nuremberg main station (10-15 min), then take the train to Regensburg (about 1 hour). Trains for Regensburg are leaving from Nuremberg every hour. Maps Regensburg/Overview University/Campus Last Update: 17/8/2007 Impressum</field>
<field name="important">How to reach us! Institute of Pharmacy Students Emil-Fischer Grad.School GK 1910 MedChem DPhG GK 760 MedChem Contact Coworkers Open Positions Publications Research Report Directions Our research group is located in the building of the Faculty Chemistry and Pharmacy (see map) By car: From Nuremberg or Passau via A3: follow signs for Regensburg, take exit 'Klinikum/Universität' (A3) From Munich or Berlin via A 93: change to A3 at 'Autobahnkreuz Regensburg', direction Passau, then take 'Klinikum/Universität' (A3). (the university is located very close to A3; see map). By train: Arrival at Regensburg main station (Hauptbahnhof): - The university is located within 15-20 min walking distance (see map). - Taxi stand: in front of the station - Bus (Albertstraße, 2 min from station): take line 6 (direction Klinikum)   or line 11 (direction Burgweinting) to the University (bus stop 'Mensa'),   then follow the signs to the Chemistry/Pharmacy building (see map). By airplane: Arrival at Frankfurt/Main Int. Airport: take the train to Regensburg main station (Hauptbahnhof; see above). Trains for Regensburg are leaving every hour. Arrival at Munich Airport: take the bus shuttle to Freising main station, then take the train to Regensburg. Trains for Regensburg are leaving from Freising every hour. As an alternative you can book the Airport Shuttle. Arrival at Nuremberg Airport: take the subway or the bus to Nuremberg main station (10-15 min), then take the train to Regensburg (about 1 hour). Trains for Regensburg are leaving from Nuremberg every hour. Maps Regensburg/Overview University/Campus Last Update: 17/8/2007 Impressum</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_IV/Pharmazie/buschauer/coworker/antoni.html</field>
<field name="title">Frauke Antoni</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_IV/Pharmazie/buschauer/coworker/antoni.html</field>
<field name="content">Frauke Antoni Department Prof. Dr. Armin Buschauer DPhG GK 1910 MedChem GK 760 MedChem Contact Coworkers Open Positions Publications Research Report Teaching Links Frauke Antoni PhD Student Research project tbd Tel: +49 941 943-4696 Fax: +49 941 943-4820 E-Mail to Frauke Antoni Last Update: 10/29/2008 Impressum</field>
<field name="important">Frauke Antoni Department Prof. Dr. Armin Buschauer DPhG GK 1910 MedChem GK 760 MedChem Contact Coworkers Open Positions Publications Research Report Teaching Links Frauke Antoni PhD Student Research project tbd Tel: +49 941 943-4696 Fax: +49 941 943-4820 E-Mail to Frauke Antoni Last Update: 10/29/2008 Impressum</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_IV/Pharmazie/buschauer/coworker/bauer.html</field>
<field name="title">Stefanie Bauer</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_IV/Pharmazie/buschauer/coworker/bauer.html</field>
<field name="content">Stefanie Bauer Department Prof. Dr. Armin Buschauer DPhG GK 1910 MedChem GK 760 MedChem Contact Coworkers Open Positions Publications Research Report Teaching Links Stefanie Bauer PhD Student    Research project Modulation von ABC-Transportern zur Überwindung der Bluthirnschranke und der Chemoresistenz von Tumoren Tel: +49 941 943-4797 Fax: +49 941 943-4820 E-Mail to Stefanie Bauer Last Update: 10/29/2008 Impressum</field>
<field name="important">Stefanie Bauer Department Prof. Dr. Armin Buschauer DPhG GK 1910 MedChem GK 760 MedChem Contact Coworkers Open Positions Publications Research Report Teaching Links Stefanie Bauer PhD Student    Research project Modulation von ABC-Transportern zur Überwindung der Bluthirnschranke und der Chemoresistenz von Tumoren Tel: +49 941 943-4797 Fax: +49 941 943-4820 E-Mail to Stefanie Bauer Last Update: 10/29/2008 Impressum</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_IV/Pharmazie/buschauer/coworker/baumeister.html</field>
<field name="title">Paul Baumeister</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_IV/Pharmazie/buschauer/coworker/baumeister.html</field>
<field name="content">Paul Baumeister Department Prof. Dr. Armin Buschauer DPhG GK 1910 MedChem GK 760 MedChem Contact Coworkers Open Positions Publications Research Report Teaching Links Paul Baumeister PhD Student   Research project -Synthesis and Pharmacological Characterization of Human H4 Receptor Ligands -Radioligands as Pharmacological Tools for Histamine and NPY Y2 Receptors Tel: +49 941 943-4712 Fax: +49 941 943-4820 E-Mail to Paul Baumeister Last Update: 10/29/2008 Impressum</field>
<field name="important">Paul Baumeister Department Prof. Dr. Armin Buschauer DPhG GK 1910 MedChem GK 760 MedChem Contact Coworkers Open Positions Publications Research Report Teaching Links Paul Baumeister PhD Student   Research project -Synthesis and Pharmacological Characterization of Human H4 Receptor Ligands -Radioligands as Pharmacological Tools for Histamine and NPY Y2 Receptors Tel: +49 941 943-4712 Fax: +49 941 943-4820 E-Mail to Paul Baumeister Last Update: 10/29/2008 Impressum</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_IV/Pharmazie/buschauer/coworker/beer-kroen.html</field>
<field name="title">Maria Beer-Kroen</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_IV/Pharmazie/buschauer/coworker/beer-kroen.html</field>
<field name="content">Maria Beer-Kroen Department Prof. Dr. Armin Buschauer DPhG GK 1910 MedChem GK 760 MedChem Contact Coworkers Open Positions Publications Research Report Teaching Links Maria Beer-Krön Technician Tel: +49 941 943-4703 Fax: +49 941 943-4820 E-Mail to Maria Beer-Krön Last Update: 10/29/2008 Impressum</field>
<field name="important">Maria Beer-Kroen Department Prof. Dr. Armin Buschauer DPhG GK 1910 MedChem GK 760 MedChem Contact Coworkers Open Positions Publications Research Report Teaching Links Maria Beer-Krön Technician Tel: +49 941 943-4703 Fax: +49 941 943-4820 E-Mail to Maria Beer-Krön Last Update: 10/29/2008 Impressum</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_IV/Pharmazie/buschauer/coworker/bernhardt.htm</field>
<field name="title">Prof. Dr. Günther Bernhardt</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_IV/Pharmazie/buschauer/coworker/bernhardt.htm</field>
<field name="content">Prof. Dr. Günther Bernhardt Department Prof. Dr. Armin Buschauer DPhG IQN-MC GK MedChem Contact Coworkers Open Positions Publications Research Report Teaching Links Prof. Dr. Günther Bernhardt Akademischer Oberrat Tel: +49 941 943-4822 Fax: +49 941 943-4820 E-Mail to Günther Bernhardt Fields of Research: Biochemical / pharmacological exploration of neuropeptide Y / histamine receptor ligands and of potential anti-cancer agents Development and application of luminescence-based methods for the determination of the affinity and activity of GPCR ligands In vivo imaging (fluorescence, bioluminescence, PET) Analytical and biopharmaceutical investigations (HPLC, CE, AAS) Heterologous expression, renaturation, purification and enzymological characterization of human hyaluronidases Investigation of the effect of hyaluronidase and hyaluronan synthetase on tumorigenicity, growth and metastasis of human malignant tumors in nude mice Preclinical (in vitro / in vivo) studies on the treatment of primary and secondary brain tumors Preclinical investigations on hormone sensitive malignancies (especially mammary carcinoma, cancer of the prostate) Additional Research Interest: Medical occultism Recent Publications Last Update: 10/29/2008 Impressum</field>
<field name="important">Prof. Dr. Günther Bernhardt Department Prof. Dr. Armin Buschauer DPhG IQN-MC GK MedChem Contact Coworkers Open Positions Publications Research Report Teaching Links Prof. Dr. Günther Bernhardt Akademischer Oberrat Tel: +49 941 943-4822 Fax: +49 941 943-4820 E-Mail to Günther Bernhardt Fields of Research: Biochemical / pharmacological exploration of neuropeptide Y / histamine receptor ligands and of potential anti-cancer agents Development and application of luminescence-based methods for the determination of the affinity and activity of GPCR ligands In vivo imaging (fluorescence, bioluminescence, PET) Analytical and biopharmaceutical investigations (HPLC, CE, AAS) Heterologous expression, renaturation, purification and enzymological characterization of human hyaluronidases Investigation of the effect of hyaluronidase and hyaluronan synthetase on tumorigenicity, growth and metastasis of human malignant tumors in nude mice Preclinical (in vitro / in vivo) studies on the treatment of primary and secondary brain tumors Preclinical investigations on hormone sensitive malignancies (especially mammary carcinoma, cancer of the prostate) Additional Research Interest: Medical occultism Recent Publications Last Update: 10/29/2008 Impressum</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_IV/Pharmazie/buschauer/coworker/biselli.html</field>
<field name="title">Sabrina Biselli</field>
<field name="url">http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/nat_Fak_IV/Pharmazie/buschauer/coworker/biselli.html</field>
<field name="content">Sabrina Biselli Department Prof. Dr. Armin Buschauer DPhG GK 1910 MedChem GK 760 MedChem Contact Coworkers Open Positions Publications Research Report Teaching Links Sabrina Biselli PhD Student Research project Synthese und pharmakologische Charakterisierung subtypselektiver Histamin-H2-Rezeptorliganden Tel: +49 941 943-4816 Fax: +49 941 943-4820 E-Mail to Sabrina Biselli Last Update: 10/29/2008 Impressum</field>
<field name="important">Sabrina Biselli Department Prof. Dr. Armin Buschauer DPhG GK 1910 MedChem GK 760 MedChem Contact Coworkers Open Positions Publications Research Report Teaching Links Sabrina Biselli PhD Student Research project Synthese und pharmakologische Charakterisierung subtypselektiver Histamin-H2-Rezeptorliganden Tel: +49 941 943-4816 Fax: +49 941 943-4820 E-Mail to Sabrina Biselli Last Update: 10/29/2008 Impressum</field>
</doc>

</add>