<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<add>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/prettl/mitarbeiter/mitarbeiter.html</field>
<field name="title"></field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/prettl/mitarbeiter/mitarbeiter.html</field>
<field name="content">Ehemalige Mitarbeiter der Arbeitsgruppe Prettl In den E-mail Adressen ist ++ durch @ zu ersetzen Please replace in the e-mail-addresses ++ by @ Alshuth, Moritz Moritz.Alshuth++infineon.com Arendt, Brigitte Arendt.Brigitte++infineon.com Dr. Arenholz, Enno enno.arenholz++voestalpine.com Dr. Bel'kov, Vasily bel++epi.ioffe.ru Prof. Dr. Böhm, Willi Dr. Brandl, Alberet albert.brandl++onlinehome.de Prof. Dr. Daiminger, Franz franz.daiminger++fh.deggendorf.de Daiminger, Elke++ franz.daiminger++fh.deggendorf.de Dr. Danilov, Sergey sergey.danilov++physik.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Diener, Joachim jdiener++ph.tum.de Dr. Eberle, Werner werner++movimiento.de Ermer, Christof ChristofErmer++gmx.de Fowley, Ciaran    Prof. Dr. Ganichev, Sergey     sergey.ganichev++physik.uni-regensburg.de Geissler, Christian Giglberger, Stephan stephan.giglberger-qt-physik.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Gleim, Thomas Dr. Grebler, Jürgen juergen.grebler++siemens.com Gruener, Marcus (1) marcus.gruener++web.de Gruener, Marcus (2) Hecht, Thomas tom.hecht++gms.de Dr. Heisel, Wilfried Dr. Hirschinger, Jürgen juergen.hirschinger++gdm.de Dr. Huber, Wolfgang wolfgang-dr.huber++osram-os.com Humbs, Anton Anton.Humbs++physik.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Huggard, Peter G. p.g.huggard++rl.ac.uk Dr. Jungwirt, Günter guenter.jungwirt++roche.com Dr. Kalbeck, Alexander alexander.kalbeck++kalbeck.de - alexander.kalbeck++siemens.com Dr. Kalz, Franz-Peter Dr. Ketterl, Hermann hermann.ketterl++siemens.com Kiermaier, Josef josef.kiermaier++physik.uni-regensburg.de Kilger, Thomas Dr. Klimenta, Harald klimenta++attac.de - hww++gmx.de Dr. Knorr, Christine Kroeninger, Werner Kropf, Rainer Dr. Lohner, Andrea andrea.lohner ++ t-online.de MacMathuna, Diarmaid diarmaid.mac++agtel.ie Dr. Margull, Uli margull++margull.de Mayerhofer, Boris Boris.Mayerhofer++grammer.com Dr. Novák, Vit novakvit++fzu.cz Olteanu, Matei Raab, Wolfgang Dr. Reitebuch, Oliver Dr. Ritzer, Alphons ritzer++mucl.de ritzer++mucl.de Schilz, Arno arno.h.schilz ++t-online.de - artas++csi.com Dr. Schneider, Giselher Giselher.Schneider++bigfoot.com Dr. Schneider, Petra petra.schneider1++web.de Schnellbögl, Andreas andreas.schnellboegl++gmx.de Dr. Schowalter, Dieter dieter.schowalter++gmx.de Sollinger, Martin martin.sollinger++gmx.de Spangler, Josef Josef.Spangler++rz.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Tranitz, Peter peter.tranitz++physik.uni-regensburg.de Weber, Wolfgang wolfgang.weber++physik.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Weispfenning, Martin Dr. Wimmer, Christian christian.wimmer++dlr.de Dr. Zepezauer, Edmund edmund.zepezauer++eads.com Dr. Zeuner, Stephan szeuner++szeuner.de Dr. Ziemann, Elke eziemann++genion.de (zum Anfang) File translated from TEX by TTH, version 3.05. On 10 Jul 2007, 16:23.</field>
<field name="important">Ehemalige Mitarbeiter der Arbeitsgruppe Prettl In den E-mail Adressen ist ++ durch @ zu ersetzen Please replace in the e-mail-addresses ++ by @ Alshuth, Moritz Moritz.Alshuth++infineon.com Arendt, Brigitte Arendt.Brigitte++infineon.com Dr. Arenholz, Enno enno.arenholz++voestalpine.com Dr. Bel'kov, Vasily bel++epi.ioffe.ru Prof. Dr. Böhm, Willi Dr. Brandl, Alberet albert.brandl++onlinehome.de Prof. Dr. Daiminger, Franz franz.daiminger++fh.deggendorf.de Daiminger, Elke++ franz.daiminger++fh.deggendorf.de Dr. Danilov, Sergey sergey.danilov++physik.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Diener, Joachim jdiener++ph.tum.de Dr. Eberle, Werner werner++movimiento.de Ermer, Christof ChristofErmer++gmx.de Fowley, Ciaran    Prof. Dr. Ganichev, Sergey     sergey.ganichev++physik.uni-regensburg.de Geissler, Christian Giglberger, Stephan stephan.giglberger-qt-physik.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Gleim, Thomas Dr. Grebler, Jürgen juergen.grebler++siemens.com Gruener, Marcus (1) marcus.gruener++web.de Gruener, Marcus (2) Hecht, Thomas tom.hecht++gms.de Dr. Heisel, Wilfried Dr. Hirschinger, Jürgen juergen.hirschinger++gdm.de Dr. Huber, Wolfgang wolfgang-dr.huber++osram-os.com Humbs, Anton Anton.Humbs++physik.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Huggard, Peter G. p.g.huggard++rl.ac.uk Dr. Jungwirt, Günter guenter.jungwirt++roche.com Dr. Kalbeck, Alexander alexander.kalbeck++kalbeck.de - alexander.kalbeck++siemens.com Dr. Kalz, Franz-Peter Dr. Ketterl, Hermann hermann.ketterl++siemens.com Kiermaier, Josef josef.kiermaier++physik.uni-regensburg.de Kilger, Thomas Dr. Klimenta, Harald klimenta++attac.de - hww++gmx.de Dr. Knorr, Christine Kroeninger, Werner Kropf, Rainer Dr. Lohner, Andrea andrea.lohner ++ t-online.de MacMathuna, Diarmaid diarmaid.mac++agtel.ie Dr. Margull, Uli margull++margull.de Mayerhofer, Boris Boris.Mayerhofer++grammer.com Dr. Novák, Vit novakvit++fzu.cz Olteanu, Matei Raab, Wolfgang Dr. Reitebuch, Oliver Dr. Ritzer, Alphons ritzer++mucl.de ritzer++mucl.de Schilz, Arno arno.h.schilz ++t-online.de - artas++csi.com Dr. Schneider, Giselher Giselher.Schneider++bigfoot.com Dr. Schneider, Petra petra.schneider1++web.de Schnellbögl, Andreas andreas.schnellboegl++gmx.de Dr. Schowalter, Dieter dieter.schowalter++gmx.de Sollinger, Martin martin.sollinger++gmx.de Spangler, Josef Josef.Spangler++rz.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Tranitz, Peter peter.tranitz++physik.uni-regensburg.de Weber, Wolfgang wolfgang.weber++physik.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Weispfenning, Martin Dr. Wimmer, Christian christian.wimmer++dlr.de Dr. Zepezauer, Edmund edmund.zepezauer++eads.com Dr. Zeuner, Stephan szeuner++szeuner.de Dr. Ziemann, Elke eziemann++genion.de (zum Anfang) File translated from TEX by TTH, version 3.05. On 10 Jul 2007, 16:23.</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/profs_e.phtml</field>
<field name="title">Physics ? Research ? Faculty</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/profs_e.phtml</field>
<field name="content">Physics ? Research ? Faculty Physics ? Research ? Faculty Physics Professors in Regensburg Christian Back Magnetism, magneto-electronics Gunnar Bali Lattice QCD and Hadron Physics Dominique Bougeard   Low Dimensional Semiconductor Systems Vladimir Braun Quantum field theory and quantum chromodynamics Jaroslav Fabian Spintronics Sergey Ganichev Terahertz physics Franz J. Giessibl Atomic Force Microscopy Anja Göhring NWT - Natural science and technics Milena Grifoni Quantum transport and dissipation Rupert Huber Ultrafast quantum physics and photonics John Lupton Organic semiconductors, optical nanostructures Ingo Morgenstern Superconductivity, optimization of industrial processes Thomas Niehaus Light Matter Interaction in Nanostructures Dirk Pleiter Lattice quantum chromodynamics and Supercomputing Klaus Richter Complex quantum systems Jascha Repp Scanning tunneling microscopy Karsten Rincke Didactics of Physics Andreas Schäfer Quantum chromodynamics and hadron physics John Schliemann Spin dynamics in semiconductor nanostructures, spintronics Christian Schüller Optical spectroscopy on semiconductor quantum structures Christoph Strunk Mesoscopic systems Dieter Weiss Semiconducting nanostructures Tilo Wettig Lattice quantum chromodynamics, QCD on a Chip Josef Zweck Electron microscopy Heisenberg-Stipendiary Falk Bruckmann Lattice quantum chromodynamics and solitons Emmy Noether Research Groups Andreas Hüttel Carbon Nanotube Transport and Nanomechanics Tobias Kramer Quantum dynamics in mesoscopic and atomic Systems Sofja Kovalevskaja Award Winner Pavel Buividovich ? Assistant Professors       ? Retired professors   Legal Notice Last modified: 12 th May, 2014 by Webmaster</field>
<field name="important">Physics ? Research ? Faculty Physics ? Research ? Faculty Physics Professors in Regensburg Christian Back Magnetism, magneto-electronics Gunnar Bali Lattice QCD and Hadron Physics Dominique Bougeard   Low Dimensional Semiconductor Systems Vladimir Braun Quantum field theory and quantum chromodynamics Jaroslav Fabian Spintronics Sergey Ganichev Terahertz physics Franz J. Giessibl Atomic Force Microscopy Anja Göhring NWT - Natural science and technics Milena Grifoni Quantum transport and dissipation Rupert Huber Ultrafast quantum physics and photonics John Lupton Organic semiconductors, optical nanostructures Ingo Morgenstern Superconductivity, optimization of industrial processes Thomas Niehaus Light Matter Interaction in Nanostructures Dirk Pleiter Lattice quantum chromodynamics and Supercomputing Klaus Richter Complex quantum systems Jascha Repp Scanning tunneling microscopy Karsten Rincke Didactics of Physics Andreas Schäfer Quantum chromodynamics and hadron physics John Schliemann Spin dynamics in semiconductor nanostructures, spintronics Christian Schüller Optical spectroscopy on semiconductor quantum structures Christoph Strunk Mesoscopic systems Dieter Weiss Semiconducting nanostructures Tilo Wettig Lattice quantum chromodynamics, QCD on a Chip Josef Zweck Electron microscopy Heisenberg-Stipendiary Falk Bruckmann Lattice quantum chromodynamics and solitons Emmy Noether Research Groups Andreas Hüttel Carbon Nanotube Transport and Nanomechanics Tobias Kramer Quantum dynamics in mesoscopic and atomic Systems Sofja Kovalevskaja Award Winner Pavel Buividovich ? Assistant Professors       ? Retired professors   Legal Notice Last modified: 12 th May, 2014 by Webmaster</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/repp/</field>
<field name="title">AG Repp - Research</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/repp/</field>
<field name="content">AG Repp - Research AG Repp - Research Atomic-Scale Science on Insulating Films Jascha Repp, Faculty of Physics, University of Regensburg   Research     People     Recent Results     Teaching     Publications     Join     Contact   Research The objective of our team is to study the physical and chemical properties of single adsorbates and adsorbate structures on the atomic length scale. The technique of choice is low-temperature scanning probe microscopy, primarily scanning tunneling microscopy (STM). The strength of the scanning probe techniques lies in their ability to analyze the structural environment of one particular defect or adsorbate on the atomic length scale and to probe the local properties of this individual, well-characterized structure. In the last years we were mainly interested in STM experiments on individual adsorbates on ultrathin insulating films. Ultrathin insulating films on metal substrates facilitate the use of the scanning tunneling microscope to study the electronic properties of single atoms and molecules, which are electronically decoupled from the metallic substrate. Most importantly, many physical and chemical properties are not only quantitatively but also qualitatively different on an insulating surface from those on a (semi-)conducting surface. Hence, it becomes of supreme importance to the scope of science, as it advances to the atomic length scale, to include insulating materials. New experimental possibilities which are to be examined comprise (meta-)stable charging processes of individual adsorbates and STM-induced chemistry of single molecules on insulators. Furthermore, these investigations shall open new research avenues in molecular electronics, as they combine the following two elements: the electronic decoupling of an adsorbate provided by the insulator and the ability of STM to analyze the structural environment of an adsorbed molecule. Our running scanning tunneling microscope works at a temperature of 5K under ultra-high vacuum conditions. A second machine is presently being built up that includes the possibility to measure forces on the atomic length scale. In the following years, a third apparatus is planned which will allow measurements in strong magnetic fields to additionally study magnetic properties. The group was established in March 2007 by the hiring of Jascha Repp on a Lichtenberg-professorship, funded by the Volkswagenstiftung.</field>
<field name="important">AG Repp - Research AG Repp - Research Atomic-Scale Science on Insulating Films Jascha Repp, Faculty of Physics, University of Regensburg   Research     People     Recent Results     Teaching     Publications     Join     Contact   Research The objective of our team is to study the physical and chemical properties of single adsorbates and adsorbate structures on the atomic length scale. The technique of choice is low-temperature scanning probe microscopy, primarily scanning tunneling microscopy (STM). The strength of the scanning probe techniques lies in their ability to analyze the structural environment of one particular defect or adsorbate on the atomic length scale and to probe the local properties of this individual, well-characterized structure. In the last years we were mainly interested in STM experiments on individual adsorbates on ultrathin insulating films. Ultrathin insulating films on metal substrates facilitate the use of the scanning tunneling microscope to study the electronic properties of single atoms and molecules, which are electronically decoupled from the metallic substrate. Most importantly, many physical and chemical properties are not only quantitatively but also qualitatively different on an insulating surface from those on a (semi-)conducting surface. Hence, it becomes of supreme importance to the scope of science, as it advances to the atomic length scale, to include insulating materials. New experimental possibilities which are to be examined comprise (meta-)stable charging processes of individual adsorbates and STM-induced chemistry of single molecules on insulators. Furthermore, these investigations shall open new research avenues in molecular electronics, as they combine the following two elements: the electronic decoupling of an adsorbate provided by the insulator and the ability of STM to analyze the structural environment of an adsorbed molecule. Our running scanning tunneling microscope works at a temperature of 5K under ultra-high vacuum conditions. A second machine is presently being built up that includes the possibility to measure forces on the atomic length scale. In the following years, a third apparatus is planned which will allow measurements in strong magnetic fields to additionally study magnetic properties. The group was established in March 2007 by the hiring of Jascha Repp on a Lichtenberg-professorship, funded by the Volkswagenstiftung.</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/repp/publications.htm</field>
<field name="title">AG Repp - Publications</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/repp/publications.htm</field>
<field name="content">AG Repp - Publications AG Repp - Publications Atomic-Scale Science on Insulating Films Jascha Repp, Faculty of Physics, University of Regensburg   Research     People     Recent Results     Teaching     Publications     Join     Contact   Publications Gerhard Münnich, Andrea Donarini, Martin Wenderoth, and Jascha Repp, Fixing the Energy Scale in Scanning Tunneling Microscopy on Semiconductor Surfaces, Physical Review Letters 111, 216802 (2013). Niko Pavli?ek, Coral Herranz-Lancho, Benoit Fleury, Mathias Neu, Judith Niedenführ, Mario Ruben, and Jascha Repp, High-resolution scanning tunneling and atomic force microscopy of stereochemically resolved dibenzo[a,h]thianthrene molecules, physica status solidi b 250, 2424 (2013). Niko Pavli?ek, Scanning probe methods applied to molecular electronics, Dissertation (2013). Florian Albrecht, Mathias Neu, Christina Quest, Ingmar Swart, and Jascha Repp, Formation and Characterization of a Molecule?Metal?Molecule Bridge in Real Space, Journal of the American Chemical Society 135, 9200 (2013). Christof Uhlmann, Tieftemperatur-Rastertunnelmikroskopie an Phthalocyanin-Molekülen auf ultradünnen Isolatorfilmen: Ladungszustand, Jahn-Teller Effekt und ein molekularer Schalter, Dissertation (2013). Niko Pavli?ek, Ingmar Swart, Judith Niedenführ, Gerhard Meyer, and Jascha Repp, Symmetry Dependence of Vibration-Assisted Tunneling, Physical Review Letters 110,136101 (2013). Christof Uhlmann, Ingmar Swart, and Jascha Repp, Controlling the Orbital Sequence in Individual Cu-Phthalocyanine Molecules, Nano Letters 13, 777 (2013). Gerhard Münnich, Florian Albrecht, Christophe Nacci, Martin Utz, Dieter Schuh, Kiyoshi Kanisawa, Stefan Fölsch, and Jascha Repp, Probing individual weakly-coupled ?-conjugated molecules on semiconductor surfaces, Journal of Applied Physics 112, 034312 (2012). Fabian Mohn, Probing electronic and structural properties of single molecules on the atomic scale, Dissertation (2012). Niko Pavli?ek, Benoit Fleury, Mathias Neu, Judith Niedenführ, Coral Herranz-Lancho, Mario Ruben, and Jascha Repp, Atomic Force Microscopy Reveals Bistable Configurations of Dibenzo[a,h]thianthrene and their Interconversion Pathway, Physical Review Letters 108, 086101 (2012). Gerhard Meyer, Leo Gross, Fabian Mohn, and Jascha Repp , Scanning Probe Microscopy of Atoms and Molecules on Insulating Films: From Imaging to Molecular Manipulation Chimia 66, 10 (2012). Ingmar Swart, Tobias Sonnleitner, Judith Niedenführ, and Jascha Repp, Controlled Lateral Manipulation of Molecules on Insulating Films by STM, Nano Letters 12, 1070 (2012). Gerhard Meyer, Leo Gross, and Jascha Repp, Atomic and Molecular Manipulation, Wiley-VCH, Aachen, 282-302 (2012). Tobias Sonnleitner, Symmetrien und Manipulation des Ladungszustands von Molekülen auf NaCl-Filmen, Dissertation (2011). Tobias Sonnleitner, Ingmar Swart, Niko Pavli?ek, Andreas Pöllmann, and Jascha Repp, Molecular Symmetry Governs Surface Diffusion Physical Review Letters 107, 186103 (2011). Christoph Strunk, Dieter Weiss, Jascha Repp, Andreas Schäfer, Thomas A. Niehaus, and Tilo Wettig, Spins, Moleküle und Supercomputer, Blick in die Wissenschaft 23, 28 (2011). Ingmar Swart, Tobias Sonnleitner, and Jascha Repp, Charge State Control of Molecules Reveals Modification of the Tunneling Barrier with Intramolecular Contrast, Nano Letters 11, 1580 (2011). F. Mohn, J. Repp, L. Gross, G. Meyer, M. S. Dyer, M. Persson, Reversible Bond Formation in a Gold-Atom-Organic-Molecule Complex as a Molecular Switch, Physical Review Letters 105, 266102 (2010). J. Repp, P. Liljeroth, and G. Meyer, Coherent electron?nuclear coupling in oligothiophene molecular wires Nature Physics 6, 975 (2010). P. Liljeroth, I. Swart, S. Paavilainen, J. Repp, G. Meyer, Single-Molecule Synthesis and Characterization of Metal?Ligand Complexes by Low-Temperature STM Nano Letters 10, 2475 (2010). J. Repp, and G. Meyer, Scanning Tunneling Spectroscopy of Molecules on Insulating Films CHIMIA 64, 370 (2010). L. Gross, F. Mohn, P. Liljeroth, J. Repp, F. J. Giessibl, G. Meyer, Measuring the charge state of an adatom with noncontact atomic force microscopy, Science 324, 1428 (2009). N. N. Negulyaev, V. S. Stepanyuk, L. Niebergall, P. Bruno, W. Hergert, J. Repp, K.-H. Rieder, and G. Meyer, Direct Evidence for the Effect of Quantum Confinement of Surface-State Electrons on Atomic Diffusion, Physical Review Letters 101, 226601 (2008). J. A. Larsson, S. D. Elliott, J. C. Greer, J. Repp, G. Meyer, and R. Allenspach, Orientation of individual C60 molecules adsorbed on Cu(111): Low-temperature scanning tunneling microscopy and density functional calculations, Physical Review B 77, 115434 (2008). P. Liljeroth, J. Repp, and G. Meyer, Current-Induced Hydrogen Tautomerization and Conductance Switching of Naphthalocyanine Molecules, Science 317, 1203 (2007). F. E. Olsson, S. Paavilainen, M. Persson, J. Repp, and G. Meyer, Multiple Charge States of Ag Atoms on Ultrathin NaCl Films, Physical Review Letters 98, 176803 (2007). J. Repp and G. Meyer, Molekulare Hüllen im Portrait: Rastertunnelmikroskop bildet Molekülorbitale ab, Physik in unserer Zeit 37, 266 (2006). Jascha Repp and Gerhard Meyer, Scanning tunneling microscopy of adsorbates on insulating films, Applied Physics A 85, 399 (2006). J. Repp, G. Meyer, S. Paavilainen, F. E. Olsson, and M. Persson, Imaging Bond Formation Between a Gold Atom and Pentacene on an Insulating Surface, Science 312, 1196 (2006). J. Repp, G. Meyer, S. Paavilainen, F. E. Olsson, and M. Persson, Scanning Tunneling Spectroscopy of Cl Vacancies in NaCl Films: Strong Electron-Phonon Coupling in Double-Barrier Tunneling Junctions, Physical Review Letters 95, 225503 (2005). F. Olsson, M. Persson, J. Repp, and G. Meyer, Scanning tunneling microscopy and work functions of sodium chloride overlayers on a stepped copper surface, from experiment and theory, Physical Review B 71, 075419 (2005). J. Repp, G. Meyer, S. M. Stojkovic, A. Gourdon, and C. Joachim, Molecules on insulating films: Scanning tunneling microscopy imaging of individual molecular orbitals, Physical Review Letters 94, 026803 (2005). J. Repp, and G. Meyer, Gezielte Umladung einzelner Goldatome, Physik in unserer Zeit 35, 207 (2004). J. Repp, G. Meyer, F. Olsson, and M. Persson, Controlling the charge state of individual gold adatoms, Science 305, 493 (2004). K. H. Rieder, G. Meyer, S.W. Hla, F. Moresco, K.-F. Braun, K. Morgenstern, J. Repp, S. Foelsch, and L. Bartels, The scanning tunneling microscope as operative tool: doing physics and chemistry with single atoms and molecules, Phil. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. A 362, 1207 (2004). J. Repp, G. Meyer, and K. H. Rieder, Snell's law for surface electrons: Refraction of an electron gas imaged in real space, Physical Review Letters 92, 036803 (2004). J. Repp, G. Meyer, K. H. Rieder, and P. Hyldgaard, Site determination and thermally assisted tunneling in homogenous nucleation, Physical Review Letters 91, 206102 (2003). S. Fölsch, A. Riemann, J. Repp, G. Meyer, and K. H. Rieder, From atomic kinks to mesoscopic surface patterns: Ionic layers on vicinal metal surfaces, Physical Review B 66, 161409(R) (2002). S. Fölsch, A. Helms, A. Riemann, J. Repp, G. Meyer, and K. H. Rieder, Nanoscale surface patterning by adsorbate-induced faceting and selective growth: NaCl on Cu(211), Surface Science 497, 113 (2002) G. Meyer, F. Moresco, S.W. Hla, J. Repp, K.-F. Braun, S. Fölsch, and K. H. Rieder, Manipulation of atoms and molecules with the low temperature scanning tunneling microscope, Japanese Journal of Applied Physics 40, 4409 (2001). J. Repp, S. Fölsch, G. Meyer, and K. H. Rieder, Ionic films on vicinal metal surfaces: Enhanced binding due to charge modulation, Physical Review Letters 86, 252 (2001). J. Repp, F. Moresco, G. Meyer, K. H. Rieder, P. Hyldgaard, and M. Persson, Substrate mediated long range interaction between adatoms: Cu/Cu(111), Physical Review Letters 85, 2981 (2000). G. Meyer, J. Repp, S. Zöphel, K.-F. Braun, S.W. Hla, S. Fölsch, L. Bartels, F. Moresco, and K. H. Rieder, Controlled manipulation of atoms and small molecules with a low temperature scanning tunneling microscope, Single Molecules 1, 79 (2000). S. Fölsch, A. Helms, S. Zöphel, J. Repp, G. Meyer, and K. H. Rieder, Self-organized patterning of an insulator-on-metal system by surface-faceting and selective growth: NaCl/Cu(211), Physical Review Letters 84, 123 (2000). G. Meyer, J. Repp, S. Zöphel, and K. H. Rieder, Low temperature scanning tunneling microscopy study on the growth and atomic manipulation of NaCl on vicinal copper surfaces, Proceedings of the ICPE 1999, Osaka (1999). S. Zöphel, J. Repp, G. Meyer, and K. H. Rieder, Determination of binding sites in ordered phases of CO/Cu(211) employing molecular level manipulation, Chemical Physics Letters 310, 145 (1999).</field>
<field name="important">AG Repp - Publications AG Repp - Publications Atomic-Scale Science on Insulating Films Jascha Repp, Faculty of Physics, University of Regensburg   Research     People     Recent Results     Teaching     Publications     Join     Contact   Publications Gerhard Münnich, Andrea Donarini, Martin Wenderoth, and Jascha Repp, Fixing the Energy Scale in Scanning Tunneling Microscopy on Semiconductor Surfaces, Physical Review Letters 111, 216802 (2013). Niko Pavli?ek, Coral Herranz-Lancho, Benoit Fleury, Mathias Neu, Judith Niedenführ, Mario Ruben, and Jascha Repp, High-resolution scanning tunneling and atomic force microscopy of stereochemically resolved dibenzo[a,h]thianthrene molecules, physica status solidi b 250, 2424 (2013). Niko Pavli?ek, Scanning probe methods applied to molecular electronics, Dissertation (2013). Florian Albrecht, Mathias Neu, Christina Quest, Ingmar Swart, and Jascha Repp, Formation and Characterization of a Molecule?Metal?Molecule Bridge in Real Space, Journal of the American Chemical Society 135, 9200 (2013). Christof Uhlmann, Tieftemperatur-Rastertunnelmikroskopie an Phthalocyanin-Molekülen auf ultradünnen Isolatorfilmen: Ladungszustand, Jahn-Teller Effekt und ein molekularer Schalter, Dissertation (2013). Niko Pavli?ek, Ingmar Swart, Judith Niedenführ, Gerhard Meyer, and Jascha Repp, Symmetry Dependence of Vibration-Assisted Tunneling, Physical Review Letters 110,136101 (2013). Christof Uhlmann, Ingmar Swart, and Jascha Repp, Controlling the Orbital Sequence in Individual Cu-Phthalocyanine Molecules, Nano Letters 13, 777 (2013). Gerhard Münnich, Florian Albrecht, Christophe Nacci, Martin Utz, Dieter Schuh, Kiyoshi Kanisawa, Stefan Fölsch, and Jascha Repp, Probing individual weakly-coupled ?-conjugated molecules on semiconductor surfaces, Journal of Applied Physics 112, 034312 (2012). Fabian Mohn, Probing electronic and structural properties of single molecules on the atomic scale, Dissertation (2012). Niko Pavli?ek, Benoit Fleury, Mathias Neu, Judith Niedenführ, Coral Herranz-Lancho, Mario Ruben, and Jascha Repp, Atomic Force Microscopy Reveals Bistable Configurations of Dibenzo[a,h]thianthrene and their Interconversion Pathway, Physical Review Letters 108, 086101 (2012). Gerhard Meyer, Leo Gross, Fabian Mohn, and Jascha Repp , Scanning Probe Microscopy of Atoms and Molecules on Insulating Films: From Imaging to Molecular Manipulation Chimia 66, 10 (2012). Ingmar Swart, Tobias Sonnleitner, Judith Niedenführ, and Jascha Repp, Controlled Lateral Manipulation of Molecules on Insulating Films by STM, Nano Letters 12, 1070 (2012). Gerhard Meyer, Leo Gross, and Jascha Repp, Atomic and Molecular Manipulation, Wiley-VCH, Aachen, 282-302 (2012). Tobias Sonnleitner, Symmetrien und Manipulation des Ladungszustands von Molekülen auf NaCl-Filmen, Dissertation (2011). Tobias Sonnleitner, Ingmar Swart, Niko Pavli?ek, Andreas Pöllmann, and Jascha Repp, Molecular Symmetry Governs Surface Diffusion Physical Review Letters 107, 186103 (2011). Christoph Strunk, Dieter Weiss, Jascha Repp, Andreas Schäfer, Thomas A. Niehaus, and Tilo Wettig, Spins, Moleküle und Supercomputer, Blick in die Wissenschaft 23, 28 (2011). Ingmar Swart, Tobias Sonnleitner, and Jascha Repp, Charge State Control of Molecules Reveals Modification of the Tunneling Barrier with Intramolecular Contrast, Nano Letters 11, 1580 (2011). F. Mohn, J. Repp, L. Gross, G. Meyer, M. S. Dyer, M. Persson, Reversible Bond Formation in a Gold-Atom-Organic-Molecule Complex as a Molecular Switch, Physical Review Letters 105, 266102 (2010). J. Repp, P. Liljeroth, and G. Meyer, Coherent electron?nuclear coupling in oligothiophene molecular wires Nature Physics 6, 975 (2010). P. Liljeroth, I. Swart, S. Paavilainen, J. Repp, G. Meyer, Single-Molecule Synthesis and Characterization of Metal?Ligand Complexes by Low-Temperature STM Nano Letters 10, 2475 (2010). J. Repp, and G. Meyer, Scanning Tunneling Spectroscopy of Molecules on Insulating Films CHIMIA 64, 370 (2010). L. Gross, F. Mohn, P. Liljeroth, J. Repp, F. J. Giessibl, G. Meyer, Measuring the charge state of an adatom with noncontact atomic force microscopy, Science 324, 1428 (2009). N. N. Negulyaev, V. S. Stepanyuk, L. Niebergall, P. Bruno, W. Hergert, J. Repp, K.-H. Rieder, and G. Meyer, Direct Evidence for the Effect of Quantum Confinement of Surface-State Electrons on Atomic Diffusion, Physical Review Letters 101, 226601 (2008). J. A. Larsson, S. D. Elliott, J. C. Greer, J. Repp, G. Meyer, and R. Allenspach, Orientation of individual C60 molecules adsorbed on Cu(111): Low-temperature scanning tunneling microscopy and density functional calculations, Physical Review B 77, 115434 (2008). P. Liljeroth, J. Repp, and G. Meyer, Current-Induced Hydrogen Tautomerization and Conductance Switching of Naphthalocyanine Molecules, Science 317, 1203 (2007). F. E. Olsson, S. Paavilainen, M. Persson, J. Repp, and G. Meyer, Multiple Charge States of Ag Atoms on Ultrathin NaCl Films, Physical Review Letters 98, 176803 (2007). J. Repp and G. Meyer, Molekulare Hüllen im Portrait: Rastertunnelmikroskop bildet Molekülorbitale ab, Physik in unserer Zeit 37, 266 (2006). Jascha Repp and Gerhard Meyer, Scanning tunneling microscopy of adsorbates on insulating films, Applied Physics A 85, 399 (2006). J. Repp, G. Meyer, S. Paavilainen, F. E. Olsson, and M. Persson, Imaging Bond Formation Between a Gold Atom and Pentacene on an Insulating Surface, Science 312, 1196 (2006). J. Repp, G. Meyer, S. Paavilainen, F. E. Olsson, and M. Persson, Scanning Tunneling Spectroscopy of Cl Vacancies in NaCl Films: Strong Electron-Phonon Coupling in Double-Barrier Tunneling Junctions, Physical Review Letters 95, 225503 (2005). F. Olsson, M. Persson, J. Repp, and G. Meyer, Scanning tunneling microscopy and work functions of sodium chloride overlayers on a stepped copper surface, from experiment and theory, Physical Review B 71, 075419 (2005). J. Repp, G. Meyer, S. M. Stojkovic, A. Gourdon, and C. Joachim, Molecules on insulating films: Scanning tunneling microscopy imaging of individual molecular orbitals, Physical Review Letters 94, 026803 (2005). J. Repp, and G. Meyer, Gezielte Umladung einzelner Goldatome, Physik in unserer Zeit 35, 207 (2004). J. Repp, G. Meyer, F. Olsson, and M. Persson, Controlling the charge state of individual gold adatoms, Science 305, 493 (2004). K. H. Rieder, G. Meyer, S.W. Hla, F. Moresco, K.-F. Braun, K. Morgenstern, J. Repp, S. Foelsch, and L. Bartels, The scanning tunneling microscope as operative tool: doing physics and chemistry with single atoms and molecules, Phil. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. A 362, 1207 (2004). J. Repp, G. Meyer, and K. H. Rieder, Snell's law for surface electrons: Refraction of an electron gas imaged in real space, Physical Review Letters 92, 036803 (2004). J. Repp, G. Meyer, K. H. Rieder, and P. Hyldgaard, Site determination and thermally assisted tunneling in homogenous nucleation, Physical Review Letters 91, 206102 (2003). S. Fölsch, A. Riemann, J. Repp, G. Meyer, and K. H. Rieder, From atomic kinks to mesoscopic surface patterns: Ionic layers on vicinal metal surfaces, Physical Review B 66, 161409(R) (2002). S. Fölsch, A. Helms, A. Riemann, J. Repp, G. Meyer, and K. H. Rieder, Nanoscale surface patterning by adsorbate-induced faceting and selective growth: NaCl on Cu(211), Surface Science 497, 113 (2002) G. Meyer, F. Moresco, S.W. Hla, J. Repp, K.-F. Braun, S. Fölsch, and K. H. Rieder, Manipulation of atoms and molecules with the low temperature scanning tunneling microscope, Japanese Journal of Applied Physics 40, 4409 (2001). J. Repp, S. Fölsch, G. Meyer, and K. H. Rieder, Ionic films on vicinal metal surfaces: Enhanced binding due to charge modulation, Physical Review Letters 86, 252 (2001). J. Repp, F. Moresco, G. Meyer, K. H. Rieder, P. Hyldgaard, and M. Persson, Substrate mediated long range interaction between adatoms: Cu/Cu(111), Physical Review Letters 85, 2981 (2000). G. Meyer, J. Repp, S. Zöphel, K.-F. Braun, S.W. Hla, S. Fölsch, L. Bartels, F. Moresco, and K. H. Rieder, Controlled manipulation of atoms and small molecules with a low temperature scanning tunneling microscope, Single Molecules 1, 79 (2000). S. Fölsch, A. Helms, S. Zöphel, J. Repp, G. Meyer, and K. H. Rieder, Self-organized patterning of an insulator-on-metal system by surface-faceting and selective growth: NaCl/Cu(211), Physical Review Letters 84, 123 (2000). G. Meyer, J. Repp, S. Zöphel, and K. H. Rieder, Low temperature scanning tunneling microscopy study on the growth and atomic manipulation of NaCl on vicinal copper surfaces, Proceedings of the ICPE 1999, Osaka (1999). S. Zöphel, J. Repp, G. Meyer, and K. H. Rieder, Determination of binding sites in ordered phases of CO/Cu(211) employing molecular level manipulation, Chemical Physics Letters 310, 145 (1999).</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/CMT/pages/contact.html</field>
<field name="title">Solid State Theory, contact</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/CMT/pages/contact.html</field>
<field name="content">Solid State Theory, contact Solid State Theory, contact Lehrstuhl Prof. Dr. K. Richter Universität Regensburg, 93040 Regensburg, Germany Toni Bienert, secretary room 4.1.34 tel 49-(0)941 943-2030 fax 49-(0)941 943-4382 Prof. Dr. Klaus Richter 4.1.33 49-(0)941-943-2029 Prof. Dr. Jaroslav Fabian 4.1.53 49-(0)941-943-2031 Dr. Gianaurelio Cuniberti 4.1.29 49-(0)941-943-2025 PD Dr. habil. Jens Siewert presently in Catania Prof. Dr. Joachim Keller 4.1.16 49-(0)941-943-2015 Prof. Dr. Ulrich Rößler 4.1.16 49-(0)941-943-2015 Prof. em. Dr. Ulrich Schröder 4.1.16 49-(0)941-943-2015 Prof. Dr. Dieter Strauch 4.1.16 49-(0)941-943-2015 apl. Prof. Dr. Andreas Mayer Lehrstuhl Prof. Dr. M. Grifoni Universität Regensburg, 93040 Regensburg, Germany Lizy Lazar, secretary 3.1.28 tel 49-(0)941-943-2036 fax 49-(0)941-943-2038 Prof. Dr. Milena Grifoni 3.1.29 49-(0)941-943-2035 Prof. Dr. John Schliemann 3.1.27 49-(0)941-943-2037 To contact any of the persons listed above please use the email format: FirstName.Name@physik.uni-regensburg.de last update 15.3.2006 | Imprint | © ad arte 2004</field>
<field name="important">Solid State Theory, contact Solid State Theory, contact Lehrstuhl Prof. Dr. K. Richter Universität Regensburg, 93040 Regensburg, Germany Toni Bienert, secretary room 4.1.34 tel 49-(0)941 943-2030 fax 49-(0)941 943-4382 Prof. Dr. Klaus Richter 4.1.33 49-(0)941-943-2029 Prof. Dr. Jaroslav Fabian 4.1.53 49-(0)941-943-2031 Dr. Gianaurelio Cuniberti 4.1.29 49-(0)941-943-2025 PD Dr. habil. Jens Siewert presently in Catania Prof. Dr. Joachim Keller 4.1.16 49-(0)941-943-2015 Prof. Dr. Ulrich Rößler 4.1.16 49-(0)941-943-2015 Prof. em. Dr. Ulrich Schröder 4.1.16 49-(0)941-943-2015 Prof. Dr. Dieter Strauch 4.1.16 49-(0)941-943-2015 apl. Prof. Dr. Andreas Mayer Lehrstuhl Prof. Dr. M. Grifoni Universität Regensburg, 93040 Regensburg, Germany Lizy Lazar, secretary 3.1.28 tel 49-(0)941-943-2036 fax 49-(0)941-943-2038 Prof. Dr. Milena Grifoni 3.1.29 49-(0)941-943-2035 Prof. Dr. John Schliemann 3.1.27 49-(0)941-943-2037 To contact any of the persons listed above please use the email format: FirstName.Name@physik.uni-regensburg.de last update 15.3.2006 | Imprint | © ad arte 2004</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/CMT/pages/findus.html</field>
<field name="title">Complex Quantum Systems, find us</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/CMT/pages/findus.html</field>
<field name="content">Complex Quantum Systems, find us Complex Quantum Systems, find us full address: Institut I - Theoretische Physik Universität Regensburg Universitätsstraße 31 D-93053 Regensburg Germany telephone: +49 (0)941 943-2029, -2030 fax: +49 (0)941 943-4382 Prof. Dr. Klaus Richter (chair) room Phy 4.1.33 telephone +49 (0)941 943-2029 fax +49 (0)941 943 4382 e-mail klaus.richter(at)physik.uni-regensburg.de Toni Bienert (secretary) room Phy 4.1.34 telephone +49 (0)941 943-2029, -2030 fax +49 (0)941 943 4382 e-mail toni.bienert(at)physik.uni-regensburg.de Prof. Dr. Milena Grifoni (chair) room Phy 4.1.29 telephone +49 (0)941 943-2035 fax +49 (0)941 943-2038 Lizy Lazar (secretary) The university is located at the south end of Regensburg within walking distance (appr. 30 min) of the city centre and can be easily reached by bus (10 min). How to reach us • by train • by car • by plane sketches, maps: campus map map of Regensburg main station with bus stations Regensburgs surroundigs with Autobahn-junctions links: map of Regensburg bus lines of Regensburg complex quantum systems • theory home • physics home last update:4.4.2006</field>
<field name="important">Complex Quantum Systems, find us Complex Quantum Systems, find us full address: Institut I - Theoretische Physik Universität Regensburg Universitätsstraße 31 D-93053 Regensburg Germany telephone: +49 (0)941 943-2029, -2030 fax: +49 (0)941 943-4382 Prof. Dr. Klaus Richter (chair) room Phy 4.1.33 telephone +49 (0)941 943-2029 fax +49 (0)941 943 4382 e-mail klaus.richter(at)physik.uni-regensburg.de Toni Bienert (secretary) room Phy 4.1.34 telephone +49 (0)941 943-2029, -2030 fax +49 (0)941 943 4382 e-mail toni.bienert(at)physik.uni-regensburg.de Prof. Dr. Milena Grifoni (chair) room Phy 4.1.29 telephone +49 (0)941 943-2035 fax +49 (0)941 943-2038 Lizy Lazar (secretary) The university is located at the south end of Regensburg within walking distance (appr. 30 min) of the city centre and can be easily reached by bus (10 min). How to reach us • by train • by car • by plane sketches, maps: campus map map of Regensburg main station with bus stations Regensburgs surroundigs with Autobahn-junctions links: map of Regensburg bus lines of Regensburg complex quantum systems • theory home • physics home last update:4.4.2006</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/CMT/pages/imprint.html</field>
<field name="title">Solid State Theory, contact</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/CMT/pages/imprint.html</field>
<field name="content">Solid State Theory, contact Solid State Theory, contact responsible for the content: Prof. Dr. Klaus Richter Institut I – Theoretische Physik Universität Regensburg D-93040 Regensburg, Germany Telefon: +49 (0)941 943-2029 e-mail: klaus.richter(at)physik.uni-regensburg.de www.administration: Thomas Engl Institut I – Theoretische Physik Universität Regensburg D-93040 Regensburg, Germany Telefon: +49-941-943-2020 e-mail: Thomas.Engl(at)physik.uni-regensburg.de last update 29.04.2010 | © ad arte 2004</field>
<field name="important">Solid State Theory, contact Solid State Theory, contact responsible for the content: Prof. Dr. Klaus Richter Institut I – Theoretische Physik Universität Regensburg D-93040 Regensburg, Germany Telefon: +49 (0)941 943-2029 e-mail: klaus.richter(at)physik.uni-regensburg.de www.administration: Thomas Engl Institut I – Theoretische Physik Universität Regensburg D-93040 Regensburg, Germany Telefon: +49-941-943-2020 e-mail: Thomas.Engl(at)physik.uni-regensburg.de last update 29.04.2010 | © ad arte 2004</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/CMT/pages/internal.html</field>
<field name="title">Solid State Theory, contact</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/CMT/pages/internal.html</field>
<field name="content">Solid State Theory, contact Solid State Theory, contact internal Guideline for climate protection (de) Info about computers at the institute EDV-Policy am Lehrstuhl Richter (pdf: de / eng) EDV-Manual für Lehrstuhl Richter (pdf: de / eng) Slideshow about Computing at the Institute EDV-Ansprechpartner Rechnerliste / Clusterbenutzung Liste der Linux Drucker Library (Bibliothek: Handapparat) (NetStorage rig09789) last update 04.08.2005 | Impressum | © ad arte 2004</field>
<field name="important">Solid State Theory, contact Solid State Theory, contact internal Guideline for climate protection (de) Info about computers at the institute EDV-Policy am Lehrstuhl Richter (pdf: de / eng) EDV-Manual für Lehrstuhl Richter (pdf: de / eng) Slideshow about Computing at the Institute EDV-Ansprechpartner Rechnerliste / Clusterbenutzung Liste der Linux Drucker Library (Bibliothek: Handapparat) (NetStorage rig09789) last update 04.08.2005 | Impressum | © ad arte 2004</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/CMT/pages/news.html</field>
<field name="title">Solid State Theory, contact</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/CMT/pages/news.html</field>
<field name="content">Solid State Theory, contact Solid State Theory, contact news • news • news • news • news • news • news • news • 23. Juli 2013 Herzliche Glückwünsche zum Promotionskolloquium von Martin Raith 18. März 2013 Herzliche Glückwünsche zum Promotionskolloquium von Viktor Krückl 28. November 2011 Herzliche Glückwünsche zum Promotionskolloquium von Jürgen Wurm 17. Mai 2011 Herzliche Glückwünsche zum Promotionskolloquium von Daniel Waltner 1. April 2011 Herzlichen Glückwunsch zum 10-jährigen Dienstjubiläum von Prof. Dr. Klaus Richter September 2010 Lehrstuhlausflug des Lehrstuhls Richter/Fabian. Juli 2010 Herzliche Glückwünsche zum Promotionskolloquium von Pino D'Amico April 2010 Dr. Thomas Niehaus wird zum Professor in Theoretischer Physik ernannt. März 2010 SKM-Preis für Dr. Michael Wimmer Michael Wimmer erhält den Dissertationspreis der Sektion Kondensierte Materie der Deutschen Physikalischen Gesellschaft Im Rahmen der Frühjahrstagung 2010 der Deutschen Physikalischen Gesellschaft hat Dr. Michael Wimmer für seine in der Gruppe von Klaus Richter durchgeführte Dissertation zum Thema "Quantum transport in nanostructures: From computational concepts to spintronics in Graphene and magnetic tunnel junctions" den diesjährigen Preis für die beste Promotion im Bereich der Kondensierten Materie in Deutschland erhalten. Ihm wurde der Preis verliehen für die Entwicklung eines äußerst effizienten und flexiblen Computercodes für Quantentransportrechnungen in Nanosystemen und dessen Anwendung in der Spintronik und Physik des Graphens. Michael Wimmer teilt sich den Preis mit Dr. Lena Ivanova (TU Berlin). Februar 2010 Herzliche Glückwünsche zum Promotionskolloquium von Matthias Scheid News archive last update 24.7.2013 | Impressum | © ad arte 2004</field>
<field name="important">Solid State Theory, contact Solid State Theory, contact news • news • news • news • news • news • news • news • 23. Juli 2013 Herzliche Glückwünsche zum Promotionskolloquium von Martin Raith 18. März 2013 Herzliche Glückwünsche zum Promotionskolloquium von Viktor Krückl 28. November 2011 Herzliche Glückwünsche zum Promotionskolloquium von Jürgen Wurm 17. Mai 2011 Herzliche Glückwünsche zum Promotionskolloquium von Daniel Waltner 1. April 2011 Herzlichen Glückwunsch zum 10-jährigen Dienstjubiläum von Prof. Dr. Klaus Richter September 2010 Lehrstuhlausflug des Lehrstuhls Richter/Fabian. Juli 2010 Herzliche Glückwünsche zum Promotionskolloquium von Pino D'Amico April 2010 Dr. Thomas Niehaus wird zum Professor in Theoretischer Physik ernannt. März 2010 SKM-Preis für Dr. Michael Wimmer Michael Wimmer erhält den Dissertationspreis der Sektion Kondensierte Materie der Deutschen Physikalischen Gesellschaft Im Rahmen der Frühjahrstagung 2010 der Deutschen Physikalischen Gesellschaft hat Dr. Michael Wimmer für seine in der Gruppe von Klaus Richter durchgeführte Dissertation zum Thema "Quantum transport in nanostructures: From computational concepts to spintronics in Graphene and magnetic tunnel junctions" den diesjährigen Preis für die beste Promotion im Bereich der Kondensierten Materie in Deutschland erhalten. Ihm wurde der Preis verliehen für die Entwicklung eines äußerst effizienten und flexiblen Computercodes für Quantentransportrechnungen in Nanosystemen und dessen Anwendung in der Spintronik und Physik des Graphens. Michael Wimmer teilt sich den Preis mit Dr. Lena Ivanova (TU Berlin). Februar 2010 Herzliche Glückwünsche zum Promotionskolloquium von Matthias Scheid News archive last update 24.7.2013 | Impressum | © ad arte 2004</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/CMT/pages/seminars.html</field>
<field name="title">Solid State Theory, contact</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/CMT/pages/seminars.html</field>
<field name="content">Solid State Theory, contact Solid State Theory, contact this week (overview) Condensed matter theory seminar group seminar J. Fabian, M. Grifoni, K. Richter, J. Schliemann group seminar G. Cuniberti Graduiertenkolleg "Nonlinearity and nonequilibrium in condensed matter" SFB 689 "Spinphänomene in reduzierten Dimensionen" group seminar D. Weiss / C. Strunk last update 19.10.2006 | Impressum | © ad arte 2004</field>
<field name="important">Solid State Theory, contact Solid State Theory, contact this week (overview) Condensed matter theory seminar group seminar J. Fabian, M. Grifoni, K. Richter, J. Schliemann group seminar G. Cuniberti Graduiertenkolleg "Nonlinearity and nonequilibrium in condensed matter" SFB 689 "Spinphänomene in reduzierten Dimensionen" group seminar D. Weiss / C. Strunk last update 19.10.2006 | Impressum | © ad arte 2004</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/richter/pages/impressum/impressum.html</field>
<field name="title">Complex Quantum Systems, impressum</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/richter/pages/impressum/impressum.html</field>
<field name="content">Complex Quantum Systems, impressum Complex Quantum Systems, impressum Impressum responsible for the content: Complex Quantum Systems, Research Group Klaus Richter Prof. Dr. Klaus Richter Institut I – Theoretische Physik Universität Regensburg D-93040 Regensburg Germany Telefon: +49 (0)941 943-2029 e-mail: klaus.richter(at)physik.uni-regensburg.de www.administration: Thomas Engl Institut I – Theoretische Physik Universität Regensburg D-93040 Regensburg Germany Telefon: +49-941-943-2020 E-mail: Thomas.Engl(at)physik.uni-regensburg.de complex quantum systems • theory home • physics home</field>
<field name="important">Complex Quantum Systems, impressum Complex Quantum Systems, impressum Impressum responsible for the content: Complex Quantum Systems, Research Group Klaus Richter Prof. Dr. Klaus Richter Institut I – Theoretische Physik Universität Regensburg D-93040 Regensburg Germany Telefon: +49 (0)941 943-2029 e-mail: klaus.richter(at)physik.uni-regensburg.de www.administration: Thomas Engl Institut I – Theoretische Physik Universität Regensburg D-93040 Regensburg Germany Telefon: +49-941-943-2020 E-mail: Thomas.Engl(at)physik.uni-regensburg.de complex quantum systems • theory home • physics home</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/richter/pages/joinus/joinus.html</field>
<field name="title">Complex Quantum Systems, join us</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/richter/pages/joinus/joinus.html</field>
<field name="content">Complex Quantum Systems, join us Complex Quantum Systems, join us join us Postdoc- and / PhD positions: We have presently no openings Masterarbeiten / master projects: Graphene physics spintronics molecular electronics quantum chaos Bachelor-Arbeiten / bachelor projects: on topics given above, see also Studentenprojekte / students' projects: Wir haben Stellen zu vergeben an Student(inn)en (nach dem 4. Semester), die in der Arbeitsgruppe an aktuellen Forschungsprojekten mitarbeiten möchten. contact: Klaus Richter complex quantum systems ? theory home ? physics home last update: 22.04.2010</field>
<field name="important">Complex Quantum Systems, join us Complex Quantum Systems, join us join us Postdoc- and / PhD positions: We have presently no openings Masterarbeiten / master projects: Graphene physics spintronics molecular electronics quantum chaos Bachelor-Arbeiten / bachelor projects: on topics given above, see also Studentenprojekte / students' projects: Wir haben Stellen zu vergeben an Student(inn)en (nach dem 4. Semester), die in der Arbeitsgruppe an aktuellen Forschungsprojekten mitarbeiten möchten. contact: Klaus Richter complex quantum systems ? theory home ? physics home last update: 22.04.2010</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/richter/pages/links/links.html</field>
<field name="title">Complex Quantum Systems, links</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/richter/pages/links/links.html</field>
<field name="content">Complex Quantum Systems, links Complex Quantum Systems, links Deutsche Physikalische Gesellschaft Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft Alexander von Humboldt-Stiftung preprint-Server complex quantum systems • theory home • physics home last update: 13.3.2006</field>
<field name="important">Complex Quantum Systems, links Complex Quantum Systems, links Deutsche Physikalische Gesellschaft Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft Alexander von Humboldt-Stiftung preprint-Server complex quantum systems • theory home • physics home last update: 13.3.2006</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/richter/pages/people/people.html</field>
<field name="title">Complex Quantum Systems, people</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/richter/pages/people/people.html</field>
<field name="content">Complex Quantum Systems, people Complex Quantum Systems, people head Klaus Richter secretary Toni Bienert postdocs Christopher Eltschka Viktor Krückl Jack Kuipers Ming-Hao Liu Juan Diego Urbina graduate students Jan Bundesmann Tobias Dollinger Thomas Engl Sven Essert Timo Hartmann Lisa Heße Quirin Hummel Josef Michl Fedor Tkatschenko Phillipp Reck diploma / master students Markus Biberger bachelor students Felix Bolland Benjamin Geiger Andrea Spichtinger Alexander Ross complex quantum systems • theory home • physics home last update: 08.10.2013</field>
<field name="important">Complex Quantum Systems, people Complex Quantum Systems, people head Klaus Richter secretary Toni Bienert postdocs Christopher Eltschka Viktor Krückl Jack Kuipers Ming-Hao Liu Juan Diego Urbina graduate students Jan Bundesmann Tobias Dollinger Thomas Engl Sven Essert Timo Hartmann Lisa Heße Quirin Hummel Josef Michl Fedor Tkatschenko Phillipp Reck diploma / master students Markus Biberger bachelor students Felix Bolland Benjamin Geiger Andrea Spichtinger Alexander Ross complex quantum systems • theory home • physics home last update: 08.10.2013</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/richter/pages/seminars/seminars.html</field>
<field name="title">Complex Quantum Systems, seminars</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/richter/richter/pages/seminars/seminars.html</field>
<field name="content">Complex Quantum Systems, seminars Complex Quantum Systems, seminars complex quantum systems • theory home • physics home</field>
<field name="important">Complex Quantum Systems, seminars Complex Quantum Systems, seminars complex quantum systems • theory home • physics home</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/roessler/menue.html</field>
<field name="title">menue</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/roessler/menue.html</field>
<field name="content">menue menue      Prof. Dr. Ulrich Rössler           Forschung Seminar Lehrveranstaltungen Mitarbeiter Kontakt Publikationen Links News Weisswurst 2004 Weisswurst 2005</field>
<field name="important">menue menue      Prof. Dr. Ulrich Rössler           Forschung Seminar Lehrveranstaltungen Mitarbeiter Kontakt Publikationen Links News Weisswurst 2004 Weisswurst 2005</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/roessler/start.html</field>
<field name="title">Prof. Dr. Roessler: Willkommen</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/roessler/start.html</field>
<field name="content">Prof. Dr. Roessler: Willkommen Prof. Dr. Roessler: Willkommen .                    Willkommen auf der Webseite der     Arbeitsgruppe Prof. Dr. Ulrich Rössler Institut für Theoretische Physik Universität Regensburg GERMANY                   Design &amp; Realisierung: C. Lechner 2003, M. Langenbuch 2002, R. Onderka 2000 und Oliver Steffens 1998</field>
<field name="important">Prof. Dr. Roessler: Willkommen Prof. Dr. Roessler: Willkommen .                    Willkommen auf der Webseite der     Arbeitsgruppe Prof. Dr. Ulrich Rössler Institut für Theoretische Physik Universität Regensburg GERMANY                   Design &amp; Realisierung: C. Lechner 2003, M. Langenbuch 2002, R. Onderka 2000 und Oliver Steffens 1998</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schliemann/</field>
<field name="title"></field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schliemann/</field>
<field name="content"></field>
<field name="important"></field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schoepe/welcome.html</field>
<field name="title">Homepage AG Schoepe</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schoepe/welcome.html</field>
<field name="content">Homepage AG Schoepe Homepage AG Schoepe</field>
<field name="important">Homepage AG Schoepe Homepage AG Schoepe</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schroeder/</field>
<field name="title">Homepage Lehrstuhl Schroeder</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schroeder/</field>
<field name="content">Homepage Lehrstuhl Schroeder Homepage Lehrstuhl Schroeder &amp;lt;BODY LINK=&amp;quot;#0000ff&amp;quot; VLINK=&amp;quot;#800080&amp;quot;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/BODY&amp;gt;</field>
<field name="important">Homepage Lehrstuhl Schroeder Homepage Lehrstuhl Schroeder &amp;lt;BODY LINK=&amp;quot;#0000ff&amp;quot; VLINK=&amp;quot;#800080&amp;quot;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/BODY&amp;gt;</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schueller/cschuell.phtml</field>
<field name="title">Physik ? AG Schüller ? Mitarbeiter</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schueller/cschuell.phtml</field>
<field name="content">Physik ? AG Schüller ? Mitarbeiter Physik ? AG Schüller ? Mitarbeiter Christian Schüller Fakultät für Physik Institut für Experimentelle und Angewandte Physik Universität Regensburg D-93040 Regensburg Raum : PHY 2.1.28 Telefon : ++49 / (0)941 / 943 -2078 Sekretariat : ++49 / (0)941 / 943 -2080 (Frau Weiss) FAX : ++49 / (0)941 / 943 -4226 E-mail : christian.schueller@physik.uni-regensburg.de Wissenschaftlicher Werdegang 1985 - 1990 Studium der Physik an der Universität Würzburg 1991 - 1994 Promotion an der Universität Würzburg; Raman-Spektroskopie an 2D-Lochgasen (experimentell); Berechnung von Valenz-Subband-Dispersion und Raman-Streuquerschnitten 1994-2000 Wissenschaftlicher Assistent (C1) in der Arbeitsgruppe von Prof. Dr. D. Heitmann an der Universität Hamburg; Betreuung des Bereiches "Optische Spektroskopie"; Präparation nanostrukturierter Halbleitersysteme auf der Basis von GaAs-AlGaAs-Quantum Wells; Elektronische Raman-Spektroskopie und Photolumineszenz-Spektroskopie an GaAs-Quantenstrukturen 1998 Habilitation an der Universität Hamburg 1998 - 1999 Feodor-Lynen-Stipendiat der Alexander von Humboldt-Stiftung in der Gruppe von Prof. Dr. D. S. Chemla an der University of California at Berkeley und am Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, U.S.A.; Ultrakurzzeit-Spektroskopie an GaAs-AlGaAs-Nanostrukturen im Quanten-Hall-Regime 1999 - 2004 Privatdozent an der Universität Hamburg 2000 - 2004 Heisenberg-Stipendiat der Deutschen Forschungsgemeinschaft; Leitung einer Nachwuchsgruppe 2000 Forschungsaufenthalt am Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, U.S.A. 2004 Ruf auf C3-Professur für Experimentalphysik an der Universität Regensburg Preise und Auszeichnungen 09/1998 Feodor-Lynen-Stipendium der Alexander von Humboldt-Stiftung 03/2000 Heisenberg-Stipendium der Deutschen Forschungsgemeinschaft 03/2000 1. Preis bei der Auszeichnung der besten Lehrenden des Fachbereichs Physik der Universität Hamburg im WS 1999/2000 für die Vorlesung "Nanostrukturierte Halbleitersysteme" 07/2005 1. Preis bei der Auszeichnung der besten Lehrenden der Naturwissenschaftlichen Fakultät II - Physik der Universität Regensburg im WS 2004/2005 für die Vorlesung "Moderne Physik I für Lehramt" 04/2006 Berufung ins Editorial Board der Zeitschrift Physica E, Low-Dimensional Systems and Nanostructures (Elsevier Amsterdam) Ausgewählte Publikationen von Christian Schüller   Impressum Letzte Änderung: 08.11.2013 von Webmaster</field>
<field name="important">Physik ? AG Schüller ? Mitarbeiter Physik ? AG Schüller ? Mitarbeiter Christian Schüller Fakultät für Physik Institut für Experimentelle und Angewandte Physik Universität Regensburg D-93040 Regensburg Raum : PHY 2.1.28 Telefon : ++49 / (0)941 / 943 -2078 Sekretariat : ++49 / (0)941 / 943 -2080 (Frau Weiss) FAX : ++49 / (0)941 / 943 -4226 E-mail : christian.schueller@physik.uni-regensburg.de Wissenschaftlicher Werdegang 1985 - 1990 Studium der Physik an der Universität Würzburg 1991 - 1994 Promotion an der Universität Würzburg; Raman-Spektroskopie an 2D-Lochgasen (experimentell); Berechnung von Valenz-Subband-Dispersion und Raman-Streuquerschnitten 1994-2000 Wissenschaftlicher Assistent (C1) in der Arbeitsgruppe von Prof. Dr. D. Heitmann an der Universität Hamburg; Betreuung des Bereiches "Optische Spektroskopie"; Präparation nanostrukturierter Halbleitersysteme auf der Basis von GaAs-AlGaAs-Quantum Wells; Elektronische Raman-Spektroskopie und Photolumineszenz-Spektroskopie an GaAs-Quantenstrukturen 1998 Habilitation an der Universität Hamburg 1998 - 1999 Feodor-Lynen-Stipendiat der Alexander von Humboldt-Stiftung in der Gruppe von Prof. Dr. D. S. Chemla an der University of California at Berkeley und am Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, U.S.A.; Ultrakurzzeit-Spektroskopie an GaAs-AlGaAs-Nanostrukturen im Quanten-Hall-Regime 1999 - 2004 Privatdozent an der Universität Hamburg 2000 - 2004 Heisenberg-Stipendiat der Deutschen Forschungsgemeinschaft; Leitung einer Nachwuchsgruppe 2000 Forschungsaufenthalt am Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, U.S.A. 2004 Ruf auf C3-Professur für Experimentalphysik an der Universität Regensburg Preise und Auszeichnungen 09/1998 Feodor-Lynen-Stipendium der Alexander von Humboldt-Stiftung 03/2000 Heisenberg-Stipendium der Deutschen Forschungsgemeinschaft 03/2000 1. Preis bei der Auszeichnung der besten Lehrenden des Fachbereichs Physik der Universität Hamburg im WS 1999/2000 für die Vorlesung "Nanostrukturierte Halbleitersysteme" 07/2005 1. Preis bei der Auszeichnung der besten Lehrenden der Naturwissenschaftlichen Fakultät II - Physik der Universität Regensburg im WS 2004/2005 für die Vorlesung "Moderne Physik I für Lehramt" 04/2006 Berufung ins Editorial Board der Zeitschrift Physica E, Low-Dimensional Systems and Nanostructures (Elsevier Amsterdam) Ausgewählte Publikationen von Christian Schüller   Impressum Letzte Änderung: 08.11.2013 von Webmaster</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schueller/lehre-e.phtml</field>
<field name="title">Physics ? RG Schüller ? Teaching</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schueller/lehre-e.phtml</field>
<field name="content">Physics ? RG Schüller ? Teaching Physics ? RG Schüller ? Teaching Wintersemester 2013/2014 Physik I für Chemiker und Lehramt mit Unterrichtsfach Physik (T. Korn) Organisation der Vorlesung und Einführung Skript zur Vorlesung: Teil 1 Teil 2 und 3 Teil 4 Übungsblätter: Blatt 1 Blatt 2 Blatt 3 Blatt 4 Mathematische Ergänzungen zur Vorlesung (erstellt v. Patrick Altmann) Von Rechnern der Uni Regensburg aus haben Sie Zugriff auf zur Vorlesung empfohlene Ebooks: W. Demtröder: Experimentalphysik 1 Hinweis: In Übereinstimmung mit dem geltenden Copyright-Gesetz wurden in den auf dieser Seite bereitgestellten Skripten zum Teil Bilder aus den in den Skripten empfohlenen Lehrbüchern und aus anderen, genannten Quellen entnommen. Die Skripten dürfen nur in Verbindung mit den angegebenen Vorlesungen verwendet werden. Eine Weitergabe an Dritte ist nicht zulässig. Skripten (nur für lokale Nutzer): Experimentalphysik II: Elektrodynamik vom Sommersemester 2013: vollständiges Skript Aufbau der Materie I (Quanten-, Atom- und Molekülphysik für LAUP) vom Sommersemester 2011: Kapitel 1, Kapitel 2, Kapitel 3, Kapitel 4, Kapitel 5, Kapitel 6, Kapitel 7, Kapitel 8, Kapitel 9, Zusammenfassung Struktur der Materie I (Atom- und Molekülphysik) vom Sommersemester 2010: Teil I, Teil II, Teil III, Teil IV Struktur der Materie II (Festkörperphysik) vom Wintersemester 2010/2011: Kapitel 1, Kapitel 2, Kapitel 3 und 4, Kapitel 5, Kapitel 6, Kapitel 7, Kapitel 8, Kapitel 9, Kapitel 10 Aufbau der Materie IIa (Festkörperphysik für nichtvertieftes Lehramt) vom Wintersemester 2007/2008: Teil 1, Teil 2, Teil 3, Teil 4 Moderne Physik IIa (Festkörperphysik für vertieftes Lehramt) vom Sommersemester 2011: Teil I, Teil II, Teil III, Teil IV, Teil V, Teil VI, Teil VII, Teil VIII Physik III (Optik) für LA mit Unterrichtsfach Physik und für Molekulare Medizin vom Wintersemester 2012/2013: Kapitel 1, Kapitel 2, Kapitel 3, Kapitel 4   Legal Notice Last modified: 8 th Nov, 2013 by Webmaster</field>
<field name="important">Physics ? RG Schüller ? Teaching Physics ? RG Schüller ? Teaching Wintersemester 2013/2014 Physik I für Chemiker und Lehramt mit Unterrichtsfach Physik (T. Korn) Organisation der Vorlesung und Einführung Skript zur Vorlesung: Teil 1 Teil 2 und 3 Teil 4 Übungsblätter: Blatt 1 Blatt 2 Blatt 3 Blatt 4 Mathematische Ergänzungen zur Vorlesung (erstellt v. Patrick Altmann) Von Rechnern der Uni Regensburg aus haben Sie Zugriff auf zur Vorlesung empfohlene Ebooks: W. Demtröder: Experimentalphysik 1 Hinweis: In Übereinstimmung mit dem geltenden Copyright-Gesetz wurden in den auf dieser Seite bereitgestellten Skripten zum Teil Bilder aus den in den Skripten empfohlenen Lehrbüchern und aus anderen, genannten Quellen entnommen. Die Skripten dürfen nur in Verbindung mit den angegebenen Vorlesungen verwendet werden. Eine Weitergabe an Dritte ist nicht zulässig. Skripten (nur für lokale Nutzer): Experimentalphysik II: Elektrodynamik vom Sommersemester 2013: vollständiges Skript Aufbau der Materie I (Quanten-, Atom- und Molekülphysik für LAUP) vom Sommersemester 2011: Kapitel 1, Kapitel 2, Kapitel 3, Kapitel 4, Kapitel 5, Kapitel 6, Kapitel 7, Kapitel 8, Kapitel 9, Zusammenfassung Struktur der Materie I (Atom- und Molekülphysik) vom Sommersemester 2010: Teil I, Teil II, Teil III, Teil IV Struktur der Materie II (Festkörperphysik) vom Wintersemester 2010/2011: Kapitel 1, Kapitel 2, Kapitel 3 und 4, Kapitel 5, Kapitel 6, Kapitel 7, Kapitel 8, Kapitel 9, Kapitel 10 Aufbau der Materie IIa (Festkörperphysik für nichtvertieftes Lehramt) vom Wintersemester 2007/2008: Teil 1, Teil 2, Teil 3, Teil 4 Moderne Physik IIa (Festkörperphysik für vertieftes Lehramt) vom Sommersemester 2011: Teil I, Teil II, Teil III, Teil IV, Teil V, Teil VI, Teil VII, Teil VIII Physik III (Optik) für LA mit Unterrichtsfach Physik und für Molekulare Medizin vom Wintersemester 2012/2013: Kapitel 1, Kapitel 2, Kapitel 3, Kapitel 4   Legal Notice Last modified: 8 th Nov, 2013 by Webmaster</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schueller/lit.phtml</field>
<field name="title">Physik ? AG Schüller ? Publikationen</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schueller/lit.phtml</field>
<field name="content">Physik ? AG Schüller ? Publikationen Physik ? AG Schüller ? Publikationen Ausgewählte Publikationen von Christian Schüller Monographie Christian Schüller: ?Inelastic Light Scattering of Semiconductor Nanostructures, Fundamentals and Recent Advances?, Springer Tracts in Modern Physics Vol. 219 (Springer Berlin, Heidelberg 2006).   Artikel in Letters und Rapid Communications: F. Oberhuber, S. Blien, S. Heydrich, F. Yaghobian, T. Korn, C. Schüller, C. Strunk, D. Weiss, and J. Eroms: ?Weak localization and Raman study of anisotropically etched graphene antidots ?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 103, 143111 (2013).   G. Plechinger, S. Heydrich, J. Eroms, D. Weiss, C. Schüller, and T. Korn, ?Raman spectroscopy of the interlayer shear mode in few-layer MoS2 flakes ?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 101, 101906 (2012).   M. Hirmer, M. Hirmer, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, T. Korn, R. Winkler, and C. Schüller, ?Fingerprints of the Anisotropic Spin-Split Hole Dispersion in Resonant Inelastic Light Scattering in Two-Dimensional Hole Systems?, Phys. Rev. Lett. 107, 216805 (2011).   T. Korn, S. Heydrich, M. Hirmer, J. Schmutzler, and C. Schüller ?Low-temperature photocarrier dynamics in monolayer MoS2?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 99, 102109 (2011).   R. Völkl, M. Griesbeck, S. A. Tarasenko, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, C. Schüller, and T. Korn ?Spin dephasing and photoinduced spin diffusion in a high-mobility two-dimensional electron system embedded in a GaAs-(Al,Ga)As quantum well grown in the [110] direction?, Phys. Rev. B 83, 241306(R) (2011).   S. Heydrich, M. Hirmer, C. Preis, T. Korn, J. Eroms, D. Weiss, and C. Schüller ?Scanning Raman spectroscopy of graphene antidot lattices: Evidence for systematic p-type doping ?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 97, 043113 (2010).   M. Griesbeck, M. M. Glazov, T. Korn, E. Ya. Sherman, D. Waller, C. Reichl, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller: ?Cyclotron effect on coherent spin precession of two-dimensional electrons?, Phys. Rev. B, 80, 241314(R) (2009).   Ch. Strelow, M. Sauer, S. Fehringer, T. Korn, C. Schüller, A. Stemmann, Ch. Heyn, D. Heitmann, and T. Kipp ?Time-resolved studies of a rolled-up semiconductor microtube laser?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 95, 221115(2009).   V. V. Belkov, P. Olbrich, S. A. Tarasenko, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, T. Korn, C. Schüller, D. Weiss, W. Prettl, and S. D. Ganichev: ?Symmetry and spin dephasing in (110)-grown quantum wells?, Phys. Rev. Lett. 100, 176806 (2008).   A. Wirthmann, X. Hui, N. Mecking, Y. S. Gui, T. Chakraborty, C.-M. Hu, M. Reinwald, C. Schüller, and W. Wegscheider: ?Broadband electrical detection of spin excitations in GaMnAs using a photovoltage technique?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 92, 232106 (2008).   D. Stich, J. Zhou, T. Korn, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, M.W. Wu, and C. Schüller: ?Effect of Initial Spin Polarization on Spin Dephasing and the Electron g Factor in a High-Mobility Two-Dimensional Electron System?, Phys. Rev. Lett. 98, 176401 (2007).   R. Krahne, G. Chilla, C. Schüller, L. Carbone, S. Kudera, G. Mannarini, L. Manna, D. Heitmann, and R. Cingolani: ?Confinement Effects on Optical Phonons in Polar Tetrapod Nanocrystals Detected by Resonant Inelastic Light Scattering?, Nano Lett. 6, 478 (2006).   T. Kipp, K. Petter, D. Heitmann, Ch. Heyn, and C. Schüller: ?Broadband emission and low absorption of AlGaAs alloy quantum well microdisks?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 84, 1477 (2004).   T. Brocke, M.-T. Bootsmann, M. Tews, B. Wunsch, D. Pfannkuche, Ch. Heyn, W. Hansen, D. Heitmann, and C. Schüller: ?Spectroscopy of Few-Electron Collective Excitations in Charge-Tunable Artificial Atoms?, Phys. Rev. Lett. 91, 257401 (2003).   C. Schüller, K.-B. Broocks, P. Schröter, Ch. Heyn, D. Heitmann, M. Bichler, W. Wegscheider, T. Chakraborty, and V. M. Apalkov: ?Optical probing of a fractionally-charged quasihole in an incompressible liquid?, Phys. Rev. Lett. 91, 116403 (2003).   M.-T. Bootsmann, C.-M. Hu, Ch. Heyn, D. Heitmann, and C. Schüller: ?Acoustic plasmons and indirect intersubband excitations in tunneling-coupled GaAs-AlGaAs double quantum wells?, Phys. Rev. B 67, 121309(R) (2003).   K.-B. Broocks, P. Schröter, D. Heitmann, Ch. Heyn, C. Schüller, M. Bichler, and W. Wegscheider: ?Anomalous dispersion of charged excitons in dilute two-dimensional electron systems at low temperatures?, Phys. Rev. B, 66, 041309(R) (2002).   C. Schüller, K.-B. Broocks, Ch. Heyn, and D. Heitmann: ? Oscillator strengths of dark charged excitons at low electron filling factors?, Phys. Rev. B 65, 081301(R) (2002).   K. Petter, T. Kipp, D. Heitmann, Ch. Heyn, and C. Schüller: ?Fabrication of large periodic arrays of AlGaAs microdisks by laser-interference lithography and selective etching?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 81, 592 (2002).   N. A. Fromer, C. Schüller, D. S. Chemla, T. V. Shahbazyan, I. E. Perakis, K. Maranowski, and A. C. Gossard: ?Electronic Dephasing in the Quantum Hall Regime?, Phys. Rev. Lett. 83, 4646-4649 (1999).   C. Schüller, K. Keller, G. Biese, E. Ulrichs, L. Rolf, C. Steinebach, D. Heitmann, and K. Eberl: ?Quasiatomic Fine Structure and Selection Rules in Quantum Dots?, Phys. Rev. Lett. 80, 2673-2676 (1998).   E. Ulrichs, G. Biese, C. Steinebach, C. Schüller, and D.  Heitmann: ?One-dimensional plasmons in magnetic fields?, Phys. Rev. B 56, R12760-R12763 (1997).   C. Schüller, G. Biese, K. Keller, C. Steinebach, D. Heitmann, P. Grambow, and K.  Eberl: ?Single-particle excitations and many-particle interactions in quantum wires and dots?, Phys. Rev. B 54, R17304-R17307 (1996).   C. Steinebach, R. Krahne, G. Biese, C. Schüller, D. Heitmann, and K. Eberl: ?Internal electron-electron interactions in one-dimensional systems detected by Raman spectroscopy" ,  Phys. Rev. B 54, R14281-R14284 (1996). Artikel in Physical Review B: C. Schönhuber, M. P. Walser, G. Salis, C. Reichl, W. Wegscheider, T. Korn, and C. Schüller: ?Inelastic light-scattering from spin-density excitations in the regime of the persistent spin helix in a GaAs-AlGaAs quantum well?, Phys. Rev. B 89, 085406 (2014).   K. Korzekwa, C. Gradl, M. Kugler, S. Furthmeier, M. Griesbeck, M. Hirmer, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, T. Kuhn, C. Schüller, T. Korn, and P. Machnikowski: ?Spin dynamics in p-doped semiconductor nanostructures subject to a magnetic field tilted from the Voigt geometry?, Phys. Rev. B 88, 155303 (2013).   M. Griesbeck, M. M. Glazov, E. Ya. Sherman, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, C. Schüller, and T. Korn: ?Strongly anisotropic spin relaxation revealed by resonant spin amplification in (110) GaAs quantum wells?, Phys. Rev. B 85, 085313 (2012).   M. Kugler, K. Korzekwa, P. Machnikowski, C. Gradl, S. Furthmeier, M. Griesbeck, M. Hirmer, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, T. Kuhn, C. Schüller, and T. Korn: ?Decoherence-assisted initialization of a resident hole spin polarization in a p-doped semiconductor quantum well?, Phys. Rev. B 84, 085327 (2011).   V. Lechner, L. E. Golub, F. Lomakina, V. V. Belkov, P. Olbrich, S. Stachel, I. Caspers, M. Griesbeck, M. Kugler, M. J. Hirmer, T. Korn, C. Schüller, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and S. D. Ganichev: ?Spin and orbital mechanisms of the magnetogyrotropic photogalvanic effects in GaAs/AlxGa1-xAs quantum well structures?, Phys. Rev. B 83, 155313 (2011).   M. Kugler, T. Andlauer, T. Korn, A. Wagner, S. Fehringer, R. Schulz, M. Kubova, C. Gerl, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, P. Vogl, and C. Schüller: ?Gate control of low-temperature spin dynamics in two-dimensional hole systems?, Phys. Rev. B 80, 035325 (2009).   P. Olbrich, J. Allerdings, V. V. Belkov, S. A. Tarasenko, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, T. Korn, C. Schüller, D. Weiss, and S. D. Ganichev: ?Magnetogyrotropic photogalvanic effect and spin dephasing in (110)-grown GaAs/AlxGa1-xAs quantum well structures?, Phys. Rev. B 79, 245329 (2009).   J. H. Jiang, Y. Zhou, T. Korn, C. Schüller, and M. W. Wu: ?Electron spin relaxation in paramagnetic Ga(Mn)As quantum wells?, Phys. Rev. B 79, 155201(2009).   D. Stich, J. H. Jiang, T. Korn, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, M.W. Wu, and C. Schüller: ?Detection of large magneto-anisotropy of electron spin desphasing in a high mobility two-dimensional electron system in a [001] GaAs/AlGaAs quantum well?, Phys. Rev. B 76, 073309 (2007).   D. Stich, J. Zhou, T. Korn, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, M.W. Wu, and C. Schüller: ?Dependence of spin dephasing on initial spin polarization in a high-mobility two-dimensional electron system?, Phys. Rev. B 76, 205301 (2007).   A. F. Dethlefsen, Ch. Heyn, D. Heitmann, and C. Schüller: ?Confined acoustic and optical plasmons in double-layered quantum-wire arrays with strong tunneling?, Phys. Rev. B 73, 193307 (2006).   V. M. Apalkov T. Chakraborty, and C. Schüller: ?Spin transitions in an incompressible liquid Coulomb-coupled to a quantum dot?, Phys. Rev. B 73, 073310 (2006).   N. A. Fromer, C. Schüller, D. S. Chemla, I. E. Perakis, D. Driscoll, and A. C. Gossard: ?Investigation of Coulomb correlations in a two-dimensional electron gas in large magnetic fields?, Phys. Rev. B 66, 205314 (2002).   C.-M. Hu, C. Schüller, and D. Heitmann: ?Space asymmetry induced plasmon mode-mixing and anti-crossing in coupled bilayer structures?, Phys. Rev. B 64, 073303-073306 (2001).   T. Kipp, L. Rolf, C. Schüller, D. Endler, Ch. Heyn, and D. Heitmann: ?Selectively Enhanced Inelastic Light Scattering of Electronic Excitations in a Semiconductor Microcavity?, Phys. Rev. B 63, 195304-195307 (2001).   C. Steinebach, C. Schüller, and D. Heitmann: ?Single-particle-like states in few-electron quantum dots?, Phys. Rev. B 61, 15600-15603 (2000).   C. Steinebach, C. Schüller, and D. Heitmann: ?Resonant Raman scattering of quantum dots?, Phys. Rev. B 59, 10240-10245 (1999).   C. Steinebach, C. Schüller, G. Biese, D. Heitmann, and K. Eberl: ?Observation of finite-thickness effects on the spin-density excitations in quantum wires?, Phys. Rev. B 57, 1703-1706 (1998).   C. Schüller, R. Krahne, G. Biese, C. Steinebach, E. Ulrichs, D. Heitmann, and K. Eberl: ?Multiple cyclotron resonances in GaAs-AlGaAs quantum wells detected by resonant inelastic light scattering?, Phys. Rev. B 56, 1037-1040 (1997).   G. Biese, C. Schüller, K. Keller, C. Steinebach, D. Heitmann, P. Grambow, and K. Eberl: ?Coupling of lateral and vertical electron motion in GaAs-AlGaAs quantum wires and dots?, Phys. Rev. B 53, 9565-9567 (1996).   C. Schüller, J. Kraus, G. Schaack, G. Weimann, and K. Panzlaff: ?Electronic Raman scattering in p-doped GaAs/GaAlAs quantum-well structures: Scattering mechanisms and many-particle interactions?, Phys. Rev. B 50, 18387-18394 (1994).   M. Kirchner, C. Schüller, J. Kraus, G. Schaack, K. Panzlaff, and G. Weimann: ?Consequences of subband nonparabolicity on intersubband excitations in p-doped GaAs/AlGaAs quantum wells?, Phys. Rev. B 47, 9706-9709 (1993). Weitere referierte Journale: F. Yaghobian, T. Korn, and C. Schüller: ?Frequency Shift in Graphene-Enhanced Raman Signal of Molecules?, ChemPhysChem 13, 4271 (2012).   G. Plechinger, F.-X. Schrettenbrunner, J. Eroms, D. Weiss, C. Schüller, and T. Korn ?Low-temperature photoluminescence of oxide-covered single-layer MoS2?, physica status solidi (RRL) - Rapid Research Letters (2012) / DOI 10.1002/pssr.201105589   T. Korn, M. Kugler, M. Griesbeck, R. Schulz, A. Wagner, M. Hirmer, C. Gerl, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller ?Engineering ultralong spin coherence in two-dimensional hole systems at low temperatures ?, New J. Phys. 12, 043003 (2010).   R. Schulz, T. Korn, U. Wurstbauer, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller: ?Ultrafast optical studies of diffusion barriers between ferromagnetic Ga(Mn)As layers and non-magnetic quantum wells?, Physica E 40, 2163 (2007).   T. Korn, D. Stich, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller: ?Large in-plane spin-dephasing anisotropy in a [001]-grown two-dimensional electron system?, Physica E 40, 1542 (2008).   D. Stich, T. Korn, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller: ?Increase of spin dephasing times in a 2D electron system with degree of initial spin polarization?, Physica E 40, 1545 (2008).   K.-B. Broocks, B. Su, P. Schröter, Ch. Heyn, D. Heitmann, W. Wegscheider, V. M. Apalkov, T. Chakraborty, I. E. Perakis, and C. Schüller: ?Linear and ultrafast optical spectroscopy in the regime of the quantum Hall effect?, phys. Stat. sol. B 245, 321 (2008).   R. Krahne, G. Chilla, C. Schüller, S. Kudera, D. Tari, M. De Giorgi, D. Heitmann, R. Cingolani, and L. Manna: ?Shape Dependence of the Scattering Processes of Optical Phonons in Colloidal Nanocrystals Detected by Raman Spectroscopy?, J. Nanoelectron. Optoelectron. 1, 107 (2006).   T. Korn, F. Giesen, J. Podbielski, D. Ravlic, C. Schueller, and D. Grundler: ?Time-resolved study of the increased magnetization precession frequency in Fe wires?, Journal of Magnetism and Magnetic Materials, JMMM, 285, 240 (2005).   T. Korn, F. Müller, D. Grundler, and C. Schüller: ?Characterization of Permalloy films on high-bandwidth striplines?, Journal of Magnetism and Magnetic Materials, JMMM, 272-276, E1341 (2004).   C. Schüller, K.-B. Broocks, P. Schröter, Ch. Heyn, D. Heitmann, V. Apalkov, T. Chakraborty, M. Bichler, and W. Wegscheider: ?How to Probe a Fractionally-Charged Quasihole??, Physica E 22, 131 (2004).   T. Brocke, M.-T. Bootsmann, B. Wunsch, M. Tews, D. Pfannkuche, Ch. Heyn, W. Hansen, D. Heitmann, and C. Schüller: ?Inelastic Light Scattering on Few-Electron Quantum-Dot Atoms?, Physica E 22, 478 (2004).   T. Kipp, K. Petter, Ch. Heyn, D. Heitmann, and C. Schüller: ?Spectroscopy of Individual AlGaAs Microdisks in Large Periodic Arrays?, Physica E 21, 830 (2004).   T. Kipp, L. Rolf, C. Schüller, D. Endler, Ch. Heyn, and D. Heitmann: ?Optical double resonance of electronic Raman scattering in a AlAs-AlGaAs microcavity?, Physica E 13, 408 (2002).   N. A. Fromer, C. Schüller, D. S. Chemla, T. V. Shahbazyan, I. E. Perakis, D. Driscoll, and A. C. Gossard: ?Femtosecond dynamics of inter-Landau level excitations of a two-dimensional electron gas in the quantum Hall regime?, Physica E 12, 550 (2002).   K.-B. Broocks, T. Ebeling, L. Karsten, C. Schüller, Ch. Heyn, and D. Heitmann: ?Electric field-dependent Zeeman splitting of excitons in diluted two-dimensional electron systems?, phys. stat. sol. (b) 227, 339-342 (2001).   C. Steinebach, C. Schüller, E. Ulrichs, Ch. Heyn, and D. Heitmann: ?Resonant inelastic light scattering on GaAs-AlGaAs quantum dots?, phys. stat. sol. (b) 224, 97-100 (2001)..   N. A. Fromer, C. Schüller, D. S. Chemla, K. Maranowski, and A. C. Gossard: ?Dephasing in the presence of a two-dimensional electron gas at high magnetic fields?, Physica E 6, 210-213 (2000).   E. Ulrichs, C. Steinebach, C. Schüller, Ch. Heyn, and D. Heitmann: ?Coulomb-interaction induced crossover from confined to bulk quantum-dot states in a magnetic field?, Physica E 6, 364-366 (2000).   D. Heitmann, V. Gudmundsson, L. Rolf, C. Schüller, C. Steinebach, and E. Ulrichs, ?Spectroscopy of few-electron quantum dots?, Acta Physica Polonica A 96, 545 (1999).   G. Biese, E. Ulrichs, L. Rolf, C. Schüller, C. Steinebach, S. Bargstädt-Franke, Ch. Heyn, D. Heitmann, and K. Eberl: ?Edge spin-density modes in quantum dots in a magnetic field?, Physica E 2, 619-622 (1998).   E. Ulrichs, G. Biese, C. Steinebach, C. Schüller, D. Heitmann, and K. Eberl: ?Skipping-orbit electron motion in GaAs-AlGaAs quantum wires detected by Raman spectroscopy?, phys. stat. sol. (a) 164, 277-280 (1997).   F. Rademacher, H. Eggers, T. O. Wiegard, C. Schüller, S. Bargstädt-Franke, Ch. Heyn, K. Eberl, and D. Heitmann: ?Magneto-optical investigation of excitons in narrow GaAs-AlGaAs quantum wires?, phys. stat. sol. (a) 164, 325-329 (1997).   G. Biese, C. Schüller, T. Kurth, D. Heitmann, P. Grambow, and K. Eberl: ?Combined 1D-2D intersubband excitations and 1D single-particle spectrum in narrow quantum wires?, Surf. Sci. 361/362, 797-800 (1996).   C. Schüller, J. Kraus, V. Latussek, G. Schaack, and J. K. Ebeling: ?Collective intersubband excitations in p-doped GaAs-AlGaAs multiple quantum wells?, Solid State Commun. 81, 3-7 (1992).   J. Kraus, P. Ils, C. Schüller, G. Schaack, J. K. Ebeling, W. Schlapp, and G. Weimann: ?The coupling of intersubband transitions and the quantum-well LO phonon in p-doped GaAs-GaAlAs multiple quantum wells?, J. Phys. Condens. Matter 3, 8267-8279 (1991).   M. Dahl, P. Ils, J. Kraus, B. Müller, G. Schaack, C. Schüller, J. K. Ebeling, and G. Weimann: ?Hole-intersubband excitations and luminescence transitions in p-doped GaAs-AlGaAs multiple quantum wells?, Superlatt. and Microstruc. 9, 77-81 (1991). Eingeladene Übersichtsartikel: T. Korn, G. Plechinger, S. Heydrich, F.-X. Schrettenbrunner, J. Eroms, D. Weiss,and C. Schüller: ?Optical Characterization, Low-Temperature Photoluminescence, and Photocarrier Dynamics in MoS2 ?, Springer Lecture Notes in Nanoscale Science and Technology 21, 217-236 (2014).   T. Korn, D. Stich, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller (invited article): ?Spin Dynamics in high-mobility two-dimensional electron systems?, Advances in Solid State Physics, Vol. 48, Ed. R. Haug (Springer Berlin, Heidelberg, New York, 2009).   C. Schüller, K.-B. Broocks, P. Schröter, C. Heyn, D. Heitmann, M. Bichler, W. Wegscheider, V. M. Apalkov, and T. Chakraborty (invited article): ?Charged Excitons in the Quantum Hall regime?, Acta Physica Polonica 106, 341 (2004).   Christian Schüller, Kay-Birger Broocks, Patrick Schröter, Christian Heyn, Detlef Heitmann, Max Bichler, Werner Wegscheider, Vadim Apalkov, and Tapash Chakraborty (invited article): ?Charged Excitons in the Quantum Hall Regime: Optical Probe of Fractionally Charged Quasiholes?, Advances in Solid State Physics, Vol. 44, Ed. B. Kramer (Springer Berlin, Heidelberg, New York, 2004).   Christian Schüller (invited article): ?Quantum Dots: Inelastic Light Scattering on Electronic Excitations?, Marcel Dekkers's Encyclopedia of Nanoscience and Nanotechnology, Marcel Dekker Inc., New York 2004.   C. Schüller, C. Steinebach, and D. Heitmann (invited article) ?Spin-and Charge-Density Excitations in Quantum Dots: A Raman Study?, Solid State Commun. 119, 323-331 (2001).   Christian Schüller, Ilias E. Perakis, Neil A. Fromer, and Daniel S. Chemla (invited book chapter) ?Ultrafast Spectroscopy in the Quantum Hall Regime?, in: Nonequilibrium Physics at Short Time Scales: Formation of Correlations, ed. by Klaus Morawetz (Springer Berlin, Heidelberg, New York, 2004) 209-230.   Christian Schüller (invited article) ?Raman Spectroscopy of Quantum Dots?, Festkörperprobleme, Advances in Solid State Physics 38, 167-181 (1999).   Christian Schüller (invited article) ?Raman Spectroscopy of Quantum Wires and Dots: Magnetoplasmons   and Edge-Spin-Density Modes?, Proceedings of the 10th International Winterschool on New Developments in Solid State Physics: New Frontiers in Low-Dimensional Physics, Mauterndorf, Austria, 23-27 February 1998, Physica E 3, 121-128 (1998).     Impressum Letzte Änderung: 07.02.2014 von Webmaster</field>
<field name="important">Physik ? AG Schüller ? Publikationen Physik ? AG Schüller ? Publikationen Ausgewählte Publikationen von Christian Schüller Monographie Christian Schüller: ?Inelastic Light Scattering of Semiconductor Nanostructures, Fundamentals and Recent Advances?, Springer Tracts in Modern Physics Vol. 219 (Springer Berlin, Heidelberg 2006).   Artikel in Letters und Rapid Communications: F. Oberhuber, S. Blien, S. Heydrich, F. Yaghobian, T. Korn, C. Schüller, C. Strunk, D. Weiss, and J. Eroms: ?Weak localization and Raman study of anisotropically etched graphene antidots ?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 103, 143111 (2013).   G. Plechinger, S. Heydrich, J. Eroms, D. Weiss, C. Schüller, and T. Korn, ?Raman spectroscopy of the interlayer shear mode in few-layer MoS2 flakes ?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 101, 101906 (2012).   M. Hirmer, M. Hirmer, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, T. Korn, R. Winkler, and C. Schüller, ?Fingerprints of the Anisotropic Spin-Split Hole Dispersion in Resonant Inelastic Light Scattering in Two-Dimensional Hole Systems?, Phys. Rev. Lett. 107, 216805 (2011).   T. Korn, S. Heydrich, M. Hirmer, J. Schmutzler, and C. Schüller ?Low-temperature photocarrier dynamics in monolayer MoS2?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 99, 102109 (2011).   R. Völkl, M. Griesbeck, S. A. Tarasenko, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, C. Schüller, and T. Korn ?Spin dephasing and photoinduced spin diffusion in a high-mobility two-dimensional electron system embedded in a GaAs-(Al,Ga)As quantum well grown in the [110] direction?, Phys. Rev. B 83, 241306(R) (2011).   S. Heydrich, M. Hirmer, C. Preis, T. Korn, J. Eroms, D. Weiss, and C. Schüller ?Scanning Raman spectroscopy of graphene antidot lattices: Evidence for systematic p-type doping ?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 97, 043113 (2010).   M. Griesbeck, M. M. Glazov, T. Korn, E. Ya. Sherman, D. Waller, C. Reichl, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller: ?Cyclotron effect on coherent spin precession of two-dimensional electrons?, Phys. Rev. B, 80, 241314(R) (2009).   Ch. Strelow, M. Sauer, S. Fehringer, T. Korn, C. Schüller, A. Stemmann, Ch. Heyn, D. Heitmann, and T. Kipp ?Time-resolved studies of a rolled-up semiconductor microtube laser?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 95, 221115(2009).   V. V. Belkov, P. Olbrich, S. A. Tarasenko, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, T. Korn, C. Schüller, D. Weiss, W. Prettl, and S. D. Ganichev: ?Symmetry and spin dephasing in (110)-grown quantum wells?, Phys. Rev. Lett. 100, 176806 (2008).   A. Wirthmann, X. Hui, N. Mecking, Y. S. Gui, T. Chakraborty, C.-M. Hu, M. Reinwald, C. Schüller, and W. Wegscheider: ?Broadband electrical detection of spin excitations in GaMnAs using a photovoltage technique?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 92, 232106 (2008).   D. Stich, J. Zhou, T. Korn, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, M.W. Wu, and C. Schüller: ?Effect of Initial Spin Polarization on Spin Dephasing and the Electron g Factor in a High-Mobility Two-Dimensional Electron System?, Phys. Rev. Lett. 98, 176401 (2007).   R. Krahne, G. Chilla, C. Schüller, L. Carbone, S. Kudera, G. Mannarini, L. Manna, D. Heitmann, and R. Cingolani: ?Confinement Effects on Optical Phonons in Polar Tetrapod Nanocrystals Detected by Resonant Inelastic Light Scattering?, Nano Lett. 6, 478 (2006).   T. Kipp, K. Petter, D. Heitmann, Ch. Heyn, and C. Schüller: ?Broadband emission and low absorption of AlGaAs alloy quantum well microdisks?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 84, 1477 (2004).   T. Brocke, M.-T. Bootsmann, M. Tews, B. Wunsch, D. Pfannkuche, Ch. Heyn, W. Hansen, D. Heitmann, and C. Schüller: ?Spectroscopy of Few-Electron Collective Excitations in Charge-Tunable Artificial Atoms?, Phys. Rev. Lett. 91, 257401 (2003).   C. Schüller, K.-B. Broocks, P. Schröter, Ch. Heyn, D. Heitmann, M. Bichler, W. Wegscheider, T. Chakraborty, and V. M. Apalkov: ?Optical probing of a fractionally-charged quasihole in an incompressible liquid?, Phys. Rev. Lett. 91, 116403 (2003).   M.-T. Bootsmann, C.-M. Hu, Ch. Heyn, D. Heitmann, and C. Schüller: ?Acoustic plasmons and indirect intersubband excitations in tunneling-coupled GaAs-AlGaAs double quantum wells?, Phys. Rev. B 67, 121309(R) (2003).   K.-B. Broocks, P. Schröter, D. Heitmann, Ch. Heyn, C. Schüller, M. Bichler, and W. Wegscheider: ?Anomalous dispersion of charged excitons in dilute two-dimensional electron systems at low temperatures?, Phys. Rev. B, 66, 041309(R) (2002).   C. Schüller, K.-B. Broocks, Ch. Heyn, and D. Heitmann: ? Oscillator strengths of dark charged excitons at low electron filling factors?, Phys. Rev. B 65, 081301(R) (2002).   K. Petter, T. Kipp, D. Heitmann, Ch. Heyn, and C. Schüller: ?Fabrication of large periodic arrays of AlGaAs microdisks by laser-interference lithography and selective etching?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 81, 592 (2002).   N. A. Fromer, C. Schüller, D. S. Chemla, T. V. Shahbazyan, I. E. Perakis, K. Maranowski, and A. C. Gossard: ?Electronic Dephasing in the Quantum Hall Regime?, Phys. Rev. Lett. 83, 4646-4649 (1999).   C. Schüller, K. Keller, G. Biese, E. Ulrichs, L. Rolf, C. Steinebach, D. Heitmann, and K. Eberl: ?Quasiatomic Fine Structure and Selection Rules in Quantum Dots?, Phys. Rev. Lett. 80, 2673-2676 (1998).   E. Ulrichs, G. Biese, C. Steinebach, C. Schüller, and D.  Heitmann: ?One-dimensional plasmons in magnetic fields?, Phys. Rev. B 56, R12760-R12763 (1997).   C. Schüller, G. Biese, K. Keller, C. Steinebach, D. Heitmann, P. Grambow, and K.  Eberl: ?Single-particle excitations and many-particle interactions in quantum wires and dots?, Phys. Rev. B 54, R17304-R17307 (1996).   C. Steinebach, R. Krahne, G. Biese, C. Schüller, D. Heitmann, and K. Eberl: ?Internal electron-electron interactions in one-dimensional systems detected by Raman spectroscopy" ,  Phys. Rev. B 54, R14281-R14284 (1996). Artikel in Physical Review B: C. Schönhuber, M. P. Walser, G. Salis, C. Reichl, W. Wegscheider, T. Korn, and C. Schüller: ?Inelastic light-scattering from spin-density excitations in the regime of the persistent spin helix in a GaAs-AlGaAs quantum well?, Phys. Rev. B 89, 085406 (2014).   K. Korzekwa, C. Gradl, M. Kugler, S. Furthmeier, M. Griesbeck, M. Hirmer, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, T. Kuhn, C. Schüller, T. Korn, and P. Machnikowski: ?Spin dynamics in p-doped semiconductor nanostructures subject to a magnetic field tilted from the Voigt geometry?, Phys. Rev. B 88, 155303 (2013).   M. Griesbeck, M. M. Glazov, E. Ya. Sherman, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, C. Schüller, and T. Korn: ?Strongly anisotropic spin relaxation revealed by resonant spin amplification in (110) GaAs quantum wells?, Phys. Rev. B 85, 085313 (2012).   M. Kugler, K. Korzekwa, P. Machnikowski, C. Gradl, S. Furthmeier, M. Griesbeck, M. Hirmer, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, T. Kuhn, C. Schüller, and T. Korn: ?Decoherence-assisted initialization of a resident hole spin polarization in a p-doped semiconductor quantum well?, Phys. Rev. B 84, 085327 (2011).   V. Lechner, L. E. Golub, F. Lomakina, V. V. Belkov, P. Olbrich, S. Stachel, I. Caspers, M. Griesbeck, M. Kugler, M. J. Hirmer, T. Korn, C. Schüller, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and S. D. Ganichev: ?Spin and orbital mechanisms of the magnetogyrotropic photogalvanic effects in GaAs/AlxGa1-xAs quantum well structures?, Phys. Rev. B 83, 155313 (2011).   M. Kugler, T. Andlauer, T. Korn, A. Wagner, S. Fehringer, R. Schulz, M. Kubova, C. Gerl, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, P. Vogl, and C. Schüller: ?Gate control of low-temperature spin dynamics in two-dimensional hole systems?, Phys. Rev. B 80, 035325 (2009).   P. Olbrich, J. Allerdings, V. V. Belkov, S. A. Tarasenko, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, T. Korn, C. Schüller, D. Weiss, and S. D. Ganichev: ?Magnetogyrotropic photogalvanic effect and spin dephasing in (110)-grown GaAs/AlxGa1-xAs quantum well structures?, Phys. Rev. B 79, 245329 (2009).   J. H. Jiang, Y. Zhou, T. Korn, C. Schüller, and M. W. Wu: ?Electron spin relaxation in paramagnetic Ga(Mn)As quantum wells?, Phys. Rev. B 79, 155201(2009).   D. Stich, J. H. Jiang, T. Korn, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, M.W. Wu, and C. Schüller: ?Detection of large magneto-anisotropy of electron spin desphasing in a high mobility two-dimensional electron system in a [001] GaAs/AlGaAs quantum well?, Phys. Rev. B 76, 073309 (2007).   D. Stich, J. Zhou, T. Korn, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, M.W. Wu, and C. Schüller: ?Dependence of spin dephasing on initial spin polarization in a high-mobility two-dimensional electron system?, Phys. Rev. B 76, 205301 (2007).   A. F. Dethlefsen, Ch. Heyn, D. Heitmann, and C. Schüller: ?Confined acoustic and optical plasmons in double-layered quantum-wire arrays with strong tunneling?, Phys. Rev. B 73, 193307 (2006).   V. M. Apalkov T. Chakraborty, and C. Schüller: ?Spin transitions in an incompressible liquid Coulomb-coupled to a quantum dot?, Phys. Rev. B 73, 073310 (2006).   N. A. Fromer, C. Schüller, D. S. Chemla, I. E. Perakis, D. Driscoll, and A. C. Gossard: ?Investigation of Coulomb correlations in a two-dimensional electron gas in large magnetic fields?, Phys. Rev. B 66, 205314 (2002).   C.-M. Hu, C. Schüller, and D. Heitmann: ?Space asymmetry induced plasmon mode-mixing and anti-crossing in coupled bilayer structures?, Phys. Rev. B 64, 073303-073306 (2001).   T. Kipp, L. Rolf, C. Schüller, D. Endler, Ch. Heyn, and D. Heitmann: ?Selectively Enhanced Inelastic Light Scattering of Electronic Excitations in a Semiconductor Microcavity?, Phys. Rev. B 63, 195304-195307 (2001).   C. Steinebach, C. Schüller, and D. Heitmann: ?Single-particle-like states in few-electron quantum dots?, Phys. Rev. B 61, 15600-15603 (2000).   C. Steinebach, C. Schüller, and D. Heitmann: ?Resonant Raman scattering of quantum dots?, Phys. Rev. B 59, 10240-10245 (1999).   C. Steinebach, C. Schüller, G. Biese, D. Heitmann, and K. Eberl: ?Observation of finite-thickness effects on the spin-density excitations in quantum wires?, Phys. Rev. B 57, 1703-1706 (1998).   C. Schüller, R. Krahne, G. Biese, C. Steinebach, E. Ulrichs, D. Heitmann, and K. Eberl: ?Multiple cyclotron resonances in GaAs-AlGaAs quantum wells detected by resonant inelastic light scattering?, Phys. Rev. B 56, 1037-1040 (1997).   G. Biese, C. Schüller, K. Keller, C. Steinebach, D. Heitmann, P. Grambow, and K. Eberl: ?Coupling of lateral and vertical electron motion in GaAs-AlGaAs quantum wires and dots?, Phys. Rev. B 53, 9565-9567 (1996).   C. Schüller, J. Kraus, G. Schaack, G. Weimann, and K. Panzlaff: ?Electronic Raman scattering in p-doped GaAs/GaAlAs quantum-well structures: Scattering mechanisms and many-particle interactions?, Phys. Rev. B 50, 18387-18394 (1994).   M. Kirchner, C. Schüller, J. Kraus, G. Schaack, K. Panzlaff, and G. Weimann: ?Consequences of subband nonparabolicity on intersubband excitations in p-doped GaAs/AlGaAs quantum wells?, Phys. Rev. B 47, 9706-9709 (1993). Weitere referierte Journale: F. Yaghobian, T. Korn, and C. Schüller: ?Frequency Shift in Graphene-Enhanced Raman Signal of Molecules?, ChemPhysChem 13, 4271 (2012).   G. Plechinger, F.-X. Schrettenbrunner, J. Eroms, D. Weiss, C. Schüller, and T. Korn ?Low-temperature photoluminescence of oxide-covered single-layer MoS2?, physica status solidi (RRL) - Rapid Research Letters (2012) / DOI 10.1002/pssr.201105589   T. Korn, M. Kugler, M. Griesbeck, R. Schulz, A. Wagner, M. Hirmer, C. Gerl, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller ?Engineering ultralong spin coherence in two-dimensional hole systems at low temperatures ?, New J. Phys. 12, 043003 (2010).   R. Schulz, T. Korn, U. Wurstbauer, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller: ?Ultrafast optical studies of diffusion barriers between ferromagnetic Ga(Mn)As layers and non-magnetic quantum wells?, Physica E 40, 2163 (2007).   T. Korn, D. Stich, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller: ?Large in-plane spin-dephasing anisotropy in a [001]-grown two-dimensional electron system?, Physica E 40, 1542 (2008).   D. Stich, T. Korn, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller: ?Increase of spin dephasing times in a 2D electron system with degree of initial spin polarization?, Physica E 40, 1545 (2008).   K.-B. Broocks, B. Su, P. Schröter, Ch. Heyn, D. Heitmann, W. Wegscheider, V. M. Apalkov, T. Chakraborty, I. E. Perakis, and C. Schüller: ?Linear and ultrafast optical spectroscopy in the regime of the quantum Hall effect?, phys. Stat. sol. B 245, 321 (2008).   R. Krahne, G. Chilla, C. Schüller, S. Kudera, D. Tari, M. De Giorgi, D. Heitmann, R. Cingolani, and L. Manna: ?Shape Dependence of the Scattering Processes of Optical Phonons in Colloidal Nanocrystals Detected by Raman Spectroscopy?, J. Nanoelectron. Optoelectron. 1, 107 (2006).   T. Korn, F. Giesen, J. Podbielski, D. Ravlic, C. Schueller, and D. Grundler: ?Time-resolved study of the increased magnetization precession frequency in Fe wires?, Journal of Magnetism and Magnetic Materials, JMMM, 285, 240 (2005).   T. Korn, F. Müller, D. Grundler, and C. Schüller: ?Characterization of Permalloy films on high-bandwidth striplines?, Journal of Magnetism and Magnetic Materials, JMMM, 272-276, E1341 (2004).   C. Schüller, K.-B. Broocks, P. Schröter, Ch. Heyn, D. Heitmann, V. Apalkov, T. Chakraborty, M. Bichler, and W. Wegscheider: ?How to Probe a Fractionally-Charged Quasihole??, Physica E 22, 131 (2004).   T. Brocke, M.-T. Bootsmann, B. Wunsch, M. Tews, D. Pfannkuche, Ch. Heyn, W. Hansen, D. Heitmann, and C. Schüller: ?Inelastic Light Scattering on Few-Electron Quantum-Dot Atoms?, Physica E 22, 478 (2004).   T. Kipp, K. Petter, Ch. Heyn, D. Heitmann, and C. Schüller: ?Spectroscopy of Individual AlGaAs Microdisks in Large Periodic Arrays?, Physica E 21, 830 (2004).   T. Kipp, L. Rolf, C. Schüller, D. Endler, Ch. Heyn, and D. Heitmann: ?Optical double resonance of electronic Raman scattering in a AlAs-AlGaAs microcavity?, Physica E 13, 408 (2002).   N. A. Fromer, C. Schüller, D. S. Chemla, T. V. Shahbazyan, I. E. Perakis, D. Driscoll, and A. C. Gossard: ?Femtosecond dynamics of inter-Landau level excitations of a two-dimensional electron gas in the quantum Hall regime?, Physica E 12, 550 (2002).   K.-B. Broocks, T. Ebeling, L. Karsten, C. Schüller, Ch. Heyn, and D. Heitmann: ?Electric field-dependent Zeeman splitting of excitons in diluted two-dimensional electron systems?, phys. stat. sol. (b) 227, 339-342 (2001).   C. Steinebach, C. Schüller, E. Ulrichs, Ch. Heyn, and D. Heitmann: ?Resonant inelastic light scattering on GaAs-AlGaAs quantum dots?, phys. stat. sol. (b) 224, 97-100 (2001)..   N. A. Fromer, C. Schüller, D. S. Chemla, K. Maranowski, and A. C. Gossard: ?Dephasing in the presence of a two-dimensional electron gas at high magnetic fields?, Physica E 6, 210-213 (2000).   E. Ulrichs, C. Steinebach, C. Schüller, Ch. Heyn, and D. Heitmann: ?Coulomb-interaction induced crossover from confined to bulk quantum-dot states in a magnetic field?, Physica E 6, 364-366 (2000).   D. Heitmann, V. Gudmundsson, L. Rolf, C. Schüller, C. Steinebach, and E. Ulrichs, ?Spectroscopy of few-electron quantum dots?, Acta Physica Polonica A 96, 545 (1999).   G. Biese, E. Ulrichs, L. Rolf, C. Schüller, C. Steinebach, S. Bargstädt-Franke, Ch. Heyn, D. Heitmann, and K. Eberl: ?Edge spin-density modes in quantum dots in a magnetic field?, Physica E 2, 619-622 (1998).   E. Ulrichs, G. Biese, C. Steinebach, C. Schüller, D. Heitmann, and K. Eberl: ?Skipping-orbit electron motion in GaAs-AlGaAs quantum wires detected by Raman spectroscopy?, phys. stat. sol. (a) 164, 277-280 (1997).   F. Rademacher, H. Eggers, T. O. Wiegard, C. Schüller, S. Bargstädt-Franke, Ch. Heyn, K. Eberl, and D. Heitmann: ?Magneto-optical investigation of excitons in narrow GaAs-AlGaAs quantum wires?, phys. stat. sol. (a) 164, 325-329 (1997).   G. Biese, C. Schüller, T. Kurth, D. Heitmann, P. Grambow, and K. Eberl: ?Combined 1D-2D intersubband excitations and 1D single-particle spectrum in narrow quantum wires?, Surf. Sci. 361/362, 797-800 (1996).   C. Schüller, J. Kraus, V. Latussek, G. Schaack, and J. K. Ebeling: ?Collective intersubband excitations in p-doped GaAs-AlGaAs multiple quantum wells?, Solid State Commun. 81, 3-7 (1992).   J. Kraus, P. Ils, C. Schüller, G. Schaack, J. K. Ebeling, W. Schlapp, and G. Weimann: ?The coupling of intersubband transitions and the quantum-well LO phonon in p-doped GaAs-GaAlAs multiple quantum wells?, J. Phys. Condens. Matter 3, 8267-8279 (1991).   M. Dahl, P. Ils, J. Kraus, B. Müller, G. Schaack, C. Schüller, J. K. Ebeling, and G. Weimann: ?Hole-intersubband excitations and luminescence transitions in p-doped GaAs-AlGaAs multiple quantum wells?, Superlatt. and Microstruc. 9, 77-81 (1991). Eingeladene Übersichtsartikel: T. Korn, G. Plechinger, S. Heydrich, F.-X. Schrettenbrunner, J. Eroms, D. Weiss,and C. Schüller: ?Optical Characterization, Low-Temperature Photoluminescence, and Photocarrier Dynamics in MoS2 ?, Springer Lecture Notes in Nanoscale Science and Technology 21, 217-236 (2014).   T. Korn, D. Stich, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller (invited article): ?Spin Dynamics in high-mobility two-dimensional electron systems?, Advances in Solid State Physics, Vol. 48, Ed. R. Haug (Springer Berlin, Heidelberg, New York, 2009).   C. Schüller, K.-B. Broocks, P. Schröter, C. Heyn, D. Heitmann, M. Bichler, W. Wegscheider, V. M. Apalkov, and T. Chakraborty (invited article): ?Charged Excitons in the Quantum Hall regime?, Acta Physica Polonica 106, 341 (2004).   Christian Schüller, Kay-Birger Broocks, Patrick Schröter, Christian Heyn, Detlef Heitmann, Max Bichler, Werner Wegscheider, Vadim Apalkov, and Tapash Chakraborty (invited article): ?Charged Excitons in the Quantum Hall Regime: Optical Probe of Fractionally Charged Quasiholes?, Advances in Solid State Physics, Vol. 44, Ed. B. Kramer (Springer Berlin, Heidelberg, New York, 2004).   Christian Schüller (invited article): ?Quantum Dots: Inelastic Light Scattering on Electronic Excitations?, Marcel Dekkers's Encyclopedia of Nanoscience and Nanotechnology, Marcel Dekker Inc., New York 2004.   C. Schüller, C. Steinebach, and D. Heitmann (invited article) ?Spin-and Charge-Density Excitations in Quantum Dots: A Raman Study?, Solid State Commun. 119, 323-331 (2001).   Christian Schüller, Ilias E. Perakis, Neil A. Fromer, and Daniel S. Chemla (invited book chapter) ?Ultrafast Spectroscopy in the Quantum Hall Regime?, in: Nonequilibrium Physics at Short Time Scales: Formation of Correlations, ed. by Klaus Morawetz (Springer Berlin, Heidelberg, New York, 2004) 209-230.   Christian Schüller (invited article) ?Raman Spectroscopy of Quantum Dots?, Festkörperprobleme, Advances in Solid State Physics 38, 167-181 (1999).   Christian Schüller (invited article) ?Raman Spectroscopy of Quantum Wires and Dots: Magnetoplasmons   and Edge-Spin-Density Modes?, Proceedings of the 10th International Winterschool on New Developments in Solid State Physics: New Frontiers in Low-Dimensional Physics, Mauterndorf, Austria, 23-27 February 1998, Physica E 3, 121-128 (1998).     Impressum Letzte Änderung: 07.02.2014 von Webmaster</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schueller/mitarbeiter.phtml</field>
<field name="title">Physik ? AG Schüller ? Mitarbeiter</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schueller/mitarbeiter.phtml</field>
<field name="content">Physik ? AG Schüller ? Mitarbeiter Physik ? AG Schüller ? Mitarbeiter Arbeitsgruppenleiter Christian Schüller, Prof. Dr. Büro: PHY 2.1.28 Labor: PHY 5.0.05 / PHY 2.1.17 Tel.: 0941 943 2078 (2080) FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: christian.schueller Tobias Korn, PD Dr. Büro: PHY 2.0.06 Labor: PHY 5.0.05 / PHY 2.1.17 Tel.: 0941 943 2055 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: tobias.korn Sekretärin / Techniker Eva Weiss, Sekretärin Büro: PHY 2.1.26 Tel.: 0941 943 2080 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: eva.weiss Christof Ermer, Techniker Büro: PHY 2.0.10 Labor: PHY 5.0.05 / PHY 2.1.17 Tel.: 0941 943 2140 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: christof.ermer Postdoc / Doktorandin / Doktoranden Fatemeh Yaghobian, Dr. Büro: PHY 2.0.03 Labor: PHY 2.1.17 / 2.0.21 Tel.: 0941 943 4213 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: fatemeh.yaghobian Markus Schwemmer, M.Sc. Büro: PHY 2.0.04 Labor: PHY 5.0.05 Tel.: 0941 943 2053 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: markus.schwemmer Christoph Schönhuber, Dipl.-Phys. Büro: PHY 2.0.03 Labor: PHY 2.1.17 Tel.: 0941 943 4213 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: christoph.schoenhuber Stefanie Heydrich, Dipl.-Phys. Büro: PHY 2.0.05 Labor: PHY 2.1.17 Tel.: 0941 943 2048 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: stefanie.heydrich Gerd Plechinger, M.Sc. Büro: PHY 2.0.04 Labor: PHY 5.0.05 Tel.: 0941 943 2053 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: gerd.plechinger Christian Gradl, M.Sc. Büro: PHY 2.0.03 Labor: PHY 5.0.05 Tel.: 0941 943 4213 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: christian.gradl Master / Lehramtsstudierende Philipp Nagler, B.Sc. Büro: PHY 2.0.04 Labor: PHY 2.0.22 Tel.: 0941 943 2053 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: Philipp.Nagler Sven Gelfert, B.Sc. Büro: PHY 2.0.04 Labor: PHY 2.0.22 Tel.: 0941 943 2053 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: Sven.Gelfert Bachelor-Studierende Felix Beck Büro: PHY 2.0.05 Labor: PHY 2.1.17 Tel.: 0941 943 2048 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: Felix Beck Johannes Holler Büro: PHY 2.0.03 Labor: PHY 5.0.05 Tel.: 0941 943 4213 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: Johannes.Holler Fabian Mooshammer Büro: PHY 2.0.05 Labor: PHY 2.1.17 Tel.: 0941 943 2048 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: Fabian Mooshammer Jennifer Zehner Büro: PHY 2.0.05 Labor: PHY 2.1.17 Tel.: 0941 943 2048 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: Jennifer Zehner   Impressum Letzte Änderung: 28.04.2014 von Webmaster</field>
<field name="important">Physik ? AG Schüller ? Mitarbeiter Physik ? AG Schüller ? Mitarbeiter Arbeitsgruppenleiter Christian Schüller, Prof. Dr. Büro: PHY 2.1.28 Labor: PHY 5.0.05 / PHY 2.1.17 Tel.: 0941 943 2078 (2080) FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: christian.schueller Tobias Korn, PD Dr. Büro: PHY 2.0.06 Labor: PHY 5.0.05 / PHY 2.1.17 Tel.: 0941 943 2055 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: tobias.korn Sekretärin / Techniker Eva Weiss, Sekretärin Büro: PHY 2.1.26 Tel.: 0941 943 2080 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: eva.weiss Christof Ermer, Techniker Büro: PHY 2.0.10 Labor: PHY 5.0.05 / PHY 2.1.17 Tel.: 0941 943 2140 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: christof.ermer Postdoc / Doktorandin / Doktoranden Fatemeh Yaghobian, Dr. Büro: PHY 2.0.03 Labor: PHY 2.1.17 / 2.0.21 Tel.: 0941 943 4213 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: fatemeh.yaghobian Markus Schwemmer, M.Sc. Büro: PHY 2.0.04 Labor: PHY 5.0.05 Tel.: 0941 943 2053 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: markus.schwemmer Christoph Schönhuber, Dipl.-Phys. Büro: PHY 2.0.03 Labor: PHY 2.1.17 Tel.: 0941 943 4213 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: christoph.schoenhuber Stefanie Heydrich, Dipl.-Phys. Büro: PHY 2.0.05 Labor: PHY 2.1.17 Tel.: 0941 943 2048 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: stefanie.heydrich Gerd Plechinger, M.Sc. Büro: PHY 2.0.04 Labor: PHY 5.0.05 Tel.: 0941 943 2053 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: gerd.plechinger Christian Gradl, M.Sc. Büro: PHY 2.0.03 Labor: PHY 5.0.05 Tel.: 0941 943 4213 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: christian.gradl Master / Lehramtsstudierende Philipp Nagler, B.Sc. Büro: PHY 2.0.04 Labor: PHY 2.0.22 Tel.: 0941 943 2053 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: Philipp.Nagler Sven Gelfert, B.Sc. Büro: PHY 2.0.04 Labor: PHY 2.0.22 Tel.: 0941 943 2053 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: Sven.Gelfert Bachelor-Studierende Felix Beck Büro: PHY 2.0.05 Labor: PHY 2.1.17 Tel.: 0941 943 2048 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: Felix Beck Johannes Holler Büro: PHY 2.0.03 Labor: PHY 5.0.05 Tel.: 0941 943 4213 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: Johannes.Holler Fabian Mooshammer Büro: PHY 2.0.05 Labor: PHY 2.1.17 Tel.: 0941 943 2048 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: Fabian Mooshammer Jennifer Zehner Büro: PHY 2.0.05 Labor: PHY 2.1.17 Tel.: 0941 943 2048 FAX: 0941 943 4226 Email: Jennifer Zehner   Impressum Letzte Änderung: 28.04.2014 von Webmaster</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schueller/pmwiki/pmwiki.php</field>
<field name="title">AG Schueller/Lupton PmWiki - Home Page</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schueller/pmwiki/pmwiki.php</field>
<field name="content">AG Schueller/Lupton PmWiki - Home Page AG Schueller/Lupton PmWiki - Home Page Hauptseite WikiSandbox Wiki-Inhalt Helium Unteres Labor Oberes Labor kleines Ramanlabor Aufdampfanlage Bougeard-Labors Probenpr?paration Ansteuerung von Me?ger?ten Origin-FAQ EDV-FAQ Samba Windows 7 Backups machen! Einkaufs-FAQ Druckgasflaschen Sicherheit N?tzliches f?r Abschlussarbeiten von B.Sc. bis Dr. Benutzer Wiki-Bildupload Wiki-Einrichtungs-Doku Anleitungen Einrichtung Kurzanleitung Dokumentation PmWiki FAQ PmWikiPhilosophy Men? editieren Suchen: Main/? Edit Page Eigenschaften Page History Hochladen Home Page Willkommen auf dem Wiki der Arbeitsgruppen Lupton/Sch?ller Auf diesem Wiki ist Platz, um Verschiedenes zu dokumentieren, Notizen zu machen und noch vieles mehr. Zum Lesen und Editieren aller Seiten (au?er dieser Startseite und dem EDV-FAQ) ist ein Passwort erforderlich, das bei Michael Kugler erfragt werden kann! Neue Seiten anlegen Anf?nger Einfach auf eine der folgenden Platzhalterseiten klicken und direkt zu schreiben anfangen, die Profis verschieben es dann an die passende Stelle. Platzhalter 1 Platzhalter 2 Platzhalter 3 Platzhalter 4 Platzhalter 5 Profis 1. Neue Haupt?berschriften anlegen "Men? edititieren" links in der Navigation dr?cken, neuen Link an passender Stelle einf?gen, Speichern, dann neuen Link klicken und neue Seite erstellen 2. Neue Unterpunkte in Hauptseiten erstellen Hauptseite ?ffnen, edititieren, neuen Link dort anlegen, speichern. Neuen Link klicken, im dann erscheinenden Edit-Fenster der neuen Seite diese erstellen --&amp;gt; f?hrt zu sch?ner Hierarchie und ?bersichtlichkeit! Bilder Hochladen Erste Schritte N?tzlich zum Einstieg sind die folgenden Links: Erzeugung und Bearbeiten von Seiten in PmWiki Grundlagen der Bearbeitung - Erzeugung neuer Seiten - Verweise - Bilder - Grundlegende Textformatierungsregeln - Die Dokumentation zu diesem Wiki findet sich im Dokumentations-Index. Ge?bt werden ohne etwas kaputtzumachen kann in der wiki sandbox. Mehr auf http://www.pmwiki.org . Zuletzt geändert am 07.10.2011 12:27 Uhr ? Nach oben ? Suchen Aktuelle Änderungen Alle aktuellen Änderungen</field>
<field name="important">AG Schueller/Lupton PmWiki - Home Page AG Schueller/Lupton PmWiki - Home Page Hauptseite WikiSandbox Wiki-Inhalt Helium Unteres Labor Oberes Labor kleines Ramanlabor Aufdampfanlage Bougeard-Labors Probenpr?paration Ansteuerung von Me?ger?ten Origin-FAQ EDV-FAQ Samba Windows 7 Backups machen! Einkaufs-FAQ Druckgasflaschen Sicherheit N?tzliches f?r Abschlussarbeiten von B.Sc. bis Dr. Benutzer Wiki-Bildupload Wiki-Einrichtungs-Doku Anleitungen Einrichtung Kurzanleitung Dokumentation PmWiki FAQ PmWikiPhilosophy Men? editieren Suchen: Main/? Edit Page Eigenschaften Page History Hochladen Home Page Willkommen auf dem Wiki der Arbeitsgruppen Lupton/Sch?ller Auf diesem Wiki ist Platz, um Verschiedenes zu dokumentieren, Notizen zu machen und noch vieles mehr. Zum Lesen und Editieren aller Seiten (au?er dieser Startseite und dem EDV-FAQ) ist ein Passwort erforderlich, das bei Michael Kugler erfragt werden kann! Neue Seiten anlegen Anf?nger Einfach auf eine der folgenden Platzhalterseiten klicken und direkt zu schreiben anfangen, die Profis verschieben es dann an die passende Stelle. Platzhalter 1 Platzhalter 2 Platzhalter 3 Platzhalter 4 Platzhalter 5 Profis 1. Neue Haupt?berschriften anlegen "Men? edititieren" links in der Navigation dr?cken, neuen Link an passender Stelle einf?gen, Speichern, dann neuen Link klicken und neue Seite erstellen 2. Neue Unterpunkte in Hauptseiten erstellen Hauptseite ?ffnen, edititieren, neuen Link dort anlegen, speichern. Neuen Link klicken, im dann erscheinenden Edit-Fenster der neuen Seite diese erstellen --&amp;gt; f?hrt zu sch?ner Hierarchie und ?bersichtlichkeit! Bilder Hochladen Erste Schritte N?tzlich zum Einstieg sind die folgenden Links: Erzeugung und Bearbeiten von Seiten in PmWiki Grundlagen der Bearbeitung - Erzeugung neuer Seiten - Verweise - Bilder - Grundlegende Textformatierungsregeln - Die Dokumentation zu diesem Wiki findet sich im Dokumentations-Index. Ge?bt werden ohne etwas kaputtzumachen kann in der wiki sandbox. Mehr auf http://www.pmwiki.org . Zuletzt geändert am 07.10.2011 12:27 Uhr ? Nach oben ? Suchen Aktuelle Änderungen Alle aktuellen Änderungen</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schueller/tkorn.phtml</field>
<field name="title">Physik ? AG Schüller ? Mitarbeiter</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schueller/tkorn.phtml</field>
<field name="content">Physik ? AG Schüller ? Mitarbeiter Physik ? AG Schüller ? Mitarbeiter Tobias Korn, Dr. rer. nat. Fakultät für Physik Institut für Experimentelle und Angewandte Physik Universität Regensburg D-93040 Regensburg Raum : PHY 2.0.06 Telefon : ++49 / (0)941 / 943 -2055 Sekretariat : ++49 / (0)941 / 943 -2080 (Frau Weiss) FAX : ++49 / (0)941 / 943 -4226 E-mail : tobias.korn@physik.uni-regensburg.de Wissenschaftlicher Werdegang 1994-2000 Studium der Physik an der Universität Hamburg 2001 - 2004 Promotion am Institut für Angewandte Physik der Universität Hamburg in der Gruppe von Professor Heitmann. Thema der Dissertation: 'Zeitaufgelöste Magnetisierungsmessungen an ferromagnetischen Filmen und Mikrostrukturen' 2004-2005 PostDoc am SPINTEC-Labor, CEA/CNRS Grenoble Seit September 2005 Wissenschaftlicher Assistent an der Universität Regensburg in der Gruppe von Professor Christian Schüller Januar 2011 Habilitation Juni 2011 Ernennung zum Privatdozenten Veröffentlichungen, nach Themen geordnet (a) Magneto-Optik und Magnetisierungsdynamik in ferromagnetischen Schichten und Mikrostrukturen G. Neuber, R. Rauer, J. Kunze, T. Korn, C. Pels, G. Meier, U. Merkt, J. Bäckström, and M. Rübhausen , ?Temperature-dependent spectral generalized magneto-optical ellipsometry?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 83, 4509 (2003) T. Korn, F. Giesen, J. Podbielski, D. Ravlic, C. Schüller, D. Grundler, ?Time-resolved study of the increased magnetization precession frequency in Fe wires?, J. of Magnetism and Magnetic Materials 285, 240 (2005) F. Giesen, J. Podbielski, T. Korn, D. Grundler, ?Multiple ferromagnetic resonance in mesoscopic permalloy rings?, J. Appl. Phys. 97, 10A712 (2005) T. Korn, M. Kerekes, U. Ebels, D. Stanescu, P. Xavier, ?Pumping-field-induced dynamic effects in micron-sized Permalloy lines and their influence on HF filter applications?, IEEE trans. Mag. 41, 3514 (2005) F. Giesen, J. Podbielski, T. Korn, M. Steiner, A. van Staa, and D. Grundler, ?Hysteresis and control of ferromagnetic resonances in rings?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 86, 112510 (2005) (b) Spin-und Ladungsträgerdynamik in Halbleitern T. Korn, A. Franke-Wiekhorst, S. Schnüll, I. Wilke, Characterization of nanometer As-Clusters in low-temperature-grown GaAs by transient reflectivity measurements, Journal of Applied Physics 91, 2333 (2001) D. Stich, J. Zhou, T. Korn, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, M.W. Wu, and C. Schüller: ?Effect of Initial Spin Polarization on Spin Dephasing and the Electron g Factor in a High-Mobility Two-Dimensional Electron System?, Phys. Rev. Lett. 98, 176401 (2007).   D. Stich, J. H. Jiang, T. Korn, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, M.W. Wu, and C. Schüller: ?Detection of large magneto-anisotropy of electron spin desphasing in a high mobility two-dimensional electron system in a [001] GaAs/AlGaAs quantum well?, Phys. Rev. B 76, 073309 (2007).   D. Stich, J. Zhou, T. Korn, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, M.W. Wu, and C. Schüller: ?Dependence of spin dephasing on initial spin polarizationin a high-mobility two-dimensional electron system?, Phys. Rev. B 76, 205301 (2007).   R. Schulz, T. Korn, U. Wurstbauer, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller: ?Ultrafast optical studies of diffusion barriers between ferromagnetic Ga(Mn)As layers and non-magnetic quantum wells?, Physica E 40, 2163 (2007).   T. Korn, D. Stich, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller: ?Large in-plane spin-dephasing anisotropy in a [001]-grown two-dimensional electron system?, Physica E 40, 1542 (2008).   D. Stich, T. Korn, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller: ?Increase of spin dephasing times in a 2D electron system with degree of initial spin polarization?, Physica E 40, 1545 (2008).   V. V. Belkov, P. Olbrich, S. A. Tarasenko, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, T. Korn, C. Schüller, D. Weiss, W. Prettl, and S. D. Ganichev: ?Symmetry and spin dephasing in (110)-grown quantum wells?, Phys. Rev. Lett. 100, 176806 (2008).   T. Korn, D. Stich, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller: (invited article): ?Spin Dynamics in high-mobility two-dimensional electron systems?, Advances in Solid State Physics, Vol. 48, Ed. R. Haug (Springer Berlin, Heidelberg, New York, 2009). P. Olbrich, J. Allerdings, V. V. Belkov, S. A. Tarasenko, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, T. Korn, C. Schüller, D. Weiss, and S. D. Ganichev: ?Magnetogyrotropic photogalvanic effect and spin dephasing in (110)-grown GaAs/Al xGa 1-xAs quantum well structures?, Phys. Rev. B 79, 245329 (2009).   J. H. Jiang, Y. Zhou, T. Korn, C. Schüller, and M. W. Wu: ?Electron spin relaxation in paramagnetic Ga(Mn)As quantum wells?, Phys. Rev. B 79, 155201(2009).   M. Kugler, T. Andlauer, T. Korn, A. Wagner, S. Fehringer, R. Schulz, M. Kubova, C. Gerl, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, P. Vogl, and C. Schüller: ?Gate control of low-temperature spin dynamics in two-dimensional hole systems?, Phys. Rev. B 80, 035325(2009).   Ch. Strelow, M. Sauer, S. Fehringer, T. Korn, C. Schüller, A. Stemmann, Ch. Heyn, D. Heitmann, and T. Kipp ?Time-resolved studies of a rolled-up semiconductor microtube laser?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 80, 221115(2009).   M. Griesbeck, M. M. Glazov, T. Korn, E. Ya. Sherman, D. Waller, C. Reichl, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller ?Cyclotron effect on coherent spin precession of two-dimensional electrons?, Phys. Rev. B, 80, 241314(R) (2009)   T. Korn, M. Kugler , M. Griesbeck , R. Schulz , A. Wagner , M. Hirmer , C. Gerl , D. Schuh , W. Wegscheider, and C Schüller ?Engineering ultralong spin coherence in two-dimensional hole systems at low temperatures ?, New J. Phys. 12, 043003 (2010)   T. Korn, ?Time-resolved studies of electron and hole spin dynamics in modulation-doped GaAs/AlGaAs quantum wells ?, Physics Reports 494, 415 (2010)   V. Lechner, L. E. Golub, F. Lomakina, V. V. Belkov, P. Olbrich, S. Stachel, I. Caspers, M. Griesbeck,1 M. Kugler, M. J. Hirmer, T. Korn,1 C. Schüller, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and S. D. Ganichev ?Spin and orbital mechanisms of the magnetogyrotropic photogalvanic effects in GaAs/AlxGa1-xAs quantum well structures?, Phys. Rev. B, 83, 155313 (2011)   R. Völkl, M. Griesbeck, S. A. Tarasenko, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, C. Schüller, and T. Korn ?Spin dephasing and photoinduced spin diffusion in a high-mobility two-dimensional electron system embedded in a GaAs-(Al,Ga)As quantum well grown in the [110] direction?, Phys. Rev. B, 83, 241306(R) (2011)   M. Kugler, K. Korzekwa, P. Machnikowski, C. Gradl, S. Furthmeier, M. Griesbeck, M. Hirmer, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, T. Kuhn, C. Schüller, and T. Korn ?Decoherence-assisted initialization of a resident hole spin polarization in a p-doped semiconductor quantum well?, Phys. Rev. B, 84, 085327 (2011)   M. Hirmer, M. Hirmer, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, T. Korn, R. Winkler, and C. Schüller, ?Fingerprints of the Anisotropic Spin-Split Hole Dispersion in Resonant Inelastic Light Scattering in Two-Dimensional Hole Systems?, Phys. Rev. Lett. 107, 216805(2011)   M. Griesbeck, M. M. Glazov, E. Ya. Sherman, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, C. Schüller, and T. Korn, ?Strongly anisotropic spin relaxation revealed by resonant spin amplification in (110) GaAs quantum wells?, Phys. Rev. B 85, 085313(2012)   K. Korzekwa, C. Gradl, M. Kugler, S. Furthmeier, M. Griesbeck, M. Hirmer, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, T. Kuhn, C. Schüller, T. Korn, and P. Machnikowski ?Spin dynamics in p-doped semiconductor nanostructures subject to a magnetic field tilted from the Voigt geometry?, Phys. Rev. B 88, 155303 (2013)   T. Korn and C. Schüller ?Hole spin dynamics and valence-band spin excitations in two-dimensional hole systems?, Phys. Status Solidi B., in press.   C. Schönhuber, M. P. Walser, G. Salis, C. Reichl, W. Wegscheider, T. Korn, and C. Schüller: ?Inelastic light-scattering from spin-density excitations in the regime of the persistent spin helix in a GaAs-AlGaAs quantum well?, Phys. Rev. B 89, 085406 (2014).   R. Völkl, M. Schwemmer, M. Griesbeck, S. A. Tarasenko, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, C. Schüller, and T. Korn ?Spin polarization, dephasing, and photoinduced spin diffusion in (110)-grown two-dimensional electron systems?, Phys. Rev. B 89, 075424 (2014)   (c) Optische Spektroskopie an zweidimensionalen Kristallstrukturen S. Heydrich, M. Hirmer, C. Preis, T. Korn, J. Eroms, D. Weiss, and C. Schüller ?Scanning Raman spectroscopy of graphene antidot lattices: Evidence for systematic p-type doping ?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 97, 043113(2010). T. Korn, S. Heydrich, M. Hirmer, J. Schmutzler, and C. Schüller ?Low-temperature photocarrier dynamics in monolayer MoS 2?, Appl. Phys. Lett., 99, 102109 (2011)   G. Plechinger, F.-X. Schrettenbrunner, J. Eroms, D. Weiss, C. Schüller, and T. Korn ?Low-temperature photoluminescence of oxide-covered single-layer MoS 2?, Phys. Status Solidi Rapid Research Letters, 6, 126 (2012)   G. Plechinger, S. Heydrich, J. Eroms, D. Weiss, C. Schüller, and T. Korn ?Raman spectroscopy of the interlayer shear mode in few-layer MoS 2 flakes ?, Appl. Phys. Lett., 101, 101906 (2012)   F. Yaghobian, T. Korn, and C. Schüller ?Frequency Shift in Graphene-Enhanced Raman Signal of Molecules?, ChemPhysChem , 13, 4271 (2012)   F. Oberhuber, S. Blien, S. Heydrich, F. Yaghobian, T. Korn, C. Schüller, C. Strunk, D. Weiss, and J. Eroms ?Weak localization and Raman study of anisotropically etched graphene antidots ?, Appl. Phys. Lett., 103, 143111 (2013)   T. Korn, G. Plechinger, S. Heydrich, F.-X. Schrettenbrunner, J. Eroms, D. Weiss,and C. Schüller ?Optical Characterization, Low-Temperature Photoluminescence, and Photocarrier Dynamics in MoS 2 ?, Springer Lecture Notes in Nanoscale Science and Technology 21, 217-236 (2014)   G. Plechinger, .J Mann, E. Preciado, D. Barroso, A. Nguyen, J. Eroms, C. Schüller, L. Bartels, and T. Korn ?A direct comparison of CVD-grown and exfoliated MoS 2 using optical spectroscopy ?, Semicond. Sci. Technol. 29, 064008 (2014)     Impressum Letzte Änderung: 07.05.2014 von Webmaster</field>
<field name="important">Physik ? AG Schüller ? Mitarbeiter Physik ? AG Schüller ? Mitarbeiter Tobias Korn, Dr. rer. nat. Fakultät für Physik Institut für Experimentelle und Angewandte Physik Universität Regensburg D-93040 Regensburg Raum : PHY 2.0.06 Telefon : ++49 / (0)941 / 943 -2055 Sekretariat : ++49 / (0)941 / 943 -2080 (Frau Weiss) FAX : ++49 / (0)941 / 943 -4226 E-mail : tobias.korn@physik.uni-regensburg.de Wissenschaftlicher Werdegang 1994-2000 Studium der Physik an der Universität Hamburg 2001 - 2004 Promotion am Institut für Angewandte Physik der Universität Hamburg in der Gruppe von Professor Heitmann. Thema der Dissertation: 'Zeitaufgelöste Magnetisierungsmessungen an ferromagnetischen Filmen und Mikrostrukturen' 2004-2005 PostDoc am SPINTEC-Labor, CEA/CNRS Grenoble Seit September 2005 Wissenschaftlicher Assistent an der Universität Regensburg in der Gruppe von Professor Christian Schüller Januar 2011 Habilitation Juni 2011 Ernennung zum Privatdozenten Veröffentlichungen, nach Themen geordnet (a) Magneto-Optik und Magnetisierungsdynamik in ferromagnetischen Schichten und Mikrostrukturen G. Neuber, R. Rauer, J. Kunze, T. Korn, C. Pels, G. Meier, U. Merkt, J. Bäckström, and M. Rübhausen , ?Temperature-dependent spectral generalized magneto-optical ellipsometry?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 83, 4509 (2003) T. Korn, F. Giesen, J. Podbielski, D. Ravlic, C. Schüller, D. Grundler, ?Time-resolved study of the increased magnetization precession frequency in Fe wires?, J. of Magnetism and Magnetic Materials 285, 240 (2005) F. Giesen, J. Podbielski, T. Korn, D. Grundler, ?Multiple ferromagnetic resonance in mesoscopic permalloy rings?, J. Appl. Phys. 97, 10A712 (2005) T. Korn, M. Kerekes, U. Ebels, D. Stanescu, P. Xavier, ?Pumping-field-induced dynamic effects in micron-sized Permalloy lines and their influence on HF filter applications?, IEEE trans. Mag. 41, 3514 (2005) F. Giesen, J. Podbielski, T. Korn, M. Steiner, A. van Staa, and D. Grundler, ?Hysteresis and control of ferromagnetic resonances in rings?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 86, 112510 (2005) (b) Spin-und Ladungsträgerdynamik in Halbleitern T. Korn, A. Franke-Wiekhorst, S. Schnüll, I. Wilke, Characterization of nanometer As-Clusters in low-temperature-grown GaAs by transient reflectivity measurements, Journal of Applied Physics 91, 2333 (2001) D. Stich, J. Zhou, T. Korn, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, M.W. Wu, and C. Schüller: ?Effect of Initial Spin Polarization on Spin Dephasing and the Electron g Factor in a High-Mobility Two-Dimensional Electron System?, Phys. Rev. Lett. 98, 176401 (2007).   D. Stich, J. H. Jiang, T. Korn, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, M.W. Wu, and C. Schüller: ?Detection of large magneto-anisotropy of electron spin desphasing in a high mobility two-dimensional electron system in a [001] GaAs/AlGaAs quantum well?, Phys. Rev. B 76, 073309 (2007).   D. Stich, J. Zhou, T. Korn, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, M.W. Wu, and C. Schüller: ?Dependence of spin dephasing on initial spin polarizationin a high-mobility two-dimensional electron system?, Phys. Rev. B 76, 205301 (2007).   R. Schulz, T. Korn, U. Wurstbauer, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller: ?Ultrafast optical studies of diffusion barriers between ferromagnetic Ga(Mn)As layers and non-magnetic quantum wells?, Physica E 40, 2163 (2007).   T. Korn, D. Stich, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller: ?Large in-plane spin-dephasing anisotropy in a [001]-grown two-dimensional electron system?, Physica E 40, 1542 (2008).   D. Stich, T. Korn, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller: ?Increase of spin dephasing times in a 2D electron system with degree of initial spin polarization?, Physica E 40, 1545 (2008).   V. V. Belkov, P. Olbrich, S. A. Tarasenko, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, T. Korn, C. Schüller, D. Weiss, W. Prettl, and S. D. Ganichev: ?Symmetry and spin dephasing in (110)-grown quantum wells?, Phys. Rev. Lett. 100, 176806 (2008).   T. Korn, D. Stich, R. Schulz, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller: (invited article): ?Spin Dynamics in high-mobility two-dimensional electron systems?, Advances in Solid State Physics, Vol. 48, Ed. R. Haug (Springer Berlin, Heidelberg, New York, 2009). P. Olbrich, J. Allerdings, V. V. Belkov, S. A. Tarasenko, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, T. Korn, C. Schüller, D. Weiss, and S. D. Ganichev: ?Magnetogyrotropic photogalvanic effect and spin dephasing in (110)-grown GaAs/Al xGa 1-xAs quantum well structures?, Phys. Rev. B 79, 245329 (2009).   J. H. Jiang, Y. Zhou, T. Korn, C. Schüller, and M. W. Wu: ?Electron spin relaxation in paramagnetic Ga(Mn)As quantum wells?, Phys. Rev. B 79, 155201(2009).   M. Kugler, T. Andlauer, T. Korn, A. Wagner, S. Fehringer, R. Schulz, M. Kubova, C. Gerl, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, P. Vogl, and C. Schüller: ?Gate control of low-temperature spin dynamics in two-dimensional hole systems?, Phys. Rev. B 80, 035325(2009).   Ch. Strelow, M. Sauer, S. Fehringer, T. Korn, C. Schüller, A. Stemmann, Ch. Heyn, D. Heitmann, and T. Kipp ?Time-resolved studies of a rolled-up semiconductor microtube laser?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 80, 221115(2009).   M. Griesbeck, M. M. Glazov, T. Korn, E. Ya. Sherman, D. Waller, C. Reichl, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and C. Schüller ?Cyclotron effect on coherent spin precession of two-dimensional electrons?, Phys. Rev. B, 80, 241314(R) (2009)   T. Korn, M. Kugler , M. Griesbeck , R. Schulz , A. Wagner , M. Hirmer , C. Gerl , D. Schuh , W. Wegscheider, and C Schüller ?Engineering ultralong spin coherence in two-dimensional hole systems at low temperatures ?, New J. Phys. 12, 043003 (2010)   T. Korn, ?Time-resolved studies of electron and hole spin dynamics in modulation-doped GaAs/AlGaAs quantum wells ?, Physics Reports 494, 415 (2010)   V. Lechner, L. E. Golub, F. Lomakina, V. V. Belkov, P. Olbrich, S. Stachel, I. Caspers, M. Griesbeck,1 M. Kugler, M. J. Hirmer, T. Korn,1 C. Schüller, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, and S. D. Ganichev ?Spin and orbital mechanisms of the magnetogyrotropic photogalvanic effects in GaAs/AlxGa1-xAs quantum well structures?, Phys. Rev. B, 83, 155313 (2011)   R. Völkl, M. Griesbeck, S. A. Tarasenko, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, C. Schüller, and T. Korn ?Spin dephasing and photoinduced spin diffusion in a high-mobility two-dimensional electron system embedded in a GaAs-(Al,Ga)As quantum well grown in the [110] direction?, Phys. Rev. B, 83, 241306(R) (2011)   M. Kugler, K. Korzekwa, P. Machnikowski, C. Gradl, S. Furthmeier, M. Griesbeck, M. Hirmer, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, T. Kuhn, C. Schüller, and T. Korn ?Decoherence-assisted initialization of a resident hole spin polarization in a p-doped semiconductor quantum well?, Phys. Rev. B, 84, 085327 (2011)   M. Hirmer, M. Hirmer, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, T. Korn, R. Winkler, and C. Schüller, ?Fingerprints of the Anisotropic Spin-Split Hole Dispersion in Resonant Inelastic Light Scattering in Two-Dimensional Hole Systems?, Phys. Rev. Lett. 107, 216805(2011)   M. Griesbeck, M. M. Glazov, E. Ya. Sherman, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, C. Schüller, and T. Korn, ?Strongly anisotropic spin relaxation revealed by resonant spin amplification in (110) GaAs quantum wells?, Phys. Rev. B 85, 085313(2012)   K. Korzekwa, C. Gradl, M. Kugler, S. Furthmeier, M. Griesbeck, M. Hirmer, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, T. Kuhn, C. Schüller, T. Korn, and P. Machnikowski ?Spin dynamics in p-doped semiconductor nanostructures subject to a magnetic field tilted from the Voigt geometry?, Phys. Rev. B 88, 155303 (2013)   T. Korn and C. Schüller ?Hole spin dynamics and valence-band spin excitations in two-dimensional hole systems?, Phys. Status Solidi B., in press.   C. Schönhuber, M. P. Walser, G. Salis, C. Reichl, W. Wegscheider, T. Korn, and C. Schüller: ?Inelastic light-scattering from spin-density excitations in the regime of the persistent spin helix in a GaAs-AlGaAs quantum well?, Phys. Rev. B 89, 085406 (2014).   R. Völkl, M. Schwemmer, M. Griesbeck, S. A. Tarasenko, D. Schuh, W. Wegscheider, C. Schüller, and T. Korn ?Spin polarization, dephasing, and photoinduced spin diffusion in (110)-grown two-dimensional electron systems?, Phys. Rev. B 89, 075424 (2014)   (c) Optische Spektroskopie an zweidimensionalen Kristallstrukturen S. Heydrich, M. Hirmer, C. Preis, T. Korn, J. Eroms, D. Weiss, and C. Schüller ?Scanning Raman spectroscopy of graphene antidot lattices: Evidence for systematic p-type doping ?, Appl. Phys. Lett. 97, 043113(2010). T. Korn, S. Heydrich, M. Hirmer, J. Schmutzler, and C. Schüller ?Low-temperature photocarrier dynamics in monolayer MoS 2?, Appl. Phys. Lett., 99, 102109 (2011)   G. Plechinger, F.-X. Schrettenbrunner, J. Eroms, D. Weiss, C. Schüller, and T. Korn ?Low-temperature photoluminescence of oxide-covered single-layer MoS 2?, Phys. Status Solidi Rapid Research Letters, 6, 126 (2012)   G. Plechinger, S. Heydrich, J. Eroms, D. Weiss, C. Schüller, and T. Korn ?Raman spectroscopy of the interlayer shear mode in few-layer MoS 2 flakes ?, Appl. Phys. Lett., 101, 101906 (2012)   F. Yaghobian, T. Korn, and C. Schüller ?Frequency Shift in Graphene-Enhanced Raman Signal of Molecules?, ChemPhysChem , 13, 4271 (2012)   F. Oberhuber, S. Blien, S. Heydrich, F. Yaghobian, T. Korn, C. Schüller, C. Strunk, D. Weiss, and J. Eroms ?Weak localization and Raman study of anisotropically etched graphene antidots ?, Appl. Phys. Lett., 103, 143111 (2013)   T. Korn, G. Plechinger, S. Heydrich, F.-X. Schrettenbrunner, J. Eroms, D. Weiss,and C. Schüller ?Optical Characterization, Low-Temperature Photoluminescence, and Photocarrier Dynamics in MoS 2 ?, Springer Lecture Notes in Nanoscale Science and Technology 21, 217-236 (2014)   G. Plechinger, .J Mann, E. Preciado, D. Barroso, A. Nguyen, J. Eroms, C. Schüller, L. Bartels, and T. Korn ?A direct comparison of CVD-grown and exfoliated MoS 2 using optical spectroscopy ?, Semicond. Sci. Technol. 29, 064008 (2014)     Impressum Letzte Änderung: 07.05.2014 von Webmaster</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schueller/webmaster.phtml</field>
<field name="title">Physik ? AG Schüller ? Webmaster</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schueller/webmaster.phtml</field>
<field name="content">Physik ? AG Schüller ? Webmaster Physik ? AG Schüller ? Webmaster Impressum - Legal Notice Dies hier ist das offizielle Webangebot der Arbeitsgruppe von Prof. Dr. Christian Schüller an der Fakultät für Physik der Universität Regensburg. Die Anbieterinformationen entsprechend der einschlägigen rechtlichen Vorschriften finden Sie im Impressum der Universität Regensburg. Technisch gesehen handelt es sich um einen virtuellen Server auf dem zentralen Webserver der Universität. Dieser Webserver wird betrieben vom Rechenzentrum der Universität. Haftungsausschluss und Privacy Policy des Rechenzentrums gelten entsprechend auch für die Webseiten der Fakultät für Physik und damit auch für diese Seiten. Wenn Sie Probleme irgendeiner Art mit diesem Web-Server haben, dann senden Sie doch bitte eine Mail an Christian Schüller. Programmierung: Bernhard Mendl Design: Franz Stadler Fotos: Robert Schulz, Christian Schüller These are the official pages of the research group of Christian Schüller of the faculty of physics at the university of Regensburg. The provider information according to the appropriate German law is available in the imprint of the University of Regensburg. Technically speaking this is a virtual instance of the central Webserver from the university. This Server is operated by the Computer Center of the university. Therefore nonliability and privacy policy of the Computer Center are also in force for the website of the Faculty of Physics and of this site. If you face any problems with this website, please send a short mail to Christian Schüller. Coding: Bernhard Mendl Design: Franz Stadler Photos: Robert Schulz, Christian Schüller   Impressum Letzte Änderung: 01.08.2008 von Webmaster</field>
<field name="important">Physik ? AG Schüller ? Webmaster Physik ? AG Schüller ? Webmaster Impressum - Legal Notice Dies hier ist das offizielle Webangebot der Arbeitsgruppe von Prof. Dr. Christian Schüller an der Fakultät für Physik der Universität Regensburg. Die Anbieterinformationen entsprechend der einschlägigen rechtlichen Vorschriften finden Sie im Impressum der Universität Regensburg. Technisch gesehen handelt es sich um einen virtuellen Server auf dem zentralen Webserver der Universität. Dieser Webserver wird betrieben vom Rechenzentrum der Universität. Haftungsausschluss und Privacy Policy des Rechenzentrums gelten entsprechend auch für die Webseiten der Fakultät für Physik und damit auch für diese Seiten. Wenn Sie Probleme irgendeiner Art mit diesem Web-Server haben, dann senden Sie doch bitte eine Mail an Christian Schüller. Programmierung: Bernhard Mendl Design: Franz Stadler Fotos: Robert Schulz, Christian Schüller These are the official pages of the research group of Christian Schüller of the faculty of physics at the university of Regensburg. The provider information according to the appropriate German law is available in the imprint of the University of Regensburg. Technically speaking this is a virtual instance of the central Webserver from the university. This Server is operated by the Computer Center of the university. Therefore nonliability and privacy policy of the Computer Center are also in force for the website of the Faculty of Physics and of this site. If you face any problems with this website, please send a short mail to Christian Schüller. Coding: Bernhard Mendl Design: Franz Stadler Photos: Robert Schulz, Christian Schüller   Impressum Letzte Änderung: 01.08.2008 von Webmaster</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/strauch/strauch.html</field>
<field name="title"></field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/strauch/strauch.html</field>
<field name="content">  Einen Moment bitte...   Falls Sie nicht innerhalb von 5 Sekunden auf unserer Homepage landen, klicken Sie bitte auf http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schroeder/index.html</field>
<field name="important">  Einen Moment bitte...   Falls Sie nicht innerhalb von 5 Sekunden auf unserer Homepage landen, klicken Sie bitte auf http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/schroeder/index.html</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/wegscheider/gebhardt.html</field>
<field name="title">Gebhardt-Homepage</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/wegscheider/gebhardt.html</field>
<field name="content">Gebhardt-Homepage Gebhardt-Homepage Prof. em. Dr. Wolfgang Gebhardt Institut für Angewandte und Experimentelle Physik Universität?Regensburg????????? Raum PHY 9.1.01 93040 Regensburg? Telefon: +49 941 943 2791 Telefax: +49 941 943 4223 email:wolfgang.gebhardt@physik.uni-regensburg.de Veranstaltungen: Vorl.Nr.52460 Aushang Seminar für Bachelor- und Masterstudium im WS 14/15: Seminar "The Quest for a Second Earth" WS 14/15: weitere Skripten Seminar BigBang im WS 13/14: Skript zur Vorlesung: ?Vom Urknall zu den Sternen?. Handouts und Skripten zu früheren Vorlesungen</field>
<field name="important">Gebhardt-Homepage Gebhardt-Homepage Prof. em. Dr. Wolfgang Gebhardt Institut für Angewandte und Experimentelle Physik Universität?Regensburg????????? Raum PHY 9.1.01 93040 Regensburg? Telefon: +49 941 943 2791 Telefax: +49 941 943 4223 email:wolfgang.gebhardt@physik.uni-regensburg.de Veranstaltungen: Vorl.Nr.52460 Aushang Seminar für Bachelor- und Masterstudium im WS 14/15: Seminar "The Quest for a Second Earth" WS 14/15: weitere Skripten Seminar BigBang im WS 13/14: Skript zur Vorlesung: ?Vom Urknall zu den Sternen?. Handouts und Skripten zu früheren Vorlesungen</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/weiss/aktuelles.html</field>
<field name="title">Lehrstuhl Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss: Aktuelles</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/weiss/aktuelles.html</field>
<field name="content">Lehrstuhl Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss: Aktuelles Lehrstuhl Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss: Aktuelles Veranstaltungen im Sommersemester 2014 Lehrstuhlseminar Do 13.30, PHY 9.2.01 AG-Seminar (Strunk/Paradiso) Do 13.30, PHY 8.1.09 SFB-Seminar Di 14:15 Uhr, PHY 9.2.01 Journal Club Mi 10:45, PHY 8.1.09 Vorlesung  Semiconductor Physics (Weiss) Di, Fr 10-12, PHY 9.2.01Skript: Halbleiter2014 (08.04.2014) Folien (13.05.2014) Folien Teil 2 (25.06.2014) Folien Teil 3 (01.07.2014) Klausur am 21.07.2014 im H 36, Uhrzeit: 10.15 - 12.00 Vorlesung Thermodynamik (Eroms) Mo 08-10, Do 10-12, H 36 Übungen zu Thermodynamik, Übungsblätter Journal Club (Strunk) Fr 12ct, PHY 8.1.09   Frühere Veranstaltungen: Skripten &amp; Handouts Aktuelles Masterarbeiten bei AG Weiss Masterarbeiten bei AG Strunk Masterarbeiten bei AG Hüttel Ergebnisse Wiederholungsklauskur Struktur der Materie II (Festkörperphysik) vom 17.04.2014 webmaster, letzte Änderung 01.07.2014</field>
<field name="important">Lehrstuhl Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss: Aktuelles Lehrstuhl Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss: Aktuelles Veranstaltungen im Sommersemester 2014 Lehrstuhlseminar Do 13.30, PHY 9.2.01 AG-Seminar (Strunk/Paradiso) Do 13.30, PHY 8.1.09 SFB-Seminar Di 14:15 Uhr, PHY 9.2.01 Journal Club Mi 10:45, PHY 8.1.09 Vorlesung  Semiconductor Physics (Weiss) Di, Fr 10-12, PHY 9.2.01Skript: Halbleiter2014 (08.04.2014) Folien (13.05.2014) Folien Teil 2 (25.06.2014) Folien Teil 3 (01.07.2014) Klausur am 21.07.2014 im H 36, Uhrzeit: 10.15 - 12.00 Vorlesung Thermodynamik (Eroms) Mo 08-10, Do 10-12, H 36 Übungen zu Thermodynamik, Übungsblätter Journal Club (Strunk) Fr 12ct, PHY 8.1.09   Frühere Veranstaltungen: Skripten &amp; Handouts Aktuelles Masterarbeiten bei AG Weiss Masterarbeiten bei AG Strunk Masterarbeiten bei AG Hüttel Ergebnisse Wiederholungsklauskur Struktur der Materie II (Festkörperphysik) vom 17.04.2014 webmaster, letzte Änderung 01.07.2014</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/weiss/bilder.html</field>
<field name="title">Arbeitsgruppe Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss: Bildergalerie</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/weiss/bilder.html</field>
<field name="content">Arbeitsgruppe Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss: Bildergalerie Arbeitsgruppe Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss: Bildergalerie Bildergalerie Elektronenmikroskopaufnahme eines Multiwall-Carbon-Nanotubes kontaktiert mit einem Pd(3nm)Nb(45nm) Zweischichtsystem aufgenommen unter einem Winkel von 80 Grad. Palladium und Niob sind von oben auf den Tube durch Sputter aufgebracht worden. Man erkennt noch Flocken vom Lift-Off. Die Zuleitungen sind aus einer Palladium-Gold-Legierung. E. Pallecchi, M. Gaass, F. Otto.   September 2008 Juni 2008 Dezember 2007 Januar 2008 Juli 2007 Mai 2007 Februar 2007 Januar 2007 August 2006 September 2006 Juni 2006 Juli 2006 August 2004 März 2004 Juli 2003 Mai 2003 Dezember 2002 Oktober 2002 September 2001 Juni 2002 August 2001 Juli 2001 M?rz 2001 November 2000 September 2000 Juli 2000 Juni 2000 April 2000 M?rz 2000 Februar 2000 Januar 2000 Dezember 1999 webmaster, letzte Änderung am 08.01.2008  </field>
<field name="important">Arbeitsgruppe Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss: Bildergalerie Arbeitsgruppe Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss: Bildergalerie Bildergalerie Elektronenmikroskopaufnahme eines Multiwall-Carbon-Nanotubes kontaktiert mit einem Pd(3nm)Nb(45nm) Zweischichtsystem aufgenommen unter einem Winkel von 80 Grad. Palladium und Niob sind von oben auf den Tube durch Sputter aufgebracht worden. Man erkennt noch Flocken vom Lift-Off. Die Zuleitungen sind aus einer Palladium-Gold-Legierung. E. Pallecchi, M. Gaass, F. Otto.   September 2008 Juni 2008 Dezember 2007 Januar 2008 Juli 2007 Mai 2007 Februar 2007 Januar 2007 August 2006 September 2006 Juni 2006 Juli 2006 August 2004 März 2004 Juli 2003 Mai 2003 Dezember 2002 Oktober 2002 September 2001 Juni 2002 August 2001 Juli 2001 M?rz 2001 November 2000 September 2000 Juli 2000 Juni 2000 April 2000 M?rz 2000 Februar 2000 Januar 2000 Dezember 1999 webmaster, letzte Änderung am 08.01.2008  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/weiss/forschergruppe/fogrusemSS05.html</field>
<field name="title">Seminar der Forschergruppe</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/weiss/forschergruppe/fogrusemSS05.html</field>
<field name="content">Seminar der Forschergruppe Seminar der Forschergruppe Forschergruppenseminar Ferromagnet-Halbleiter-Nanostrukturen SS 2005 Fr. 13.45 h, Phys. 5.0.20   29.04.05 Dr. Sergey Ganichev, Universit?t Regensburg ?Spin drives current, current drives spin? 12.05.05 PHY 5.0.21 15.15 Uhr   Sonderveranstaltung Dr. Rogerio de Sousa, University of California , Berkeley ?Electron spin decoherence due to interaction with nuclear spins: Mechanisms and control? 20.05.05 Dr. Can-Ming Hu, Uni Hamburg ?Has Maxwell anything to do with Spintronics?? 31.05.05 PHY 2.0.31 14.30 Uhr   Sonderveranstaltung Dr. Saskia Fischer, Uni Bochum ?Energy-level spectroscopy of coupled one-dimensional electron systemsl? 02.06.05 PHY 8.1.09 13.30 Uhr   Sonderveranstaltung Dr. Ragnar Fleischmann, MPI G?ttingen ?Fraktale Leitwertsfluktuationen? 03.06.05 Prof. Dr. Christian Pfleiderer, TU M?nchen ?Ferromagnetic Superconductors? 16.06.05 PHY 7.3.14 13.15 Uhr   Sonderveranstaltung A.V. Kimmel, IMM, Radboud University Nijmegen "Coupling between magnetism and optics in (Ga,Mn)As? 16.06.05 PHY 7.3.14 15.15 Uhr   Sonderveranstaltung A. Kirilyuk, IMM, Radboud University Nijmegen "Ultrafast laser control of spins in magnetic materials? 17.06.05 Dr. John Schliemann, Universit?t Basel ?Theory of ferromagnetic semiconductors? 24.06.05 Rolf Allenspach, IBM Z?rich ?Tailoring and manipulating magnetic domain walls? 30.06.05 PHY 8.1.09 13.30 Uhr   Sonderveranstaltung Dr. Stavros Komineas, Cavendish Laboratory, Cambridge ?Bubble domains in disc-shaped ferromagnetic particles? Programm vergangener Semester webmaster , letzte ?nderung am 13.10.04</field>
<field name="important">Seminar der Forschergruppe Seminar der Forschergruppe Forschergruppenseminar Ferromagnet-Halbleiter-Nanostrukturen SS 2005 Fr. 13.45 h, Phys. 5.0.20   29.04.05 Dr. Sergey Ganichev, Universit?t Regensburg ?Spin drives current, current drives spin? 12.05.05 PHY 5.0.21 15.15 Uhr   Sonderveranstaltung Dr. Rogerio de Sousa, University of California , Berkeley ?Electron spin decoherence due to interaction with nuclear spins: Mechanisms and control? 20.05.05 Dr. Can-Ming Hu, Uni Hamburg ?Has Maxwell anything to do with Spintronics?? 31.05.05 PHY 2.0.31 14.30 Uhr   Sonderveranstaltung Dr. Saskia Fischer, Uni Bochum ?Energy-level spectroscopy of coupled one-dimensional electron systemsl? 02.06.05 PHY 8.1.09 13.30 Uhr   Sonderveranstaltung Dr. Ragnar Fleischmann, MPI G?ttingen ?Fraktale Leitwertsfluktuationen? 03.06.05 Prof. Dr. Christian Pfleiderer, TU M?nchen ?Ferromagnetic Superconductors? 16.06.05 PHY 7.3.14 13.15 Uhr   Sonderveranstaltung A.V. Kimmel, IMM, Radboud University Nijmegen "Coupling between magnetism and optics in (Ga,Mn)As? 16.06.05 PHY 7.3.14 15.15 Uhr   Sonderveranstaltung A. Kirilyuk, IMM, Radboud University Nijmegen "Ultrafast laser control of spins in magnetic materials? 17.06.05 Dr. John Schliemann, Universit?t Basel ?Theory of ferromagnetic semiconductors? 24.06.05 Rolf Allenspach, IBM Z?rich ?Tailoring and manipulating magnetic domain walls? 30.06.05 PHY 8.1.09 13.30 Uhr   Sonderveranstaltung Dr. Stavros Komineas, Cavendish Laboratory, Cambridge ?Bubble domains in disc-shaped ferromagnetic particles? Programm vergangener Semester webmaster , letzte ?nderung am 13.10.04</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/weiss/forschmenu.html</field>
<field name="title">Arbeitsgruppe Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss: Forschung</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/weiss/forschmenu.html</field>
<field name="content">Arbeitsgruppe Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss: Forschung Arbeitsgruppe Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss: Forschung Forschung Forschungsschwerpunkte AG Weiss Forschungsschwerpunkte AG Strunk Ver?ffentlichungen Ver?ffentlichungen AG Weiss Ver?ffentlichungen AG Strunk</field>
<field name="important">Arbeitsgruppe Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss: Forschung Arbeitsgruppe Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss: Forschung Forschung Forschungsschwerpunkte AG Weiss Forschungsschwerpunkte AG Strunk Ver?ffentlichungen Ver?ffentlichungen AG Weiss Ver?ffentlichungen AG Strunk</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/weiss/impressum.html</field>
<field name="title">Lehrstuhl Weiss - Haftungshinweis</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/weiss/impressum.html</field>
<field name="content">Lehrstuhl Weiss - Haftungshinweis Lehrstuhl Weiss - Haftungshinweis Haftungshinweis: Trotz sorgf?ltiger inhaltlicher Kontrolle ?bernimmt die Universit?t keine Haftung f?r Inhalte externer Links. F?r den Inhalt der verlinkten Seiten sind ausschlie?lich deren Betreiber verantwortlich. Adresse:     Lehrstuhl Prof. Dr. D. Weiss     Institut f?r Experimentelle und Angewandte Physik     Universit?t Regensburg     Universit?tsstr. 31     93040 Regensburg   Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss     Joachim Stahl, 04.05.2006</field>
<field name="important">Lehrstuhl Weiss - Haftungshinweis Lehrstuhl Weiss - Haftungshinweis Haftungshinweis: Trotz sorgf?ltiger inhaltlicher Kontrolle ?bernimmt die Universit?t keine Haftung f?r Inhalte externer Links. F?r den Inhalt der verlinkten Seiten sind ausschlie?lich deren Betreiber verantwortlich. Adresse:     Lehrstuhl Prof. Dr. D. Weiss     Institut f?r Experimentelle und Angewandte Physik     Universit?t Regensburg     Universit?tsstr. 31     93040 Regensburg   Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss     Joachim Stahl, 04.05.2006</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/weiss/index.html</field>
<field name="title">Arbeitsgruppe Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss</field>
<field name="url">http://www.physik.uni-regensburg.de/forschung/weiss/index.html</field>
<field name="content">Arbeitsgruppe Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss Arbeitsgruppe Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss</field>
<field name="important">Arbeitsgruppe Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss Arbeitsgruppe Prof. Dr. Dieter Weiss</field>
</doc>

</add>