<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<add>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Elite/html/st2010.html</field>
<field name="title">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Elite/html/st2010.html</field>
<field name="content">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   Our Students » Student Careers » Student Publications you are here: Home » Our Students » 2010-2012 2010-2012 Blumenstock, Sonja Germany Chen, Xufeng China Chennappan, Saravanakkumar India Gehring, Isabell Germany Grotheer, Mareike Germany Izurieta Hidalgo, Natalie Ecuador Kaczmarek, Veronika Germany Kalepu, Srikrishna Rajakiran India Lo, Aileen Rose Y. Philippines Schrödl, Magdalena Germany Stankova, Trayana Hristova Bulgaria Thuy, Andreas USA   Blumenstock, Sonja City and country of origin: Regensburg, Germany Educational background: B.Sc. in Biochemistry, University of Regensburg, bachelor thesis on ?Expression and Purification of two DNA-binding Proteins and their Interaction with DNA? Research Internship at Dublin City University (Ireland) on steroid contamination in wastewater Research Internship at Arizona State University (USA) on the usage of the transcription factor AP-1 as a marker for neuronal activity Main scientific interests: Molecular neurosciences and neurobiochemistry Developmntal neuroscience Regenerative medicine Neurodegenerative and other neurological disorders Future plans and objectives: Proceed to a PhD in a field of my scientific interests Constantly improve my technical skills and knowledge in science Pursue a career in research or industry   page up Chen, Xufeng City and country of origin: Xiangfan, Hubei province, China Educational background: Bachelor of Science in Biotechnology in Hainan University ECN       Main scientific interests: Electrophysiology:  recording and analysis of cell current, patch clam (whole cell and single channel configuration) Cellular and molecular biology: primary neuron cell culture, live cell image Neuropathology: Parkinson's disease, Alzheimer etc  Future plans and objectives: Based on electrophysiology and molecular biology, through the knowledge and technologies I grasped in ECN, explore the fundamental pathogen of at least one neurology disease and thereout delve the pharmaceutically and therapeutically critical links      page up Chennappan, Saravanakkumar City and country of origin: Tamilnadu, India Educational background: B.Tech (Biotechnology), Bharathidasan University, India. MSc (Developmental Cell Biology), University of Sussex, UK.       Main scientific interests: Neurodegenerative diseases Neuronal development Neural plasticity and Neural stem cell biology. Future plans and objectives: Use the expertise gained from this masters program to bridge the gap between the core research of cellular neuroscience and the complex part of clinical studies, to address various questions arising in the field of regenerative neurobiology.   page up Gehring, Isabell City and country of origin: Rosenheim, Deutschland Educational background Studium Generale at Leibniz Kolleg Tuebingen (focus on Biochemistry, Journalism) B. Sc. in Biology, Ludwig- Maximilians- University Munich Bachelor thesis: Stem cells during the development of the brain- a comparison of Insecta with Mammalia   Main scientific interests neuronal dysfunction molecular background of neurological diseases (especially the molecular mechanisms behind neurodegeneration) stem cell based therapy of neurodegenerative disorders different imaging techniques Future plans After finishing the ECN programme successfully, I will start my PhD in molecular neurosciences. I would love to work in the field of neurodegenerative diseases. Within the framework of my PhD I am very keen to learn and apply new techniques, methods and tools. page up Grotheer, Mareike City and country of origin: Osterholz-Scharmbeck, Germany Educational background: B. Sc. in Biology (with a main focus on Neurobiology and Behaviour), Universität Göttingen Bachelor thesis: Neuroprotection through erythropoietin in the central nervous system of insects. Research on the mechanism of transduction. Student exchange program (ERASMUS), University of Aberdeen   Main scientific interests: Cognitive Neuroscience Functional MRI Behavioural Neuroscience ECN project internships: Evaluation of noninvasive high spatial resolution electromyography in patients with neuromuscular disorders. Supervisors: Dr. Ingo Kleiter, Prof. Dr. Willhelm Schulte-Mattler White matter alterations after Macular Degeneration examined by Diffusion Tensor Imaging. Supervisors: Dr. Anton L. Beer, Prof. Dr. Mark Greenlee Effects of Oxytocin in a social fear conditioning paradigm. Supervisors: Iulia Toth, Dr. David Slattery Future Plans and objectives: I wish to continue pursuing a career in neuroscience and in particular in cognitive neuroscience. The next steps on that path are first to successfully earn my Master?s Degree and then to start an interesting PhD project in psychology. page up Izurieta Hidalgo, Natalie City and country of origin: Quito, Ecuador Educational background: Medical Doctor (MD) (2003 ? 2009), Universidad San Francisco de Quito. Ecuador B.A in Psychology (2003-2010), Universidad San Francisco de Quito. Ecuador       Main scientific interests: Psychiatry Neuroendocrinology Neuropsychopharmacology Project Practicums: Multidimensional Assessment of Daytime Sleepiness: The association of different diagnostic measurements of sleepiness with different sleep disorders. Bezirksklinikum. Department of Psychiatry, Psychosomatic Medicine and Psychotherapy, University of Regensburg. Supervision: Dr. Peter Gesler, Dr. Roland Popp. Neuroimaging in Niemann Pick Disease Patients with mutations in the cholesterol transporter NPC. Department of Psychiatry, Psychosomatic Medicine and Psychotherapy, University of Regensburg, Germany. Supervision: P.D. Hans Klünemann. The effect of a specific GSK3 Inhibitor on maternal behavior in rats. Department of Behavioural and Molecular Neurobiology, University of Regensburg. Supervision: Dr. David Slattery, Katherina Hillerer. Future plans and objectives: During my Master thesis my objective is to learn further methods for translational and clinical research, specially functional neuroimaging, cognitive neuroscience and neuroendocrinology. After successful completion of my Master degree, I want to become a psychiatrist and do clinical research on the field. page up Kaczmarek, Veronika City and country of origin: Sinsheim, Deutschland Educational background: Bachelor of Science in Biology at University of Regensburg. Bachelor thesis: Pharmacological manipulation of Vasopressin 1aand Oxytocin Receptors in the brain of lactating rats: The influence on maternal aggression. Supervison: Dr. Oliver Bosch   Internships: Research on Niemann Pick Disease Type C? mutations in the NPC gene lead to deficits in cholesterol transport. Department of Psychiatry, Psychosomatic Medicine and Psychotherapy, Memory clinc; Bezirksklinikum, Regensburg. Supervision: P.D. Hans Klünemann. High spatial resolution electromyography: a noninvasive approach for the diagnosis of neuromuscular disorders. Department of Neurology, Bezirksklinikum Regensburg. Supervision: Prof. Schulte? Mattler. Fluoxetine mediated effects on adult neural stem cells. Department of molecular Neurology, University hospital, Erlangen. Supervision: Prof. Jürgen Winkler, Dr. Zacharias Kohl, and PhD Tina Schrödel. Publication: During my internship at the memory clinc: NeuroTransmitter, Springer Medizin, 2011/09: Frühdiagnostik bei Demenz: DemTect? einfach, schnell und trotzdem zuverlässig. Kaczmarek V., Kastner I., Klünemann H.H. Main scientific interest Neuroendocrinology Neurodegenerative diseases: stem cell based therapy, molecular mechanisms Future plans and objectives: During my Master thesis I want to improve my technical skills and gain expertise in further methods. After finishing the Master´s Programme in Experimental and clinical Neurosciences I will continue with a PhD in a field of my scientific interest. page up Kalepu, Srikrishna Rajakiran City and country of origin: Hyderabad, India. Educational background: Engineering in Biotechnology (2006-2010) from Sreenidhi Institute of Science and Technology, Hyderabad. Summer Project : Study of NADH Dehydrogenase Gene Mutations in Neuromuscular Disorders under supervision of Dr. K. Thangaraj, Scientist E-II, Evolutionary and Medical Genetics Laboratory, Centre for Cellular and Molecular Biology (CCMB), Hyderabad. Thesis : Electrophysiological study of Autonomic Nervous System in Non-Diabetic End Stage Renal Disease (ESRD) Patients under supervision of Dr. E. Srikanth Reddy, Consultant Neurophysician, Kamineni Hospitals, Hyderabad. Main scientific interests: Psychopathology Psychotherapy Influence of Circadian Rhythm on emotions Molecular Mechanisms &amp; intention of dreams Molecular drug targets for neurodegenerative diseases Project Practicums : Functional analysis of a new Drosophila model for Parkinson?s disease.Supervisors: Juan Antonio Navarro Langa, Postdoctoral Researcher &amp; Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly, Department of  Developmental Biology, University of Regensburg, Regensburg. Modulation of Ion Channels in Human Retinal Pigment Epithelium by Complement Activation. Supervisors: Andreas Genewsky, ECN Master?s student &amp; Prof. Dr. Olaf Strauss, Department of Experimental Ophthalmology, University Hospital Regensburg, Regensburg. Analysis of the Effect of the Receptor Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor 'Sunitinib' on the Migration and Proliferation of Brain Tumour Initiating Cells. Supervisors: Sylvia Moeckel, PhD student &amp; Dr. med. Peter Hau, Department of Neuro-oncology, University Hospital Regensburg, Regensburg. Future plans and objectives: To gain work experience after  Master?s to further improve scientific knowledge and pursue higher studies later on. page up Lo, Aileen Rose Y. City and country of origin: Manila, Philippines Educational background: 9/2010 to present:  International Master?s Program in Experimental and Clinical Neurosciences, University of Regensburg 2002-2006: Doctor of Medicine, University of Santo Tomas, Manila, Philippines 1998-2002: Bachelor of Science in Medical Technology, University of Santo Tomas, Manila, Philippines   Main scientific interests: Molecular and cellular interactions between the nervous system and immune system in health and disease, e.g., cell-cell communication via various signaling pathways, CNS immunodynamics, immunoregulatory mechanisms and the development of CNS autoimmunity, neuroinflammation, and neuroprotection. Project Internships: 6/2011-8/2011: The Role of Smad 7 in Immune Regulation.  Institute for Molecular Medicine, Universitätsmedizin der Johannes Gutenberg-Universität Mainz.  Supervisors: Dr. Ari Waisman and Dominika Lukas. 4/2011-6/2011:  Analysis of Smad-Independent TGF-beta Signaling during Th17 Differentiation, Neuroimmunology Laboratory, University Hospital, Regensburg.  Supervisors:  Dr. Ingo Kleiter and Maruf Hasan. 2/2011-4/2011: Characterization of the Novel Retinitis Pigmentosa Protein FAM161A.  Institute of Human Genetics, University Hospital, Regensburg.  Supervisors:  Dr. Heidi Stoehr and Frank Zach. Future Plans and Objectives: Further studies/training to unravel the very atoms of the normal and diseased human brain particularly in the context of Neuroimmunology, and ultimately to translate the knowledge into the clinic. page up Schrödl, Magdalena City and country of origin: Mühldorf am Inn, Germany Educational Background: B.Sc. Biology, University of Regensburg (2007-2010) International Master?s Programme ?Experimental and Clinical Neuroscience? (2010-2012)     Main scientific interest: Brain tumor research Research on stem cells as therapy for certain diseases Neurodeg. diseases Project Practicums: ?Auditory evoked potentials generated by rTMS-associated ?click?-stimuli? Supervision: Dr. Martin Schecklmann, Dr. Berthold Langguth Department of Psychiatry, University of Regensburg, Germany ?High-grade gliomas and BTICs: C/EBP ? and Stat 3 as master regulators of specific cancer signatures? Supervision: Dr. Arabel Vollmann, Dr. Peter Hau Department of Neurology, UKR Regensburg, Germany ?Role of CAIX in U251 cells: Endogenous hypoxia marker or pathogenic factor?? Supervision: Dr. Martin Proescholdt Department of Neurosurgery, UKR Regensburg, Germany Future Plans: PhD in Neuroscience or related subject E-Mail address: LenaSchroedl[at]web.de page up Stankova, Trayana Hristova City and country of origin: Sandanski, Bulgaria Educational background: Bachelor of Science in Molecular Biology, Sofia University       Main scientific interests: Mechanisms of memory formation Psychiatric diseases Future plans and objectives: PhD in Neuroscience page up Thuy, Andreas City and country of origin: Philadelphia, Pennsylvania Educational background: The Pennsylvania State University; Bachelor?s Degrees in Biology, German, and International Studies       Main scientific interests: Neurodegenerative Disease Neurological Disease Future plans and objectives: MD/Ph.D. in Neuroscience/Neurology I page up   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
<field name="important">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   Our Students » Student Careers » Student Publications you are here: Home » Our Students » 2010-2012 2010-2012 Blumenstock, Sonja Germany Chen, Xufeng China Chennappan, Saravanakkumar India Gehring, Isabell Germany Grotheer, Mareike Germany Izurieta Hidalgo, Natalie Ecuador Kaczmarek, Veronika Germany Kalepu, Srikrishna Rajakiran India Lo, Aileen Rose Y. Philippines Schrödl, Magdalena Germany Stankova, Trayana Hristova Bulgaria Thuy, Andreas USA   Blumenstock, Sonja City and country of origin: Regensburg, Germany Educational background: B.Sc. in Biochemistry, University of Regensburg, bachelor thesis on ?Expression and Purification of two DNA-binding Proteins and their Interaction with DNA? Research Internship at Dublin City University (Ireland) on steroid contamination in wastewater Research Internship at Arizona State University (USA) on the usage of the transcription factor AP-1 as a marker for neuronal activity Main scientific interests: Molecular neurosciences and neurobiochemistry Developmntal neuroscience Regenerative medicine Neurodegenerative and other neurological disorders Future plans and objectives: Proceed to a PhD in a field of my scientific interests Constantly improve my technical skills and knowledge in science Pursue a career in research or industry   page up Chen, Xufeng City and country of origin: Xiangfan, Hubei province, China Educational background: Bachelor of Science in Biotechnology in Hainan University ECN       Main scientific interests: Electrophysiology:  recording and analysis of cell current, patch clam (whole cell and single channel configuration) Cellular and molecular biology: primary neuron cell culture, live cell image Neuropathology: Parkinson's disease, Alzheimer etc  Future plans and objectives: Based on electrophysiology and molecular biology, through the knowledge and technologies I grasped in ECN, explore the fundamental pathogen of at least one neurology disease and thereout delve the pharmaceutically and therapeutically critical links      page up Chennappan, Saravanakkumar City and country of origin: Tamilnadu, India Educational background: B.Tech (Biotechnology), Bharathidasan University, India. MSc (Developmental Cell Biology), University of Sussex, UK.       Main scientific interests: Neurodegenerative diseases Neuronal development Neural plasticity and Neural stem cell biology. Future plans and objectives: Use the expertise gained from this masters program to bridge the gap between the core research of cellular neuroscience and the complex part of clinical studies, to address various questions arising in the field of regenerative neurobiology.   page up Gehring, Isabell City and country of origin: Rosenheim, Deutschland Educational background Studium Generale at Leibniz Kolleg Tuebingen (focus on Biochemistry, Journalism) B. Sc. in Biology, Ludwig- Maximilians- University Munich Bachelor thesis: Stem cells during the development of the brain- a comparison of Insecta with Mammalia   Main scientific interests neuronal dysfunction molecular background of neurological diseases (especially the molecular mechanisms behind neurodegeneration) stem cell based therapy of neurodegenerative disorders different imaging techniques Future plans After finishing the ECN programme successfully, I will start my PhD in molecular neurosciences. I would love to work in the field of neurodegenerative diseases. Within the framework of my PhD I am very keen to learn and apply new techniques, methods and tools. page up Grotheer, Mareike City and country of origin: Osterholz-Scharmbeck, Germany Educational background: B. Sc. in Biology (with a main focus on Neurobiology and Behaviour), Universität Göttingen Bachelor thesis: Neuroprotection through erythropoietin in the central nervous system of insects. Research on the mechanism of transduction. Student exchange program (ERASMUS), University of Aberdeen   Main scientific interests: Cognitive Neuroscience Functional MRI Behavioural Neuroscience ECN project internships: Evaluation of noninvasive high spatial resolution electromyography in patients with neuromuscular disorders. Supervisors: Dr. Ingo Kleiter, Prof. Dr. Willhelm Schulte-Mattler White matter alterations after Macular Degeneration examined by Diffusion Tensor Imaging. Supervisors: Dr. Anton L. Beer, Prof. Dr. Mark Greenlee Effects of Oxytocin in a social fear conditioning paradigm. Supervisors: Iulia Toth, Dr. David Slattery Future Plans and objectives: I wish to continue pursuing a career in neuroscience and in particular in cognitive neuroscience. The next steps on that path are first to successfully earn my Master?s Degree and then to start an interesting PhD project in psychology. page up Izurieta Hidalgo, Natalie City and country of origin: Quito, Ecuador Educational background: Medical Doctor (MD) (2003 ? 2009), Universidad San Francisco de Quito. Ecuador B.A in Psychology (2003-2010), Universidad San Francisco de Quito. Ecuador       Main scientific interests: Psychiatry Neuroendocrinology Neuropsychopharmacology Project Practicums: Multidimensional Assessment of Daytime Sleepiness: The association of different diagnostic measurements of sleepiness with different sleep disorders. Bezirksklinikum. Department of Psychiatry, Psychosomatic Medicine and Psychotherapy, University of Regensburg. Supervision: Dr. Peter Gesler, Dr. Roland Popp. Neuroimaging in Niemann Pick Disease Patients with mutations in the cholesterol transporter NPC. Department of Psychiatry, Psychosomatic Medicine and Psychotherapy, University of Regensburg, Germany. Supervision: P.D. Hans Klünemann. The effect of a specific GSK3 Inhibitor on maternal behavior in rats. Department of Behavioural and Molecular Neurobiology, University of Regensburg. Supervision: Dr. David Slattery, Katherina Hillerer. Future plans and objectives: During my Master thesis my objective is to learn further methods for translational and clinical research, specially functional neuroimaging, cognitive neuroscience and neuroendocrinology. After successful completion of my Master degree, I want to become a psychiatrist and do clinical research on the field. page up Kaczmarek, Veronika City and country of origin: Sinsheim, Deutschland Educational background: Bachelor of Science in Biology at University of Regensburg. Bachelor thesis: Pharmacological manipulation of Vasopressin 1aand Oxytocin Receptors in the brain of lactating rats: The influence on maternal aggression. Supervison: Dr. Oliver Bosch   Internships: Research on Niemann Pick Disease Type C? mutations in the NPC gene lead to deficits in cholesterol transport. Department of Psychiatry, Psychosomatic Medicine and Psychotherapy, Memory clinc; Bezirksklinikum, Regensburg. Supervision: P.D. Hans Klünemann. High spatial resolution electromyography: a noninvasive approach for the diagnosis of neuromuscular disorders. Department of Neurology, Bezirksklinikum Regensburg. Supervision: Prof. Schulte? Mattler. Fluoxetine mediated effects on adult neural stem cells. Department of molecular Neurology, University hospital, Erlangen. Supervision: Prof. Jürgen Winkler, Dr. Zacharias Kohl, and PhD Tina Schrödel. Publication: During my internship at the memory clinc: NeuroTransmitter, Springer Medizin, 2011/09: Frühdiagnostik bei Demenz: DemTect? einfach, schnell und trotzdem zuverlässig. Kaczmarek V., Kastner I., Klünemann H.H. Main scientific interest Neuroendocrinology Neurodegenerative diseases: stem cell based therapy, molecular mechanisms Future plans and objectives: During my Master thesis I want to improve my technical skills and gain expertise in further methods. After finishing the Master´s Programme in Experimental and clinical Neurosciences I will continue with a PhD in a field of my scientific interest. page up Kalepu, Srikrishna Rajakiran City and country of origin: Hyderabad, India. Educational background: Engineering in Biotechnology (2006-2010) from Sreenidhi Institute of Science and Technology, Hyderabad. Summer Project : Study of NADH Dehydrogenase Gene Mutations in Neuromuscular Disorders under supervision of Dr. K. Thangaraj, Scientist E-II, Evolutionary and Medical Genetics Laboratory, Centre for Cellular and Molecular Biology (CCMB), Hyderabad. Thesis : Electrophysiological study of Autonomic Nervous System in Non-Diabetic End Stage Renal Disease (ESRD) Patients under supervision of Dr. E. Srikanth Reddy, Consultant Neurophysician, Kamineni Hospitals, Hyderabad. Main scientific interests: Psychopathology Psychotherapy Influence of Circadian Rhythm on emotions Molecular Mechanisms &amp; intention of dreams Molecular drug targets for neurodegenerative diseases Project Practicums : Functional analysis of a new Drosophila model for Parkinson?s disease.Supervisors: Juan Antonio Navarro Langa, Postdoctoral Researcher &amp; Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly, Department of  Developmental Biology, University of Regensburg, Regensburg. Modulation of Ion Channels in Human Retinal Pigment Epithelium by Complement Activation. Supervisors: Andreas Genewsky, ECN Master?s student &amp; Prof. Dr. Olaf Strauss, Department of Experimental Ophthalmology, University Hospital Regensburg, Regensburg. Analysis of the Effect of the Receptor Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor 'Sunitinib' on the Migration and Proliferation of Brain Tumour Initiating Cells. Supervisors: Sylvia Moeckel, PhD student &amp; Dr. med. Peter Hau, Department of Neuro-oncology, University Hospital Regensburg, Regensburg. Future plans and objectives: To gain work experience after  Master?s to further improve scientific knowledge and pursue higher studies later on. page up Lo, Aileen Rose Y. City and country of origin: Manila, Philippines Educational background: 9/2010 to present:  International Master?s Program in Experimental and Clinical Neurosciences, University of Regensburg 2002-2006: Doctor of Medicine, University of Santo Tomas, Manila, Philippines 1998-2002: Bachelor of Science in Medical Technology, University of Santo Tomas, Manila, Philippines   Main scientific interests: Molecular and cellular interactions between the nervous system and immune system in health and disease, e.g., cell-cell communication via various signaling pathways, CNS immunodynamics, immunoregulatory mechanisms and the development of CNS autoimmunity, neuroinflammation, and neuroprotection. Project Internships: 6/2011-8/2011: The Role of Smad 7 in Immune Regulation.  Institute for Molecular Medicine, Universitätsmedizin der Johannes Gutenberg-Universität Mainz.  Supervisors: Dr. Ari Waisman and Dominika Lukas. 4/2011-6/2011:  Analysis of Smad-Independent TGF-beta Signaling during Th17 Differentiation, Neuroimmunology Laboratory, University Hospital, Regensburg.  Supervisors:  Dr. Ingo Kleiter and Maruf Hasan. 2/2011-4/2011: Characterization of the Novel Retinitis Pigmentosa Protein FAM161A.  Institute of Human Genetics, University Hospital, Regensburg.  Supervisors:  Dr. Heidi Stoehr and Frank Zach. Future Plans and Objectives: Further studies/training to unravel the very atoms of the normal and diseased human brain particularly in the context of Neuroimmunology, and ultimately to translate the knowledge into the clinic. page up Schrödl, Magdalena City and country of origin: Mühldorf am Inn, Germany Educational Background: B.Sc. Biology, University of Regensburg (2007-2010) International Master?s Programme ?Experimental and Clinical Neuroscience? (2010-2012)     Main scientific interest: Brain tumor research Research on stem cells as therapy for certain diseases Neurodeg. diseases Project Practicums: ?Auditory evoked potentials generated by rTMS-associated ?click?-stimuli? Supervision: Dr. Martin Schecklmann, Dr. Berthold Langguth Department of Psychiatry, University of Regensburg, Germany ?High-grade gliomas and BTICs: C/EBP ? and Stat 3 as master regulators of specific cancer signatures? Supervision: Dr. Arabel Vollmann, Dr. Peter Hau Department of Neurology, UKR Regensburg, Germany ?Role of CAIX in U251 cells: Endogenous hypoxia marker or pathogenic factor?? Supervision: Dr. Martin Proescholdt Department of Neurosurgery, UKR Regensburg, Germany Future Plans: PhD in Neuroscience or related subject E-Mail address: LenaSchroedl[at]web.de page up Stankova, Trayana Hristova City and country of origin: Sandanski, Bulgaria Educational background: Bachelor of Science in Molecular Biology, Sofia University       Main scientific interests: Mechanisms of memory formation Psychiatric diseases Future plans and objectives: PhD in Neuroscience page up Thuy, Andreas City and country of origin: Philadelphia, Pennsylvania Educational background: The Pennsylvania State University; Bachelor?s Degrees in Biology, German, and International Studies       Main scientific interests: Neurodegenerative Disease Neurological Disease Future plans and objectives: MD/Ph.D. in Neuroscience/Neurology I page up   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Elite/html/students.html</field>
<field name="title">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Elite/html/students.html</field>
<field name="content">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   What is ECN? Programme Committee Our Faculty Our Students News News Archive you are here: Home » Our Students Our Students 2013-2015 2012-2014 2011-2013 2010-2012 2009-2011 2008-2010 2007-2009 2006-2008 Student Careers Student Publications New Students 2011-2013 Students of the Programme 2011-2013: We are proud to announce that 14 new students have been selected to join the ECN programme 2011-2013. Their names can be found here: » Students   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
<field name="important">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   What is ECN? Programme Committee Our Faculty Our Students News News Archive you are here: Home » Our Students Our Students 2013-2015 2012-2014 2011-2013 2010-2012 2009-2011 2008-2010 2007-2009 2006-2008 Student Careers Student Publications New Students 2011-2013 Students of the Programme 2011-2013: We are proud to announce that 14 new students have been selected to join the ECN programme 2011-2013. Their names can be found here: » Students   home | contact us | imprint | webmaster   © University of Regensburg  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Elite/html/who.html</field>
<field name="title">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Elite/html/who.html</field>
<field name="content">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   Application &amp; Enrolment Required Documents Tuition Fees &amp; Costs of living FAQs you are here: Home » Application Who Should Attend? Applicants must hold a Bachelor degree, or equivalent, in biology, chemistry, medicine, psychology, or a closely related subject area. Also eligible to apply are students in the final year of their Bachelor, or equivalent, degree courses, provided that the degree will be conferred prior to the enrollment date within the MSc programme. Applicants who are not native speakers of the English language must demonstrate English proficiency by obtaining acceptable results in an internationally recognized test (e.g., TOEFL, IELTS, APIEL, CPE). Proof of higher education in English or a residence of reasonable length in an English-speaking country may also be acceptable upon the decision of the Admissions Committee. Language skills may also be evaluated during the personal interviews of selected candidates (see » Application &amp; Enrolment). page up     home | contact us | imprint | webmaster 2011 © University of Regensburg  </field>
<field name="important">ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg ECN Experimental &amp; Clinical Neurosciences | Master's Programme University of Regensburg   Home About ECN Programme Description Application Links Contact Us   Application &amp; Enrolment Required Documents Tuition Fees &amp; Costs of living FAQs you are here: Home » Application Who Should Attend? Applicants must hold a Bachelor degree, or equivalent, in biology, chemistry, medicine, psychology, or a closely related subject area. Also eligible to apply are students in the final year of their Bachelor, or equivalent, degree courses, provided that the degree will be conferred prior to the enrollment date within the MSc programme. Applicants who are not native speakers of the English language must demonstrate English proficiency by obtaining acceptable results in an internationally recognized test (e.g., TOEFL, IELTS, APIEL, CPE). Proof of higher education in English or a residence of reasonable length in an English-speaking country may also be acceptable upon the decision of the Admissions Committee. Language skills may also be evaluated during the personal interviews of selected candidates (see » Application &amp; Enrolment). page up     home | contact us | imprint | webmaster 2011 © University of Regensburg  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Flor/Download/index.html</field>
<field name="title">AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Flor/Download/index.html</field>
<field name="content">AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor Most relevant recent Publications (year 2000 until present) 1) Orthosteric versus allosteric GPCR activation: The great challenge of group-III mGluRs. Flor PJ, Acher FC. Biochem Pharmacol. 2012 Apr 24; in press. PMID: 22554564 (PDF file) 2) Pharmacological interference with metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 7 but not subtype 5 differentially affects within- and between-session extinction of Pavlovian conditioned fear. Toth I, Dietz M, Peterlik D, Huber SE, Fendt M, Neumann ID, Flor PJ, Slattery DA. Neuropharmacology. 2012 Mar;62(4):1619-26. PMID: 22079159 (PDF file) 3) Pharmacological modulation of mGluR7 with AMN082 and MMPIP exerts specific influences on alcohol consumption and preference in rats. Bahi A, Fizia K, Dietz M, Gasparini F, Flor PJ. Addict Biol. 2012 Mar;17(2):235-47. PMID: 21392179 (PDF file) 4) Exciting times beyond the brain: metabotropic glutamate receptors in peripheral and non-neural tissues. Julio-Pieper M, Flor PJ, Dinan TG, Cryan JF. Pharmacol Rev. 2011 Mar;63(1):35-58. PMID: 21228260 (PDF file) 5) Metabotropic glutamate 7 receptor subtype modulates motor symptoms in rodent models of Parkinson's disease. Greco B, Lopez S, van der Putten H, Flor PJ, Amalric M. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 2010 Mar;332(3):1064-71. PMID:19940105 (PDF file) 6) mGluR7 facilitates extinction of aversive memories and controls amygdala plasticity. Fendt M, Schmid S, Thakker DR, Jacobson LH, Yamamoto R, Mitsukawa K, Maier R, Natt F, Hüsken D, Kelly PH, McAllister KH, Hoyer D, van der Putten H, Cryan JF, Flor PJ. Mol Psychiatry. 2008 Oct;13(10):970-9.   PMID: 17712315 (PDF file) 7) Metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 7 ablation causes dysregulation of the HPA axis and increases hippocampal BDNF protein levels: implications for stress-related psychiatric disorders. Mitsukawa K, Mombereau C, Lötscher E, Uzunov DP, van der Putten H, Flor PJ, Cryan JF. Neuropsychopharmacology. 2006 Jun;31(6):1112-22. PMID: 16237391 (PDF file) 8) A selective metabotropic glutamate receptor 7 agonist: activation of receptor signaling via an allosteric site modulates stress parameters in vivo. Mitsukawa K, Yamamoto R, Ofner S, Nozulak J, Pescott O, Lukic S, Stoehr N, Mombereau C, Kuhn R, McAllister KH, van der Putten H, Cryan JF, Flor PJ. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2005 Dec 20;102(51):18712-7.   PMID: 16339898 (PDF file) 9) (-)-PHCCC, a positive allosteric modulator of mGluR4: characterization, mechanism of action, and neuroprotection. Maj M, Bruno V, Dragic Z, Yamamoto R, Battaglia G, Inderbitzin W, Stoehr N, Stein T, Gasparini F, Vranesic I, Kuhn R, Nicoletti F, Flor PJ. Neuropharmacology. 2003 Dec;45(7):895-906. PMID: 14573382 (PDF file)   10) Antidepressant and anxiolytic-like effects in mice lacking the group III metabotropic glutamate receptor mGluR7. Cryan JF, Kelly PH, Neijt HC, Sansig G, Flor PJ, van Der Putten H. Eur J Neurosci. 2003 Jun;17(11):2409-17. PMID: 12814372 (PDF file) 11) Selective blockade of metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 5 is neuroprotective. Bruno V, Ksiazek I, Battaglia G, Lukic S, Leonhardt T, Sauer D, Gasparini F, Kuhn R, Nicoletti F, Flor PJ. Neuropharmacology. 2000 Sep;39(12):2223-30. PMID: 10974306 (PDF file) 12) Selective activation of mGlu4 metabotropic glutamate receptors is protective against excitotoxic neuronal death. Bruno V, Battaglia G, Ksiazek I, van der Putten H, Catania MV, Giuffrida R, Lukic S, Leonhardt T, Inderbitzin W, Gasparini F, Kuhn R, Hampson DR, Nicoletti F, Flor PJ. J Neurosci. 2000 Sep 1;20(17):6413-20. PMID: 10964947 (PDF file)</field>
<field name="important">AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor Most relevant recent Publications (year 2000 until present) 1) Orthosteric versus allosteric GPCR activation: The great challenge of group-III mGluRs. Flor PJ, Acher FC. Biochem Pharmacol. 2012 Apr 24; in press. PMID: 22554564 (PDF file) 2) Pharmacological interference with metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 7 but not subtype 5 differentially affects within- and between-session extinction of Pavlovian conditioned fear. Toth I, Dietz M, Peterlik D, Huber SE, Fendt M, Neumann ID, Flor PJ, Slattery DA. Neuropharmacology. 2012 Mar;62(4):1619-26. PMID: 22079159 (PDF file) 3) Pharmacological modulation of mGluR7 with AMN082 and MMPIP exerts specific influences on alcohol consumption and preference in rats. Bahi A, Fizia K, Dietz M, Gasparini F, Flor PJ. Addict Biol. 2012 Mar;17(2):235-47. PMID: 21392179 (PDF file) 4) Exciting times beyond the brain: metabotropic glutamate receptors in peripheral and non-neural tissues. Julio-Pieper M, Flor PJ, Dinan TG, Cryan JF. Pharmacol Rev. 2011 Mar;63(1):35-58. PMID: 21228260 (PDF file) 5) Metabotropic glutamate 7 receptor subtype modulates motor symptoms in rodent models of Parkinson's disease. Greco B, Lopez S, van der Putten H, Flor PJ, Amalric M. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 2010 Mar;332(3):1064-71. PMID:19940105 (PDF file) 6) mGluR7 facilitates extinction of aversive memories and controls amygdala plasticity. Fendt M, Schmid S, Thakker DR, Jacobson LH, Yamamoto R, Mitsukawa K, Maier R, Natt F, Hüsken D, Kelly PH, McAllister KH, Hoyer D, van der Putten H, Cryan JF, Flor PJ. Mol Psychiatry. 2008 Oct;13(10):970-9.   PMID: 17712315 (PDF file) 7) Metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 7 ablation causes dysregulation of the HPA axis and increases hippocampal BDNF protein levels: implications for stress-related psychiatric disorders. Mitsukawa K, Mombereau C, Lötscher E, Uzunov DP, van der Putten H, Flor PJ, Cryan JF. Neuropsychopharmacology. 2006 Jun;31(6):1112-22. PMID: 16237391 (PDF file) 8) A selective metabotropic glutamate receptor 7 agonist: activation of receptor signaling via an allosteric site modulates stress parameters in vivo. Mitsukawa K, Yamamoto R, Ofner S, Nozulak J, Pescott O, Lukic S, Stoehr N, Mombereau C, Kuhn R, McAllister KH, van der Putten H, Cryan JF, Flor PJ. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2005 Dec 20;102(51):18712-7.   PMID: 16339898 (PDF file) 9) (-)-PHCCC, a positive allosteric modulator of mGluR4: characterization, mechanism of action, and neuroprotection. Maj M, Bruno V, Dragic Z, Yamamoto R, Battaglia G, Inderbitzin W, Stoehr N, Stein T, Gasparini F, Vranesic I, Kuhn R, Nicoletti F, Flor PJ. Neuropharmacology. 2003 Dec;45(7):895-906. PMID: 14573382 (PDF file)   10) Antidepressant and anxiolytic-like effects in mice lacking the group III metabotropic glutamate receptor mGluR7. Cryan JF, Kelly PH, Neijt HC, Sansig G, Flor PJ, van Der Putten H. Eur J Neurosci. 2003 Jun;17(11):2409-17. PMID: 12814372 (PDF file) 11) Selective blockade of metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 5 is neuroprotective. Bruno V, Ksiazek I, Battaglia G, Lukic S, Leonhardt T, Sauer D, Gasparini F, Kuhn R, Nicoletti F, Flor PJ. Neuropharmacology. 2000 Sep;39(12):2223-30. PMID: 10974306 (PDF file) 12) Selective activation of mGlu4 metabotropic glutamate receptors is protective against excitotoxic neuronal death. Bruno V, Battaglia G, Ksiazek I, van der Putten H, Catania MV, Giuffrida R, Lukic S, Leonhardt T, Inderbitzin W, Gasparini F, Kuhn R, Hampson DR, Nicoletti F, Flor PJ. J Neurosci. 2000 Sep 1;20(17):6413-20. PMID: 10964947 (PDF file)</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Flor/OpenPositions/index.html</field>
<field name="title">AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Flor/OpenPositions/index.html</field>
<field name="content">AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor Open Positions - not available at the moment -</field>
<field name="important">AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor Open Positions - not available at the moment -</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Flor/Publications/NicoleUschold/index.html</field>
<field name="title">AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Flor/Publications/NicoleUschold/index.html</field>
<field name="content">AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor Publications ? Dr. Nicole Uschold-Schmidt 2014 Gee CE, Peterlik D, Neuhäuser C, Bouhelal R, Kaupmann K, Laue G, Uschold-Schmidt N, Feuerbach D, Zimmermann K, Ofner S, Cryan JF, van der Putten H, Fendt M, Vranesic I, Glatthar R, Flor PJ. Blocking Metabotropic Glutamate Receptor Subtype 7 (mGlu7) via the Venus Flytrap Domain (VFTD) Inhibits Amygdala Plasticity, Stress, and Anxiety-related Behavior. Journal of Biological Chemistry 289(16):10975-8 Peters S, Slattery DA, Uschold-Schmidt N, Reber SO, Neumann ID. Dose-dependent effects of chronic central infusion of oxytocin on anxiety, chronic stress-related parameters and oxytocin receptor binding in mice. Psychoneuroendocrinology 42:225-36. 2013 Füchsl AM*, Uschold-Schmidt N*, Reber SO. Chronic psychosocial stress in male mice causes an up-regulation of scavenger receptor class B type 1 protein in the adrenal glands. Stress 16(4):461-8.  * Co-First Authors Uschold-Schmidt N, Peterlik D, Füchsl AM, Reber SO. HPA axis changes during the initial phase of psychosocial stressor exposure in male mice. Journal of Endocrinology 218(2):193-203. 2012 Bartlang MS, Neumann ID, Slattery DA, Uschold-Schmidt N, Kraus D, Helfrich-Forster C &amp; Reber SO. Time matters: pathological effects of repeated psychosocial stress during the active, but not inactive, phase of male mice. Journal of Endocrinology 215: 425-437. Uschold-Schmidt N, Nyuyki KD, Fuechsl AM, Neumann ID &amp; Reber SO. Chronic psychosocial stress results in sensitization of the HPA axis to acute heterotypic stressors despite a reduction of adrenal in vitro ACTH responsiveness. Psychoneuroendocrinology 37: 1676-1687. Slattery DA, Uschold N, Magoni M, Bar J, Popoli M, Neumann ID &amp; Reber SO. Behavioural consequences of two chronic psychosocial stress paradigms: anxiety without depression. Psychoneuroendocrinology 37: 702-714.   2010 Schmidt D, Reber SO, Botteron C, Barth T, Peterlik D, Uschold N, Mannel DN &amp; Lechner A. Chronic psychosocial stress promotes systemic immune activation and the development of inflammatory Th cell responses. Brain, Behavior and Immunity 24: 1097-1104.  </field>
<field name="important">AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor Publications ? Dr. Nicole Uschold-Schmidt 2014 Gee CE, Peterlik D, Neuhäuser C, Bouhelal R, Kaupmann K, Laue G, Uschold-Schmidt N, Feuerbach D, Zimmermann K, Ofner S, Cryan JF, van der Putten H, Fendt M, Vranesic I, Glatthar R, Flor PJ. Blocking Metabotropic Glutamate Receptor Subtype 7 (mGlu7) via the Venus Flytrap Domain (VFTD) Inhibits Amygdala Plasticity, Stress, and Anxiety-related Behavior. Journal of Biological Chemistry 289(16):10975-8 Peters S, Slattery DA, Uschold-Schmidt N, Reber SO, Neumann ID. Dose-dependent effects of chronic central infusion of oxytocin on anxiety, chronic stress-related parameters and oxytocin receptor binding in mice. Psychoneuroendocrinology 42:225-36. 2013 Füchsl AM*, Uschold-Schmidt N*, Reber SO. Chronic psychosocial stress in male mice causes an up-regulation of scavenger receptor class B type 1 protein in the adrenal glands. Stress 16(4):461-8.  * Co-First Authors Uschold-Schmidt N, Peterlik D, Füchsl AM, Reber SO. HPA axis changes during the initial phase of psychosocial stressor exposure in male mice. Journal of Endocrinology 218(2):193-203. 2012 Bartlang MS, Neumann ID, Slattery DA, Uschold-Schmidt N, Kraus D, Helfrich-Forster C &amp; Reber SO. Time matters: pathological effects of repeated psychosocial stress during the active, but not inactive, phase of male mice. Journal of Endocrinology 215: 425-437. Uschold-Schmidt N, Nyuyki KD, Fuechsl AM, Neumann ID &amp; Reber SO. Chronic psychosocial stress results in sensitization of the HPA axis to acute heterotypic stressors despite a reduction of adrenal in vitro ACTH responsiveness. Psychoneuroendocrinology 37: 1676-1687. Slattery DA, Uschold N, Magoni M, Bar J, Popoli M, Neumann ID &amp; Reber SO. Behavioural consequences of two chronic psychosocial stress paradigms: anxiety without depression. Psychoneuroendocrinology 37: 702-714.   2010 Schmidt D, Reber SO, Botteron C, Barth T, Peterlik D, Uschold N, Mannel DN &amp; Lechner A. Chronic psychosocial stress promotes systemic immune activation and the development of inflammatory Th cell responses. Brain, Behavior and Immunity 24: 1097-1104.  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Flor/Publications/PeterFlor/index.html</field>
<field name="title">AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Flor/Publications/PeterFlor/index.html</field>
<field name="content">AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor Publications ? Prof. Dr. Peter J. Flor http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?Db=pubmed&amp;Cmd=Search&amp;Term=%22Flor%20P%22 53) Functional monoclonal antibody acts as a biased agonist by inducing internalization of metabotropic glutamate receptor 7. Ullmer C, Zoffmann S, Bohrmann B, Matile BH, Lindemann L, Flor PJ, Malherbe P. British Journal of Pharmacology. 2012; in press. IF=4.4 52) Orthosteric versus allosteric GPCR activation: The great challenge of group-III mGluRs. Flor PJ, Acher FC. Biochemical Pharmacology. 2012; in press. IF=4.7 PMID:22554564 51) Pharmacological interference with metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 7 but not subtype 5 differentially affects within- and between-session extinction of Pavlovian conditioned fear. Toth I, Dietz M, Peterlik D, Huber SE, Fendt M, Neumann ID, Flor PJ, Slattery DA. Neuropharmacology. 2012 Mar;62(4):1619-26. IF=4.8 PMID:22079159   50) Pharmacological modulation of mGluR7 with AMN082 and MMPIP exerts specific influences on alcohol consumption and preference in rats. Bahi A, Fizia K, Dietz M, Gasparini F, Flor PJ. Addict Biol. 2012 Mar;17(2):235-47. IF=4.8 PMID:21392179 49) Exciting times beyond the brain: metabotropic glutamate receptors in peripheral and non-neural tissues. Julio-Pieper M, Flor PJ, Dinan TG, Cryan JF. Pharmacol Rev. 2011 Mar;63(1):35-58. IF=20.2 PMID: 21228260 48) Metabotropic glutamate receptor 7: at the interface of cognition and emotion. O'Connor RM, Finger BC, Flor PJ, Cryan JF. Eur J Pharmacol. 2010 Aug 10;639(1-3):123-31. IF=2.7 PMID: 20371242  47) Antisense oligonucleotides. Neumann ID, Flor PJ. Encyclopedia of Psychopharmacology. 2010, Ian P. Stolerman (ed.), Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg 2010.   46) Metabotropic glutamate 7 receptor subtype modulates motor symptoms in rodent models of Parkinson's disease. Greco B, Lopez S, van der Putten H, Flor PJ, Amalric M. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 2010 Mar;332(3):1064-71. IF=4.0 PMID: 19940105  ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------- Publications before coming to Regensburg: 45) Selective activation of metabotropic G-protein-coupled glutamate 7 receptor elicits anxiolytic-like effects in mice by modulating GABAergic neurotransmission. Stachowicz K, Brañski P, K?ak K, van der Putten H, Cryan JF, Flor PJ, Andrzej P. Behav Pharmacol. 2008 Sep;19(5-6):597-603. PMID: 18690114   44) Amygdaloid metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 7 is involved in the acquisition of conditioned fear. Siegl S, Flor PJ, Fendt M. Neuroreport. 2008 Jul 16;19(11):1147-50. PMID: 18596617   43) mGluR7 facilitates extinction of aversive memories and controls amygdala plasticity. Fendt M, Schmid S, Thakker DR, Jacobson LH, Yamamoto R, Mitsukawa K, Maier R, Natt F, Hüsken D, Kelly PH, McAllister KH, Hoyer D, van der Putten H, Cryan JF, Flor PJ. Mol Psychiatry. 2008 Oct;13(10):970-9. IF=12.5   PMID: 17712315 42) Activation of the mGlu7 receptor elicits antidepressant-like effects in mice. Palucha A, Klak K, Branski P, van der Putten H, Flor PJ, Pilc A. Psychopharmacology (Berl). 2007 Nov;194(4):555-62.   PMID: 17622518 ] 41) Functional role of mGluR1 and mGluR4 in pilocarpine-induced temporal lobe epilepsy. Pitsch J, Schoch S, Gueler N, Flor PJ, van der Putten H, Becker AJ. Neurobiol Dis. 2007 Jun;26(3):623-33.   PMID: 17446080   40) Night blindness-associated mutations in the ligand-binding, cysteine-rich, and intracellular domains of the metabotropic glutamate receptor 6 abolish protein trafficking. Zeitz C, Forster U, Neidhardt J, Feil S, Kälin S, Leifert D, Flor PJ, Berger W. Hum Mutat. 2007 Aug;28(8):771-80. PMID: 17405131  ] 39) Synthesis and preliminary pharmacological evaluation of the four stereoisomers of (2S)-2-(2'-phosphono-3'-phenylcyclopropyl)glycine, the first class of 3'-substituted trans C1'-2'-2-(2'-phosphonocyclopropyl)glycines. Marinozzi M, Serpi M, Amori L, Gavilan Diaz M, Costantino G, Meyer U, Flor PJ, Gasparini F, Heckendorn R, Kuhn R, Giorgi G, Hermit MB, Thomsen C, Pellicciari R. Bioorg Med Chem. 2007 May 1;15(9):3161-70.   PMID: 17350267   38) Global down-regulation of gene expression in the brain using RNA interference, with emphasis on monoamine transporters and GPCRs: implications for target characterization in psychiatric and neurological disorders. Hoyer D, Thakker DR, Natt F, Maier R, Huesken D, Müller M, Flor P, VAN DER Putten H, Schmutz M, Bilbe G, Cryan JF. J Recept Signal Transduct Res. 2006;26(5-6):527-47. PMID: 17118797   37) Metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 7 ablation causes dysregulation of the HPA axis and increases hippocampal BDNF protein levels: implications for stress-related psychiatric disorders. Mitsukawa K, Mombereau C, Lötscher E, Uzunov DP, van der Putten H, Flor PJ, Cryan JF. Neuropsychopharmacology. 2006 Jun;31(6):1112-22. PMID: 16237391  36) A selective metabotropic glutamate receptor 7 agonist: activation of receptor signaling via an allosteric site modulates stress parameters in vivo. Mitsukawa K, Yamamoto R, Ofner S, Nozulak J, Pescott O, Lukic S, Stoehr N, Mombereau C, Kuhn R, McAllister KH, van der Putten H, Cryan JF, Flor PJ. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2005 Dec 20;102(51):18712-7. IF=10.2    PMID: 16339898   35) (-)-PHCCC, a positive allosteric modulator of mGluR4: characterization, mechanism of action, and neuroprotection. Maj M, Bruno V, Dragic Z, Yamamoto R, Battaglia G, Inderbitzin W, Stoehr N, Stein T, Gasparini F, Vranesic I, Kuhn R, Nicoletti F, Flor PJ. Neuropharmacology. 2003 Dec;45(7):895-906. PMID: 14573382   34) Antidepressant and anxiolytic-like effects in mice lacking the group III metabotropic glutamate receptor mGluR7. Cryan JF, Kelly PH, Neijt HC, Sansig G, Flor PJ, van Der Putten H. Eur J Neurosci. 2003 Jun;17(11):2409-17. PMID: 12814372   33) Neuroprotective activity of metabotropic glutamate receptor ligands. Flor PJ, Battaglia G, Nicoletti F, Gasparini F, Bruno V. Adv Exp Med Biol. 2002;513:197-223. Review. PMID: 12575822   32) In vitro and in vivo characterization of MPEP, an allosteric modulator of the metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 5: review article. Kuhn R, Pagano A, Stoehr N, Vranesic I, Flor PJ, Lingenhöhl K, Spooren W, Gentsch C, Vassout A, Pilc A, Gasparini F. Amino Acids. 2002;23(1-3):207-11. Review. PMID: 12373539   31) [(3)H]-M-MPEP, a potent, subtype-selective radioligand for the metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 5. Gasparini F, Andres H, Flor PJ, Heinrich M, Inderbitzin W, Lingenhöhl K, Müller H, Munk VC, Omilusik K, Stierlin C, Stoehr N, Vranesic I, Kuhn R. Bioorg Med Chem Lett. 2002 Feb 11;12(3):407-9. PMID: 11814808   30) Increased seizure susceptibility in mice lacking metabotropic glutamate receptor 7. Sansig G, Bushell TJ, Clarke VR, Rozov A, Burnashev N, Portet C, Gasparini F, Schmutz M, Klebs K, Shigemoto R, Flor PJ, Kuhn R, Knoepfel T, Schroeder M, Hampson DR, Collett VJ, Zhang C, Duvoisin RM, Collingridge GL, van Der Putten H. J Neurosci. 2001 Nov 15;21(22):8734-45. PMID: 11698585   29) Metabotropic glutamate receptor subtypes as targets for neuroprotective drugs. Bruno V, Battaglia G, Copani A, D'Onofrio M, Di Iorio P, De Blasi A, Melchiorri D, Flor PJ, Nicoletti F. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab. 2001 Sep;21(9):1013-33. Review. PMID: 11524608 28) Discovery and characterization of non-competitive antagonists of group I metabotropic glutamate receptors. Gasparini F, Floersheim P, Flor PJ, Heinrich M, Inderbitzin W, Ott D, Pagano A, Stierlin C, Stoehr N, Vranesic I, Kuhn R. Farmaco. 2001 Jan-Feb;56(1-2):95-9. Review. PMID: 11347975   27) An activity-dependent switch from facilitation to inhibition in the control of excitotoxicity by group I metabotropic glutamate receptors. Bruno V, Battaglia G, Copani A, Cespédes VM, Galindo MF, Ceña V, Sánchez-Prieto J, Gasparini F, Kuhn R, Flor PJ, Nicoletti F. Eur J Neurosci. 2001 Apr;13(8):1469-78. PMID: 11328342   26) Chiral resolution, pharmacological characterization, and receptor docking of the noncompetitive mGlu1 receptor antagonist (+/-)-2-hydroxyimino- 1a, 2-dihydro-1H-7-oxacyclopropa[b]naphthalene-7a-carboxylic acid ethyl ester. Ott D, Floersheim P, Inderbitzin W, Stoehr N, Francotte E, Lecis G, Richert P, Rihs G, Flor PJ, Kuhn R, Gasparini F. J Med Chem. 2000 Nov 16;43(23):4428-36. PMID: 11087567   25) Metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 5 (mGlu5) and nociceptive function. I. Selective blockade of mGlu5 receptors in models of acute, persistent and chronic pain. Walker K, Bowes M, Panesar M, Davis A, Gentry C, Kesingland A, Gasparini F, Spooren W, Stoehr N, Pagano A, Flor PJ, Vranesic I, Lingenhoehl K, Johnson EC, Varney M, Urban L, Kuhn R. Neuropharmacology. 2001;40(1):1-9. PMID: 11077065   24) Selective blockade of metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 5 is neuroprotective. Bruno V, Ksiazek I, Battaglia G, Lukic S, Leonhardt T, Sauer D, Gasparini F, Kuhn R, Nicoletti F, Flor PJ. Neuropharmacology. 2000 Sep;39(12):2223-30. PMID: 10974306   23) Selective activation of mGlu4 metabotropic glutamate receptors is protective against excitotoxic neuronal death. Bruno V, Battaglia G, Ksiazek I, van der Putten H, Catania MV, Giuffrida R, Lukic S, Leonhardt T, Inderbitzin W, Gasparini F, Kuhn R, Hampson DR, Nicoletti F, Flor PJ. J Neurosci. 2000 Sep 1;20(17):6413-20. PMID: 10964947 22) The non-competitive antagonists 2-methyl-6-(phenylethynyl)pyridine and 7-hydroxyiminocyclopropan[b]chromen-1a-carboxylic acid ethyl ester interact with overlapping binding pockets in the transmembrane region of group I metabotropic glutamate receptors. Pagano A, Ruegg D, Litschig S, Stoehr N, Stierlin C, Heinrich M, Floersheim P, Prezèau L, Carroll F, Pin JP, Cambria A, Vranesic I, Flor PJ, Gasparini F, Kuhn R. J Biol Chem. 2000 Oct 27;275(43):33750-8. PMID: 10934211 21) Synthesis, molecular modeling and preliminary biological evaluation of 1-amino-3-phosphono-3-cyclopentene-1-carboxylic acid and 1-amino-3-phosphono-2-cyclopentene-1-carboxylic acid, two novel agonists of metabotropic glutamate receptors of group III. Amori L, Costantino G, Marinozzi M, Pellicciari R, Gasparini F, Flor PJ, Kuhn R, Vranesic I. Bioorg Med Chem Lett. 2000 Jul 3;10(13):1447-50. PMID: 10888329   20) (+)-4-phosphonophenylglycine (PPG) a new group III selective metabotropic glutamate receptor agonist. Gasparini F, Inderbitzin W, Francotte E, Lecis G, Richert P, Dragic Z, Kuhn R, Flor PJ. Bioorg Med Chem Lett. 2000 Jun 5;10(11):1241-4. PMID: 10866390   19) Distinct influence of the group III metabotropic glutamate receptor agonist (R,S)-4-phosphonophenylglycine [(R,S)-PPG] on different forms of neuronal damage. Henrich-Noack P, Flor PJ, Sabelhaus CF, Prass K, Dirnagl U, Gasparini F, Sauter A, Rudin M, Reymann KG. Neuropharmacology. 2000 Mar 3;39(5):911-7. PMID: 10699457   18) 2-Methyl-6-(phenylethynyl)-pyridine (MPEP), a potent, selective and systemically active mGlu5 receptor antagonist. Gasparini F, Lingenhöhl K, Stoehr N, Flor PJ, Heinrich M, Vranesic I, Biollaz M, Allgeier H, Heckendorn R, Urwyler S, Varney MA, Johnson EC, Hess SD, Rao SP, Sacaan AI, Santori EM, Veliçelebi G, Kuhn R. Neuropharmacology. 1999 Oct;38(10):1493-503. PMID: 10530811   17) SIB-1757 and SIB-1893: selective, noncompetitive antagonists of metabotropic glutamate receptor type 5. Varney MA, Cosford ND, Jachec C, Rao SP, Sacaan A, Lin FF, Bleicher L, Santori EM, Flor PJ, Allgeier H, Gasparini F, Kuhn R, Hess SD, Veliçelebi G, Johnson EC. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 1999 Jul;290(1):170-81. PMID: 10381773 16) (R,S)-4-phosphonophenylglycine, a potent and selective group III metabotropic glutamate receptor agonist, is anticonvulsive and neuroprotective in vivo. Gasparini F, Bruno V, Battaglia G, Lukic S, Leonhardt T, Inderbitzin W, Laurie D, Sommer B, Varney MA, Hess SD, Johnson EC, Kuhn R, Urwyler S, Sauer D, Portet C, Schmutz M, Nicoletti F, Flor PJ. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 1999 Jun;289(3):1678-87. PMID: 10336568 15) CPCCOEt, a noncompetitive metabotropic glutamate receptor 1 antagonist, inhibits receptor signaling without affecting glutamate binding. Litschig S, Gasparini F, Rueegg D, Stoehr N, Flor PJ, Vranesic I, Prézeau L, Pin JP, Thomsen C, Kuhn R. Mol Pharmacol. 1999 Mar;55(3):453-61. PMID: 10051528   14) Functional coupling of a human retinal metabotropic glutamate receptor (hmGluR6) to bovine rod transducin and rat Go in an in vitro reconstitution system. Weng K, Lu C, Daggett LP, Kuhn R, Flor PJ, Johnson EC, Robinson PR. J Biol Chem. 1997 Dec 26;272(52):33100-4. PMID: 9407094   13) Differential presynaptic localization of metabotropic glutamate receptor subtypes in the rat hippocampus. Shigemoto R, Kinoshita A, Wada E, Nomura S, Ohishi H, Takada M, Flor PJ, Neki A, Abe T, Nakanishi S, Mizuno N. J Neurosci. 1997 Oct 1;17(19):7503-22. PMID: 9295396   12) Cloning and stable expression of the mGluR1b subtype of human metabotropic receptors and pharmacological comparison with the mGluR5a subtype. Lin FF, Varney M, Sacaan AI, Jachec C, Daggett LP, Rao S, Flor P, Kuhn R, Kerner JA, Standaert D, Young AB, Veliçelebi G. Neuropharmacology. 1997 Jul;36(7):917-31. PMID: 9257936   11) Expression cloning of GABA(B) receptors uncovers similarity to metabotropic glutamate receptors. Kaupmann K, Huggel K, Heid J, Flor PJ, Bischoff S, Mickel SJ, McMaster G, Angst C, Bittiger H, Froestl W, Bettler B. Nature. 1997 Mar 20;386(6622):239-46. PMID: 9069281   10) A novel splice variant of a metabotropic glutamate receptor, human mGluR7b. Flor PJ, Van Der Putten H, Rüegg D, Lukic S, Leonhardt T, Bence M, Sansig G, Knöpfel T, Kuhn R. Neuropharmacology. 1997 Feb;36(2):153-9. PMID: 9144652   9) The C-terminal domain of the mGluR1 metabotropic glutamate receptor affects sensitivity to agonists. Flor PJ, Gomeza J, Tones MA, Kuhn R, Pin JP, Knöpfel T. J Neurochem. 1996 Jul;67(1):58-63. PMID: 8667026   8) The agonist selectivity of a class III metabotropic glutamate receptor, human mGluR4a, is determined by the N-terminal extracellular domain. Tones MA, Bendali N, Flor PJ, Knöpfel T, Kuhn R. Neuroreport. 1995 Dec 29;7(1):117-20. PMID: 8742431   7) Pharmacological characterization of MCCG and MAP4 at the mGluR1b, mGluR2 and mGluR4a human metabotropic glutamate receptor subtypes. Knöpfel T, Lukic S, Leonard T, Flor PJ, Kuhn R, Gasparini F. Neuropharmacology. 1995 Aug;34(8):1099-102. PMID: 8532159   6) Molecular cloning, functional expression and pharmacological characterization of the human metabotropic glutamate receptor type 2. Flor PJ, Lindauer K, Püttner I, Rüegg D, Lukic S, Knöpfel T, Kuhn R. Eur J Neurosci. 1995 Apr 1;7(4):622-9. PMID: 7620613 5) Profiling of trans-azetidine-2,4-dicarboxylic acid at the human metabotropic glutamate receptors mGlu1b, -2, -4a and -5a. Knöpfel T, Sakaki J, Flor PJ, Baumann P, Sacaan AI, Veliçelebi G, Kuhn R, Allgeier H. Eur J Pharmacol. 1995 Feb 15;288(3):389-92. PMID: 7774685   4) Molecular cloning, functional expression and pharmacological characterization of the human metabotropic glutamate receptor type 4. Flor PJ, Lukic S, Rüegg D, Leonhardt T, Knöpfel T, Kuhn R. Neuropharmacology. 1995 Feb;34(2):149-55. PMID: 7617140   3) Characterization of the Antirrhinum floral homeotic MADS-box gene deficiens: evidence for DNA binding and autoregulation of its persistent expression throughout flower development. Schwarz-Sommer Z, Hue I, Huijser P, Flor PJ, Hansen R, Tetens F, Lönnig WE, Saedler H, Sommer H. EMBO J. 1992 Jan;11(1):251-63. PMID: 1346760   2) Properties of deficiens, a homeotic gene involved in the control of flower morphogenesis in Antirrhinum-majus. Sommer H, Nacken W, Beltran P, Huijser P, Pape H, Hansen R, Flor P, Saedler H, Schwarz-Sommer Z. DEVELOPMENT. 1991 Supplement (1):169-75. Accession Number: WOS:A1991GA05000019  1) A conserved base pair within helix P4 of the Tetrahymena ribozyme helps to form the tertiary structure required for self-splicing. Flor PJ, Flanegan JB, Cech TR. EMBO J. 1989 Nov;8(11):3391-9. PMID: 2684642  </field>
<field name="important">AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor Publications ? Prof. Dr. Peter J. Flor http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?Db=pubmed&amp;Cmd=Search&amp;Term=%22Flor%20P%22 53) Functional monoclonal antibody acts as a biased agonist by inducing internalization of metabotropic glutamate receptor 7. Ullmer C, Zoffmann S, Bohrmann B, Matile BH, Lindemann L, Flor PJ, Malherbe P. British Journal of Pharmacology. 2012; in press. IF=4.4 52) Orthosteric versus allosteric GPCR activation: The great challenge of group-III mGluRs. Flor PJ, Acher FC. Biochemical Pharmacology. 2012; in press. IF=4.7 PMID:22554564 51) Pharmacological interference with metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 7 but not subtype 5 differentially affects within- and between-session extinction of Pavlovian conditioned fear. Toth I, Dietz M, Peterlik D, Huber SE, Fendt M, Neumann ID, Flor PJ, Slattery DA. Neuropharmacology. 2012 Mar;62(4):1619-26. IF=4.8 PMID:22079159   50) Pharmacological modulation of mGluR7 with AMN082 and MMPIP exerts specific influences on alcohol consumption and preference in rats. Bahi A, Fizia K, Dietz M, Gasparini F, Flor PJ. Addict Biol. 2012 Mar;17(2):235-47. IF=4.8 PMID:21392179 49) Exciting times beyond the brain: metabotropic glutamate receptors in peripheral and non-neural tissues. Julio-Pieper M, Flor PJ, Dinan TG, Cryan JF. Pharmacol Rev. 2011 Mar;63(1):35-58. IF=20.2 PMID: 21228260 48) Metabotropic glutamate receptor 7: at the interface of cognition and emotion. O'Connor RM, Finger BC, Flor PJ, Cryan JF. Eur J Pharmacol. 2010 Aug 10;639(1-3):123-31. IF=2.7 PMID: 20371242  47) Antisense oligonucleotides. Neumann ID, Flor PJ. Encyclopedia of Psychopharmacology. 2010, Ian P. Stolerman (ed.), Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg 2010.   46) Metabotropic glutamate 7 receptor subtype modulates motor symptoms in rodent models of Parkinson's disease. Greco B, Lopez S, van der Putten H, Flor PJ, Amalric M. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 2010 Mar;332(3):1064-71. IF=4.0 PMID: 19940105  ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------- Publications before coming to Regensburg: 45) Selective activation of metabotropic G-protein-coupled glutamate 7 receptor elicits anxiolytic-like effects in mice by modulating GABAergic neurotransmission. Stachowicz K, Brañski P, K?ak K, van der Putten H, Cryan JF, Flor PJ, Andrzej P. Behav Pharmacol. 2008 Sep;19(5-6):597-603. PMID: 18690114   44) Amygdaloid metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 7 is involved in the acquisition of conditioned fear. Siegl S, Flor PJ, Fendt M. Neuroreport. 2008 Jul 16;19(11):1147-50. PMID: 18596617   43) mGluR7 facilitates extinction of aversive memories and controls amygdala plasticity. Fendt M, Schmid S, Thakker DR, Jacobson LH, Yamamoto R, Mitsukawa K, Maier R, Natt F, Hüsken D, Kelly PH, McAllister KH, Hoyer D, van der Putten H, Cryan JF, Flor PJ. Mol Psychiatry. 2008 Oct;13(10):970-9. IF=12.5   PMID: 17712315 42) Activation of the mGlu7 receptor elicits antidepressant-like effects in mice. Palucha A, Klak K, Branski P, van der Putten H, Flor PJ, Pilc A. Psychopharmacology (Berl). 2007 Nov;194(4):555-62.   PMID: 17622518 ] 41) Functional role of mGluR1 and mGluR4 in pilocarpine-induced temporal lobe epilepsy. Pitsch J, Schoch S, Gueler N, Flor PJ, van der Putten H, Becker AJ. Neurobiol Dis. 2007 Jun;26(3):623-33.   PMID: 17446080   40) Night blindness-associated mutations in the ligand-binding, cysteine-rich, and intracellular domains of the metabotropic glutamate receptor 6 abolish protein trafficking. Zeitz C, Forster U, Neidhardt J, Feil S, Kälin S, Leifert D, Flor PJ, Berger W. Hum Mutat. 2007 Aug;28(8):771-80. PMID: 17405131  ] 39) Synthesis and preliminary pharmacological evaluation of the four stereoisomers of (2S)-2-(2'-phosphono-3'-phenylcyclopropyl)glycine, the first class of 3'-substituted trans C1'-2'-2-(2'-phosphonocyclopropyl)glycines. Marinozzi M, Serpi M, Amori L, Gavilan Diaz M, Costantino G, Meyer U, Flor PJ, Gasparini F, Heckendorn R, Kuhn R, Giorgi G, Hermit MB, Thomsen C, Pellicciari R. Bioorg Med Chem. 2007 May 1;15(9):3161-70.   PMID: 17350267   38) Global down-regulation of gene expression in the brain using RNA interference, with emphasis on monoamine transporters and GPCRs: implications for target characterization in psychiatric and neurological disorders. Hoyer D, Thakker DR, Natt F, Maier R, Huesken D, Müller M, Flor P, VAN DER Putten H, Schmutz M, Bilbe G, Cryan JF. J Recept Signal Transduct Res. 2006;26(5-6):527-47. PMID: 17118797   37) Metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 7 ablation causes dysregulation of the HPA axis and increases hippocampal BDNF protein levels: implications for stress-related psychiatric disorders. Mitsukawa K, Mombereau C, Lötscher E, Uzunov DP, van der Putten H, Flor PJ, Cryan JF. Neuropsychopharmacology. 2006 Jun;31(6):1112-22. PMID: 16237391  36) A selective metabotropic glutamate receptor 7 agonist: activation of receptor signaling via an allosteric site modulates stress parameters in vivo. Mitsukawa K, Yamamoto R, Ofner S, Nozulak J, Pescott O, Lukic S, Stoehr N, Mombereau C, Kuhn R, McAllister KH, van der Putten H, Cryan JF, Flor PJ. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2005 Dec 20;102(51):18712-7. IF=10.2    PMID: 16339898   35) (-)-PHCCC, a positive allosteric modulator of mGluR4: characterization, mechanism of action, and neuroprotection. Maj M, Bruno V, Dragic Z, Yamamoto R, Battaglia G, Inderbitzin W, Stoehr N, Stein T, Gasparini F, Vranesic I, Kuhn R, Nicoletti F, Flor PJ. Neuropharmacology. 2003 Dec;45(7):895-906. PMID: 14573382   34) Antidepressant and anxiolytic-like effects in mice lacking the group III metabotropic glutamate receptor mGluR7. Cryan JF, Kelly PH, Neijt HC, Sansig G, Flor PJ, van Der Putten H. Eur J Neurosci. 2003 Jun;17(11):2409-17. PMID: 12814372   33) Neuroprotective activity of metabotropic glutamate receptor ligands. Flor PJ, Battaglia G, Nicoletti F, Gasparini F, Bruno V. Adv Exp Med Biol. 2002;513:197-223. Review. PMID: 12575822   32) In vitro and in vivo characterization of MPEP, an allosteric modulator of the metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 5: review article. Kuhn R, Pagano A, Stoehr N, Vranesic I, Flor PJ, Lingenhöhl K, Spooren W, Gentsch C, Vassout A, Pilc A, Gasparini F. Amino Acids. 2002;23(1-3):207-11. Review. PMID: 12373539   31) [(3)H]-M-MPEP, a potent, subtype-selective radioligand for the metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 5. Gasparini F, Andres H, Flor PJ, Heinrich M, Inderbitzin W, Lingenhöhl K, Müller H, Munk VC, Omilusik K, Stierlin C, Stoehr N, Vranesic I, Kuhn R. Bioorg Med Chem Lett. 2002 Feb 11;12(3):407-9. PMID: 11814808   30) Increased seizure susceptibility in mice lacking metabotropic glutamate receptor 7. Sansig G, Bushell TJ, Clarke VR, Rozov A, Burnashev N, Portet C, Gasparini F, Schmutz M, Klebs K, Shigemoto R, Flor PJ, Kuhn R, Knoepfel T, Schroeder M, Hampson DR, Collett VJ, Zhang C, Duvoisin RM, Collingridge GL, van Der Putten H. J Neurosci. 2001 Nov 15;21(22):8734-45. PMID: 11698585   29) Metabotropic glutamate receptor subtypes as targets for neuroprotective drugs. Bruno V, Battaglia G, Copani A, D'Onofrio M, Di Iorio P, De Blasi A, Melchiorri D, Flor PJ, Nicoletti F. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab. 2001 Sep;21(9):1013-33. Review. PMID: 11524608 28) Discovery and characterization of non-competitive antagonists of group I metabotropic glutamate receptors. Gasparini F, Floersheim P, Flor PJ, Heinrich M, Inderbitzin W, Ott D, Pagano A, Stierlin C, Stoehr N, Vranesic I, Kuhn R. Farmaco. 2001 Jan-Feb;56(1-2):95-9. Review. PMID: 11347975   27) An activity-dependent switch from facilitation to inhibition in the control of excitotoxicity by group I metabotropic glutamate receptors. Bruno V, Battaglia G, Copani A, Cespédes VM, Galindo MF, Ceña V, Sánchez-Prieto J, Gasparini F, Kuhn R, Flor PJ, Nicoletti F. Eur J Neurosci. 2001 Apr;13(8):1469-78. PMID: 11328342   26) Chiral resolution, pharmacological characterization, and receptor docking of the noncompetitive mGlu1 receptor antagonist (+/-)-2-hydroxyimino- 1a, 2-dihydro-1H-7-oxacyclopropa[b]naphthalene-7a-carboxylic acid ethyl ester. Ott D, Floersheim P, Inderbitzin W, Stoehr N, Francotte E, Lecis G, Richert P, Rihs G, Flor PJ, Kuhn R, Gasparini F. J Med Chem. 2000 Nov 16;43(23):4428-36. PMID: 11087567   25) Metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 5 (mGlu5) and nociceptive function. I. Selective blockade of mGlu5 receptors in models of acute, persistent and chronic pain. Walker K, Bowes M, Panesar M, Davis A, Gentry C, Kesingland A, Gasparini F, Spooren W, Stoehr N, Pagano A, Flor PJ, Vranesic I, Lingenhoehl K, Johnson EC, Varney M, Urban L, Kuhn R. Neuropharmacology. 2001;40(1):1-9. PMID: 11077065   24) Selective blockade of metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 5 is neuroprotective. Bruno V, Ksiazek I, Battaglia G, Lukic S, Leonhardt T, Sauer D, Gasparini F, Kuhn R, Nicoletti F, Flor PJ. Neuropharmacology. 2000 Sep;39(12):2223-30. PMID: 10974306   23) Selective activation of mGlu4 metabotropic glutamate receptors is protective against excitotoxic neuronal death. Bruno V, Battaglia G, Ksiazek I, van der Putten H, Catania MV, Giuffrida R, Lukic S, Leonhardt T, Inderbitzin W, Gasparini F, Kuhn R, Hampson DR, Nicoletti F, Flor PJ. J Neurosci. 2000 Sep 1;20(17):6413-20. PMID: 10964947 22) The non-competitive antagonists 2-methyl-6-(phenylethynyl)pyridine and 7-hydroxyiminocyclopropan[b]chromen-1a-carboxylic acid ethyl ester interact with overlapping binding pockets in the transmembrane region of group I metabotropic glutamate receptors. Pagano A, Ruegg D, Litschig S, Stoehr N, Stierlin C, Heinrich M, Floersheim P, Prezèau L, Carroll F, Pin JP, Cambria A, Vranesic I, Flor PJ, Gasparini F, Kuhn R. J Biol Chem. 2000 Oct 27;275(43):33750-8. PMID: 10934211 21) Synthesis, molecular modeling and preliminary biological evaluation of 1-amino-3-phosphono-3-cyclopentene-1-carboxylic acid and 1-amino-3-phosphono-2-cyclopentene-1-carboxylic acid, two novel agonists of metabotropic glutamate receptors of group III. Amori L, Costantino G, Marinozzi M, Pellicciari R, Gasparini F, Flor PJ, Kuhn R, Vranesic I. Bioorg Med Chem Lett. 2000 Jul 3;10(13):1447-50. PMID: 10888329   20) (+)-4-phosphonophenylglycine (PPG) a new group III selective metabotropic glutamate receptor agonist. Gasparini F, Inderbitzin W, Francotte E, Lecis G, Richert P, Dragic Z, Kuhn R, Flor PJ. Bioorg Med Chem Lett. 2000 Jun 5;10(11):1241-4. PMID: 10866390   19) Distinct influence of the group III metabotropic glutamate receptor agonist (R,S)-4-phosphonophenylglycine [(R,S)-PPG] on different forms of neuronal damage. Henrich-Noack P, Flor PJ, Sabelhaus CF, Prass K, Dirnagl U, Gasparini F, Sauter A, Rudin M, Reymann KG. Neuropharmacology. 2000 Mar 3;39(5):911-7. PMID: 10699457   18) 2-Methyl-6-(phenylethynyl)-pyridine (MPEP), a potent, selective and systemically active mGlu5 receptor antagonist. Gasparini F, Lingenhöhl K, Stoehr N, Flor PJ, Heinrich M, Vranesic I, Biollaz M, Allgeier H, Heckendorn R, Urwyler S, Varney MA, Johnson EC, Hess SD, Rao SP, Sacaan AI, Santori EM, Veliçelebi G, Kuhn R. Neuropharmacology. 1999 Oct;38(10):1493-503. PMID: 10530811   17) SIB-1757 and SIB-1893: selective, noncompetitive antagonists of metabotropic glutamate receptor type 5. Varney MA, Cosford ND, Jachec C, Rao SP, Sacaan A, Lin FF, Bleicher L, Santori EM, Flor PJ, Allgeier H, Gasparini F, Kuhn R, Hess SD, Veliçelebi G, Johnson EC. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 1999 Jul;290(1):170-81. PMID: 10381773 16) (R,S)-4-phosphonophenylglycine, a potent and selective group III metabotropic glutamate receptor agonist, is anticonvulsive and neuroprotective in vivo. Gasparini F, Bruno V, Battaglia G, Lukic S, Leonhardt T, Inderbitzin W, Laurie D, Sommer B, Varney MA, Hess SD, Johnson EC, Kuhn R, Urwyler S, Sauer D, Portet C, Schmutz M, Nicoletti F, Flor PJ. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 1999 Jun;289(3):1678-87. PMID: 10336568 15) CPCCOEt, a noncompetitive metabotropic glutamate receptor 1 antagonist, inhibits receptor signaling without affecting glutamate binding. Litschig S, Gasparini F, Rueegg D, Stoehr N, Flor PJ, Vranesic I, Prézeau L, Pin JP, Thomsen C, Kuhn R. Mol Pharmacol. 1999 Mar;55(3):453-61. PMID: 10051528   14) Functional coupling of a human retinal metabotropic glutamate receptor (hmGluR6) to bovine rod transducin and rat Go in an in vitro reconstitution system. Weng K, Lu C, Daggett LP, Kuhn R, Flor PJ, Johnson EC, Robinson PR. J Biol Chem. 1997 Dec 26;272(52):33100-4. PMID: 9407094   13) Differential presynaptic localization of metabotropic glutamate receptor subtypes in the rat hippocampus. Shigemoto R, Kinoshita A, Wada E, Nomura S, Ohishi H, Takada M, Flor PJ, Neki A, Abe T, Nakanishi S, Mizuno N. J Neurosci. 1997 Oct 1;17(19):7503-22. PMID: 9295396   12) Cloning and stable expression of the mGluR1b subtype of human metabotropic receptors and pharmacological comparison with the mGluR5a subtype. Lin FF, Varney M, Sacaan AI, Jachec C, Daggett LP, Rao S, Flor P, Kuhn R, Kerner JA, Standaert D, Young AB, Veliçelebi G. Neuropharmacology. 1997 Jul;36(7):917-31. PMID: 9257936   11) Expression cloning of GABA(B) receptors uncovers similarity to metabotropic glutamate receptors. Kaupmann K, Huggel K, Heid J, Flor PJ, Bischoff S, Mickel SJ, McMaster G, Angst C, Bittiger H, Froestl W, Bettler B. Nature. 1997 Mar 20;386(6622):239-46. PMID: 9069281   10) A novel splice variant of a metabotropic glutamate receptor, human mGluR7b. Flor PJ, Van Der Putten H, Rüegg D, Lukic S, Leonhardt T, Bence M, Sansig G, Knöpfel T, Kuhn R. Neuropharmacology. 1997 Feb;36(2):153-9. PMID: 9144652   9) The C-terminal domain of the mGluR1 metabotropic glutamate receptor affects sensitivity to agonists. Flor PJ, Gomeza J, Tones MA, Kuhn R, Pin JP, Knöpfel T. J Neurochem. 1996 Jul;67(1):58-63. PMID: 8667026   8) The agonist selectivity of a class III metabotropic glutamate receptor, human mGluR4a, is determined by the N-terminal extracellular domain. Tones MA, Bendali N, Flor PJ, Knöpfel T, Kuhn R. Neuroreport. 1995 Dec 29;7(1):117-20. PMID: 8742431   7) Pharmacological characterization of MCCG and MAP4 at the mGluR1b, mGluR2 and mGluR4a human metabotropic glutamate receptor subtypes. Knöpfel T, Lukic S, Leonard T, Flor PJ, Kuhn R, Gasparini F. Neuropharmacology. 1995 Aug;34(8):1099-102. PMID: 8532159   6) Molecular cloning, functional expression and pharmacological characterization of the human metabotropic glutamate receptor type 2. Flor PJ, Lindauer K, Püttner I, Rüegg D, Lukic S, Knöpfel T, Kuhn R. Eur J Neurosci. 1995 Apr 1;7(4):622-9. PMID: 7620613 5) Profiling of trans-azetidine-2,4-dicarboxylic acid at the human metabotropic glutamate receptors mGlu1b, -2, -4a and -5a. Knöpfel T, Sakaki J, Flor PJ, Baumann P, Sacaan AI, Veliçelebi G, Kuhn R, Allgeier H. Eur J Pharmacol. 1995 Feb 15;288(3):389-92. PMID: 7774685   4) Molecular cloning, functional expression and pharmacological characterization of the human metabotropic glutamate receptor type 4. Flor PJ, Lukic S, Rüegg D, Leonhardt T, Knöpfel T, Kuhn R. Neuropharmacology. 1995 Feb;34(2):149-55. PMID: 7617140   3) Characterization of the Antirrhinum floral homeotic MADS-box gene deficiens: evidence for DNA binding and autoregulation of its persistent expression throughout flower development. Schwarz-Sommer Z, Hue I, Huijser P, Flor PJ, Hansen R, Tetens F, Lönnig WE, Saedler H, Sommer H. EMBO J. 1992 Jan;11(1):251-63. PMID: 1346760   2) Properties of deficiens, a homeotic gene involved in the control of flower morphogenesis in Antirrhinum-majus. Sommer H, Nacken W, Beltran P, Huijser P, Pape H, Hansen R, Flor P, Saedler H, Schwarz-Sommer Z. DEVELOPMENT. 1991 Supplement (1):169-75. Accession Number: WOS:A1991GA05000019  1) A conserved base pair within helix P4 of the Tetrahymena ribozyme helps to form the tertiary structure required for self-splicing. Flor PJ, Flanegan JB, Cech TR. EMBO J. 1989 Nov;8(11):3391-9. PMID: 2684642  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Flor/Teaching/index.html</field>
<field name="title">AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Flor/Teaching/index.html</field>
<field name="content">AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor Lehre (Teaching) 1. Beteiligungen an den Lehrveranstaltungen im Wintersemester, Studiengang:    - Vorlesung Tierphysiologie, BSc und Lehramt    - Spezialvorlesung ?Molecular and Cellular Neurosciences?, MSc und ECN    - Spezialvorlesung ?Systemic Neurosciences?, MSc und ECN    - Spezialvorlesung/Seminar: ?Molecular and Behavioural Neurobiology?, BSc/MSc    - Seminar Biologie im Nebenfach, BSc und MSc (für Studierende anderer Fakultäten)    - Praktikum Biologie im Nebenfach, BSc und MSc (für Studierende anderer Fakultäten)    - Forschungspraktikum Molekulare und zellulare Neurobiologie, BSc    - Projektpraktikum und Methodenpraktikum Neurobiologie, BSc und ECN    - Laborpraktikum Neurobiologie, MSc 2. Beteiligungen an den Lehrveranstaltungen im Sommersemester, Studiengang:    - Vorlesung Neurobiologie und Ethologie, BSc und Lehramt    - Wahlpflichtpraktikum Tierphysiologie, BSc    - Spezialvorlesung: ?Molecular and Behavioural Neurobiology?, BSc und MSc    - Forschungspraktikum Molekulare und zellulare Neurobiologie, BSc    - Laborpraktikum Neurobiologie, MSc    - Projektpraktikum Neurobiologie, BSc 3. Betreuung von Studienabschlussarbeiten seit dem Jahr 2010 ? insg. 13 Arbeiten (Stand Juni 2012):    - BSc-Theses: 8x (M. Linsmeier, A. Dillinger, T. Neder, A. Bauer, S. Eggerstorfer, A. Graßkamp, R. Öller, T. Killian)    - MSc-Theses: 2x (S. Huber, D. Peterlik)    - Dipl.-Biol.-Theses: 2x (M. Dietz, L. Adelfinger)    - PhD-Theses: 1x (D. Peterlik)    - Mentorentätigkeit bei ca. 8 aktuellen PhD-Arbeiten und bei einer Habilitation</field>
<field name="important">AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor AG Prof. Dr. Peter Flor Lehre (Teaching) 1. Beteiligungen an den Lehrveranstaltungen im Wintersemester, Studiengang:    - Vorlesung Tierphysiologie, BSc und Lehramt    - Spezialvorlesung ?Molecular and Cellular Neurosciences?, MSc und ECN    - Spezialvorlesung ?Systemic Neurosciences?, MSc und ECN    - Spezialvorlesung/Seminar: ?Molecular and Behavioural Neurobiology?, BSc/MSc    - Seminar Biologie im Nebenfach, BSc und MSc (für Studierende anderer Fakultäten)    - Praktikum Biologie im Nebenfach, BSc und MSc (für Studierende anderer Fakultäten)    - Forschungspraktikum Molekulare und zellulare Neurobiologie, BSc    - Projektpraktikum und Methodenpraktikum Neurobiologie, BSc und ECN    - Laborpraktikum Neurobiologie, MSc 2. Beteiligungen an den Lehrveranstaltungen im Sommersemester, Studiengang:    - Vorlesung Neurobiologie und Ethologie, BSc und Lehramt    - Wahlpflichtpraktikum Tierphysiologie, BSc    - Spezialvorlesung: ?Molecular and Behavioural Neurobiology?, BSc und MSc    - Forschungspraktikum Molekulare und zellulare Neurobiologie, BSc    - Laborpraktikum Neurobiologie, MSc    - Projektpraktikum Neurobiologie, BSc 3. Betreuung von Studienabschlussarbeiten seit dem Jahr 2010 ? insg. 13 Arbeiten (Stand Juni 2012):    - BSc-Theses: 8x (M. Linsmeier, A. Dillinger, T. Neder, A. Bauer, S. Eggerstorfer, A. Graßkamp, R. Öller, T. Killian)    - MSc-Theses: 2x (S. Huber, D. Peterlik)    - Dipl.-Biol.-Theses: 2x (M. Dietz, L. Adelfinger)    - PhD-Theses: 1x (D. Peterlik)    - Mentorentätigkeit bei ca. 8 aktuellen PhD-Arbeiten und bei einer Habilitation</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Foerster/index.html</field>
<field name="title">Prof. Dr. Charlotte Föster</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Foerster/index.html</field>
<field name="content">Prof. Dr. Charlotte Föster Prof. Dr. Charlotte Föster Arbeitsgruppe Prof. Dr. Charlotte Föster Naturwissenschaftliche Fakultät III Biologie und Vorklinische Medizin Universität Regensburg 93040 Regensburg</field>
<field name="important">Prof. Dr. Charlotte Föster Prof. Dr. Charlotte Föster Arbeitsgruppe Prof. Dr. Charlotte Föster Naturwissenschaftliche Fakultät III Biologie und Vorklinische Medizin Universität Regensburg 93040 Regensburg</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Geier/stechmuecken-krankheiten.html</field>
<field name="title">Von Stechm?cken ?bertragene Infektionskrankheiten: ein ?berblick.</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Geier/stechmuecken-krankheiten.html</field>
<field name="content">Von Stechm?cken ?bertragene Infektionskrankheiten: ein ?berblick. Von Stechm?cken ?bertragene Infektionskrankheiten: ein ?berblick.     Von Stechm?cken ?bertragene Infektionskrankheiten: ein ?berblick. Von Sebastian Haas, leicht ver?ndert - © 2005   AG Geier Forschungsthemen (Von Stechm?cken ?bertragende Krankheiten) Arbeitsgruppe Ver?ffentlichungen Diplom- und Zulassungsarbeiten Links Kontakt Institut f?r Zoologie der Universit?t Regensburg Malaria Weltweit leben auch heute noch etwa 40 % der Weltbev?lkerung mit dem Risiko an dem durch Anopheles-M?cken ?bertragenen Malaria zu erkranken. Vor allem die ?rmsten Regionen der Tropen und Subtropen sind j?hrlich mit ?ber 300 Millionen akuten Infektionen und etwa einer Million Todesf?lle betroffen (RBM-WHO Infosheet). Dabei zeichnet sich ein Teufelskreis aus Armut und mangelnder Gesundheitsvorsorge ab: die enormen Ausf?lle Erwerbst?tiger durch Malaria, oft in Verbindung mit anderen Krankheiten wie Tuberkulose, Unterern?hrung und AIDS schw?chen die Wirtschaftskraft ganzer Regionen (RBM-WHO Infosheet). Aus Mangel an finanziellen Mitteln greifen moderne Strategien der Medikation und Seuchenbek?mpfung oft zu kurz, was wiederum das Eind?mmen von Epidemien erschwert. Der gro?fl?chige Einsatz von DDT, wie auch anderer Insektizide f?hrte in relativ kurzer Zeit zur Ausbildung von resistenten M?ckenpopulationen (WIRTH et al., 2004; HEMMINGWAY et al., 2004; TRIPATHI et al., 2004). Daneben haben sich auch unter den eigentlichen Erregern der Malaria, den Plasmodien, Resistenzen gegen allzu gro?z?gig verwandte Medikamente, wie Chloroquin, Mefloquin, Halofantrin und Primaquin ausgebildet (SPIELMAN &amp; D?ANTONIO, 2001). Gelbfieber Obwohl es gegen das Gelbfieber seit Jahrzehnten einen hochwirksamen Impfstoff gibt, verzeichnet die Weltgesundheits-Organisation (WHO) eine wieder zunehmende Zahl infizierter Menschen in Afrika und S?damerika (WHO Fact sheet N? 100). Grund hierf?r ist die zu niedrige Impfquote: sie liegt meist weit unter den erforderlichen 85 %. M?cken ?bertragen die Flaviviren des Gelbfiebers immer wieder von den als Reservoir-Wirt fungierenden Affen auf Waldarbeiter und J?ger. Die so mit dem ?Jungle Yellow Fever? infizierten Menschen transportieren das Virus in die Ballungsr?ume. Dort schlie?lich f?hrt das aggressive Blutsaugeverhalten der eng mit den Menschen vergesellschafteten Stechm?cke Aedes aegypti zur ?bertragung der Viren von Mensch zu Mensch. Dieses sogenannte ?Urban Yellow Fever? f?hrte bereits zu gro?en Epidemien ?ber weite Landstriche hinweg. Die WHO sch?tzt, dass dieser Infektion j?hrlich rund 30 000 Menschen zum Opfer fallen, bei etwa 200 000 F?llen weltweit. Ein Infektionsrisiko bestehe demnach f?r mindestens 42 L?nder mit insgesamt ?ber 600 Millionen Einwohnern (WHO Fact sheet N? 100). Dengue und Dengue-h?morrhagisches Fieber Im Gegensatz zu Gelbfieber ist gegen Dengue und das h?morrhagische Denguefieber (DHF) noch kein Impfstoff entwickelt worden. Auch d?rfte sich die Entwicklung eines Serums als ?u?erst schwierig gestalten, da nicht weniger als vier verschiedene Serotypen dieses Flavivirus bekannt sind (CDC-Dengue). Aktuell sind etwa zwei F?nftel der Weltbev?lkerung von einer Dengueinfektion bedroht. Die WHO sch?tzt die Zahl der weltweit pro Jahr auftretenden F?lle auf 50 Millionen (WHO Fact sheet N? 117). In den zur?ckliegenden Jahrzehnten war zudem eine dramatische Ausbreitung der h?morrhagischen Variante zu verzeichnen. Mit einer Letalrate von 2,5 - 5 % der Infizierten, wird das DHF haupts?chlich Kindern zum Verh?ngnis. Waren vor 1970 nur neun Staaten von DHF betroffen, so erh?hte sich die Zahl bis 1995 auf mehr als das Vierfache (WHO- TDR-Dengue). Diese enorme Zunahme erkl?rt sich zum Teil durch die stark anwachsende Bev?lkerungsdichte in gro?en Ballungsr?umen. Gerade in ?rmeren Regionen, den Favelas und Slums, leben Menschen auf engstem Raum zusammen. H?ufig fehlt ein Anschlu? an das Trinkwassersystem, so dass Zisternen verbreitet sind, welche den M?ckenlarven von Ae. aegypti als Lebensraum dienen. Zudem ist meist die M?llentsorgung unterentwickelt, wodurch sich in tropisch humidem Klima unz?hlige Joghurtbecher, Dosen und Kanister zu ?Kleinstgew?ssern? entwickeln, die f?r die anspruchslosen Larven von Ae. aegypti ausreichende Biotope darstellen (SCHAFFNER et al., 2001; BECKER et al., 2003). Ein solches Umfeld ist geradezu ideal f?r diese tagaktive, aggressive Stechm?cke, welche nicht nur der bedeutendste ?bertr?ger f?r Gelbfieber-, sondern auch f?r Denguefieberviren ist (WHO Fact sheet N?117). Neben Ae. aegypti sind auch die sich weltweit ausbreitende Tigerm?cke Aedes albopictus und die im tropischen Pazifik heimische Aedes polynesiensis wichtige ?bertr?ger von Dengue. Weitere von Stechm?cken ?bertragene Krankheiten Neben diesen, bei weitem gef?hrlichsten Infektionen ?bertragen Stechm?cken (Culicidae) eine ganze Reihe von weiteren veterin?r- und humanmedizinisch relevanten Krankheitserregern: Endoparasiten der tropischen Elephantiasis, diverse Filariasisformen und neben den oben genannten Gelbfieber- und Dengue-Erregern viele weitere Viren (Zusammenfassung in: EDMAN &amp; ELDRIDGE, 2000; SCHAFFNER et al., 2001; MEHLHORN &amp; PIEKARSKI, 2002). Wie die Ausbreitung des bis dahin nur in Afrika und Europa bekannten West-Nile-Virus in j?ngster Vergangenheit in Nordamerika zeigte, sind ?hnliche Krankheiten dabei keinesfalls nur auf die Tropen begrenzt: das im Sommer 1999 erstmals in New York D.C., USA, entdeckte West-Nile-Virus erreichte bereits 2003 die Bundesstaaten der US-Westk?ste. Von 4000 F?llen mit 300 Toten im Jahr 2002 stieg die Zahl der Betroffenen auf beinahe 9000 im Jahr 2003 (EDMAN, 2004). Durch den internationalen Warenverkehr wurde vor kurzem in Europa ein weiterer ?bertr?ger des West-Nile-Virus eingef?hrt (REBORA et al., 1993; REITER, 1998). Die in den Tropen und Subtropen als Dengue-?bertr?ger gef?rchtete Tigerm?cke Aedes albopictus hat sich bereits in Albanien, Italien, Frankreich, Belgien und Teilen der Schweiz etabliert (pers. Mitt. GUERIN, 2004). Sie gilt zudem als potentieller ?bertr?ger f?r eine Vielzahl weiterer human- und veterin?rmedizinisch relevanter Pathogene (SCHAFFNER et al., 2001). Eine ?bertragung dieser Infektionskrankheiten von einem infizierten Menschen via Stechm?cke auf einen Gesunden ist nur m?glich, wenn ein und dieselbe M?cke mindestens zweimal an verschiedenen Personen Blut saugen kann. Daher sind Stechm?cken mit einer Vorliebe f?r Menschen ? die sogenannten anthropophilen Spezies ? wie zum Beispiel Aedes aegypti oder Anopheles gambiae besonders effektive und damit gef?hrliche Vektoren f?r Infektionskrankheiten (CLEMENTS, 1992). Modernes Management der Stechm?ckenpopulationen in Risikogebieten Von der noch Mitte des letzten Jahrhunderts intensiv verfolgten Utopie vom vollst?ndigen Ausrotten der Stechm?cken durch DDT und andere Insektizide hat man sich verabschiedet. Die Bem?hungen zielen heute vielmehr auf eine realistische Risikominimierung ab, indem versucht wird Brutst?tten der M?cken in der N?he von Siedlungen aufzusp?ren und zu zerst?ren, sowie die Fieberm?cken durch gezielten, wohl dosierten Insektizideinsatz zu dezimieren (pers. Mitt. EIRAS, 2004). Ein m?glichst detailliertes Wissen ?ber den Erreger, aber auch ?ber den Vektor stellt das Kernst?ck der modernen Seuchenbek?mpfung dar. In Bezug auf Stechm?cken bedeutet dies, dass Partnerfindung, Eiablageverhalten, Larvalentwicklung, die Ortung von Kohlenhydratquellen und vor allem die spezifische Auswahl der Blutwirte ? um nur die wichtigsten zu nennen ? Gegenstand intensiver Forschung sind. Entomologen gewinnen beispielsweise durch Verhaltenstests in Freiland und Labor neue Erkenntnisse ?ber attraktive und abschreckende Stimuli dieser Lebensstationen. Mit chemischer Analytik und physiologischen Messungen wird versucht, diese ? meist olfaktorischen ? Stimuli zu definieren und zu quantifizieren. Die Elektrophysiologie untersucht die Reaktion von Rezeptorzellen der Sinnesorgane als Antwort auf das Einwirken solcher Stimuli auf das Insekt. Diese Disziplinen werden seit einigen Jahren unter dem Begriff der Chemischen ?kologie vereint und haben u.a. zur Entwicklung der sogenannten olfaktorischen ?Push and Pull-Strategie? beigetragen: Repellentien (Schreckstoffe) halten dabei die M?cken von Menschen fern, Attraktanzien (Lockstoffe) locken sie in spezielle M?ckenfallen. Letztere dienen dabei in erster Linie der Bestands?berwachung (engl. monitoring oder surveillance) und k?nnen so ein Massenauftreten fr?hzeitig zu erfassen. Die eigentliche Dezimierung der Stechm?cken kann dann relativ kleinr?umig und bedarfsgerecht mit Insektiziden erfolgen. Dadurch wird das Risiko der Resistenzbildung verringert, unn?tige Umweltbelastungen und finanzieller Aufwand werden minimiert. Literatur BECKER, N.; PETRIC, S.; ZGOMBA, M.; BOASE, C.; DAHL, C.; LANE, J. &amp; KAISER, A. (2003). Mosquitoes and their Control. Kluwer Academic/ Plenum Publishers. New York, Boston, Dordrecht, London, Moscow CDC-Dengue: http://www.cdc.gov/ncidod/dvbid/dengue/ (16.02. 2005) CHARLWOOD, J. D.; BILLINGSLEY, P. F. ; HOC, T. Q. (1995). Mosquito-mediated attraction of female European but not African mosquitoes to hosts. Ann. Trop. Med. Parasitol., 89, 327-9. CLEMENTS, A. N. (1992). The biology of mosquitoes, Volume I. London: Chapman &amp; Hall EDMAN, J. D. &amp; ELDRIDGE, B. F. (Hrsg.) (2000). Medical Entomology. Dordrecht, Boston, London: Kluwer Academic Publishers EDMAN, J. D. (2004). North American invasion, epidemic spread and control of West Nile Virus. Abstracts of Papers, 227th ACS National Meeting, Anaheim, CA, United States, March 28-April 1, 2004. HEMMINGWAY, J.; HAWKES, N. J.; MCCARROLL, L. &amp; RANSON, H. (2004). The molecular basis of insecticide resistance in mosquitoes (General Review). Insect Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, 34(7), 653-665. MEHLHORN, H. &amp; PIEKARSKI, G. (2002). Grundriss der Parasitenkunde. 6. Aufl. Heidelberg: Spektrum Akademischer Verlag. REBORA, A.; RONGIOLETTI, F. &amp; RAINERI, V. (1993). Aedes albopictus in Europe: a new challenge for dermatologists. Dermatology 187(1): 6-8. REITER, P. (2003). Aedes albopictus and the world trade in used tires, 1988-1995: the shape of things to come? Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association 14(1), 83-94. RMB-WHO Infosheet: http://mosquito.who.int/cmc_upload/0/000/015/372/RBMInfosheet_1.htm (16.02.2005) SCHAFFNER, F.; ANGEL, G.; GEOFFROY, B.; HERVY, J.-P.; RHAIEM, A. &amp; BRUNHES, J. (2001). Les Moustiques d?Europe; EID Mediterrane?, Centre IRD de Montpellier, France; IRD ?ditions. SPIELMAN, A. &amp; D'ANTONIO, M. (2001) Mosquito - A Nautal History of Man's Most Persistent and Deadly Foe. New York: Hyperion. TRIPATHI, A. K.; PRAJAPATI, V.; AHMAD, A.; AGGERWAL, K. K. &amp; KHANUJA, S. P. P. (2004). Piperitenone oxide as toxic, repellent, and reproduction retardant toward malarial vector Anopheles stephensi (Diptera: Anophelinae). Journal of Medical Entomology 41(4), 691-698. WHO- TDR-Dengue: http://www.who.int/tdr/diseases/dengue/direction.htm (16.02. 2005) WHO fact sheet N? 100: http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs100/en/print.html (16.02. 2005) WHO fact sheet N? 117: http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs117/en/print.html (16.02. 2005) WIRTH, M. C.; DELECLUSE, A.; WALTON, W. E. (2004). Laboratory selection for resistence to Bacillus thuringiensis subsp. jegathesan or a component toxin, Cry11B, in Culex quinquefasciatus (Diptera: Culicidae). Journal of Medical Entomology 41(3), 435-441.     © M. Geier version 1.0 updated 15. VII. 2005   Haftungshinweis: Trotz sorgf?ltiger inhaltlicher Kontrolle ?bernehme ich keine Haftung f?r die Inhalte externer Links. F?r den Inhalt der verlinkten Seiten sind ausschlie?lich deren Betreiber verantwortlich.</field>
<field name="important">Von Stechm?cken ?bertragene Infektionskrankheiten: ein ?berblick. Von Stechm?cken ?bertragene Infektionskrankheiten: ein ?berblick.     Von Stechm?cken ?bertragene Infektionskrankheiten: ein ?berblick. Von Sebastian Haas, leicht ver?ndert - © 2005   AG Geier Forschungsthemen (Von Stechm?cken ?bertragende Krankheiten) Arbeitsgruppe Ver?ffentlichungen Diplom- und Zulassungsarbeiten Links Kontakt Institut f?r Zoologie der Universit?t Regensburg Malaria Weltweit leben auch heute noch etwa 40 % der Weltbev?lkerung mit dem Risiko an dem durch Anopheles-M?cken ?bertragenen Malaria zu erkranken. Vor allem die ?rmsten Regionen der Tropen und Subtropen sind j?hrlich mit ?ber 300 Millionen akuten Infektionen und etwa einer Million Todesf?lle betroffen (RBM-WHO Infosheet). Dabei zeichnet sich ein Teufelskreis aus Armut und mangelnder Gesundheitsvorsorge ab: die enormen Ausf?lle Erwerbst?tiger durch Malaria, oft in Verbindung mit anderen Krankheiten wie Tuberkulose, Unterern?hrung und AIDS schw?chen die Wirtschaftskraft ganzer Regionen (RBM-WHO Infosheet). Aus Mangel an finanziellen Mitteln greifen moderne Strategien der Medikation und Seuchenbek?mpfung oft zu kurz, was wiederum das Eind?mmen von Epidemien erschwert. Der gro?fl?chige Einsatz von DDT, wie auch anderer Insektizide f?hrte in relativ kurzer Zeit zur Ausbildung von resistenten M?ckenpopulationen (WIRTH et al., 2004; HEMMINGWAY et al., 2004; TRIPATHI et al., 2004). Daneben haben sich auch unter den eigentlichen Erregern der Malaria, den Plasmodien, Resistenzen gegen allzu gro?z?gig verwandte Medikamente, wie Chloroquin, Mefloquin, Halofantrin und Primaquin ausgebildet (SPIELMAN &amp; D?ANTONIO, 2001). Gelbfieber Obwohl es gegen das Gelbfieber seit Jahrzehnten einen hochwirksamen Impfstoff gibt, verzeichnet die Weltgesundheits-Organisation (WHO) eine wieder zunehmende Zahl infizierter Menschen in Afrika und S?damerika (WHO Fact sheet N? 100). Grund hierf?r ist die zu niedrige Impfquote: sie liegt meist weit unter den erforderlichen 85 %. M?cken ?bertragen die Flaviviren des Gelbfiebers immer wieder von den als Reservoir-Wirt fungierenden Affen auf Waldarbeiter und J?ger. Die so mit dem ?Jungle Yellow Fever? infizierten Menschen transportieren das Virus in die Ballungsr?ume. Dort schlie?lich f?hrt das aggressive Blutsaugeverhalten der eng mit den Menschen vergesellschafteten Stechm?cke Aedes aegypti zur ?bertragung der Viren von Mensch zu Mensch. Dieses sogenannte ?Urban Yellow Fever? f?hrte bereits zu gro?en Epidemien ?ber weite Landstriche hinweg. Die WHO sch?tzt, dass dieser Infektion j?hrlich rund 30 000 Menschen zum Opfer fallen, bei etwa 200 000 F?llen weltweit. Ein Infektionsrisiko bestehe demnach f?r mindestens 42 L?nder mit insgesamt ?ber 600 Millionen Einwohnern (WHO Fact sheet N? 100). Dengue und Dengue-h?morrhagisches Fieber Im Gegensatz zu Gelbfieber ist gegen Dengue und das h?morrhagische Denguefieber (DHF) noch kein Impfstoff entwickelt worden. Auch d?rfte sich die Entwicklung eines Serums als ?u?erst schwierig gestalten, da nicht weniger als vier verschiedene Serotypen dieses Flavivirus bekannt sind (CDC-Dengue). Aktuell sind etwa zwei F?nftel der Weltbev?lkerung von einer Dengueinfektion bedroht. Die WHO sch?tzt die Zahl der weltweit pro Jahr auftretenden F?lle auf 50 Millionen (WHO Fact sheet N? 117). In den zur?ckliegenden Jahrzehnten war zudem eine dramatische Ausbreitung der h?morrhagischen Variante zu verzeichnen. Mit einer Letalrate von 2,5 - 5 % der Infizierten, wird das DHF haupts?chlich Kindern zum Verh?ngnis. Waren vor 1970 nur neun Staaten von DHF betroffen, so erh?hte sich die Zahl bis 1995 auf mehr als das Vierfache (WHO- TDR-Dengue). Diese enorme Zunahme erkl?rt sich zum Teil durch die stark anwachsende Bev?lkerungsdichte in gro?en Ballungsr?umen. Gerade in ?rmeren Regionen, den Favelas und Slums, leben Menschen auf engstem Raum zusammen. H?ufig fehlt ein Anschlu? an das Trinkwassersystem, so dass Zisternen verbreitet sind, welche den M?ckenlarven von Ae. aegypti als Lebensraum dienen. Zudem ist meist die M?llentsorgung unterentwickelt, wodurch sich in tropisch humidem Klima unz?hlige Joghurtbecher, Dosen und Kanister zu ?Kleinstgew?ssern? entwickeln, die f?r die anspruchslosen Larven von Ae. aegypti ausreichende Biotope darstellen (SCHAFFNER et al., 2001; BECKER et al., 2003). Ein solches Umfeld ist geradezu ideal f?r diese tagaktive, aggressive Stechm?cke, welche nicht nur der bedeutendste ?bertr?ger f?r Gelbfieber-, sondern auch f?r Denguefieberviren ist (WHO Fact sheet N?117). Neben Ae. aegypti sind auch die sich weltweit ausbreitende Tigerm?cke Aedes albopictus und die im tropischen Pazifik heimische Aedes polynesiensis wichtige ?bertr?ger von Dengue. Weitere von Stechm?cken ?bertragene Krankheiten Neben diesen, bei weitem gef?hrlichsten Infektionen ?bertragen Stechm?cken (Culicidae) eine ganze Reihe von weiteren veterin?r- und humanmedizinisch relevanten Krankheitserregern: Endoparasiten der tropischen Elephantiasis, diverse Filariasisformen und neben den oben genannten Gelbfieber- und Dengue-Erregern viele weitere Viren (Zusammenfassung in: EDMAN &amp; ELDRIDGE, 2000; SCHAFFNER et al., 2001; MEHLHORN &amp; PIEKARSKI, 2002). Wie die Ausbreitung des bis dahin nur in Afrika und Europa bekannten West-Nile-Virus in j?ngster Vergangenheit in Nordamerika zeigte, sind ?hnliche Krankheiten dabei keinesfalls nur auf die Tropen begrenzt: das im Sommer 1999 erstmals in New York D.C., USA, entdeckte West-Nile-Virus erreichte bereits 2003 die Bundesstaaten der US-Westk?ste. Von 4000 F?llen mit 300 Toten im Jahr 2002 stieg die Zahl der Betroffenen auf beinahe 9000 im Jahr 2003 (EDMAN, 2004). Durch den internationalen Warenverkehr wurde vor kurzem in Europa ein weiterer ?bertr?ger des West-Nile-Virus eingef?hrt (REBORA et al., 1993; REITER, 1998). Die in den Tropen und Subtropen als Dengue-?bertr?ger gef?rchtete Tigerm?cke Aedes albopictus hat sich bereits in Albanien, Italien, Frankreich, Belgien und Teilen der Schweiz etabliert (pers. Mitt. GUERIN, 2004). Sie gilt zudem als potentieller ?bertr?ger f?r eine Vielzahl weiterer human- und veterin?rmedizinisch relevanter Pathogene (SCHAFFNER et al., 2001). Eine ?bertragung dieser Infektionskrankheiten von einem infizierten Menschen via Stechm?cke auf einen Gesunden ist nur m?glich, wenn ein und dieselbe M?cke mindestens zweimal an verschiedenen Personen Blut saugen kann. Daher sind Stechm?cken mit einer Vorliebe f?r Menschen ? die sogenannten anthropophilen Spezies ? wie zum Beispiel Aedes aegypti oder Anopheles gambiae besonders effektive und damit gef?hrliche Vektoren f?r Infektionskrankheiten (CLEMENTS, 1992). Modernes Management der Stechm?ckenpopulationen in Risikogebieten Von der noch Mitte des letzten Jahrhunderts intensiv verfolgten Utopie vom vollst?ndigen Ausrotten der Stechm?cken durch DDT und andere Insektizide hat man sich verabschiedet. Die Bem?hungen zielen heute vielmehr auf eine realistische Risikominimierung ab, indem versucht wird Brutst?tten der M?cken in der N?he von Siedlungen aufzusp?ren und zu zerst?ren, sowie die Fieberm?cken durch gezielten, wohl dosierten Insektizideinsatz zu dezimieren (pers. Mitt. EIRAS, 2004). Ein m?glichst detailliertes Wissen ?ber den Erreger, aber auch ?ber den Vektor stellt das Kernst?ck der modernen Seuchenbek?mpfung dar. In Bezug auf Stechm?cken bedeutet dies, dass Partnerfindung, Eiablageverhalten, Larvalentwicklung, die Ortung von Kohlenhydratquellen und vor allem die spezifische Auswahl der Blutwirte ? um nur die wichtigsten zu nennen ? Gegenstand intensiver Forschung sind. Entomologen gewinnen beispielsweise durch Verhaltenstests in Freiland und Labor neue Erkenntnisse ?ber attraktive und abschreckende Stimuli dieser Lebensstationen. Mit chemischer Analytik und physiologischen Messungen wird versucht, diese ? meist olfaktorischen ? Stimuli zu definieren und zu quantifizieren. Die Elektrophysiologie untersucht die Reaktion von Rezeptorzellen der Sinnesorgane als Antwort auf das Einwirken solcher Stimuli auf das Insekt. Diese Disziplinen werden seit einigen Jahren unter dem Begriff der Chemischen ?kologie vereint und haben u.a. zur Entwicklung der sogenannten olfaktorischen ?Push and Pull-Strategie? beigetragen: Repellentien (Schreckstoffe) halten dabei die M?cken von Menschen fern, Attraktanzien (Lockstoffe) locken sie in spezielle M?ckenfallen. Letztere dienen dabei in erster Linie der Bestands?berwachung (engl. monitoring oder surveillance) und k?nnen so ein Massenauftreten fr?hzeitig zu erfassen. Die eigentliche Dezimierung der Stechm?cken kann dann relativ kleinr?umig und bedarfsgerecht mit Insektiziden erfolgen. Dadurch wird das Risiko der Resistenzbildung verringert, unn?tige Umweltbelastungen und finanzieller Aufwand werden minimiert. Literatur BECKER, N.; PETRIC, S.; ZGOMBA, M.; BOASE, C.; DAHL, C.; LANE, J. &amp; KAISER, A. (2003). Mosquitoes and their Control. Kluwer Academic/ Plenum Publishers. New York, Boston, Dordrecht, London, Moscow CDC-Dengue: http://www.cdc.gov/ncidod/dvbid/dengue/ (16.02. 2005) CHARLWOOD, J. D.; BILLINGSLEY, P. F. ; HOC, T. Q. (1995). Mosquito-mediated attraction of female European but not African mosquitoes to hosts. Ann. Trop. Med. Parasitol., 89, 327-9. CLEMENTS, A. N. (1992). The biology of mosquitoes, Volume I. London: Chapman &amp; Hall EDMAN, J. D. &amp; ELDRIDGE, B. F. (Hrsg.) (2000). Medical Entomology. Dordrecht, Boston, London: Kluwer Academic Publishers EDMAN, J. D. (2004). North American invasion, epidemic spread and control of West Nile Virus. Abstracts of Papers, 227th ACS National Meeting, Anaheim, CA, United States, March 28-April 1, 2004. HEMMINGWAY, J.; HAWKES, N. J.; MCCARROLL, L. &amp; RANSON, H. (2004). The molecular basis of insecticide resistance in mosquitoes (General Review). Insect Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, 34(7), 653-665. MEHLHORN, H. &amp; PIEKARSKI, G. (2002). Grundriss der Parasitenkunde. 6. Aufl. Heidelberg: Spektrum Akademischer Verlag. REBORA, A.; RONGIOLETTI, F. &amp; RAINERI, V. (1993). Aedes albopictus in Europe: a new challenge for dermatologists. Dermatology 187(1): 6-8. REITER, P. (2003). Aedes albopictus and the world trade in used tires, 1988-1995: the shape of things to come? Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association 14(1), 83-94. RMB-WHO Infosheet: http://mosquito.who.int/cmc_upload/0/000/015/372/RBMInfosheet_1.htm (16.02.2005) SCHAFFNER, F.; ANGEL, G.; GEOFFROY, B.; HERVY, J.-P.; RHAIEM, A. &amp; BRUNHES, J. (2001). Les Moustiques d?Europe; EID Mediterrane?, Centre IRD de Montpellier, France; IRD ?ditions. SPIELMAN, A. &amp; D'ANTONIO, M. (2001) Mosquito - A Nautal History of Man's Most Persistent and Deadly Foe. New York: Hyperion. TRIPATHI, A. K.; PRAJAPATI, V.; AHMAD, A.; AGGERWAL, K. K. &amp; KHANUJA, S. P. P. (2004). Piperitenone oxide as toxic, repellent, and reproduction retardant toward malarial vector Anopheles stephensi (Diptera: Anophelinae). Journal of Medical Entomology 41(4), 691-698. WHO- TDR-Dengue: http://www.who.int/tdr/diseases/dengue/direction.htm (16.02. 2005) WHO fact sheet N? 100: http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs100/en/print.html (16.02. 2005) WHO fact sheet N? 117: http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs117/en/print.html (16.02. 2005) WIRTH, M. C.; DELECLUSE, A.; WALTON, W. E. (2004). Laboratory selection for resistence to Bacillus thuringiensis subsp. jegathesan or a component toxin, Cry11B, in Culex quinquefasciatus (Diptera: Culicidae). Journal of Medical Entomology 41(3), 435-441.     © M. Geier version 1.0 updated 15. VII. 2005   Haftungshinweis: Trotz sorgf?ltiger inhaltlicher Kontrolle ?bernehme ich keine Haftung f?r die Inhalte externer Links. F?r den Inhalt der verlinkten Seiten sind ausschlie?lich deren Betreiber verantwortlich.</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Geier/veroeffentlichungen.html</field>
<field name="title">AG Geier - ausgew?hlte Ver?ffentlichungen in Zeitschriften und auf Kongressen.</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Geier/veroeffentlichungen.html</field>
<field name="content">AG Geier - ausgew?hlte Ver?ffentlichungen in Zeitschriften und auf Kongressen. AG Geier - ausgew?hlte Ver?ffentlichungen in Zeitschriften und auf Kongressen.     AG Geier - ausgew?hlte Ver?ffentlichungen in Zeitschriften und auf Kongressen.   AG Geier Forschungsthemen Von Stechm?cken ?bertragende Krankheiten Arbeitsgruppe (Ver?ffentlichungen) Diplom- und Zulassungsarbeiten Links Kontakt Institut f?r Zoologie der Universit?t Regensburg Dekker T., Geier M. &amp; Card? R.T. (2005) Carbon dioxide instantly sensitizes female yellow fever mosquitoes to human skin odours. The Journal of Experimental Biology 208, 2963-2972. Geier M., Rose A. &amp; Eiras ?.E. (2004) Attractive host odours for mosquitoes: the blend ratio makes the difference. XXII International Congress of Entomology, Brisbane, Australia. (Klicken Sie auf den Titel um eine pdf-Datei der Zusammenfassung herunterzuladen.) Geier M., Rose A., Baptista C., Richie S.A., Kr?ckel U. &amp; Eiras ?.E. (2004) Specific monitoring tools for anthropohilic mosquitoes. XXII International Congress of Entomology, Brisbane, Australia. (Klicken Sie auf den Titel um eine pdf-Datei der Zusammenfassung herunterzuladen.) Eiras ?.E., Silva I.M., Roque R.A., Matosinhos I.M. &amp; Geier M. (2004) Behavioural responses of gravid Aedes aegypti (Diptera: Culicidae) to synthetic oviposition attractants identified from grass infusions volatiles. XXII International Congress of Entomology, Brisbane, Australia. (Klicken Sie auf den Titel um eine pdf-Datei der Zusammenfassung herunterzuladen.) Eiras ?.E., Silva I.M., Costa C.F., Antonacci R.G., Silva E.M., Rose A. &amp; Geier M. (2004) Monitoring the mosquito Aedes aegypti: A novel surveillance method and new entomological indices using the gravid trap MosquiTRAP® and a synthetic oviposition attractant AtrAedes®. XXII International Congress of Entomology, Brisbane, Australia. (Klicken Sie auf den Titel um eine pdf-Datei der Zusammenfassung herunterzuladen.) Rose A. &amp; Geier M. (2004) Warum es n?tzt, den Feind zu locken: Stechm?cken in die Irre gef?hrt. In: F?rst W. &amp; Bauernschmitt J. (Hrsg.) Biotechnologie in Bayern. Media Mind, M?nchen. 64 - 68. (Klicken Sie auf den Titel um diesen Artikel als pdf-Datei herunterzuladen - 145 kb.) Geier M., Rose A. &amp; Eiras ?.E. (2004) A new lure for host-seeking anthropophilic mosquitoes and a novel type of a simple, non-CO2 mosquito trap. International Journal of Medical Microbiology 293, Suppl. 38, 50. Eiras ?.E., Rose A. &amp; Geier M.(2004) New tools for monitoring gravid females of the mosquitoes Aedes aegypti and Aedes albopictus (Diptera: Culicidae), vectors of Dengue and other arboviral diseases. International Journal of Medical Microbiology 293, Suppl. 38, 51-52. Eiras ?.E., Geier M. &amp; Rose A. (2004) MosquiTRAP &amp; AtrAedes: New tools for monitoring gravid females of Aedes aegypti &amp; Aedes albopictus. The Abstract Book, 70th Annual Meeting of the American Mosquito Control Association. 40. Rose A., Eiras ?.E. &amp; Geier M. (2004) New attractants for host-finding mosquitoes &amp; innovative designs for non-CO2 traps. The Abstract Book, 70th Annual Meeting of the American Mosquito Control Association. 41. Geier M., Bosch O., Steib B., Rose A. &amp; Boeckh J. (2002) Odour-guided host finding of mosquitoes: identification of new attractants on human skin. In: Jones S.C., Zhai J. &amp; Robinson W.H. (Hrsg.) Proceedings of the 4th International Conference on Urban Pests. Blacksburg, Virginia. 37-46. Smallegange R., Geier M. &amp; Takken W. (2002) Behavioural responses of Anopheles gambiae to ammonia, lactic acid and a fatty acid in a y-tube olfactometer. Proceedings of the Section Experimental and Applied Entomology of the Netherlands Entomological Society (NEV) 13, 147-152. Dekker T., Card? R. &amp; Geier M. (2002) L-lactic acid: a human-signifying host cue for the anthropophilic mosquito Anopheles gambiae. Medical and Veterinary Entomology 16, 91-98. Geier M., Rose A.M. &amp; Mutzbauer I. (2001) Repellentien zum Schutz vor Blutsaugern. Journal f?r Flug- und Reisemedizin 8, 18-32. Steib B., Geier M. &amp; Boeckh J. (2001) The effect of lactic acid on odor related host preference of yellow fever mosquitoes. Chemical Senses 26, 523-528 Rose A. (2001) Sonnengold - von der Herstellung eines guten Helichrysum-?ls. Forum f?r Aromatherapie und Aromapflege 21, 9-11. Geier M. (2000) Olfaktorische Wirtsfindung bei Stechm?cken. Journal Flug-und Reisemedizin 7, 16-20. Bosch J.O., Geier M. &amp; Boeckh J. (2000) Contribution of fatty acids to olfactory host finding of female Aedes aegypti. Chemical Senses 25, 323-330. Geier M., Franz H., Rose A.M., and Boeckh J. (2000) How the fine-scale plume structure of host-odours affect the flight behaviour of mosquitoes. In: Book of Abstracts, XXI ICE, Foz do Iguassu, # 2872. Geier M. &amp; Boeckh J. (1999) A new Y-tube olfactometer for mosquitoes to measure the attractiveness of host odours. Entomologia Experimentalis et Applicata 92, 9-19. Geier M., Bosch J.O. &amp; Boeckh J. (1999) Influence of odour plume structure on upwind flight of mosquitoes towards hosts. Journal of Experimental Biology 202, 1639-1648. Geier M., Bosch J.O. &amp; Boeckh J. (1999) Ammonia as an attractive component of host odour for the yellow fever mosquito, Aedes aegypti. Chemical Senses 24, 647-653. Card? R.T., Dekker T. &amp; Geier M. (1998): Flight behavior of mosquitoes on plumes of natural and synthetic host odor: mechanisms of orientation and influence of environmental factors. Annual Report of Mosquito Control Research, 47-49. Rose A.M. (1998) The effect of host stimuli on the host finding behaviour of the bloodsucking bug Triatoma infestans (Hemiptera: Reduviidae), under quasi-natural conditions. In: Brunnhofer V. &amp; Sold?n T. (Hrsg.) Book of Abstracts, Volume 2 VIth European Congress of Entomology. Cesk? Budejovice, 680-681. Geier M., Bosch O.J. &amp; Boeckh J. (1998): The effect of odour plume structure on the upwind flight of female Aedes aegypti (Diptera, Culicidae). In: Brunnhofer V. &amp; Sold?n T. (Hrsg.) Book of Abstracts, Volume 2 VIth European Congress of Entomology. Cesk? Budejovice, 677-678. Stengl, M. &amp; H?rbrand, T. (1997): What is the role of cyclic GMP in insect olfaction? Society for Neuroscience Abstracts. 23, 1826. Geier M., Sass H. &amp; Boeckh, J. (1996): A search for components in human body odour that attract females of Aedes aegypti. In: Cardew, G. and Goode, J. (Hrsg.): Mosquito olfaction and olfactory-mediated mosquito-host interactions. Ciba Foundation Symposium. New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, 132-148. Pappenberger B., Geier M. &amp; Boeckh, J. (1996): Responses of antennal olfactory receptors to odours from the human body in the yellow fever mosquito, Aedes aegypti. In: Cardew, G. and Goode, J. (Hrsg.): Mosquito olfaction and olfactory-mediated mosquito-host interactions. Ciba Foundation Symposium 200. New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, 254-266. Boeckh J., Breer H., Geier M., Hoever F.-P., Kr?ger B.-W., Nentwig G. &amp; Sass H. (1996): Acylated 1,3- Aminopropanols as repellents against bloodsucking arthropods. Pesticide Science, 48, 359-373. Rose A.M. &amp; Boeckh J. (1996) Host-finding of the bloodsucking bug Triatoma infestans (Hemiptera: Reduviidae), a vector of Chagas' disease: Observations under conditions resembling the natural environment. In: Wildey K.B. (Hrsg.) Proceedings of the 2nd International Conference on Insect Pests in the Urban Environement. BPC Wheatons, Exeter. 612. Rose A.M. &amp; Boeckh J. (1996) Host-finding of the bloodsucking bug Triatoma infestans (Hemiptera: Reduviidae), a vectors of Chagas' disease: an olfactometer study. In: Proceedings of the XX International Congress of Entomology. Florence. 768. Geier M., Sass H., Boeckh J. (1996): Olfactory host finding of yellow fever mosquitoes Aedes aegypti (Diptera: Culicidae): Synergetic effect of different host odour components. In: Proceedings of the XX International Congress of Entomology. Florence. Dolzer J., H?rbrand T., Pophof B. &amp; Stengl M. (1996) Tip recordings in situ and patch clamp measurements in vitro of adapted olfactory receptor neurons of the hawkmoth Manduca sexta. In: Elsner N. &amp; Schnitzler H.-U. (Hrsg.) G?ttingen Neurobiology Report 1996, 262. Geier, M. (1995): The role of lactic acid in olfactory host finding of the mosquito Aedes aegypti. European Symposium on Insect Taste and Olfaction IV. Geier, M. (1993): Olfactory host finding of mosquitoes Aedes aegypti: a search for key stimuli. European Symposium on Insect Taste and Olfaction III. Geier, M. (1991): Receptors for host odours and repellents on the antenna of the mosquito Aedes aegypti. European Symposium on Insect Taste and Olfaction II.     © M. Geier version 1.0 updated 15. VII. 2005   Haftungshinweis: Trotz sorgf?ltiger inhaltlicher Kontrolle ?bernehme ich keine Haftung f?r die Inhalte externer Links. F?r den Inhalt der verlinkten Seiten sind ausschlie?lich deren Betreiber verantwortlich.</field>
<field name="important">AG Geier - ausgew?hlte Ver?ffentlichungen in Zeitschriften und auf Kongressen. AG Geier - ausgew?hlte Ver?ffentlichungen in Zeitschriften und auf Kongressen.     AG Geier - ausgew?hlte Ver?ffentlichungen in Zeitschriften und auf Kongressen.   AG Geier Forschungsthemen Von Stechm?cken ?bertragende Krankheiten Arbeitsgruppe (Ver?ffentlichungen) Diplom- und Zulassungsarbeiten Links Kontakt Institut f?r Zoologie der Universit?t Regensburg Dekker T., Geier M. &amp; Card? R.T. (2005) Carbon dioxide instantly sensitizes female yellow fever mosquitoes to human skin odours. The Journal of Experimental Biology 208, 2963-2972. Geier M., Rose A. &amp; Eiras ?.E. (2004) Attractive host odours for mosquitoes: the blend ratio makes the difference. XXII International Congress of Entomology, Brisbane, Australia. (Klicken Sie auf den Titel um eine pdf-Datei der Zusammenfassung herunterzuladen.) Geier M., Rose A., Baptista C., Richie S.A., Kr?ckel U. &amp; Eiras ?.E. (2004) Specific monitoring tools for anthropohilic mosquitoes. XXII International Congress of Entomology, Brisbane, Australia. (Klicken Sie auf den Titel um eine pdf-Datei der Zusammenfassung herunterzuladen.) Eiras ?.E., Silva I.M., Roque R.A., Matosinhos I.M. &amp; Geier M. (2004) Behavioural responses of gravid Aedes aegypti (Diptera: Culicidae) to synthetic oviposition attractants identified from grass infusions volatiles. XXII International Congress of Entomology, Brisbane, Australia. (Klicken Sie auf den Titel um eine pdf-Datei der Zusammenfassung herunterzuladen.) Eiras ?.E., Silva I.M., Costa C.F., Antonacci R.G., Silva E.M., Rose A. &amp; Geier M. (2004) Monitoring the mosquito Aedes aegypti: A novel surveillance method and new entomological indices using the gravid trap MosquiTRAP® and a synthetic oviposition attractant AtrAedes®. XXII International Congress of Entomology, Brisbane, Australia. (Klicken Sie auf den Titel um eine pdf-Datei der Zusammenfassung herunterzuladen.) Rose A. &amp; Geier M. (2004) Warum es n?tzt, den Feind zu locken: Stechm?cken in die Irre gef?hrt. In: F?rst W. &amp; Bauernschmitt J. (Hrsg.) Biotechnologie in Bayern. Media Mind, M?nchen. 64 - 68. (Klicken Sie auf den Titel um diesen Artikel als pdf-Datei herunterzuladen - 145 kb.) Geier M., Rose A. &amp; Eiras ?.E. (2004) A new lure for host-seeking anthropophilic mosquitoes and a novel type of a simple, non-CO2 mosquito trap. International Journal of Medical Microbiology 293, Suppl. 38, 50. Eiras ?.E., Rose A. &amp; Geier M.(2004) New tools for monitoring gravid females of the mosquitoes Aedes aegypti and Aedes albopictus (Diptera: Culicidae), vectors of Dengue and other arboviral diseases. International Journal of Medical Microbiology 293, Suppl. 38, 51-52. Eiras ?.E., Geier M. &amp; Rose A. (2004) MosquiTRAP &amp; AtrAedes: New tools for monitoring gravid females of Aedes aegypti &amp; Aedes albopictus. The Abstract Book, 70th Annual Meeting of the American Mosquito Control Association. 40. Rose A., Eiras ?.E. &amp; Geier M. (2004) New attractants for host-finding mosquitoes &amp; innovative designs for non-CO2 traps. The Abstract Book, 70th Annual Meeting of the American Mosquito Control Association. 41. Geier M., Bosch O., Steib B., Rose A. &amp; Boeckh J. (2002) Odour-guided host finding of mosquitoes: identification of new attractants on human skin. In: Jones S.C., Zhai J. &amp; Robinson W.H. (Hrsg.) Proceedings of the 4th International Conference on Urban Pests. Blacksburg, Virginia. 37-46. Smallegange R., Geier M. &amp; Takken W. (2002) Behavioural responses of Anopheles gambiae to ammonia, lactic acid and a fatty acid in a y-tube olfactometer. Proceedings of the Section Experimental and Applied Entomology of the Netherlands Entomological Society (NEV) 13, 147-152. Dekker T., Card? R. &amp; Geier M. (2002) L-lactic acid: a human-signifying host cue for the anthropophilic mosquito Anopheles gambiae. Medical and Veterinary Entomology 16, 91-98. Geier M., Rose A.M. &amp; Mutzbauer I. (2001) Repellentien zum Schutz vor Blutsaugern. Journal f?r Flug- und Reisemedizin 8, 18-32. Steib B., Geier M. &amp; Boeckh J. (2001) The effect of lactic acid on odor related host preference of yellow fever mosquitoes. Chemical Senses 26, 523-528 Rose A. (2001) Sonnengold - von der Herstellung eines guten Helichrysum-?ls. Forum f?r Aromatherapie und Aromapflege 21, 9-11. Geier M. (2000) Olfaktorische Wirtsfindung bei Stechm?cken. Journal Flug-und Reisemedizin 7, 16-20. Bosch J.O., Geier M. &amp; Boeckh J. (2000) Contribution of fatty acids to olfactory host finding of female Aedes aegypti. Chemical Senses 25, 323-330. Geier M., Franz H., Rose A.M., and Boeckh J. (2000) How the fine-scale plume structure of host-odours affect the flight behaviour of mosquitoes. In: Book of Abstracts, XXI ICE, Foz do Iguassu, # 2872. Geier M. &amp; Boeckh J. (1999) A new Y-tube olfactometer for mosquitoes to measure the attractiveness of host odours. Entomologia Experimentalis et Applicata 92, 9-19. Geier M., Bosch J.O. &amp; Boeckh J. (1999) Influence of odour plume structure on upwind flight of mosquitoes towards hosts. Journal of Experimental Biology 202, 1639-1648. Geier M., Bosch J.O. &amp; Boeckh J. (1999) Ammonia as an attractive component of host odour for the yellow fever mosquito, Aedes aegypti. Chemical Senses 24, 647-653. Card? R.T., Dekker T. &amp; Geier M. (1998): Flight behavior of mosquitoes on plumes of natural and synthetic host odor: mechanisms of orientation and influence of environmental factors. Annual Report of Mosquito Control Research, 47-49. Rose A.M. (1998) The effect of host stimuli on the host finding behaviour of the bloodsucking bug Triatoma infestans (Hemiptera: Reduviidae), under quasi-natural conditions. In: Brunnhofer V. &amp; Sold?n T. (Hrsg.) Book of Abstracts, Volume 2 VIth European Congress of Entomology. Cesk? Budejovice, 680-681. Geier M., Bosch O.J. &amp; Boeckh J. (1998): The effect of odour plume structure on the upwind flight of female Aedes aegypti (Diptera, Culicidae). In: Brunnhofer V. &amp; Sold?n T. (Hrsg.) Book of Abstracts, Volume 2 VIth European Congress of Entomology. Cesk? Budejovice, 677-678. Stengl, M. &amp; H?rbrand, T. (1997): What is the role of cyclic GMP in insect olfaction? Society for Neuroscience Abstracts. 23, 1826. Geier M., Sass H. &amp; Boeckh, J. (1996): A search for components in human body odour that attract females of Aedes aegypti. In: Cardew, G. and Goode, J. (Hrsg.): Mosquito olfaction and olfactory-mediated mosquito-host interactions. Ciba Foundation Symposium. New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, 132-148. Pappenberger B., Geier M. &amp; Boeckh, J. (1996): Responses of antennal olfactory receptors to odours from the human body in the yellow fever mosquito, Aedes aegypti. In: Cardew, G. and Goode, J. (Hrsg.): Mosquito olfaction and olfactory-mediated mosquito-host interactions. Ciba Foundation Symposium 200. New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, 254-266. Boeckh J., Breer H., Geier M., Hoever F.-P., Kr?ger B.-W., Nentwig G. &amp; Sass H. (1996): Acylated 1,3- Aminopropanols as repellents against bloodsucking arthropods. Pesticide Science, 48, 359-373. Rose A.M. &amp; Boeckh J. (1996) Host-finding of the bloodsucking bug Triatoma infestans (Hemiptera: Reduviidae), a vector of Chagas' disease: Observations under conditions resembling the natural environment. In: Wildey K.B. (Hrsg.) Proceedings of the 2nd International Conference on Insect Pests in the Urban Environement. BPC Wheatons, Exeter. 612. Rose A.M. &amp; Boeckh J. (1996) Host-finding of the bloodsucking bug Triatoma infestans (Hemiptera: Reduviidae), a vectors of Chagas' disease: an olfactometer study. In: Proceedings of the XX International Congress of Entomology. Florence. 768. Geier M., Sass H., Boeckh J. (1996): Olfactory host finding of yellow fever mosquitoes Aedes aegypti (Diptera: Culicidae): Synergetic effect of different host odour components. In: Proceedings of the XX International Congress of Entomology. Florence. Dolzer J., H?rbrand T., Pophof B. &amp; Stengl M. (1996) Tip recordings in situ and patch clamp measurements in vitro of adapted olfactory receptor neurons of the hawkmoth Manduca sexta. In: Elsner N. &amp; Schnitzler H.-U. (Hrsg.) G?ttingen Neurobiology Report 1996, 262. Geier, M. (1995): The role of lactic acid in olfactory host finding of the mosquito Aedes aegypti. European Symposium on Insect Taste and Olfaction IV. Geier, M. (1993): Olfactory host finding of mosquitoes Aedes aegypti: a search for key stimuli. European Symposium on Insect Taste and Olfaction III. Geier, M. (1991): Receptors for host odours and repellents on the antenna of the mosquito Aedes aegypti. European Symposium on Insect Taste and Olfaction II.     © M. Geier version 1.0 updated 15. VII. 2005   Haftungshinweis: Trotz sorgf?ltiger inhaltlicher Kontrolle ?bernehme ich keine Haftung f?r die Inhalte externer Links. F?r den Inhalt der verlinkten Seiten sind ausschlie?lich deren Betreiber verantwortlich.</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Heinze/index.html</field>
<field name="title">Prof. Dr. Jürgen Heinze - Evolution, Verhalten und Genetik</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Heinze/index.html</field>
<field name="content">Prof. Dr. Jürgen Heinze - Evolution, Verhalten und Genetik Prof. Dr. Jürgen Heinze - Evolution, Verhalten und Genetik Prof. Dr. Jürgen Heinze  Biologie I  Universität Regensburg  Universitätsstraße 31 D-93053 Regensburg  Tel. --49 941 943 3054 or 2475  Fax --49 941 943 3304 frontiers in zoology            </field>
<field name="important">Prof. Dr. Jürgen Heinze - Evolution, Verhalten und Genetik Prof. Dr. Jürgen Heinze - Evolution, Verhalten und Genetik Prof. Dr. Jürgen Heinze  Biologie I  Universität Regensburg  Universitätsstraße 31 D-93053 Regensburg  Tel. --49 941 943 3054 or 2475  Fax --49 941 943 3304 frontiers in zoology            </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Heinze/index_en.html</field>
<field name="title">Prof. Dr. Jürgen Heinze - Evolution, Verhalten und Genetik</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Heinze/index_en.html</field>
<field name="content">Prof. Dr. Jürgen Heinze - Evolution, Verhalten und Genetik Prof. Dr. Jürgen Heinze - Evolution, Verhalten und Genetik Prof. Dr. Jürgen Heinze  Biologie I  Universität Regensburg Universitätsstraße 31  D-93053 Regensburg  Tel. --49 941 943 3054 or 2475  Fax --49 941 943 3304 frontiers in zoology            </field>
<field name="important">Prof. Dr. Jürgen Heinze - Evolution, Verhalten und Genetik Prof. Dr. Jürgen Heinze - Evolution, Verhalten und Genetik Prof. Dr. Jürgen Heinze  Biologie I  Universität Regensburg Universitätsstraße 31  D-93053 Regensburg  Tel. --49 941 943 3054 or 2475  Fax --49 941 943 3304 frontiers in zoology            </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Heinze/iussi/europe.html</field>
<field name="title">IUSSI</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Heinze/iussi/europe.html</field>
<field name="content">IUSSI IUSSI back to Regensburg homepage International Union for the Study of Social Insects Sections in Europe   Links to European sections  Link to IUSSI homepage  previous conferences: Berlin 2001  St. Petersburg 2005 future conferences: La-Roche en Ardenne, 2008      </field>
<field name="important">IUSSI IUSSI back to Regensburg homepage International Union for the Study of Social Insects Sections in Europe   Links to European sections  Link to IUSSI homepage  previous conferences: Berlin 2001  St. Petersburg 2005 future conferences: La-Roche en Ardenne, 2008      </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Heinze/iussi/iussi-de.html</field>
<field name="title">IUSSI</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Heinze/iussi/iussi-de.html</field>
<field name="content">IUSSI IUSSI Home   Subscription changes IUSSI circular 2010 Neue Satzung Internationales ARCHIVE     International Union for the Study of Social Insects Jetzt anmelden zur vom 25. bis 28. März 2011 Die Anmeldung zur 2. Tagung der Zentraleuropäischen Sektion der IUSSI ist ab sofort möglich. Die Tagung wird vom 25. bis zum 28. März 2011 in der Historisch-Ökologischen Bildungsstätte (HOEB) in Papenburg in Norddeutschland stattfinden. Redner für Hauptvorträge werden Kevin Foster (Harvard University, USA) und Andy Gardner (Oxford University, GB) sein. Die Tagung wird von Judith Korb und ihrer Arbeitsgruppe von der Universität Osnabrück organisiert. Für weitere Informationen und zum anmelden bitte auf die homepage zur Tagung schauen: http://www.biologie.uni-osnabrueck.de/Verhaltensbiologie/iussi2011/ Die Zentraleuropäische Sektion der IUSSI stellt sich vor: Soziale Insekten (Bienen, Wespen, Ameisen und Termiten) sind ideale Modellsysteme, um grundlegende biologische Fragen zu untersuchen. In den letzten Jahrzehnten wurden sie daher verstärkt zum Objekt wissenschaftlicher Forschung. Soziale Insekten sind nahezu überall in großer Dichte anzutreffen und spielen deshalb in den meisten terrestrischen Ökosystemen eine entscheidende Rolle. Ein Verständnis ökologischer Prozesse ist somit nur bei genauer Kenntnis der Lebensweise sozialer Insekten möglich. Soziale Insekten leben in Staaten mit einer Arbeitsteilung zwischen sich fortpflanzenden und sterilen Individuen. Königinnen (und Könige) produzieren die Nachkommen, während Arbeiterinnen (und Arbeiter) die täglichen Arbeiten im Nest, wie Futtersuche, Nestinstandhaltung und -verteidigung übernehmen. Wie eine solche Kooperation zwischen "egoistischen" Individuen in der Evolution entstehen kann, war lange Zeit eines der wichtigsten Probleme der Evolutionsbiologie.  Wissenschaftler, die sich für soziale Insekten interessieren, haben sich in der Internationalen Union zum Studium sozialer Insekten (IUSSI) zusammengeschlossen. Die IUSSI wurde 1951 während des Internationalen Entomologie-Kongresses in Amsterdam gegründet und besteht heute aus rund 15 regionalen oder nationalen Sektionen. Sie gibt eine international anerkannte, vierteljährlich erscheinende Zeitschrift, Insectes Sociaux, heraus und veranstaltet alle vier Jahre eine internationale Konferenz. Die letzte internationale IUSSI-Tagung fand im Sommer 2010 in Kopenhagen in Dänemark statt und wurde von rund 700 Wissenschaftlern, die sich mit sozialen Insekten beschäftigen besucht. Außerdem organisieren die einzelnen Sektionen nationale bzw. regionale Treffen. Die letzte europäische IUSSI-Tagung fand 2008 in den Ardennen in Belgien statt, 2012 wird die Tagung in der Toskana in Italien stattfinden. Die deutschsprachige Sektion der IUSSI ist eine der größten regionalen Sektionen. Im Herbst 2007 änderte sie ihren Namen in "Zentraleuropäische Sektion" und öffnete sich damit für potentielle Interessenten aus anderen europäischen Ländern. Informationen zur Mitgliedschaft finden Sie hier. Die letzte Tagung der Zentraleuropäischen Sektion fand im Herbst 2009 gemeinsam mit dem Central European Workshop in Myrmecology (CEWiM) in der Abtei Frauenwörth auf der Fraueninsel im Chiemsee statt und wurde von der Arbeitsgruppe von Susanne Foitzik an der LMU München organisiert. Der Vorstand der zentraleuropäischen Sektion der IUSSI setzt sich zusammen aus Judith Korb, Universität Osnabrück, Detuschland (Präsidentin) Heike Feldhaar, Universität Osnabrück, Detuschland (Sekretärin)  Susanne Foitzik, LMU München, Deutschland Karl Crailsheim, Universität Graz, Österreich  Wolfgang Kirchner, Ruhr-Universität Bochum, Deutschland  Robin Moritz, Universität Halle, Deutschland Marko Balint, Babes-Bolyai University Cluj-Napoca, Rumänien  Jürgen Heinze, Universität Regensburg, Deutschland         </field>
<field name="important">IUSSI IUSSI Home   Subscription changes IUSSI circular 2010 Neue Satzung Internationales ARCHIVE     International Union for the Study of Social Insects Jetzt anmelden zur vom 25. bis 28. März 2011 Die Anmeldung zur 2. Tagung der Zentraleuropäischen Sektion der IUSSI ist ab sofort möglich. Die Tagung wird vom 25. bis zum 28. März 2011 in der Historisch-Ökologischen Bildungsstätte (HOEB) in Papenburg in Norddeutschland stattfinden. Redner für Hauptvorträge werden Kevin Foster (Harvard University, USA) und Andy Gardner (Oxford University, GB) sein. Die Tagung wird von Judith Korb und ihrer Arbeitsgruppe von der Universität Osnabrück organisiert. Für weitere Informationen und zum anmelden bitte auf die homepage zur Tagung schauen: http://www.biologie.uni-osnabrueck.de/Verhaltensbiologie/iussi2011/ Die Zentraleuropäische Sektion der IUSSI stellt sich vor: Soziale Insekten (Bienen, Wespen, Ameisen und Termiten) sind ideale Modellsysteme, um grundlegende biologische Fragen zu untersuchen. In den letzten Jahrzehnten wurden sie daher verstärkt zum Objekt wissenschaftlicher Forschung. Soziale Insekten sind nahezu überall in großer Dichte anzutreffen und spielen deshalb in den meisten terrestrischen Ökosystemen eine entscheidende Rolle. Ein Verständnis ökologischer Prozesse ist somit nur bei genauer Kenntnis der Lebensweise sozialer Insekten möglich. Soziale Insekten leben in Staaten mit einer Arbeitsteilung zwischen sich fortpflanzenden und sterilen Individuen. Königinnen (und Könige) produzieren die Nachkommen, während Arbeiterinnen (und Arbeiter) die täglichen Arbeiten im Nest, wie Futtersuche, Nestinstandhaltung und -verteidigung übernehmen. Wie eine solche Kooperation zwischen "egoistischen" Individuen in der Evolution entstehen kann, war lange Zeit eines der wichtigsten Probleme der Evolutionsbiologie.  Wissenschaftler, die sich für soziale Insekten interessieren, haben sich in der Internationalen Union zum Studium sozialer Insekten (IUSSI) zusammengeschlossen. Die IUSSI wurde 1951 während des Internationalen Entomologie-Kongresses in Amsterdam gegründet und besteht heute aus rund 15 regionalen oder nationalen Sektionen. Sie gibt eine international anerkannte, vierteljährlich erscheinende Zeitschrift, Insectes Sociaux, heraus und veranstaltet alle vier Jahre eine internationale Konferenz. Die letzte internationale IUSSI-Tagung fand im Sommer 2010 in Kopenhagen in Dänemark statt und wurde von rund 700 Wissenschaftlern, die sich mit sozialen Insekten beschäftigen besucht. Außerdem organisieren die einzelnen Sektionen nationale bzw. regionale Treffen. Die letzte europäische IUSSI-Tagung fand 2008 in den Ardennen in Belgien statt, 2012 wird die Tagung in der Toskana in Italien stattfinden. Die deutschsprachige Sektion der IUSSI ist eine der größten regionalen Sektionen. Im Herbst 2007 änderte sie ihren Namen in "Zentraleuropäische Sektion" und öffnete sich damit für potentielle Interessenten aus anderen europäischen Ländern. Informationen zur Mitgliedschaft finden Sie hier. Die letzte Tagung der Zentraleuropäischen Sektion fand im Herbst 2009 gemeinsam mit dem Central European Workshop in Myrmecology (CEWiM) in der Abtei Frauenwörth auf der Fraueninsel im Chiemsee statt und wurde von der Arbeitsgruppe von Susanne Foitzik an der LMU München organisiert. Der Vorstand der zentraleuropäischen Sektion der IUSSI setzt sich zusammen aus Judith Korb, Universität Osnabrück, Detuschland (Präsidentin) Heike Feldhaar, Universität Osnabrück, Detuschland (Sekretärin)  Susanne Foitzik, LMU München, Deutschland Karl Crailsheim, Universität Graz, Österreich  Wolfgang Kirchner, Ruhr-Universität Bochum, Deutschland  Robin Moritz, Universität Halle, Deutschland Marko Balint, Babes-Bolyai University Cluj-Napoca, Rumänien  Jürgen Heinze, Universität Regensburg, Deutschland         </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Heinze/iussi/iussi-en.html</field>
<field name="title">IUSSI</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Heinze/iussi/iussi-en.html</field>
<field name="content">IUSSI IUSSI Home   Subscription changes IUSSI circular 2010 Neue Satzung Internationales ARCHIVE International Union for the Study of Social Insects Central European section Upcoming: 2nd Central European Meeting of the IUSSI 25th to 28th of March 2011 The registration for the 2nd IUSSI Central European meeting is now open. The meeting will be held from 25th to the 28th of March 2011 at the Historical Ecological Education Center (HOEB) in Papenburg in northern Germany. Plenary lectures will be given by Kevin Foster (Harvard University, USA) and Andy Gardner (Oxford University, UK). The meeting is organized by Judith Korb and her group from the University of Osnabrueck. Please see the homepage of the meeting: http://www.biologie.uni-osnabrueck.de/Verhaltensbiologie/iussi2011/ Introduction to the Central European section of the IUSSI During the last few decades, more and more researchers have become interested in social insects (bees, wasps, ants and termites) and have found that for many fundamental questions in biology, they make perfect study systems. Social insects are almost ubiquitous, and wherever they occur, they occur in large numbers. Consequently, they play an enormous role in most terrestrial ecosystems. A thorough insight into ecological processes therefore requires a deep understanding of social insects. The life history traits of social insects are the basis for their ecological success: social insects live in societies which are characterized by a division of labour between reproductives (kings and queens), which produce young, and non-reproductives (workers and soldiers), which perform the daily tasks in the nest. How such a deep co-operation among egoistic entities evolved has long been a major puzzle in biology, and much research therefore focuses on how colony life is established and maintained. Researchers working on social insects are drawn together in the International Union for the Study of Social Insects (IUSSI). It was founded by a group of entomologists during the International Congress of Entomology in Amsterdam in 1951 and today consists of around 15 regional or national sections worldwide. It publishes an internationally renowned quarterly journal, Insectes Sociaux, and international conferences are held every four years. The last International meeting was held in August 2010 in Copenhagen, Denmark. This recent meeting was attended by nearly 700 scientists interested in social insects and related topics. In addition, the individual sections have regional meetings. The last European meeting was held in the Ardennes in Belgium in 2008. The next European meeting will be held in Tuscany in Italy in 2012.   The German-Speaking section of IUSSI is currently one of the largest regional sections. In fall 2007 it changed its name to "Central European Section" and thus opened itself for potential members from other European countries. For information on membership please contact Heike Feldhaar. The managing board of the Central European section consists of Judith Korb, Universität Osnabrück, Germany (president) Heike Feldhaar, Universität Osnabrück, Germany (secretary)  Susanne Foitzik, LMU München, Germany Karl Crailsheim, Universität Graz, Austria  Wolfgang Kirchner, Ruhr-Universität Bochum, Germany  Robin Moritz, Universität Halle, Germany Marko Balint, Babes-Bolyai University Cluj-Napoca, Romania  Jürgen Heinze, Universität Regensburg, Germany         </field>
<field name="important">IUSSI IUSSI Home   Subscription changes IUSSI circular 2010 Neue Satzung Internationales ARCHIVE International Union for the Study of Social Insects Central European section Upcoming: 2nd Central European Meeting of the IUSSI 25th to 28th of March 2011 The registration for the 2nd IUSSI Central European meeting is now open. The meeting will be held from 25th to the 28th of March 2011 at the Historical Ecological Education Center (HOEB) in Papenburg in northern Germany. Plenary lectures will be given by Kevin Foster (Harvard University, USA) and Andy Gardner (Oxford University, UK). The meeting is organized by Judith Korb and her group from the University of Osnabrueck. Please see the homepage of the meeting: http://www.biologie.uni-osnabrueck.de/Verhaltensbiologie/iussi2011/ Introduction to the Central European section of the IUSSI During the last few decades, more and more researchers have become interested in social insects (bees, wasps, ants and termites) and have found that for many fundamental questions in biology, they make perfect study systems. Social insects are almost ubiquitous, and wherever they occur, they occur in large numbers. Consequently, they play an enormous role in most terrestrial ecosystems. A thorough insight into ecological processes therefore requires a deep understanding of social insects. The life history traits of social insects are the basis for their ecological success: social insects live in societies which are characterized by a division of labour between reproductives (kings and queens), which produce young, and non-reproductives (workers and soldiers), which perform the daily tasks in the nest. How such a deep co-operation among egoistic entities evolved has long been a major puzzle in biology, and much research therefore focuses on how colony life is established and maintained. Researchers working on social insects are drawn together in the International Union for the Study of Social Insects (IUSSI). It was founded by a group of entomologists during the International Congress of Entomology in Amsterdam in 1951 and today consists of around 15 regional or national sections worldwide. It publishes an internationally renowned quarterly journal, Insectes Sociaux, and international conferences are held every four years. The last International meeting was held in August 2010 in Copenhagen, Denmark. This recent meeting was attended by nearly 700 scientists interested in social insects and related topics. In addition, the individual sections have regional meetings. The last European meeting was held in the Ardennes in Belgium in 2008. The next European meeting will be held in Tuscany in Italy in 2012.   The German-Speaking section of IUSSI is currently one of the largest regional sections. In fall 2007 it changed its name to "Central European Section" and thus opened itself for potential members from other European countries. For information on membership please contact Heike Feldhaar. The managing board of the Central European section consists of Judith Korb, Universität Osnabrück, Germany (president) Heike Feldhaar, Universität Osnabrück, Germany (secretary)  Susanne Foitzik, LMU München, Germany Karl Crailsheim, Universität Graz, Austria  Wolfgang Kirchner, Ruhr-Universität Bochum, Germany  Robin Moritz, Universität Halle, Germany Marko Balint, Babes-Bolyai University Cluj-Napoca, Romania  Jürgen Heinze, Universität Regensburg, Germany         </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Arbeitsgebiete/index_en.html</field>
<field name="title">Prof. Dr. Bernd Kramer</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Arbeitsgebiete/index_en.html</field>
<field name="content">Prof. Dr. Bernd Kramer Prof. Dr. Bernd Kramer Research Topics Institut/Abteilung: Zoologie Prof. Dr. Bernd Kramer - Systematics and taxonomy of African mormyrids (Mormyridae): morphology, electric organ discharges, genetics, behaviour - Electrocommunication among mormyrids (intra- and interspecifically) - Acoustic signalling behaviour in mormyrid fishes For further particulars see 10th Research report, as well as previous Research reports.  </field>
<field name="important">Prof. Dr. Bernd Kramer Prof. Dr. Bernd Kramer Research Topics Institut/Abteilung: Zoologie Prof. Dr. Bernd Kramer - Systematics and taxonomy of African mormyrids (Mormyridae): morphology, electric organ discharges, genetics, behaviour - Electrocommunication among mormyrids (intra- and interspecifically) - Acoustic signalling behaviour in mormyrid fishes For further particulars see 10th Research report, as well as previous Research reports.  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20002.html</field>
<field name="title">img 002</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20002.html</field>
<field name="content">img 002 img 002   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 002 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 002 img 002   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 002 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20003.html</field>
<field name="title">img 003</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20003.html</field>
<field name="content">img 003 img 003   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 003 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 003 img 003   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 003 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20004.html</field>
<field name="title">img 004</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20004.html</field>
<field name="content">img 004 img 004   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 004 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 004 img 004   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 004 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20005.html</field>
<field name="title">img 005</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20005.html</field>
<field name="content">img 005 img 005   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 005 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 005 img 005   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 005 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20008.html</field>
<field name="title">img 008</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20008.html</field>
<field name="content">img 008 img 008   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 008 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 008 img 008   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 008 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20009.html</field>
<field name="title">img 009</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20009.html</field>
<field name="content">img 009 img 009   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 009 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 009 img 009   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 009 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20010.html</field>
<field name="title">img 010</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20010.html</field>
<field name="content">img 010 img 010   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 010 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 010 img 010   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 010 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20013.html</field>
<field name="title">img 013</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20013.html</field>
<field name="content">img 013 img 013   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 013 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 013 img 013   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 013 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20014.html</field>
<field name="title">img 014</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20014.html</field>
<field name="content">img 014 img 014   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 014 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 014 img 014   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 014 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20015.html</field>
<field name="title">img 015</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20015.html</field>
<field name="content">img 015 img 015   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 015 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 015 img 015   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 015 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20016.html</field>
<field name="title">img 016</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20016.html</field>
<field name="content">img 016 img 016   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 016 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 016 img 016   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 016 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20018.html</field>
<field name="title">img 018</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20018.html</field>
<field name="content">img 018 img 018   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 018 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 018 img 018   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 018 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20019.html</field>
<field name="title">img 019</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20019.html</field>
<field name="content">img 019 img 019   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 019 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 019 img 019   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 019 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20020.html</field>
<field name="title">img 020</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20020.html</field>
<field name="content">img 020 img 020   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 020 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 020 img 020   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 020 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20021.html</field>
<field name="title">img 021</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20021.html</field>
<field name="content">img 021 img 021   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 021 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 021 img 021   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 021 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20024.html</field>
<field name="title">img 024</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20024.html</field>
<field name="content">img 024 img 024   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 024 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 024 img 024   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 024 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20025.html</field>
<field name="title">img 025</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20025.html</field>
<field name="content">img 025 img 025   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 025 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 025 img 025   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 025 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20026.html</field>
<field name="title">img 026</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20026.html</field>
<field name="content">img 026 img 026   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 026 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 026 img 026   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 026 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20029.html</field>
<field name="title">img 029</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20029.html</field>
<field name="content">img 029 img 029   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 029 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 029 img 029   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 029 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20030.html</field>
<field name="title">img 030</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20030.html</field>
<field name="content">img 030 img 030   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 030 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 030 img 030   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 030 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20031.html</field>
<field name="title">img 031</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20031.html</field>
<field name="content">img 031 img 031   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 031 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 031 img 031   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 031 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20032.html</field>
<field name="title">img 032</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20032.html</field>
<field name="content">img 032 img 032   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 032 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 032 img 032   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 032 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20034.html</field>
<field name="title">img 034</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20034.html</field>
<field name="content">img 034 img 034   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 034 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 034 img 034   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 034 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20035.html</field>
<field name="title">img 035</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20035.html</field>
<field name="content">img 035 img 035   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 035 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 035 img 035   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 035 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20036.html</field>
<field name="title">img 036</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20036.html</field>
<field name="content">img 036 img 036   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 036 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 036 img 036   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 036 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20037.html</field>
<field name="title">img 037</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20037.html</field>
<field name="content">img 037 img 037   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 037 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 037 img 037   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 037 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20040.html</field>
<field name="title">img 040</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20040.html</field>
<field name="content">img 040 img 040   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 040 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 040 img 040   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 040 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20041.html</field>
<field name="title">img 041</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20041.html</field>
<field name="content">img 041 img 041   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 041 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 041 img 041   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 041 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20042.html</field>
<field name="title">img 042</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20042.html</field>
<field name="content">img 042 img 042   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 042 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 042 img 042   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 042 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20045.html</field>
<field name="title">img 045</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20045.html</field>
<field name="content">img 045 img 045   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 045 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 045 img 045   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 045 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20046.html</field>
<field name="title">img 046</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20046.html</field>
<field name="content">img 046 img 046   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 046 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 046 img 046   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 046 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20047.html</field>
<field name="title">img 047</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20047.html</field>
<field name="content">img 047 img 047   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 047 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 047 img 047   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 047 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20048.html</field>
<field name="title">img 048</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20048.html</field>
<field name="content">img 048 img 048   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 048 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 048 img 048   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 048 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20050.html</field>
<field name="title">img 050</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20050.html</field>
<field name="content">img 050 img 050   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 050 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 050 img 050   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 050 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20051.html</field>
<field name="title">img 051</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20051.html</field>
<field name="content">img 051 img 051   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 051 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 051 img 051   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 051 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20052.html</field>
<field name="title">img 052</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20052.html</field>
<field name="content">img 052 img 052   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 052 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 052 img 052   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 052 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20053.html</field>
<field name="title">img 053</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20053.html</field>
<field name="content">img 053 img 053   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 053 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 053 img 053   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 053 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20056.html</field>
<field name="title">img 056</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20056.html</field>
<field name="content">img 056 img 056   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 056 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 056 img 056   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 056 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20057.html</field>
<field name="title">img 057</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20057.html</field>
<field name="content">img 057 img 057   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 057 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 057 img 057   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 057 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20058.html</field>
<field name="title">img 058</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20058.html</field>
<field name="content">img 058 img 058   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 058 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 058 img 058   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 058 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20061.html</field>
<field name="title">img 061</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20061.html</field>
<field name="content">img 061 img 061   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 061 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 061 img 061   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 061 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20062.html</field>
<field name="title">img 062</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20062.html</field>
<field name="content">img 062 img 062   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 062 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 062 img 062   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 062 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20063.html</field>
<field name="title">img 063</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20063.html</field>
<field name="content">img 063 img 063   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 063 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 063 img 063   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 063 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20064.html</field>
<field name="title">img 064</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20064.html</field>
<field name="content">img 064 img 064   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 064 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 064 img 064   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 064 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20066.html</field>
<field name="title">img 066</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20066.html</field>
<field name="content">img 066 img 066   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 066 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 066 img 066   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 066 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20067.html</field>
<field name="title">img 067</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20067.html</field>
<field name="content">img 067 img 067   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 067 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 067 img 067   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 067 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20068.html</field>
<field name="title">img 068</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20068.html</field>
<field name="content">img 068 img 068   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 068 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 068 img 068   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 068 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20069.html</field>
<field name="title">img 069</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20069.html</field>
<field name="content">img 069 img 069   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 069 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 069 img 069   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 069 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20072.html</field>
<field name="title">img 072</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20072.html</field>
<field name="content">img 072 img 072   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 072 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 072 img 072   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 072 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20073.html</field>
<field name="title">img 073</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20073.html</field>
<field name="content">img 073 img 073   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 073 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 073 img 073   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 073 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20074.html</field>
<field name="title">img 074</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20074.html</field>
<field name="content">img 074 img 074   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 074 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 074 img 074   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 074 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20077.html</field>
<field name="title">img 077</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20077.html</field>
<field name="content">img 077 img 077   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 077 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 077 img 077   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 077 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20078.html</field>
<field name="title">img 078</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20078.html</field>
<field name="content">img 078 img 078   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 078 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 078 img 078   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 078 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20079.html</field>
<field name="title">img 079</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20079.html</field>
<field name="content">img 079 img 079   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 079 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 079 img 079   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 079 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20080.html</field>
<field name="title">img 080</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20080.html</field>
<field name="content">img 080 img 080   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 080 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 080 img 080   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 080 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20082.html</field>
<field name="title">img 082</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20082.html</field>
<field name="content">img 082 img 082   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 082 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 082 img 082   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 082 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20083.html</field>
<field name="title">img 083</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20083.html</field>
<field name="content">img 083 img 083   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 083 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 083 img 083   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 083 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20084.html</field>
<field name="title">img 084</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20084.html</field>
<field name="content">img 084 img 084   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 084 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 084 img 084   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 084 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20085.html</field>
<field name="title">img 085</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20085.html</field>
<field name="content">img 085 img 085   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 085 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 085 img 085   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 085 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20088.html</field>
<field name="title">img 088</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20088.html</field>
<field name="content">img 088 img 088   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 088 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 088 img 088   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 088 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20089.html</field>
<field name="title">img 089</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20089.html</field>
<field name="content">img 089 img 089   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 089 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 089 img 089   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 089 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20090.html</field>
<field name="title">img 090</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20090.html</field>
<field name="content">img 090 img 090   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 090 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 090 img 090   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 090 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20093.html</field>
<field name="title">img 093</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20093.html</field>
<field name="content">img 093 img 093   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 093 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 093 img 093   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 093 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20094.html</field>
<field name="title">img 094</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Fotogalerie/pages/img%20094.html</field>
<field name="content">img 094 img 094   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 094 30.04.2009        </field>
<field name="important">img 094 img 094   Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Organisation &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Info &amp;gt; Abschiedsfeier Bernd Kramer / img 094 30.04.2009        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Methoden/index.html</field>
<field name="title">Prof. Dr. Bernd Kramer</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/Methoden/index.html</field>
<field name="content">Prof. Dr. Bernd Kramer Prof. Dr. Bernd Kramer Methodenspektrum Elektronische Meßverfahren, Computersteuerung, Verhaltensbeobachtung und -analyse, Futterbelohnungsdressuren, Wahlversuche, Erfassung elektrischer Entladungen, Signalverarbeitung und Signalerzeugung (incl. Modifikation natürlicher Signale), Korrelation mit Infrarot-Videoaufnahmen, statistische Analyse, Histologie, Fang tropischer Fische im Freiland, morphometrische und meristische Methoden zur Taxonomie, Erfassung und Analyse von Fischvokalisationen.</field>
<field name="important">Prof. Dr. Bernd Kramer Prof. Dr. Bernd Kramer Methodenspektrum Elektronische Meßverfahren, Computersteuerung, Verhaltensbeobachtung und -analyse, Futterbelohnungsdressuren, Wahlversuche, Erfassung elektrischer Entladungen, Signalverarbeitung und Signalerzeugung (incl. Modifikation natürlicher Signale), Korrelation mit Infrarot-Videoaufnahmen, statistische Analyse, Histologie, Fang tropischer Fische im Freiland, morphometrische und meristische Methoden zur Taxonomie, Erfassung und Analyse von Fischvokalisationen.</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/index_en.html</field>
<field name="title">Prof. Dr. Bernd Kramer</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Kramer/index_en.html</field>
<field name="content">Prof. Dr. Bernd Kramer Prof. Dr. Bernd Kramer Animal Behaviour and Behavioural Physiology Prof. Dr. Bernd Kramer Institut für Zoologie Universitaet Regensburg Universitaetsstr. 31 D-93040 Regensburg Email: bernd.kramer@ur.de Tel.: +49 (0)941 943 2263 Fax.: +49 (0)941 943 3304 Cooperations with: English-Language Seminar WS 2014/2015 (BSc, MSc, PhD) Research Topics Electroreception in Fishes   African snoutfish (Mormyriformes) and South American knifefish (Gymnotiformes) communicate and locate objects and obstacles with their electric system, consisting of a system for sending signals (electric organ discharges) and receiving them (electroreceptor organs). The electric organ discharges are species-specific, under sexual selection and play a role in mate quality assessment. Electric organ discharges are a useful tool in taxonomic-systematic research in these speciose fish groups. Please visit the electronic publication server of the University of Regensburg for more articles to download: http://epub.uni-regensburg.de/view/people/Kramer=3ABernd=3A=3A.html In case this should not work for a specific article, please send an email, and I will send a pdf, or else scan the article.   Reviews: Kramer B (1990)Electrocommunication in teleost fishes: Behavior and experiments. Springer-Verlag, Berlin. pp xii-240 - PDF File Kramer B (1994) Communication behavior and sensory mechanisms in weakly electric fishes. In: Slater PJB, Rosenblatt JS, Snowdon CT, (eds) Advances in the Study of Behavior. Vol 23. Academic Press, San Diego, pp 233-270 Kramer B (1996) Electroreception and communication in fishes. Progress in Zoology, vol. 42. Gustav Fischer Verlag, Stuttgart. pp viii-119 - PDF File Kramer B (1999) Elektrische Kommunikation bei Nilhechten und Messerfischen. In: Gansloßer U (ed) Spitzenleistungen: Die unglaublichen Fähigkeiten der Tiere. Filander Verlag, Fürth, pp 21-48 Kramer B (2002) Kommunikation mit elektrischen Signalen bei Fischen. Praxis der Naturwissenschaften - Biologie in der Schule (PdN-BioS) 51(1):9-15 Kramer, B. (2009a). Electric communication and electrolocation. In M. D. Binder, N. Hirokawa &amp; U. Windhorst (Eds) Encyclopedia of Neuroscience (pp. 1038-1045). Berlin Heidelberg: Springer Verlag. DOI 10.1007/978-3-540-29678-2_2913 Kramer, B. (2009b). Electric fish. In M. D. Binder, N. Hirokawa &amp; U. Windhorst (Eds) Encyclopedia of Neuroscience (pp. 1045-1050). Berlin Heidelberg: Springer Verlag. DOI 10.1007/978-3-540-29678-2_2915 Kramer, B. (2009c). Electric organ discharge. In M. D. Binder, N.Hirokawa &amp; U. Windhorst (Eds) Encyclopedia of Neuroscience (pp. 1050-1056). Berlin Heidelberg: Springer Verlag. 10.1007/978-3-540-29678-2_2917 Wiltschko, W. &amp; Kramer, B. (2009). Magnetic and electric senses. In M.D. Binder, N. Hirokawa &amp; U. Windhorst (Eds) Encyclopedia ofNeuroscience (pp. 2198-2206). Berlin Heidelberg: Springer Verlag. DOI 10.1007/978-3-540-29678-2_3268 For photos of Prof. Bernd Kramer?s Retirement Party click here Feb 2010</field>
<field name="important">Prof. Dr. Bernd Kramer Prof. Dr. Bernd Kramer Animal Behaviour and Behavioural Physiology Prof. Dr. Bernd Kramer Institut für Zoologie Universitaet Regensburg Universitaetsstr. 31 D-93040 Regensburg Email: bernd.kramer@ur.de Tel.: +49 (0)941 943 2263 Fax.: +49 (0)941 943 3304 Cooperations with: English-Language Seminar WS 2014/2015 (BSc, MSc, PhD) Research Topics Electroreception in Fishes   African snoutfish (Mormyriformes) and South American knifefish (Gymnotiformes) communicate and locate objects and obstacles with their electric system, consisting of a system for sending signals (electric organ discharges) and receiving them (electroreceptor organs). The electric organ discharges are species-specific, under sexual selection and play a role in mate quality assessment. Electric organ discharges are a useful tool in taxonomic-systematic research in these speciose fish groups. Please visit the electronic publication server of the University of Regensburg for more articles to download: http://epub.uni-regensburg.de/view/people/Kramer=3ABernd=3A=3A.html In case this should not work for a specific article, please send an email, and I will send a pdf, or else scan the article.   Reviews: Kramer B (1990)Electrocommunication in teleost fishes: Behavior and experiments. Springer-Verlag, Berlin. pp xii-240 - PDF File Kramer B (1994) Communication behavior and sensory mechanisms in weakly electric fishes. In: Slater PJB, Rosenblatt JS, Snowdon CT, (eds) Advances in the Study of Behavior. Vol 23. Academic Press, San Diego, pp 233-270 Kramer B (1996) Electroreception and communication in fishes. Progress in Zoology, vol. 42. Gustav Fischer Verlag, Stuttgart. pp viii-119 - PDF File Kramer B (1999) Elektrische Kommunikation bei Nilhechten und Messerfischen. In: Gansloßer U (ed) Spitzenleistungen: Die unglaublichen Fähigkeiten der Tiere. Filander Verlag, Fürth, pp 21-48 Kramer B (2002) Kommunikation mit elektrischen Signalen bei Fischen. Praxis der Naturwissenschaften - Biologie in der Schule (PdN-BioS) 51(1):9-15 Kramer, B. (2009a). Electric communication and electrolocation. In M. D. Binder, N. Hirokawa &amp; U. Windhorst (Eds) Encyclopedia of Neuroscience (pp. 1038-1045). Berlin Heidelberg: Springer Verlag. DOI 10.1007/978-3-540-29678-2_2913 Kramer, B. (2009b). Electric fish. In M. D. Binder, N. Hirokawa &amp; U. Windhorst (Eds) Encyclopedia of Neuroscience (pp. 1045-1050). Berlin Heidelberg: Springer Verlag. DOI 10.1007/978-3-540-29678-2_2915 Kramer, B. (2009c). Electric organ discharge. In M. D. Binder, N.Hirokawa &amp; U. Windhorst (Eds) Encyclopedia of Neuroscience (pp. 1050-1056). Berlin Heidelberg: Springer Verlag. 10.1007/978-3-540-29678-2_2917 Wiltschko, W. &amp; Kramer, B. (2009). Magnetic and electric senses. In M.D. Binder, N. Hirokawa &amp; U. Windhorst (Eds) Encyclopedia ofNeuroscience (pp. 2198-2206). Berlin Heidelberg: Springer Verlag. DOI 10.1007/978-3-540-29678-2_3268 For photos of Prof. Bernd Kramer?s Retirement Party click here Feb 2010</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Neumann/index.htm</field>
<field name="title">Unbenanntes Dokument</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Neumann/index.htm</field>
<field name="content">Unbenanntes Dokument Unbenanntes Dokument Wir sind umgezogen   http://www.uni-regensburg.de/biologie-vorklinische-medizin/neurobiologie-tierphysiologie/</field>
<field name="important">Unbenanntes Dokument Unbenanntes Dokument Wir sind umgezogen   http://www.uni-regensburg.de/biologie-vorklinische-medizin/neurobiologie-tierphysiologie/</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Schneuwly/Forschung/Entwicklung/index.html</field>
<field name="title">Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Schneuwly/Forschung/Entwicklung/index.html</field>
<field name="content">Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie   Entwicklung Ein so komplexes Gebilde wie das Gehirn ist nur dann zu verstehen, wenn man weiss, wie es gebaut wird. Dazu untersuchen wir die Grundlagen der genetischen Steuerung der Entwicklung des Gehirns. Welche Gene steuern die Entwicklung des Gehirns und wie tun sie es? Damit wir uns nicht in der Komplexität der Verschaltungen verlieren suchen wir uns ein möglichst einfaches Teilsystem heraus: das visuelle System mit seinen hochgeordneten Strukturen. Hier interessiert uns insbesondere die Frage, wie die Photorezeptoren mit dem Gehirn Verbindung aufnehmen, also die Weg- und Zielfindung der Axone. Die Kombination von Molekulargenetik, Genetik, Biochemie, Entwicklungsbiologie und Neurobiologie macht dieses System zu einem faszinierenden Untersuchungsobjekt.    </field>
<field name="important">Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie   Entwicklung Ein so komplexes Gebilde wie das Gehirn ist nur dann zu verstehen, wenn man weiss, wie es gebaut wird. Dazu untersuchen wir die Grundlagen der genetischen Steuerung der Entwicklung des Gehirns. Welche Gene steuern die Entwicklung des Gehirns und wie tun sie es? Damit wir uns nicht in der Komplexität der Verschaltungen verlieren suchen wir uns ein möglichst einfaches Teilsystem heraus: das visuelle System mit seinen hochgeordneten Strukturen. Hier interessiert uns insbesondere die Frage, wie die Photorezeptoren mit dem Gehirn Verbindung aufnehmen, also die Weg- und Zielfindung der Axone. Die Kombination von Molekulargenetik, Genetik, Biochemie, Entwicklungsbiologie und Neurobiologie macht dieses System zu einem faszinierenden Untersuchungsobjekt.    </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Schneuwly/Forschung/Funktion/index.html</field>
<field name="title">Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Schneuwly/Forschung/Funktion/index.html</field>
<field name="content">Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie   Funktion cicadiane Rhythmik Alois Hofbauer PDF/PDH extraretinale Photorezeptoren Ralf Stanewsky Cryptochrome Per-luc screen neue Rhythmik-gene Alle Untersuchungen nutzen nichts, wenn man sich nicht auch mit der Funktion des Gehirns befasst. Drosophila zeigt komplexe Verhaltensmuster wie Lernen und Gedächtnis, Balz, und circadiane Rhythmik. Die Fliegen sind genau wie wir selbst einer inneren Uhr unterworfen, die uns kontinuierlich an die Tageszeit erinnert, unsere Aktivität steuert (Schlaf-Wachrhythmus) und sich nicht leicht überlisten lässt (z. B. Jetlag bei langen Flügen). Doch wie funktioniert diese Innere Uhr? Auch hier bietet uns Drosophila ein ausgezeichnetes Modell an. Seit über zwanzig Jahren gibt es Drosophila-Mutanten, die eine gestörte Rhythmik zeigen und wen wundert's, es sind die gleichen Gene, die die Uhren der Fliegen und unsere eigenen inneren Uhren steuern. Zwei Arbeitsgruppen befassen sich am Lehrstuhl mit der Frage nach der genetischen Steuerung der inneren Uhr bei Drosophila und mit den Gehirnregionen die daran beteiligt sind.        </field>
<field name="important">Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie   Funktion cicadiane Rhythmik Alois Hofbauer PDF/PDH extraretinale Photorezeptoren Ralf Stanewsky Cryptochrome Per-luc screen neue Rhythmik-gene Alle Untersuchungen nutzen nichts, wenn man sich nicht auch mit der Funktion des Gehirns befasst. Drosophila zeigt komplexe Verhaltensmuster wie Lernen und Gedächtnis, Balz, und circadiane Rhythmik. Die Fliegen sind genau wie wir selbst einer inneren Uhr unterworfen, die uns kontinuierlich an die Tageszeit erinnert, unsere Aktivität steuert (Schlaf-Wachrhythmus) und sich nicht leicht überlisten lässt (z. B. Jetlag bei langen Flügen). Doch wie funktioniert diese Innere Uhr? Auch hier bietet uns Drosophila ein ausgezeichnetes Modell an. Seit über zwanzig Jahren gibt es Drosophila-Mutanten, die eine gestörte Rhythmik zeigen und wen wundert's, es sind die gleichen Gene, die die Uhren der Fliegen und unsere eigenen inneren Uhren steuern. Zwei Arbeitsgruppen befassen sich am Lehrstuhl mit der Frage nach der genetischen Steuerung der inneren Uhr bei Drosophila und mit den Gehirnregionen die daran beteiligt sind.        </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Schneuwly/Forschung/Modell/index.html</field>
<field name="title">Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Schneuwly/Forschung/Modell/index.html</field>
<field name="content">Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie   Modell Drosophila melanogaster ist einer der beliebtesten Modellorganismen für viele Fragestellungen in der Biologie. Mit den vielseitigen Möglichkeiten der Genetik, der Molekulargenetik und der Herstellung transgener Tiere spielt Drosophila eine herausragende Rolle unter den Modellorganismen. Es ist das komplexeste Tier, von dem die komplette genetische Information bekannt ist. Es besitzt ein kleines, aber trotzdem kompliziertes Gehirn, welches vielschichtige und überraschende Fähigkeiten aufweist. Wie können wir das Gehirn verstehen lernen? Die Arbeitsgruppen am Lehrstuhl befassen sich dabei auf drei Ebenen mit dem Gehirn</field>
<field name="important">Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie   Modell Drosophila melanogaster ist einer der beliebtesten Modellorganismen für viele Fragestellungen in der Biologie. Mit den vielseitigen Möglichkeiten der Genetik, der Molekulargenetik und der Herstellung transgener Tiere spielt Drosophila eine herausragende Rolle unter den Modellorganismen. Es ist das komplexeste Tier, von dem die komplette genetische Information bekannt ist. Es besitzt ein kleines, aber trotzdem kompliziertes Gehirn, welches vielschichtige und überraschende Fähigkeiten aufweist. Wie können wir das Gehirn verstehen lernen? Die Arbeitsgruppen am Lehrstuhl befassen sich dabei auf drei Ebenen mit dem Gehirn</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Schneuwly/Forschung/Struktur/index.html</field>
<field name="title">Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Schneuwly/Forschung/Struktur/index.html</field>
<field name="content">Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie   Struktur swiss-cheese Das fertige Gehirn gleicht einem Wunder. Doch die zunehmende Überalterung der Gesellschaft zeigt, dass auch diesem Wunder Grenzen gesetzt sind. Das Gehirn ist nicht immer stabil und kann mit zunehmendem Alter abgebaut werden. Man spricht von neurodegenerativen Erkrankungen, in aller Munde ist z.B. die Alzheimersche Erkrankung. Doch was sind die Ursachen dieser Instabilität des Gehirns? Viele dieser Erkrankungen haben eine genetische Komponente. Wir untersuchen deshalb in diesem Projekt in Drosophila nach Mutanten, bei denen ebenfalls aufgrund von genetischer Störungen das Gehirn mit zunehmendem Alter abgebaut wird, und davon gibt es eine ganze Menge. Die molekulare und genetische Analyse dieser Mutanten und der betroffenen Gene gibt uns Hinweise auf die Mechanismen, die zur Stabilität des Gehirns beitragen.  </field>
<field name="important">Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie   Struktur swiss-cheese Das fertige Gehirn gleicht einem Wunder. Doch die zunehmende Überalterung der Gesellschaft zeigt, dass auch diesem Wunder Grenzen gesetzt sind. Das Gehirn ist nicht immer stabil und kann mit zunehmendem Alter abgebaut werden. Man spricht von neurodegenerativen Erkrankungen, in aller Munde ist z.B. die Alzheimersche Erkrankung. Doch was sind die Ursachen dieser Instabilität des Gehirns? Viele dieser Erkrankungen haben eine genetische Komponente. Wir untersuchen deshalb in diesem Projekt in Drosophila nach Mutanten, bei denen ebenfalls aufgrund von genetischer Störungen das Gehirn mit zunehmendem Alter abgebaut wird, und davon gibt es eine ganze Menge. Die molekulare und genetische Analyse dieser Mutanten und der betroffenen Gene gibt uns Hinweise auf die Mechanismen, die zur Stabilität des Gehirns beitragen.  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Schneuwly/Links/index.html</field>
<field name="title">Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Zoologie/Schneuwly/Links/index.html</field>
<field name="content">Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie Fliegen &amp; Forschen biomedizinische Artikelsuche PubMed Uni Regensburg, Zugang zu vielen Zeitschriften - online Uni Regensburg Journals Suchanfragen zu publizierten Sequenzen Blast at NCBI kleiner Exkurs zur Entwicklung The Interactive Fly Flybase - Gene, Sequenzen, Fliegenstämme Flybase online Atlas und Datenbank zum Drosophila Gehirn Flybrain Alles zum Thema Fliegengenom uvm. Fruitfly, GadFly</field>
<field name="important">Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie Prof. Dr. Stephan Schneuwly - Entwicklungsbiologie Fliegen &amp; Forschen biomedizinische Artikelsuche PubMed Uni Regensburg, Zugang zu vielen Zeitschriften - online Uni Regensburg Journals Suchanfragen zu publizierten Sequenzen Blast at NCBI kleiner Exkurs zur Entwicklung The Interactive Fly Flybase - Gene, Sequenzen, Fliegenstämme Flybase online Atlas und Datenbank zum Drosophila Gehirn Flybrain Alles zum Thema Fliegengenom uvm. Fruitfly, GadFly</field>
</doc>

</add>