<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<add>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Minuth/english/contact.html</field>
<field name="title">Contact</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Minuth/english/contact.html</field>
<field name="content">Contact Contact back to homepage Prof. Dr. Will W. Minuth University of Regensburg Department of Molecular and Cellular Anatomy Universitätsstr. 31 D-93040 Regensburg Germany Tel. ++49 941 943-2876 Fax. ++49 941 943-2868 E-Mail:  Will.Minuth@vkl.uni-regensburg.de</field>
<field name="important">Contact Contact back to homepage Prof. Dr. Will W. Minuth University of Regensburg Department of Molecular and Cellular Anatomy Universitätsstr. 31 D-93040 Regensburg Germany Tel. ++49 941 943-2876 Fax. ++49 941 943-2868 E-Mail:  Will.Minuth@vkl.uni-regensburg.de</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Minuth/english/proceedings.html</field>
<field name="title">Proceedings in perfusion culture</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Minuth/english/proceedings.html</field>
<field name="content">Proceedings in perfusion culture Proceedings in perfusion culture back to homepage Tissue engineering group Prof. Dr. W. W. Minuth Proceedings are based on Minusheet® technology including perfusion culture invented by Will W. Minuth Here a list of more than 200 related publications is given: References Publication Basic tissue Organ/Site Application Download PDF 253 Research paper ?lker HE, ?lker M, Botsali MS, D?ndar A, Acar H (2013). Cytoxicity evaluation of dentin contacting materials with dentin barrier test device using erbium-doped yttrium, aluminium, and garnet laser treated dentin. Human and Experimental Toxicology x:xx-xx. Connective tissue Tooth Cytotoxicity testing   252 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L (2013). Initial steps to stabilize the microenvironment for implantation of stem/progenitor cells in diseased renal parenchyma. Transplantation Technology 1:2. Epithelium Kidney Regeneration PDF 251 Research paper ?lker HE, ?lker M, G?m?s H?, Yalcin M, Seng?n A /2013). Cytotoxicity testing of temporary luting cements with two- and three-dimensional cultures of bovine dental pulp-derived cells. BioMed Research International xx: Article ID 910459. Connective tissue Tooth Repair PDF 250 Research paper Schiessl IM, Rosenauer A, Kattler V, Minuth WW, Oppermann M, Castrop H (2013). Dietary salt intake modulates differential splicing of the Na/K/2Cl cotransporter NKCC2. Am J Physiol Renal Physiol 305:F1139-48. Epithelium Kidney Adaption of epithelia PDF 249 Research paper Campos DM, Soares GA, Anselme K (2013). Role of culture conditions on in vitro transformation and cellular colonization of biomimetic HA-Col scaffolds. Biomatter 3:e24922. Connective tissue Bone Tissue engineering PDF 248 Research paper daSilva JMF, Rodrigues JR, Camargo CHR, Fernandes Jr VVB, Hiller KA, Schweikl H, Schmalz G (2013). Effectivness and biological compatibility of different generations of dentin adhesives. Clin Oral Invest xx:xx-xx. DOI 10.1007/s00784-013-1000-9. Connective tissue Tooth Dentin adhesives PDF 247 Research paper Miura Y, Huettmann G, Orzekowsky-Schroeder R, Steven P, Szaszak M, Koop N, Brinkmann R (2013). Two-photon microscopy and fluorescence lifetime imaging of retinal pigment epithelial cells under oxidative stress. Invest Ophthalmology &amp; Vis Science. 54:3366-3377. Neural tissue Eye Regenerative Medicine PDF 246 Research paper Kim HS, Chang SW, Baek SH, Han SH, Lee Y, Zhu Q, Kum KY (2013). Antimicrobial effect of alexidine and chlorhexidine against Enterococcus faecalis infection. Int J Oral Science 5:26-31 Connective tissue Tooth Adhesion of microorganisms PDF 245 Research paper Klettner A, Westhues D, Lassen J, Bartsch S, Roider J (2013). Regulation of constitutive vascular endothelial growth factor secretion in retinal pigment epithelium/choroid organ cultures: p38, nuclear factor kappa B, and the vascular endothelial growth factor receptor-2/phosphatidylinositol 3 kinase pathway. Molecular Vision 19:281-291. Epithelium Eye Regenerative Medicine PDF 244 Research paper Wei F, Song T, Ding G, Xu J, Liu D, Fan Z, Zhang C, Shi S, Wang S (2013). Functional tooth restoration by allogeneic mesenchymal stem cell-based bio-root regeneration in swine. Stem Cells and Development 22:1752-62. Connective tissue Tooth Regenerative Medicine PDF 243 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Gruber M (2013). Search for chemically defined culture medium to assist initial regeneration of diseased renal parenchyma after stem/progenitor cell implantation. Int J Stem Cell Research and Transplantation 1:202. Epithelium Kidney Tissue engineering PDF 242 Research paper Glaum R and Wiedmann-Al-Ahmad M (2013). Cocultivation of human oral keratinocytes and human osteoblast-like cells. Methods Mol Biol 946:423-9. Epithelium and connective tissue Craniomaxillofacial region Tissue engineering   241 Research paper Schneider T, Kohl B, Sauter T, Kratz K, Landlein A, Ertel W, Schulze-Tanzil G (2012). Influence of fiber orientation in electrospaun polymer scaffolds on viability, dahesion and differentation of articular chondrocytes. Clinical Hemorheology and Microcirculation 52:325-336. Connective tissue Cartilage Tissue engineering PDF 240 Research paper Korsuwannawong S, Srichan R, Vajrabhaya L (2012). Cytotoxicity evaluation of self-etching dentine bonding agents in a cell culture perfusion condition. Eur J Dentistry 6:408-414. Connective tissue Teeth Cytotoxicity PDF 239 Review Minuth WW, Denk L (2012). Supportive development of functional tissues for biomedical research by the MINUSHEET® perfusion system. Clinical and Translational Medicine 1:22. Basic tissues Different organs Wide spectrum of applications PDF 238 Research paper Astasov-Frauenhoffer M, Braissant O, Hauser-Gerspach I, Daniels AU, Weiger R, Waltimo T (2012). Isothermal microcalorimetry provides new insight into biofilm variability and dynamics. FEMS Microbiol Let 337(1):31-37. Bacteria Titanium Biomaterials PDF 237 Research paper Kim M, Kim K, Lee Y, Kim K (2012). Cytotoxicity test of dentin bonding agents using millipore filters as dentin susstitutes in a dentin barrier test. Clin Oral Invest 17:1489-96. Connective tissue Dentin Cytotoxicity testing PDF 236 Research paper Volkmer E, Otto S, Polzer H, Saller M, Trappendreher D, Zagar D, Hamisch S, Ziegler G, Wilhelmi A, Schieker M (2012). Overcoming hypoxia in 3D culture systems for tissue engineering of bone in vitro using an automated, oxygen-triggered feedback loop. J Mater Sci. 23(11):2793-2801. Connective tissue Bone Regeneration PDF 235 Research paper Mateescu M, Rguitti E, Ponche A, Descamps M, Anselme K (2012). Biomimetic evaluation of ? tricalcium phosphate prepared by hot isostatic pressing. Biomatter 2, 3: 1-11. Connective tissue Bone Biomaterial Research PDF 234 Research paper Treumer F, Klettner A, Baltz J, Hassain AA, Brinkmann AA, Roider J, Hillenkamp J (2012). Vectorial release of matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs) from poricine RPE-choroid explants following selective retina therapy (SRT): Towards slowing the macular aging process. Exp Eye Res 97(1):63-72. Epithelial-/Neural tissue Eye Regeneration PDF 233 Research paper R?der C, Sauter C, Becker T, Kratz K, Hiebl B, Jung F, Lendlein A, Zohlnhofer D (2012). Viability, proliferation and adhesion of smooth muscle cells and human umbilical vein endothelial cells on eletrospun polymer scaffolds. Clin Hemorheol Microcirc 50(1): 101-12. Epithelial-/Muscular tissue Vessel Biomaterial research PDF 232 Research paper Rath SN, Strobel LA, Arkudas A, Beier JP, Maier AK, Greil P, Horch R, Kneser U (2012). Osteoinduction and survival of osteoblasts and bone marrow stromal cells in 3D biphasic calcium phosphate scaffolds under static and dynamic culture conditions. J Cellular Molecular Medicine 16(10):2350-2361. Connective tissue Bone Regeneration PDF 231 Research paper Bruggeman LA, Doan RP, Loftis J, Darr A, Calabro A (2012). A cell culture system for the structure and hydrogel properties of basement membranes: application to capillary walls. Cellular and Molecular Bioengineering 5(2):194-204. Epithelial tissue Kidney Regeneration PDF 230 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L (2012). Interstitial interfaces show marked differences in regenerating tubules, matured tubules and the renal stem/progenitor cell niche. J Biomedical Materials Research Part A 100(5): 1115-25. Epithelial tissue Kidney Regeneration PDF 229 Research paper Schneider T, Kohl B, Sauter T, Becker T, Kratz K, Schossig M, Hiebl B, Jung F, Lendlein A, Ertel W, Schulze-Tanzil G (2011). Viability, adhesion and differentiated phenotype of articular chondrocytes of degradable polymers and electro-spun structures therof. Macromol Symp 309/310:28-39. Connective tissue Cartilage Regeneration PDF 228 Research paper Klettner AK, Doths J, Roider J (2011). Nicotine reduces VEGF-secretion and phagocytotic activity in porcine RPE. Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol 250(1): 33-8. Neural tissue Eye Regeneration PDF 227 Research paper Glashauser A, Denk L, Minuth WW (2011). Polyester fleeces used as an artificial interstitium influence the spatial growth of regenerating tubules. J Tissue Sci Eng 2: 105. DOI 10.4172/2157-7552. Epithelial tissue Kidney Regeneration PDF 226 Research paper Kalamarz-Kubiak H, Gozdowska M, Nietrzeba M, Kulcykska E (2011). A novel approach to AVT and IT studies in fish brain and pituitary: in vitro perfusion technique. Journal of Neuroscience Methods 199(1):56-61 Neural tissue Brain Endocrinology PDF 225 Research paper Farack J, Wolf-Brandstetter C, Glorius S, Nies B, Standke G, Quadbeck P, Worch H, Schwarnweber D (2011). The effect of perfusion culture on proliferation and differentiation of human mesenchymal cells on biocorrodible bone replacement material. Materials Science and Engineering B 176:1776-1772. Connective tissues Bone Tissue engineering PDF 224 Book Minuth WW and Denk L (2011). Advanced Culture Experiments with Adherent Cells. From single cells to specialized tissues in perfusion culture. Open access publishing, University of Regensburg, ISBN Nr. 978-3-88246-330-9, 414 pages. urn:nbn:de:bvb:355-epub-214847. Specialized tissues Various organs Tissue culture technology PDF 223 Research paper Seng?n A, Yalcin M, ?lker HE, Ozt?rk B, Hakki SS (2011). Cytotoxicity evaluation of dentin bonding agents by dentin barrier test on 3-dimensional pulp cells. Oral Surg Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod 112:e83-8. Connective tissue Tooth Cytotoxicity PDF 222 Research paper Yue S, Lee PD, Poologasundarampillai G (2011). Evaluation of 3D bioactive glass scaffolds dissolution in a perfusion flow system with X-ray microtomography. Acta Biomaterialia 7(6):2637-43 Connective Tissue Bone Regenerative medicine PDF 221 Research paper Dankers PY, Boomker JM, Huizinga - van der Vlag A, Wisse E, Smedts FM, Harmsen MC, Bosman AW, Meijer W, van Luyn MJ (2011). Bioengineering of living renal membranes consisting of hierarchical, bioactive supramolecular meshes and huma tubular cells. Biomaterials 32(3):723-33. Epithelial tissue Kidney Regenerative medicine PDF 220 Research paper Hamilton RD, Leach L (2011). Isolation and properties of an in vitro human outer blood-retinal barrier model. Methods Mol Biol 686:401-416. Epithelial tissue Eye Regenerative medicine PDF 219 Research paper Quadbeck P, Hauser R, K?mmel K, Standke G, Stephani G, Nies B, R??ler S, Wegener B (2010). Iron based cellular metals for degradable synthetic bone replacement. PM2010 World Congress - PM Biomaterials p 1-8. Connective tissue Bone Biomaterials PDF 218 Research paper Dankers PY, Boomker JM, Huizinga-van der Vlag A, Smedts FM, Harmsen MC, van Luyn MJ (2010). The use of fibrous, supramolecular membranes and human tubular cells for renal epithelial tissue engineering: towards a suitable membrane for a bioartificial kidney. Macromol Biosci 10(11):1345-54. Epithelial tissue Kidney Regenerative medicine PDF 217 Book chapter Minuth WW, Denk L, Roessger A (2010). Regenerating tubules for kidney repair. Stem Cell Engineering - Principals and Applications, Eds. Artmann, Minger, Hescheler, Springer Verlag, pp 321-344. Epithelial tissue Kidney Regenerative medicine PDF 216 Review article Yeatts A, Fisher JP (2010). Bone tissue engineering bioreactors: Dynamic culture and the influence of shear stress. Bone 48(2):171-81. Connective tissue Bone Regenerative medicine PDF 215 Research paper Bernhardt A, Lode A, Peters F, Gelinsky M (2010). Optimization of culture conditions for osteogenically-induced mesenchymal stem cells in ?-tricalcium phosphate ceramics with large interconnected channels. J Tissue Eng Regen Med 5(6):444-53. Connective tissue Bone Regenerative medicine PDF 214 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Glashauser A (2010). Promoting and harmful effects of steroid hormones on renal stem/progenitor cell development. J Tissue Science Engineering 1:101 Epithelial tissue Kidney Regenerative medicine PDF 213 Research paper da Silva HM, Mateescu M, Damia C, Champion E, Soares G, Anselme K (2010). Importance of dynamic culture for evaluating osteoblast activity on dense silicon-substituted hydroxyapatite. Colloids Surf B Biointerfaces 80(2):138-44. Connective tissue Bone Regenerative medicine PDF 212 Research paper Steinhagen J, Niggemeyer O, Fuerst M, Rüther W, Schünke M, Kurz B (2010). Perfusion culture system: Synovial fibroblasts modulate articular chondrocyte matrix synthesis in vitro. Tissue Cell 42(3):151-157. Connective tissue Cartilage Regenerative medicine PDF 211 Review article Minuth WW, Denk L, Glashauser A (2010). Towards a guided regeneration of renal tubules at a polyester interstitium. Materials 3:2369-2392. Epithelial tissue Kidney Regenerative medicine PDF 210 Research paper Miess C, Glashauser A, Denk L, de Vries U, Minuth W (2010). The interface between generating renal tubules and a polyester fleece in comparison to the interstitium of the developing kidney. Ann Biomed Eng 38(6):2197-209. Epithelial tissue Kidney Regenerative medicine PDF 209 Research paper Heinemannn C, Heinemann S, Bernhardt A, Lode A, Worch H, Hanke T (2010). In vitro osteoclastogenesis on textile chitosan scaffold. Eur Cell Mater 19:96-106. Connective tissue Bone Regenerative medicine PDF 208 Review article Minuth WW, Denk L, Glashauser A (2010). Cell and drug-delivery therapeutics for renal tissue regeneration. Advanced Drug Delivery Reviews 62(7-8):841-854. Epithelial tissue Kidney Regenerative medicine PDF 207 Leading opinion paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Glashauser A (2010). A modular culture system for the generation of multiple specialized tissues. Biomaterials 11:2945-2954. All tissues Specialized tissue Regenerative medicine PDF 206 Research paper da Silva HM, Mateescu M, Ponche A, Damia C, Champion E, Soares G, Anselme K (2010). Surface transformation of silicon-doped hydroxyapatite immersed in culture medium under dynamic and static conditions. Colloids and Surfaces B: Biointerfaces 75(1):349-55. Connective tissue Bone Biomaterial research PDF 205 Research paper Miura Y, Klettner A, Noelle B, Hasselbach H, Roider J (2010). Change of morphological and functional characteristics of retinal pigment epithelium cells during cultivation of retinal pigment epithelium-choroid perfusion tissue culture. Opthalmic research 43;122-133. Neural tissue Eye Regenerative medicine PDF 204 Research paper Klettner A, Kruse ML, Meyer T, Wesch D, Kabelitz D, Roider J (2009). Different properties of VEGF-antagonists: Bevacizumab but not Ranibizumab accumulates in RPE cells. Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol 247(12): 1601-8. Neural tissue Eye Regenerative medicine PDF 203 Research paper Hagedorn GM, Blank A, Weiland B, Spassov A, Lauer G (2009). Perfusion culture promotes differentiation of oral keratinocytes in vitro. J Physiol Pharmacol 60(8):25-9. Epithelial tissue Oral mucosa Regenerative medicine PDF 202 Research paper Klettner A, Roider J (2009). Constitutive and oxidative-stress-induced expression of VEGF in the RPE are differently regulated by different Mitogen-activated protein kinases. Graefs Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol 247:1487-1492. Neural tissue Eye Regenerative medicine PDF 201 Research paper Xia L, Ng S, Han R, Tuo X, Xiao G, Leo HL, Cheng T, Yu H (2009). Laminar-flow immediate-overlay hapatocyte sandwich perfusion system for drug hepatotoxicity testing. Biomaterials 30(30):5927-36. Epithelium Liver Toxicity testing PDF 200 Research paper Glaum R, Wiedmann - Al-Ahmad M, Huebner U, Schmelzeisen R (2009). Cocultivation of human keratinocytes and human osteoblast-like cells on laminin-coated polycarbonate membranes and equine collagen membranes under different culture conditions. J Biomed Mater Res A 93A(2):704-715. Epithelium/ Connective tissue Composite graft Biomaterial research PDF 199 Research paper Heinemann C, Heinemann S, Lode A, Bernhardt A, Worch H, Hanke T (2009). In vitro evaluation of textile chitosan scaffolds for tissue engineering using human bone marrow stromal cells. Biomacromolecules 10:1305-1310. Connective tissue Bone Biomaterial research PDF 198 Research paper Ulker HE, Sengun A (2009). Cytotoxicity evaluation of self adhesive composite resin cements by dentin barrier test on 3D pulp test. Eur J Dent 3(2):120-6. Connective tissue Tooth pulp Cytotoxical research PDF 197 Research paper Roessger A, Denk L, Minuth WW (2009). Potential of stem/progenitor cell cultures within polyester fleeces to regenerate renal tubules. Biomaterials 30(22):3723-32. Epithelium Kidney Stem cell research PDF 196 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Roessger A (2009). Gradient perfusion culture - simulating a tissue-specific environment for epithelia in biomedicine. J Epithel Biology &amp; Pharmacology 2:1-13. Epithelium Gradient perfusion culture Biomedicine PDF 195 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Meese C, Rachel R, Roessger A (2009). Ultrastructural insights in the interface between generated tubules and a polyester interstitium. Langmuir 25(8):4621-4627. Epithelium Kidney Stem cell research PDF 194 Research paper Anders JO, Mollenhauer J, Beberhold A, Kinne RW, Venbrocks RA (2009). Gelatin-based haemostypic Spongostan as a possible three-dimensional scaffold for a chondrocyte matrix? J Bone Joint Surg (Br) 91(B):409-16. Connective tissue Cartilage Tissue engineering PDF 193 Book Lauer G (2009). Fundamentals of Tissue engineering and Regenerative Medicine, 27.6 Optimizingg the Mucosa Graft: Developing Gingival Keratinocyte - Fibroblast Contact. pp 375 ed. by Ulrich Meyer et al. Springer Verlag Epithelium Mucosa Graft Tissue engineering PDF 192 Research paper Vajrabhaya L, Koruwannawong S, Bosl C, Schmalz G (2009). The cytotoxicity of self-etching primer bonding agents in vitro. Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Path Oral Radiol Endod 107:e86-e90. Connective tissue Tooth pulp Cytotoxical research PDF 191 Research paper Masungi C, Mensch J, Willems B, Van Dijck A, Borremans C, Noppe M, Brewster ME, Augustijns P (2009). Usefulness of a novel Caco-2 cell perfusion system II. Characterization of monolayer properties and peptidase activity. Pharmazie 64:36-42. Epithelium Intestine Pharmacology PDF 190 Research paper Hayashi M, Matsuzaki Y, Shimonaka M (2009). Impact of plasminogen on an in vitro wound healing model based on a perfusion cell culture system. Mol Cell Biochem 322(1-2):1-13. Epithelium Endothelial repair Regenerative medicine PDF 189 Research paper Heinemann C, Heinemann S, Bernhardt A, Worch H, Hanke T (2008). Novel textile chitosan scaffolds promote spreading, proliferation and differentiation of osteoblasts. Biomacromolecules 9:2913-2920. Connective tissue Bone Biomaterial research PDF 188 Research paper Dreesmann L, Hajosch R, Ahlers M, Nuernberger JV, Schlosshauer B (2008). Permeability testing of biomaterial membranes. Biomed Mater 3:034119. Connective tissue Regeneration Biomaterial research PDF 187 Book Motz A, Bur M, Schaefer UF, Lehr CM (2008). Instrumented in vitro approaches to assess epithelial permeability of drugs from pharmaceutical formulations. In: Drug Absorption Studies, Springer Verlag, ISBN 978-0-387-74900-6, pp. 430-455. Epithelium Lung Environmental toxicology PDF 186 Research paper Paur HR, Mülhopt S, Weiss C, Diabaté S (2008). In vitro exposure systems and bioassays for the assessment of toxicity of nanoparticles to the human lung. J Verbr. Lebensm. 3:319-329. Epithelium Lung Environmental toxicology PDF 185 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Blattmann A, Castrop H (2008). Collagen type III is an important linking molecule between generated renal tubules and an artificial interstitium. J Clinical Rehabilitative Tissue Engineering Research (CRTER) 12,32:6201-08. Epithelial tissue Kidney Stem cell research PDF 184 Research paper Volkmer E, Drosse I, Otto S, Stanglmeyer A, Stengele M, Kallukalam BC, Mutschler W, Schieker M (2008). Hypoxia in static and dynamic 3D culture systems for tissue engineering of bone. Tissue Engineering A 14,8:1331-40. Connective tissue Bone Regenerative Medicine PDF 183 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L (2008). Aldosterone-dependent generation of tubules derived from renal stem/progenitor cells. Transplantationsmedizin 20:42-47. Epithelial tissue Kidney Stem cell research PDF 182 Research paper Kaempf S, Johnen S, Salz AK, Weinberger A, Walter P, Thumann G (2008). Effects of Bevacizumab (Avastin) on retinal cells in organotypic culture. Invest Ophathalmol Vis Sci 49,7:3164-71. Neural tissue Eye Pharmacology PDF 181 Research paper Minuth WW, Blattmann A, Denk L, Castrop H (2008). Mineralocorticoid receptor, heat shock proteins and immunophilins participate in the transmission of the tubulogenic signal of aldosterone. J Epithelial Biology &amp; Pharmacology 1:24-34. Epithelial tissue Kidney Stem cell research PDF 180 Research paper Klettner AK, Roider J (2008). Comparison of Bevacizumab, Ranibizumab and Pegatanib in vitro: efficiency and possible additional pathways. Invest Opathalmol Vis Sci 49,10:4523-7. Neural tissue Eye Regenerative Medicine PDF 179 Research paper Demirci M, Hiller KA, Bosl C, Galler K, Schmalz G, Schweikl H (2008). The induction of oxidative stress, cytotoxicity, and genotoxicity by dental adhesives. Dental Materials 24:362-371. Connective tissue Dentin Biomaterial testing PDF 178 Research paper Frerich B, Zückmantel K, Winter K, Müller-Dürwald S, Hemprich A (2008). Maturation of capillary-like structures in a tube-like construct in perfusion and rotation culture. Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg 37:459-466. Connective tissue Vessel Regeneration research PDF 177 Research paper Hammer M, Richter S, Kobuch K, Mata N, Schweitzer D (2008). Intrinsic tissue fluorescence in an organotypic perfusion culture of the porcine ocular fundus exposed to blue light and free radicals. Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophtalmol Epub 246,7:979-88. Neural tissue Eye Regenerative Medicine PDF 176 Research paper Blattmann A, Denk L, Strehl R, Castrop H, Minuth WW (2008). The formation of pores in the basal lamina of regenerated renal tubules. Biomaterials 29:2749-2756. Epithelial tissue Kidney Stem cell research PDF 175 Research paper Kobuch K, Hermann WA, Framme C, Sachs HG, Gabel VP, Hillenkamp J (2008). Maintenance of adult porcine retina and retinal pigment epithelium in perfusion culture: Characterisation of an organotypic in vitro model. Exp Eye Res 86:661-668. Neural tissue Eye Regenerative Medicine PDF 174 Research paper Detsch R, Uhl F, Deisinger U, Ziegler G (2008). 3D-Cultivation of bone marrow stromal cells on hydroxyapatite scaffolds fabricated by dispens-plotting and negative mold technique. J Mater Sci: Mater Med 19,4:1491-6. Connective tissue Bone Tissue engineering PDF 173 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Castrop H (2008). Generation of tubular superstructures by piling of renal stem/progenitor cells. Tissue engineering 14,1:3-13. Stem cells Kidney Tissue engineering PDF 172 Research paper Du Y, Han R, Wen F, Ng San San S, Xia L, Wohland T, Leo HL, Yu H (2008). Synthetic sandwich culture of 3D hepatocyte monolayer. Biomaterials 29:290-301. Epithelium Liver Biomaterial research PDF 171 Research paper Bernhardt A, Lode A, Boxberger S, Pompe W, Gelinsky M (2008). Mineralised collagen – an artificial, extracellular bone matrix – improves osteogenic differentiation of bone marrow stromal cells. J Mater Sci-Mater Med: 19,1: 269-275. Connective tissue Bone Biomaterial research PDF 170 Research paper Maier KL, Alessandrini F, Beck-Speier I, Hofer TP et al. (2008). Health effects on ambient particulate matter - biological mechanisms and inflammatory responses to in vitro and in vivo particle exposures. Inhal Toxicol 20(3):319-37. Epithelial tissue Lung Environmental health PDF 169 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Hu K (2007). Kontrolliertes Environment für die Entwicklung von Stammzellen zu renalen Tubuli. Regenerative Medizin 1:22-27. Stem cells Kidney Tissue engineering PDF 168 Research paper Constantinescu R, Constanntinescu AT, Reichmann H, Janetzky B (2007). Neuronal differentiation and long-term culture of the human neuroblastoma line SH--SY5Y. J Neural Transm 72: 17-28. Neural tissue Dopaminergic cells Tissue engineering PDF 167 Research paper Minuth WW, Hu K, Denk L (2007). Kontrolliertes Environment für Stammzellen – Generierung renaler Tubuli in chemisch definiertem Kulturmedium. BIOforum 4:28-29. Epithelia Stem cell research Tissue engineering PDF 166 Research paper Röpke E, Schön I, Vogel J, Jamali J, Bloching M, Berghaus A (2007). Screening von modifizierten Polyethylenoberflächen für das Tissue engineering von Chondrozyten. Laryngo-Rhino-Otol 86:37-43. Connective tissue Biomaterial testing Tissue engineering PDF 165 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Hu K, Castrop H, Gomez-Sanchez C (2007). Tubulogenic effect of aldosterone is attributed to intact binding and intracellular response of the mineralocorticoid receptor. Central Eur J Biol  - CEJB 2(2):307-325. Epithelium Kidney Stem cell research PDF 164 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Hu K (2007). The role of polyester interstitium and aldosterone during structural development of renal tubules in serum-free medium.Biomaterials 28:4418-28. Epithelium Kidney Stem cell research PDF 163 Research paper Zheng W, Jimenez-Linan M, Rubin BS, Halvorson LM (2007). Anterior pituitary gen expression with reproductive aging in the femal rat. Biol Reprod 76:1091-1102. Epithelium Endocrinology anterior pituitary Gen research PDF 162 Research paper Hauser-Gerspach I, Kulik EM, Weiger R, Decker EM, von Ohle C, Meyer J (2007). Adhesion of Streptococcus sanguinis to dental implant and restorative materials in vitro. Dental Materials J 26(3):361-366. Connective tissue Enamel Biomaterial research PDF 161 Research paper Hu K, Denk L, deVries U, Minuth WW (2007). Chemically defined medium environment for the development of renal stem cells into tubules. Biotechnology J 2:992-995. Epithelium Kidney Stem cell research PDF 160 Research paper Seitz S, Ern K, Lamper G, Docheva D, Drosse I, Milz S, Mutschler, W, Schieker M (2007). Influence of in vitro cultivation on the integration of cell-matrix constructs after subcutaneous implantation. Tissue engineering 13,5:1059-1067. Connective tissue Stem cells Tissue engineering PDF 159 Research paper Jian GE, Jingbo L (2007). The stem cell and tissue engineering research in chinese ophthalmology. Front Med China 1(1):6-10. Nervous tissue Eye Stem cell research PDF 158 Research paper Hamilton RD, Foss AJ, Leach L (2007). Establishment of a human in vitro model of the outer blood-retinal barrier. J Anat 211(6):707-16. Nervous tissue Eye Regenerative medicine PDF 157 Research paper Minuth WW, Strehl R (2007). Technical and theoretical considerations about gradient perfusion culture for epithelia used in tissue engineering, biomaterial testing and pharmaceutical research. Biomed Mater 2:R1-R11. Epithelium Barrier Biomaterials/ Pharmacology PDF 156 Research paper Heber S, Denk L, Hu K, Minuth WW (2007). Modulating the development of renal tubules growing in serum-free culture medium at an artificial interstitium. Tissue Eng 13:2. Epithelium Kidney Stem cell research PDF 155 Research paper Schumacher K, Khong YM, Chang S, Ni J, Sun W, Yu H (2007). Perfusion culture improves the maintenance of cultured Liver Tissue slices. Tissue Eng 13:197-205. Epithelium Liver Pharmacology PDF 154 Research paper Yang SE, Cha JH, Kim ES, Kum KY, Lee CY, Jung IY (2006). Effect of smear layer and cholhexidine treatment on the adhesion of Enterococcus faecalis to bovine dentin. J Oral Endodont/JOE 32,7:663-667. Connective tissue Tooth, Dentin Biomaterial research PDF 153 Research paper Shearer H, Ellis MJ, Perera SP, Chaudhuri JB (2006). Effects of common sterilization methods on the structure and properties of poly(d,l lactic-co-glycolic acid) scaffold. Tissue Engineering 12,10:2717-27. Connective tissue Cartilage, Bone Biomaterial research PDF 152 Patent Minuth WW (2006).. Patent Nr. DE 10 2005 002 938: Verfahren zum Versorgen von Zellen oder Geweben.         151 Research paper Ng S, Han R, Chang S, Ni J, Hunziger W, Goryachev B, Ong SH, Yu H (2006). Improved hepatocyte excretory function by immediate presentation of polarity cues. Tissue Eng 12,8:2181-2191. Epithelium Liver Pharmacology PDF 150 Research paper Saikia P, Maisch T, Kobuch K, Jackson TL, Bäumler W, Szeimies RM, Gabel VP, Hillenkamp J (2006). Safety testing of Indocyanine Green in an ex vivo porcine retina model. Investigative Ophalmology &amp; Visual Science 47,11:4998-5003. Nervous tissue Eye Pharmacology PDF 149 Research paper Frerich B, Zückmantel K, Hemprich A (2006). Microvascular engineering in perfusion culture: immunohistochemistry and CLMS findings. Head &amp; Face Medicine 2:26. Microvessels Adipose tissue Vascular supply PDF 148 Research paper Minuth W, Denk L (2006). From the renal stem cell niche to functional parenchyme. 41. Congress of the European Society for surgical research in Rostock, Medimont, International Proceedings, Editor Brigitte Vollmar, ISBN 88-7587-244-9, pp 9-17. Epithelium Kidney Stem cell research PDF 147 Research paper Bitterle E, Karg E, Schroeppel A, Kreyling WG, Tippe A, Ferron GA, Schmid O, Hexder J, Maier KL, Hofer T (2006). Dose-controlled exposure of A549 epithelial cells at the air-liquid interphase to airborne ultrafine carbonaceous particles. Chemospehre 65,10:1784-1790. Epithelium Lung Test of Biomaterials PDF 146 Book Minuth WW, Strehl R (2006). 3D Kulturen - Zellen, Kultursysteme und Environment. Pabst Science Publishers, Lengerich, ISBN 10:3-89967-316-6 und ISBN 13:978-3-89967-316-6, 471 Seiten.     General PDF 145 Research paper Yamagishi K, Enomoto T, Ohmiya Y (2006). Perfusion-culture-based secreted bioluminescence reporter assay in living cells. Analytical Biochemistry 354:15-21. Nervous Tissue Circadian clock gene Reporter assay PDF 144 Patent Minuth WW (2006). Patent Nr. DE 199 52 847: Vorrichtung zum Kultivieren und/oder Differenzieren und/oder Halten von Zellen und/oder Geweben.         143 Research paper Gille J, Meisner U, Ehlers EM, Müller A, Russlies M, Behrens P (2005). Migration pattern, morphology and viability of cells suspended in or sealed with fibrin glue: a histo-morphological study. Tissue and Cell 37:339-348. Connective Tissue Cartilage Regenerative Medicine PDF 142 Research paper Leukers B, Gülkan H, Irsen SH, Milz S, Tille C, Schieker M, Seitz H (2005). Hydroxyapatite scaffold for bone tissue engineering made by 3D printing. J Materilas Scienc: Materials in Medicine 16:1121-1124. Connective Tissue Bone Biomaterial test PDF 141 Research paper Shearer H, Ellis MJ, Perera SP, Chaudhuri JB (2005). Sterilisation of PLGA flat sheet and hallow fiber tissue engineering scaffolds. Eur Cells and Materials 10,2:4. Connective Tissue Bone Biomaterial test PDF 140 Research paper Galler K, Hiller KA, Ettl T, Schmalz G (2005). Selective influence of dentin thickness upon cytotoxicity of dentin contacting materials. J Endod 31,5:396-399. Connective Tissue Dentin Toxicology PDF 139 Book Minuth WW, Strehl R, Schumacher K (2005). Microreactor optimization for functional tissue engineering. In Chapter 2 (pp 19-45) of Bioreactors for Tissue engineering, Principles, Design and Operation ed. by Chaudhuri J and Al-Rubeai M, Springer Biotechnology, ISBN 1-4020-3740-6.       PDF 138 Research paper Tiemann U, Bücher K, Pfarrer Ch, Pöhland R, Becker F, Kanitz W, Schmidt P (2005). Influence of ovarian steroid hormones or platelet-activating factor receptor in endometrial explant perfusion cultures from ovariectomized bovine. Prostaglandins &amp; other Lipid Mediators 76:35-47. Epithelium Femal Reproductive Tract Pharmacology PDF 137 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Heber S (2005). Growth of embryonic renal parenchyme at the interphase of a polyester artificial interstitium. Biomaterials 26:6588-6598. Epithelium and Mesenchyme Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 136 Research paper Leukers B, Gülkan H, Irsen SH, Milz S, Tille C, Seitz H, Schieker M (2005). Biocompatibility of ceramic scaffolds for bone replacemant made by 3D printing. Mat Wiss Werkstofftechnik 36(12):781-787. Connective tissue Biomaterial testing Tissue engineering PDF 135 Research paper Steuer H, Jaworsky A, Elger B, Kaussmann M, Keldenich J, Schneider H, Stoll D, Schlosshauer B (2005). Functional characterization and comparison of the outer blood-retina barrier and the blood-brain barrier. Invest Ophtalmology &amp; Visual Science 46,3:1047-1053. Nervous Tissue Blood brain barrier Pharmacology PDF 134 Book Minuth WW, Strehl R, Schumacher K (2005). Tissue Engineering - Essentials for Daily Laboratory Work. WILEY-VCH Verlag, ISBN 3527311866, 350 pages.       PDF 133 Research paper Dimova S, Vlaeminck V, Brewster ME, Noppe M, Jorissen M, Augustijns P (2005). Stable ciliary activity in human nasal epithelial cells grown in perfusion culture. Int J Pharmaceutics 292:157-168. Epithelium Respiratory Tract Pharmacology PDF 132 Research paper Strehl R, Tallheden T, Sjögren-Jansson E, Minuth WW, Lindahl A (2005). Long-term mainteance of human articular cartilage in culture for biomaterial testing. Biomaterials 26:4540-4549. Connective Tissue Cartilage Test of Biomaterials PDF 131 Research paper Minuth WW, Schumacher K, Strehl R (2005). Renal epithelia in long term gradient culture for biomaterial testing and tissue engineering. Biomed Mater Eng. 15(1-2):51-63. Epithelium Kidney Test of Biomaterials PDF 130 Research paper Bakowsky U, Ehrhardt C, Loehbach C, Li P, Kneuer C, Jahn D, Hoekstra D, Lehr CM (2005). Adhesion molecule-modified cardivasculare prothesis: Characterization of cellular adhesion in a cell culture model and by cellular force spectroscopy. Pp 157-173, Kapitel 11 in Adhesion: Current Research and Applications ed. W. Possart, Wiley-VCH. Epithelium Vascular protheses Tissue engineering PDF 129 Technical note Bruckner H (2004). Tissue engineering: Gewebe aus der Retorte LaborPraxis 4: 62-65. All tissues Missing regeneration Tissue engineering PDF 128 Research paper Sternberg K, Selent C, Hakanßon N, Töllner J, Langer T, Seiter H, Schmiitz KP (2004). Bioartifizielle Materialien in der Urologie. Urologe 10: 1200-1207. Epithelium Urogenital tract Tissue engineering PDF 127 Research paper Rothamel D, Schwarz F, Sculean A, Herten M, Scherbaum W, Becker J (2004). Biocompatibility of various collagen membranes in cultures of human PDL fibroblast and human osteoblast-like-cells. Clin Oral Impl Res 15,4:443-9. Connective tissue Bone Biomaterial research PDF 126 Research paper Steuer H, Jaworski A, Stoll D, Schlosshauer B (2004). In vitro model of the outer blood-retina barrier. Brain Research Protocols 13:26-36. Nervous Tissue Eye Pharmacology PDF 125 Research paper Gelinsky M, König U, Sewing A, Pompe W (2004). Poröse Scaffolds aus mineralisiertem Kollagen - ein biomimetisches Knochenersatzmaterial. Mat.-wiss und Werkstofftech 35,4:229-233. Connective Tissue Bone Tissue engineering PDF 124 Research paper Duda GN, Kliche A, Kleemann R, Hoffmann JE, Sittinger M, Haisch A (2004). Does low-intensity pulsed ultrasound stimulate maturation of tissue-engineered cartilage? J Biomed Mater Res Part B: Appl Biomater 68B:21-28. Connective Tissue Cartilage Tissue engineering PDF 123 Research paper Jennings P, Koppelstaetter, C, Pfaller W, Morin JP, Hartung T, Ryan MP (2004). Assessment of a new cell culture perfusion apparatus for in vitro toxicity testing. Part 2: toxicological evaluation. ALTEX 21,2:61-66. Epithelium Kidney Pharmacology PDF 122 Research paper Koppelstaetter C, Jennings P, Ryan MP, Morin JP, Hartung T, Pfaller W (2004). Assessment of a new new cell culture perfusion apparatus for in vitro chronic toxicity testing. Part 1: technical description. ALTEX 21,2?:51-60. Epithelium Kidney Pharmacology PDF 121 Book Strehl R, Schumacher K, Minuth W (2004). The current state of engineering tissues and organ parts. In Ethical, Legal, and Social Issues in Organ Transplantation, Editors T. Gutmann, AS Daar, RA Sells, W Land, Pabst Publishers, Lengerich, ISBN 3-89967-017-5 (Europe), ISBN 1-59326-063-6 (USA), pp. 405-422.       PDF 120 Research paper Masungi C, Borremans C, Willems B, Mensch J, Dijck AV, Augustijns P, Brewster ME, Noppe M (2004). Usefulness of a novel Caco-2 cell perfusion system. I. in vitro prediction of the absorption potential of passively diffused compounds. J Pharm Sci 93,10:2507-2521. Epithelium Digestive Tract Pharmacology PDF 119 Research paper Minuth WW, Sorokin L, Schumacher K (2004). Generation of renal tubules at the interface of an artificial interstitium. Cell Physiol Biochem 14,4-6:387-394. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 118 Research paper Strehl R, Schumacher K, Minuth WW (2004). Controlled respiratory gas delivery to embryonic renal epithelial explants in perfusion culture. Tissue Engineering 10,7:1196-1202. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 117 Research paper Fiegel HC, Havers J, Kneser U, Smith MK, Moeller T, Kluth D, Mooney DJ, Rogiers X, Kaufmann P (2004). Influence of flow conditions and matrix coatings on growth and differentiation of three-dimensionally cultured rat hepatocytes. Tissue Engineering 10,1-2:165-174. Epithelium Liver Conceptual Tissue Culture PDF 116 Research paper Minuth WW, Strehl R, Schumacher R (2004). Tissue factory - Conceptual design of a modular system for the in-vitro generation of functional tissues. Tissue Engineering 10,1/2:285-294. All Tissues     PDF 115 Research paper Minuth WW, Schumacher K (2004). Tissue Engineering - Schwierigkeiten und Chancen bei der Herstellung künstlicher Gewebe. Journal DGPW 29:20-22. Tissues Regeneration Tissue engineering PDF 114 Interview Minuth WW (2003). Hat die Zukunft schon begonnen? Zellbiologie 1: 16-17. All Tissues Missing regeneration Tissue engineering PDF 113 Research paper Decker EM, Weiger R, von Ohle C, Wiech I, Brecx M (2003). Susceptibility of planktonic versus attached Streptococcus sanguinis cells to chlorhexidine. Clin Oral Invst 7:98-102. Connective Tissue Enamel Biomaterial test PDF 112 Research paper Minuth WW, Schumacher K (2003). From the renal stem cell niche to functional tubule. Med Klin 15,98 Suppl2:31-35. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 111 Research paper Wang Y, Uemura T, Dong J, Kojima H, Tanaka J, Tateishi T (2003). Application of perfusion culture system improves in vitro and in vivo osteogenesis of bone marrow-derived osteoblastic cells in porous ceramic materials. Tissue Engineering 9,6:1205-1214. Connective Tissue Cartilage and Bone Improved Tissue Culture PDF 110 Research paper Bücheler M, Haisch A (2003). Tissue engineering in Otorhinolaryngology. DNA and Cell Biology 22,9:549-564. Connective Tissue Respiratory System Improved Tissue Culture PDF 109 Research paper Schumacher K, Strehl R, Minuth WW (2003). Urea restrains aldosterone-induced development of peanut agglutinin-binding on embryonic collecting duct epithelia. J Am Soc Nephrol 14:2758-2766. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 108 Research paper Uemura T, Dong J, Wang Y, Kojima H, Saito T, Iejima D, Kikuchi M, Tanaka J, Tateishi T (2003). Transplantation of cultured bone cells using combinations of scaffolds and culture techniques. Biomaterials 24:2277-2286. Connective Tissue Cartilage and Bone Improved Tissue Culture PDF 107 Book Minuth WW, Strehl R, Schumacher K (2003). Zukunftstechnologie Tissue engineering - Von der Zellbiologie zum künstlichen Gewebe. WILEY-VCH Verlag, ISBN 3-527-30793-1.       PDF 106 Research paper Stern S, Lindenhayn K, Perka C (2003). Die Knorpeltransplantation mit bioresorbierbaren Polymeren im tierexperimentellen Modell. Kapitel 9, pp 52 - 59. Fortbildung Orthopädie - Traumatologie, Springer Verlag, edited by Jörg Jerosch. Connective tissue Cartilage Tissue engineering PDF 105 Technical note Minuth WW, Schumacher K, Strehl R, de Vries U (2002). Epithelia -Biomateriaux- Genie tissuelaire. BIOforum International Edition francaise 1: 28-30. Epithelium Kidney Tissue engineering PDF 104 Research paper Guarnizo AC, Rodriguez EV, Albaladejo JMO, Carrasquer TC, Manzano JAC, Cacha JPM, Gasso CS (2002). Autoinjerto subcutaneo de cartilago neosintetizado utilizando el polimero ETHISORB en conejos. Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp 53:631-636. Connective tissue Cartilage Biomaterial research PDF 103 Research paper von Woedtke T, Jülich WD, Alhitari N, Hanschke R, Abel PU (2002). Biosensor-controlled perfusion culture to estimate the viability of cells. Medical &amp; Biological Engineering &amp; Computing 40:704-711. Epithelium Biotest Biofilm/ Fouling PDF 102 Research paper Luppens SBI, Reij MW, van der Heijden RWL, Rombouts FM, Abee T (2002). Development of a standard test to assess the resistance of Staphylococcus aureus biofilm cells to desinfectants. Applied Environ Microbiology 68,9:4194-4200. Microorganisms Biotest Biofilm/ Fouling PDF 101 Research paper Camps J, About L, Thonneman B, Mitsiadis TA, Schmaltz G, Franquin JC (2002). Two- versus three-dimensional in vitro differentiation of human pulp cells into odontoblastic cells. Connective Tissue Res 43:396-400. Connective Tissue Dentin Test of Biomaterials PDF 100 Research paper Risbud MV, Sittinger M (2002). Tissue engineering: advances in vitro cartilage generation. Trends in Biotechnology 20,8:351-356. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 99 Research paper Schumacher K, Strehl R, De Vries U, Groene HJ, Minuth WW (2002). SBA-positive fibers between the CD ampulla, mesenchyme and renal capsule. J Am Soc Nephrol 13:2446-2453. Epithelium and Mesenchyme Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 98 Research paper Spiegel D, Schefthaler M, Kobuch K (2002). Outflow facilities through Descemet's membrane in rabbits. Graefe's Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol 240:111-113. Nervous Tissue Eye Improved Tissue Culture PDF 97 Research paper Schumacher K, Castrop H, Strehl R, de Vries U, Minuth WW (2002). Cyclooxygenases in the collecting duct of neonatal rabbit kidney. Cellular Physiol Biochem 12:63-74. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 96 Research paper Woedke T, Lindequist U, Alhitari N, Kusnick C, Jülich W-D, Abel PU (2002). The usefulness of a biosensor controlled perfusion cell culture for the investigation of new drugs demonstrated with the marine fungus Kirschsteiniothelia maritima. Pharmazie 57:270-274. Epithelium General Bioengineering PDF 95 Research paper Framme C, Kobuch K, Eckert E, Monzer J, Roider J (2002). RPE in Perfusion tissue culture and ist response to laser application. Ophthalmologica 216:320-328. Epithelium Eye Regeneration PDF 94 Research paper Haisch A, Kläring S, Gröger A, Gebert C, Sittinger M (2002). A tissue-engineered model for the manufacture of auricular-shaped cartilage implants. Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol 259:316-321. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 93 Research paper Schmalz G, Schuster U, Koch A, Schweikl H (2002). Cytotoxicity of low pH dentin-bonding agents in a dentin barrier test in vitro. J Endodontics 28,3:188-192. Connective Tissue Dentin Test of Biomaterials PDF 92 Research paper Strehl R, Schumacher K, de Vries U, Minuth WW (2002). Proliferating cells versus differentiated cells in tissue engineering. Tissue Eng. 8(1):37-42. All Tissues     PDF 91 Book Minuth WW, Strehl R, Schumacher K (2002). Von der Zellkultur zum Tissue engineering. Pabst Science Publishers ISBN 3-936142-32-7.       PDF 90 Book Minuth WW, Schumacher K, Strehl R, de Vries U (2002). Mikroreaktortechnik für Tissue engineering in Medizintechnik mit biokompatiblen Werkstoffen und Verfahren. E. Wintermantel, Suk-Woo Ha, Springer Verlag, pp 305-319.       PDF 89 Research paper Schumacher K, Strehl R, de Vries U, Minuth WW (2002). Advanced technique for long term culture of epithelia in a continuous luminal - basal medium gradient. Biomaterials 23,3:805-815. Epithelium Kidney Gradient Culture PDF 88 Research paper Tippe A, Heinzmann U, Roth C (2002). Deposition of fine and ultrafine aerosol particles during exposure at the air / cell interface. Aerosol Science 33:2007-218. Epithelial tissue Lung Environmental health PDF 87 Technical note Minuth WW, Schumacher K, Strehl R, de Vries U (2001). Epithelia - Biomaterials - Tissue engineering. BIOforum International 2: 74-76. Epithelium Kidney Tissue engineering PDF 86 Patent Minuth WW (2001). Patent Nr. US 6 187 053: Process for producing a natural implant.         85 Research paper Schmalz G, Schuster U, Thonemann B, Barth M, Esterbauer S (2001). Dentin barrier test with transfected bovine pulp-derived cells. J Endodontics 27,2:96-102. Connective Tissue Dentin Test of Biomaterials PDF 84 Research paper Kremer M, Lang E, Berger A (2001). Organotypical engineering of differentiated composite-skin equivalents of human keratinocytes in a collagen-GAG matrix (INTEGRA Artifial Skin) in a perfusion culture system. Langenbeck?s Arch Sur 386:357-363. Epithelium Skin Bioengineering PDF 83 Research paper Minuth WW, Strehl R, Schumacher K, de Vries U (2001). Long term culture of epithelia in a continuous fluid gradient for biomaterial testing and tissue engineering. J Biomater Sci Polymer Edn 12,3:353-365. Connective Tissue Kidney Gradient Culture PDF 82 Technical note Bonn E (2000). Organe aus dem Reagenzglas. Via medici 2: 48-51. All tissues Missing regeneration Tissue engineering PDF 81 Research paper Fuß M, Ehlers EM, Russlies M, Rohwedel J, Behrens P (2000). Characteristics of human chondrocytes, osteoblasts and fibroblasts seeded onto a type I/III collagen sponge under different culture conditions. Annals anatomy 182:303-310. Connective Tissue Cartilage Tissue engineering PDF 80 Research paper Duda GN, Haisch A, Endres M, Gebert C, Schroeder D, Hoffmann JE, Sittinger M (2000). Mechanical quality of tissue engineered cartilage: Results after 6 and 12 weeks in vivo. J Biomed Mat Res 53,6:673-677. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 79 Research paper Hoener MC (2000). Role played by sodium in activity-dependent secretion of neutrophins ? revisited. Eur J Neuroscience 12:3096-3106. Nervous tissue Brain Pharmacology PDF 78 Research paper Kloth S, Kobuch K, Domokos J, Wanke C, Monzer J (2000). Polar application of test substances in an organotypic environment and under continous medium flow: a new tissue-based test concept for a broad range of applications in pharmacotoxicity. Toxicology in vitro 14:265-274. Vascular System Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 77 Research paper Kloth S, Suter-Crazzolara C (2000). Modulation of renal blood vessel formation by glial cell line derived neurotrophic factor. Microvasular Res 59:190-194. Vascular System Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 76 Research paper Prem C. and  Pelster B (2000). Swimbladder gas gland cells of the European eel cultured in a superfusion system. Methods in Cell Science 22:125-132. Epithelium Barrier Gradient Culture PDF 75 Research paper Minuth WW, Schumacher K, Strehl R, Kloth S (2000). Physiological and cell biological aspects of perfusion culture technique employed to generate differentiated tissues for long term biomaterial testing and tissue engineering. J Biomater Sci Poymer Edn 11,5:495-522. Epithelium Kidney Gradient Culture PDF 74 Research paper Perka C, Schultz O, Sittinger M, Zippel H (2000). Chondrozytentransplantation in PGLA/Polydioxanon-Vliesen. Orthopäde 29:112-119. Connective Tissue Cartilage Tissue Engineering PDF 73 Research paper Kloth S, Kobuch K, Domokos J, Wanke Ch, Minuth WW (1999). Interaktive Tissue Culture Systems: Innovative Tools for Toxicity Testing. BIOforum International 3: 70-72. Epithelium Kidney Toxicity testing PDF 72 Patent Minuth WW (1999). Patent Nr. DE 196 48 876: Verfahren zum Herstellen eines natürlichen Implantates.         71 Research paper Rotter N, Aigner J, Naumann A (1999). Behaviour of tissue-engineered human cartilage after transplantation into nude mice. J Mat Sci: Materials in Medicine 10:689-693. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 70 Research paper Reischl J, Prelle K, Schol H, Neumuller C, Einspanier R, Sinowatz F, Wolf E (1999). Factors affecting proliferation and dedifferentiation of primary oviduct epithelial cells in vitro. Cell Tissue Res 296:371-383. Epithelium Female Reproductive System Improved Tissue Culture PDF 69 Research paper Griesbeck O, Canossa M, Campana G, Gärtner A, Hoener MC, Nawa H, Kolbeck R, Thoenen H (1999). Are there differences between the secretion characteristics of NGF and BDNF? Implications fort he modulatory role of neurotrophins in activity-dependent neuronal plasticity. Microscopy Res Technique 45:262-275. Nervous tissue Transmitter Pharmacology PDF 68 Research paper Schumacher K, Strehl, R, Kloth S, Tauc M, Minuth WW (1999). The influence of culture media on embryonic renal CD cell differentiation. In vitro Cell Dev Biol Animal 35:465-471. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 67 Research paper Minuth WW, Steiner P, Strehl R, Schumacher K, de Vries U, Kloth S (1999). Modulation of cell differentiation in perfusion culture. Exptl. Nephrology 7:394-406. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 66 Research paper Schmalz G, Schuster U, Nuetzel K, Schweikl H (1999). An in vitro pulp chamber with three-dimensional cell cultures. J Endodontics 24-29. Connective Tissue Dentin Test of Biomaterials PDF 65 Research paper Kreklau B, Sittinger M, Mensing MB, Voight C, Berger G, Burmester GR, Rahmanzahdeh R, Gross U (1999). Tissue engineering of biphasic joint cartilage transplants. Biomaterials 20:1743-1749. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 64 Research paper Jülich WD, Hanschke R, Alitari N (1998). Schonende Sterilisation von biologisch aktiven Implantaten. Hyg Med 23,11:465-472.       PDF 63 Research paper Kloth S, Eckert E, Klein S, Monzer J, Wanke C, Minuth WW (1998). Gastric epithelium under organotypic perfusion culture. In vitro Cell Dev Biol Animal 34:515-517. Epithelium Digestive Tract Improved Tissue Culture PDF 62 Research paper Ramsauer M, Kunz J, Krause D, Dermietzel R (1998). Regulation of blood-brain  barrier –specific enzymes expressed by cerebral pericytes (pericytic aminopeptidase N/pAPN) under cell culture conditions. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab 18(11):1270-81. Nervous tissue Blood brain barrier Pharmacology PDF 61 Research paper Kloth S, Gerdes, J, Wanke C, Minuth WW (1998). Basic fibroblast factor is a morphogenic modulator in kidney vessel development. Kidney Int 53:970-978. Vascular Tissue Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 60 Research paper Rotter N, Aigner J, Naumann A, Planck H, Hammer C, Burmester G, Sittinger M (1998). Cartilage reconstruction in head and neck surgery: comparison of resorbable polymer scaffolds for tissue engineering. J Biomed Mat Res 42:347-356. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 59 Research paper Minuth WW, Sittinger M, Kloth S (1998). Tissue engineering - Generation of differentiated artificial tissues for biomedical applications. Cell Tissue Res 291:1-11. Epithelium/ Connective Tissue/ Vascular Tissue     PDF 58 Patent Minuth WW (1998). Patent Japan Nr. 329 434/95: Kammer zur Kultivierung von   Zellen, insbesondere Mikroskopkammer.         57 Technical note Minuth WW, Strehl R, Kloth S (1997). Von der Zellkultur zum Tissue engineering. Bioscope 4/5: 19-24. All tissues Cell/ Tissue simulation Improved culture technique PDF 56 Technical note Roßteuscher J (1997). Neue Zellen fürs Labor. Aviso 2: 36-38. All tissues Cell/ Tissue simulation Tissue engineering PDF 55 Patent Minuth WW (1997). US- Patenterteilung Nr. 5 665 599: Chamber for Cultivating Cells.         54 Research paper Minuth WW, Steiner P, Strehl R, Kloth S, Tauc M (1997). Electrolyte environment modulates differentiation in embryonic renal collecting duct epithelia. Exp Nephrol 5:414-422. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 53 Research paper Schultz O, Keyszer G, Zacher J, Sittinger M, Burmester GR (1997). Development of an in vitro model system for destructive joint diseases. Arthritis and Rheumatism 40:1420-1428. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 52 Research paper Lehmann P, Kloth S, Aigner J, Dammer R, Minuth W (1997). Lebende Langzeitkonservierung von humaner Gingiva in der Perfusionskultur. Mund Kiefer GesichtsChir 1:26-30. Epithelium Gingiva Improved Tissue Culture PDF 51 Research paper Steiner P, Strehl R, Kloth S, Tauc M, Minuth WW (1997). In vitro development and preservation of specific features of collecting duct epithelial cells from embryonic rabbit kidney are regulated by the electrolyte environment. Differentiation 62:193-202. Epithelium Kidney Gradient Culture PDF 50 Research paper Strehl R, Kloth S, Aigner J, Steiner P, Minuth WW (1997). P CD Amp 1, a new antigen at the interface of the embryonic collecting duct epithelium and the nephrogenic mesenchym. Kidney Int 52:1469-1477. Epithelium and Mesenchyme Kidney Gradient Culture PDF 49 Research paper Sittinger M, Schulz O, Keyszer G, Minuth WW, Burmester GR (1997). Artificial connective tissues in perfusion culture. Int J Artificial Org 20:57-62. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 48 Research paper Minuth WW, Aigner J, Kubat B, Kloth S (1997). Improved differentiation of renal tubular epithelium in vitro: Potential for tissue engineering. Exp Nephrol 5:10-17. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 47 Research paper Minuth WW, Aigner J, Kloth S, Steiner P, Tauc M, Jennings ML (1997). Culture of embryonic renal collecting duct epithelia in a gradient container. Pediatr Nephrol 11:140-147. Epithelium Kidney Gradient Culture PDF 46 Research paper Canossa M, Griesbeck O, Berninger B, Campana G, Kolbeck R, Thoenen H (1997). Neurotrophin release by neurotrophins: Implication for activity-dependent neuronal plasticity. Proc. Natl Acad Sci 94:13279-13286. Nervous Tissue Mesencephalon Improved Tissue Culture PDF 45 Minuth WW, Kloth S, Aigner J, Röckl W (1996). Approach to an organo-typical environment for cultured cells and tissues. Biotechniques 20: 498-501. All tissues Missing regeneration Tissue engineering PDF 44 Technical note Minuth WW, Sittinger M, Kloth S (1996). Tissue engineering - Herstellung von künstlichen Geweben für die Biomedizin. Bioscope 4, 5: 36-41. All tissues Cell/ Tissue simulation Tissue engineering PDF 43 Patent Minuth WW (1996). Patent Nr. 195 30 55.6: Verfahren zur Kultivation von Zellen, insbesondere Organzellen des menschlichen und tierischen Körpers.         42 Research paper Blöchl A, Sirrenberg C (1996). Neurothrophins stimulate the release of dopamine from rat mesencephalic neurons via Trk and p75Lntr receptors. J Biological Chemistry 271,35:21100-21107. Nervous Tissue Mesencephalon Improved Tissue Culture PDF 41 Research paper Gueven N., Glatthaar B.,  Manke H.G., Haemmerle H. (1996). Co-cultivation of rat pneumocytes and bovine endothelial cells on a liquid-air interface. Eur Respir J 9:968-975. Epithelium Lung Gradient Culture PDF 40 Research paper Schmalz G, Garhammer P, Schweiki H (1996). A commercially available cell culture device modified for dentin barrier tests. J Endodontics 22,5:249-252. Connective Tissue Dentin Test of Biomaterials PDF 39 Press release XX (1995). Ohren aus der Retorte. Spiegel 17: 234-238. All tissues Cell/ Tissue simulation Tissue engineering PDF 38 Press release Kuhn L (1995). Transplantate - Kultivierte Nase. Wirtschaftswoche 18: 112-115. All tissues Cell/ Tissue simulation Tissue engineering PDF 37 Technical note Minuth WW, Kloth S, Aigner J, Steiner P (1995). MINUSHEET - Perfusionskultur: Simulierung eines gewebetypischen Milieus. Bioscope 3, 4: 20-25. All tissues Cell/ Tissue simulation Improved tissue culture technique PDF 36 Patent Minuth WW (1995). Patent Nr. P 44 43 902: Kammer zur Kultivierung von Zellen, insbesondere Mikroskopkammer.         35 Research paper Sittinger M, Buija J, Rotter N, Reitzel D, Minuth WW, Burmester GR (1996). Tissue engineering and autologous transplant formation. Biomaterials 17:237-242. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 34 Research paper Aigner J, Kloth S, Minuth WW (1995). Transitional differentiation pattern of principal and intercalated cells during renal collecting duct development. Epith Cell Biol 4:121-130. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 33 Research paper Bujia J, Rotter N, Minuth WW, Burmester GR, Hammer C, Sittinger M (1995). Züchtung menschlichen Knorpelgewebes in einer Perfusionskulturkammer. Laryngo Rhino Otol 74:559-563. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 32 Research paper Kloth S, Ebenbeck C, Kubitza M, Schmidbauer A, Weich HA, Minuth WW (1995). Stimulation of renal microvasculature development under organotypical culture conditions. FASEBJ 9:963-967. Vascular System Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 31 Research paper Kloth S, Kubitza M, Röckl W, Schmidbauer A, Gerdes J, Moll R, Minuth WW (1995). Development of renal podocytes cultured under medium perifusion. Lab Invest 73:294-301. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 30 Research paper Bujia J (1995). Die Züchtung von autologem Knorpelgewebe für die rekonstruktive chirurgie: Möglichkeiten und Grenzen. Laryngo Rhino Otol 74:205-210. Connective Tissue Cartilage Improved Tissue Culture PDF 29 Research paper Sittinger M (1995). Tissue Engineering: Künstlicher Gewebeersatz aus vitalen Komponenten. Laryngo Rhino Otol 74:695-699. Connective Tissue Cartilage Improved Tissue Culture PDF 28 Research paper Bujia J, Sittinger M, Minuth WW, Hammer C, Burmester G, Kastenbauer E (1995). Engineering of cartilage tissue using bioresorbable polymer fleeces and perfusion culture. Acta Otolaryngol 115:307-310. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 27 Book Minuth WW, Aigner J, Kubat B, Kloth S, Röckl W, Kubitza M (1995). In vitro Alternativen zum Tierversuch - Möglichkeiten und Probleme, Pabst Verlag, pp 76-87.       PDF 26 Technical note Minuth WW (1994). Kultivierte Zellen - Eine neue Technik zur Simulierung eines organspezifischen Milieus. Blick in die Wissenschaft 5:30-33. All tissues Cell/ Tissue simulation Tissue engineering PDF 25 Technical note Minuth WW (1994).  Perfusionszellkultur - eine neue Methode für organspezifische, pathologische und toxikologische Fragestellungen. MTA 9: 10-13. All tissues Cell/ Tissue simulation Improved tissue culture technique PDF 24 Research paper Bujia J, Sittinger M, Hammer C, Burmester G (1994). Züchtung menschlichen Knorpelgewebes mit Hilfe einer Perfusionskammer. Laryngo Rhino Otol 73:577-580. Connective Tissue Cartilage Improved Tissue Culture PDF 23 Patent Minuth WW (1994). US - Patent 5, 316, 945: Cell carrier arrangement.         22 Patent Minuth WW (1994). Patent Nr. P 42 00 446: Zellträgeranordnung.         21 Research paper Aigner J, Kloth S, Dermietzel R, Minuth WW (1994). Maturation of renal collecting duct cells in vivo and under perfusion culture. Epithelial Cell Biol 3:70-78. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 20 Book Minuth WW (1994). MINUSHEET - Mehr Effizienz beiZellkulturen. Fremdstoffmetabolismus und Klinische Pharmakologie - Eds. Dengler und Mutschler, Gustav Fischer Verlag, pp. 197-205.       PDF 19   Minuth WW, Kloth S, Aigner J, Sittinger M, Röckl W (1994). Organ-spezifisches Environment für kultivierte Zellen und Gewebe. BIOFORUM 17:412-416.       PDF 18 Research paper Sittinger M, Buija J, Minuth WW, Hammer C, Burmester GR (1994). Engineering of cartilage tissue using bioresorbable polymer carriers in perfusion culture. Biomaterials 15:451-456. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 17 Research paper Kloth S, Schmidbauer A, Kubitza M, Minuth WW (1994). Developing renal microvasculature can be maintained under perfusion culture conditions. Eur J Cell Biol 63:84-95. Vascular System Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 16 Research paper Minuth WW, Majer V, Kloth S, Dermietzel R (1994). Growth of MDCK cells on non-transparent supports. In vitro Cell Dev Biol 30A:12-14. Epithelium Kidney Test of Biomaterials PDF 15   Minuth WW (1993). Gebrauchsmuster G 89 08 58.3: Träger für die Zellkultivation.         14 Patent Minuth WW (1993). US-Patent 5,190,878: Apparatus for cultivating cells.         13 Book Minuth WW (1993). Die Kultur von Epithelzellen unter organtypischen Bedingungen. Alternativen zu Tierversuchen in Ausbildung, Qualitätskontrolle und Herz- Kreislaufforschung. Springer Verlag Wien - New York: pp 238-245.       PDF 12 Research paper Minuth WW, Fietzek W, Kloth S, Aigner J, Röckl W, Kubitza M, Dermietzel R (1993). Aldosterone modulates the development of PNA binding cell isoforms within renal collecting duct epithelium kept in perfusion culture. Kidney Int 44: 337-344. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 11 Research paper Herter P, Laube G, Gronczewski J, Minuth WW (1993). Silver enhanced colloidal gold labelling of rabbit kidney collecting duct cell surfaces imaged by SEM. J Microscopy 171:107-115. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 10 Patent Minuth WW, Stöckl G (1992/1995). Gebrauchsmuster und Patent Nr. G 9107 283.2 / DE 42 08 805 C2: Vorrichtung zur Behandlung, insbesondere zur Kultivierung von Biomaterial mit wenigstens einem Behandlungsmedium.         9 Research paper Minuth WW, Dermietzel R, Kloth S, Henerkes B (1992). A new method culturing renal cells under permanent perfusion and producing a luminal-basal medium gradient. Kidney Int 41:215-219. Epithelium Kidney Gradient Culture PDF 8   Minuth WW (1992). MINUSHEET - ein neuer Weg zur organspezifischen Zellkultur. Spektrum der Wissenschaften 11:15-17.       PDF 7 Research paper Minuth WW, Stöckl G, Kloth S, Dermietzel R (1992). Construction of an apparatus for cell and tissue cultures which enables in vitro experiments under organo-typical conditions. Eur J Cell Biol 57:132-137. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 6 Press release Minuth WW (1991). Erster Schritt auf dem Weg zur künstlichen Leber. Ärztliche Praxis 98:27-29. Epithelium Liver Tissue engineering PDF 5 Research paper Minuth WW (1991). Eine neue Kulturmethode für anhaftende Zellen unter natürlichen Bedingungen. ALTEX 15:18-30. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 4   Minuth WW (1991). MINUSHEET - eine neue Methode um differenzierte Zellen unter nahezu natürlichen Bedingungen zu kultivieren. Bioengineering 5:66-69.       PDF 3 Press release Minuth WW (1990). Prof. Minuth geht neue Wege bei der Kultivation von hochspezialisierten Zellen. Regensburger Universitätszeitung 6:7-9. All tissue Cell/ Tissue simulation Tissue engineering PDF 2 Patent Minuth WW (1990). Patent Nr. DE-PS 3923279: Methode zur Kultivierung von Zellen.         1 Research paper Minuth WW, Rudolph U (1990). A compatible support system for cell culture in biomedical research. Cyto Technology 4:181-189. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF back to homepage</field>
<field name="important">Proceedings in perfusion culture Proceedings in perfusion culture back to homepage Tissue engineering group Prof. Dr. W. W. Minuth Proceedings are based on Minusheet® technology including perfusion culture invented by Will W. Minuth Here a list of more than 200 related publications is given: References Publication Basic tissue Organ/Site Application Download PDF 253 Research paper ?lker HE, ?lker M, Botsali MS, D?ndar A, Acar H (2013). Cytoxicity evaluation of dentin contacting materials with dentin barrier test device using erbium-doped yttrium, aluminium, and garnet laser treated dentin. Human and Experimental Toxicology x:xx-xx. Connective tissue Tooth Cytotoxicity testing   252 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L (2013). Initial steps to stabilize the microenvironment for implantation of stem/progenitor cells in diseased renal parenchyma. Transplantation Technology 1:2. Epithelium Kidney Regeneration PDF 251 Research paper ?lker HE, ?lker M, G?m?s H?, Yalcin M, Seng?n A /2013). Cytotoxicity testing of temporary luting cements with two- and three-dimensional cultures of bovine dental pulp-derived cells. BioMed Research International xx: Article ID 910459. Connective tissue Tooth Repair PDF 250 Research paper Schiessl IM, Rosenauer A, Kattler V, Minuth WW, Oppermann M, Castrop H (2013). Dietary salt intake modulates differential splicing of the Na/K/2Cl cotransporter NKCC2. Am J Physiol Renal Physiol 305:F1139-48. Epithelium Kidney Adaption of epithelia PDF 249 Research paper Campos DM, Soares GA, Anselme K (2013). Role of culture conditions on in vitro transformation and cellular colonization of biomimetic HA-Col scaffolds. Biomatter 3:e24922. Connective tissue Bone Tissue engineering PDF 248 Research paper daSilva JMF, Rodrigues JR, Camargo CHR, Fernandes Jr VVB, Hiller KA, Schweikl H, Schmalz G (2013). Effectivness and biological compatibility of different generations of dentin adhesives. Clin Oral Invest xx:xx-xx. DOI 10.1007/s00784-013-1000-9. Connective tissue Tooth Dentin adhesives PDF 247 Research paper Miura Y, Huettmann G, Orzekowsky-Schroeder R, Steven P, Szaszak M, Koop N, Brinkmann R (2013). Two-photon microscopy and fluorescence lifetime imaging of retinal pigment epithelial cells under oxidative stress. Invest Ophthalmology &amp; Vis Science. 54:3366-3377. Neural tissue Eye Regenerative Medicine PDF 246 Research paper Kim HS, Chang SW, Baek SH, Han SH, Lee Y, Zhu Q, Kum KY (2013). Antimicrobial effect of alexidine and chlorhexidine against Enterococcus faecalis infection. Int J Oral Science 5:26-31 Connective tissue Tooth Adhesion of microorganisms PDF 245 Research paper Klettner A, Westhues D, Lassen J, Bartsch S, Roider J (2013). Regulation of constitutive vascular endothelial growth factor secretion in retinal pigment epithelium/choroid organ cultures: p38, nuclear factor kappa B, and the vascular endothelial growth factor receptor-2/phosphatidylinositol 3 kinase pathway. Molecular Vision 19:281-291. Epithelium Eye Regenerative Medicine PDF 244 Research paper Wei F, Song T, Ding G, Xu J, Liu D, Fan Z, Zhang C, Shi S, Wang S (2013). Functional tooth restoration by allogeneic mesenchymal stem cell-based bio-root regeneration in swine. Stem Cells and Development 22:1752-62. Connective tissue Tooth Regenerative Medicine PDF 243 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Gruber M (2013). Search for chemically defined culture medium to assist initial regeneration of diseased renal parenchyma after stem/progenitor cell implantation. Int J Stem Cell Research and Transplantation 1:202. Epithelium Kidney Tissue engineering PDF 242 Research paper Glaum R and Wiedmann-Al-Ahmad M (2013). Cocultivation of human oral keratinocytes and human osteoblast-like cells. Methods Mol Biol 946:423-9. Epithelium and connective tissue Craniomaxillofacial region Tissue engineering   241 Research paper Schneider T, Kohl B, Sauter T, Kratz K, Landlein A, Ertel W, Schulze-Tanzil G (2012). Influence of fiber orientation in electrospaun polymer scaffolds on viability, dahesion and differentation of articular chondrocytes. Clinical Hemorheology and Microcirculation 52:325-336. Connective tissue Cartilage Tissue engineering PDF 240 Research paper Korsuwannawong S, Srichan R, Vajrabhaya L (2012). Cytotoxicity evaluation of self-etching dentine bonding agents in a cell culture perfusion condition. Eur J Dentistry 6:408-414. Connective tissue Teeth Cytotoxicity PDF 239 Review Minuth WW, Denk L (2012). Supportive development of functional tissues for biomedical research by the MINUSHEET® perfusion system. Clinical and Translational Medicine 1:22. Basic tissues Different organs Wide spectrum of applications PDF 238 Research paper Astasov-Frauenhoffer M, Braissant O, Hauser-Gerspach I, Daniels AU, Weiger R, Waltimo T (2012). Isothermal microcalorimetry provides new insight into biofilm variability and dynamics. FEMS Microbiol Let 337(1):31-37. Bacteria Titanium Biomaterials PDF 237 Research paper Kim M, Kim K, Lee Y, Kim K (2012). Cytotoxicity test of dentin bonding agents using millipore filters as dentin susstitutes in a dentin barrier test. Clin Oral Invest 17:1489-96. Connective tissue Dentin Cytotoxicity testing PDF 236 Research paper Volkmer E, Otto S, Polzer H, Saller M, Trappendreher D, Zagar D, Hamisch S, Ziegler G, Wilhelmi A, Schieker M (2012). Overcoming hypoxia in 3D culture systems for tissue engineering of bone in vitro using an automated, oxygen-triggered feedback loop. J Mater Sci. 23(11):2793-2801. Connective tissue Bone Regeneration PDF 235 Research paper Mateescu M, Rguitti E, Ponche A, Descamps M, Anselme K (2012). Biomimetic evaluation of ? tricalcium phosphate prepared by hot isostatic pressing. Biomatter 2, 3: 1-11. Connective tissue Bone Biomaterial Research PDF 234 Research paper Treumer F, Klettner A, Baltz J, Hassain AA, Brinkmann AA, Roider J, Hillenkamp J (2012). Vectorial release of matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs) from poricine RPE-choroid explants following selective retina therapy (SRT): Towards slowing the macular aging process. Exp Eye Res 97(1):63-72. Epithelial-/Neural tissue Eye Regeneration PDF 233 Research paper R?der C, Sauter C, Becker T, Kratz K, Hiebl B, Jung F, Lendlein A, Zohlnhofer D (2012). Viability, proliferation and adhesion of smooth muscle cells and human umbilical vein endothelial cells on eletrospun polymer scaffolds. Clin Hemorheol Microcirc 50(1): 101-12. Epithelial-/Muscular tissue Vessel Biomaterial research PDF 232 Research paper Rath SN, Strobel LA, Arkudas A, Beier JP, Maier AK, Greil P, Horch R, Kneser U (2012). Osteoinduction and survival of osteoblasts and bone marrow stromal cells in 3D biphasic calcium phosphate scaffolds under static and dynamic culture conditions. J Cellular Molecular Medicine 16(10):2350-2361. Connective tissue Bone Regeneration PDF 231 Research paper Bruggeman LA, Doan RP, Loftis J, Darr A, Calabro A (2012). A cell culture system for the structure and hydrogel properties of basement membranes: application to capillary walls. Cellular and Molecular Bioengineering 5(2):194-204. Epithelial tissue Kidney Regeneration PDF 230 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L (2012). Interstitial interfaces show marked differences in regenerating tubules, matured tubules and the renal stem/progenitor cell niche. J Biomedical Materials Research Part A 100(5): 1115-25. Epithelial tissue Kidney Regeneration PDF 229 Research paper Schneider T, Kohl B, Sauter T, Becker T, Kratz K, Schossig M, Hiebl B, Jung F, Lendlein A, Ertel W, Schulze-Tanzil G (2011). Viability, adhesion and differentiated phenotype of articular chondrocytes of degradable polymers and electro-spun structures therof. Macromol Symp 309/310:28-39. Connective tissue Cartilage Regeneration PDF 228 Research paper Klettner AK, Doths J, Roider J (2011). Nicotine reduces VEGF-secretion and phagocytotic activity in porcine RPE. Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol 250(1): 33-8. Neural tissue Eye Regeneration PDF 227 Research paper Glashauser A, Denk L, Minuth WW (2011). Polyester fleeces used as an artificial interstitium influence the spatial growth of regenerating tubules. J Tissue Sci Eng 2: 105. DOI 10.4172/2157-7552. Epithelial tissue Kidney Regeneration PDF 226 Research paper Kalamarz-Kubiak H, Gozdowska M, Nietrzeba M, Kulcykska E (2011). A novel approach to AVT and IT studies in fish brain and pituitary: in vitro perfusion technique. Journal of Neuroscience Methods 199(1):56-61 Neural tissue Brain Endocrinology PDF 225 Research paper Farack J, Wolf-Brandstetter C, Glorius S, Nies B, Standke G, Quadbeck P, Worch H, Schwarnweber D (2011). The effect of perfusion culture on proliferation and differentiation of human mesenchymal cells on biocorrodible bone replacement material. Materials Science and Engineering B 176:1776-1772. Connective tissues Bone Tissue engineering PDF 224 Book Minuth WW and Denk L (2011). Advanced Culture Experiments with Adherent Cells. From single cells to specialized tissues in perfusion culture. Open access publishing, University of Regensburg, ISBN Nr. 978-3-88246-330-9, 414 pages. urn:nbn:de:bvb:355-epub-214847. Specialized tissues Various organs Tissue culture technology PDF 223 Research paper Seng?n A, Yalcin M, ?lker HE, Ozt?rk B, Hakki SS (2011). Cytotoxicity evaluation of dentin bonding agents by dentin barrier test on 3-dimensional pulp cells. Oral Surg Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod 112:e83-8. Connective tissue Tooth Cytotoxicity PDF 222 Research paper Yue S, Lee PD, Poologasundarampillai G (2011). Evaluation of 3D bioactive glass scaffolds dissolution in a perfusion flow system with X-ray microtomography. Acta Biomaterialia 7(6):2637-43 Connective Tissue Bone Regenerative medicine PDF 221 Research paper Dankers PY, Boomker JM, Huizinga - van der Vlag A, Wisse E, Smedts FM, Harmsen MC, Bosman AW, Meijer W, van Luyn MJ (2011). Bioengineering of living renal membranes consisting of hierarchical, bioactive supramolecular meshes and huma tubular cells. Biomaterials 32(3):723-33. Epithelial tissue Kidney Regenerative medicine PDF 220 Research paper Hamilton RD, Leach L (2011). Isolation and properties of an in vitro human outer blood-retinal barrier model. Methods Mol Biol 686:401-416. Epithelial tissue Eye Regenerative medicine PDF 219 Research paper Quadbeck P, Hauser R, K?mmel K, Standke G, Stephani G, Nies B, R??ler S, Wegener B (2010). Iron based cellular metals for degradable synthetic bone replacement. PM2010 World Congress - PM Biomaterials p 1-8. Connective tissue Bone Biomaterials PDF 218 Research paper Dankers PY, Boomker JM, Huizinga-van der Vlag A, Smedts FM, Harmsen MC, van Luyn MJ (2010). The use of fibrous, supramolecular membranes and human tubular cells for renal epithelial tissue engineering: towards a suitable membrane for a bioartificial kidney. Macromol Biosci 10(11):1345-54. Epithelial tissue Kidney Regenerative medicine PDF 217 Book chapter Minuth WW, Denk L, Roessger A (2010). Regenerating tubules for kidney repair. Stem Cell Engineering - Principals and Applications, Eds. Artmann, Minger, Hescheler, Springer Verlag, pp 321-344. Epithelial tissue Kidney Regenerative medicine PDF 216 Review article Yeatts A, Fisher JP (2010). Bone tissue engineering bioreactors: Dynamic culture and the influence of shear stress. Bone 48(2):171-81. Connective tissue Bone Regenerative medicine PDF 215 Research paper Bernhardt A, Lode A, Peters F, Gelinsky M (2010). Optimization of culture conditions for osteogenically-induced mesenchymal stem cells in ?-tricalcium phosphate ceramics with large interconnected channels. J Tissue Eng Regen Med 5(6):444-53. Connective tissue Bone Regenerative medicine PDF 214 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Glashauser A (2010). Promoting and harmful effects of steroid hormones on renal stem/progenitor cell development. J Tissue Science Engineering 1:101 Epithelial tissue Kidney Regenerative medicine PDF 213 Research paper da Silva HM, Mateescu M, Damia C, Champion E, Soares G, Anselme K (2010). Importance of dynamic culture for evaluating osteoblast activity on dense silicon-substituted hydroxyapatite. Colloids Surf B Biointerfaces 80(2):138-44. Connective tissue Bone Regenerative medicine PDF 212 Research paper Steinhagen J, Niggemeyer O, Fuerst M, Rüther W, Schünke M, Kurz B (2010). Perfusion culture system: Synovial fibroblasts modulate articular chondrocyte matrix synthesis in vitro. Tissue Cell 42(3):151-157. Connective tissue Cartilage Regenerative medicine PDF 211 Review article Minuth WW, Denk L, Glashauser A (2010). Towards a guided regeneration of renal tubules at a polyester interstitium. Materials 3:2369-2392. Epithelial tissue Kidney Regenerative medicine PDF 210 Research paper Miess C, Glashauser A, Denk L, de Vries U, Minuth W (2010). The interface between generating renal tubules and a polyester fleece in comparison to the interstitium of the developing kidney. Ann Biomed Eng 38(6):2197-209. Epithelial tissue Kidney Regenerative medicine PDF 209 Research paper Heinemannn C, Heinemann S, Bernhardt A, Lode A, Worch H, Hanke T (2010). In vitro osteoclastogenesis on textile chitosan scaffold. Eur Cell Mater 19:96-106. Connective tissue Bone Regenerative medicine PDF 208 Review article Minuth WW, Denk L, Glashauser A (2010). Cell and drug-delivery therapeutics for renal tissue regeneration. Advanced Drug Delivery Reviews 62(7-8):841-854. Epithelial tissue Kidney Regenerative medicine PDF 207 Leading opinion paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Glashauser A (2010). A modular culture system for the generation of multiple specialized tissues. Biomaterials 11:2945-2954. All tissues Specialized tissue Regenerative medicine PDF 206 Research paper da Silva HM, Mateescu M, Ponche A, Damia C, Champion E, Soares G, Anselme K (2010). Surface transformation of silicon-doped hydroxyapatite immersed in culture medium under dynamic and static conditions. Colloids and Surfaces B: Biointerfaces 75(1):349-55. Connective tissue Bone Biomaterial research PDF 205 Research paper Miura Y, Klettner A, Noelle B, Hasselbach H, Roider J (2010). Change of morphological and functional characteristics of retinal pigment epithelium cells during cultivation of retinal pigment epithelium-choroid perfusion tissue culture. Opthalmic research 43;122-133. Neural tissue Eye Regenerative medicine PDF 204 Research paper Klettner A, Kruse ML, Meyer T, Wesch D, Kabelitz D, Roider J (2009). Different properties of VEGF-antagonists: Bevacizumab but not Ranibizumab accumulates in RPE cells. Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol 247(12): 1601-8. Neural tissue Eye Regenerative medicine PDF 203 Research paper Hagedorn GM, Blank A, Weiland B, Spassov A, Lauer G (2009). Perfusion culture promotes differentiation of oral keratinocytes in vitro. J Physiol Pharmacol 60(8):25-9. Epithelial tissue Oral mucosa Regenerative medicine PDF 202 Research paper Klettner A, Roider J (2009). Constitutive and oxidative-stress-induced expression of VEGF in the RPE are differently regulated by different Mitogen-activated protein kinases. Graefs Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol 247:1487-1492. Neural tissue Eye Regenerative medicine PDF 201 Research paper Xia L, Ng S, Han R, Tuo X, Xiao G, Leo HL, Cheng T, Yu H (2009). Laminar-flow immediate-overlay hapatocyte sandwich perfusion system for drug hepatotoxicity testing. Biomaterials 30(30):5927-36. Epithelium Liver Toxicity testing PDF 200 Research paper Glaum R, Wiedmann - Al-Ahmad M, Huebner U, Schmelzeisen R (2009). Cocultivation of human keratinocytes and human osteoblast-like cells on laminin-coated polycarbonate membranes and equine collagen membranes under different culture conditions. J Biomed Mater Res A 93A(2):704-715. Epithelium/ Connective tissue Composite graft Biomaterial research PDF 199 Research paper Heinemann C, Heinemann S, Lode A, Bernhardt A, Worch H, Hanke T (2009). In vitro evaluation of textile chitosan scaffolds for tissue engineering using human bone marrow stromal cells. Biomacromolecules 10:1305-1310. Connective tissue Bone Biomaterial research PDF 198 Research paper Ulker HE, Sengun A (2009). Cytotoxicity evaluation of self adhesive composite resin cements by dentin barrier test on 3D pulp test. Eur J Dent 3(2):120-6. Connective tissue Tooth pulp Cytotoxical research PDF 197 Research paper Roessger A, Denk L, Minuth WW (2009). Potential of stem/progenitor cell cultures within polyester fleeces to regenerate renal tubules. Biomaterials 30(22):3723-32. Epithelium Kidney Stem cell research PDF 196 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Roessger A (2009). Gradient perfusion culture - simulating a tissue-specific environment for epithelia in biomedicine. J Epithel Biology &amp; Pharmacology 2:1-13. Epithelium Gradient perfusion culture Biomedicine PDF 195 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Meese C, Rachel R, Roessger A (2009). Ultrastructural insights in the interface between generated tubules and a polyester interstitium. Langmuir 25(8):4621-4627. Epithelium Kidney Stem cell research PDF 194 Research paper Anders JO, Mollenhauer J, Beberhold A, Kinne RW, Venbrocks RA (2009). Gelatin-based haemostypic Spongostan as a possible three-dimensional scaffold for a chondrocyte matrix? J Bone Joint Surg (Br) 91(B):409-16. Connective tissue Cartilage Tissue engineering PDF 193 Book Lauer G (2009). Fundamentals of Tissue engineering and Regenerative Medicine, 27.6 Optimizingg the Mucosa Graft: Developing Gingival Keratinocyte - Fibroblast Contact. pp 375 ed. by Ulrich Meyer et al. Springer Verlag Epithelium Mucosa Graft Tissue engineering PDF 192 Research paper Vajrabhaya L, Koruwannawong S, Bosl C, Schmalz G (2009). The cytotoxicity of self-etching primer bonding agents in vitro. Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Path Oral Radiol Endod 107:e86-e90. Connective tissue Tooth pulp Cytotoxical research PDF 191 Research paper Masungi C, Mensch J, Willems B, Van Dijck A, Borremans C, Noppe M, Brewster ME, Augustijns P (2009). Usefulness of a novel Caco-2 cell perfusion system II. Characterization of monolayer properties and peptidase activity. Pharmazie 64:36-42. Epithelium Intestine Pharmacology PDF 190 Research paper Hayashi M, Matsuzaki Y, Shimonaka M (2009). Impact of plasminogen on an in vitro wound healing model based on a perfusion cell culture system. Mol Cell Biochem 322(1-2):1-13. Epithelium Endothelial repair Regenerative medicine PDF 189 Research paper Heinemann C, Heinemann S, Bernhardt A, Worch H, Hanke T (2008). Novel textile chitosan scaffolds promote spreading, proliferation and differentiation of osteoblasts. Biomacromolecules 9:2913-2920. Connective tissue Bone Biomaterial research PDF 188 Research paper Dreesmann L, Hajosch R, Ahlers M, Nuernberger JV, Schlosshauer B (2008). Permeability testing of biomaterial membranes. Biomed Mater 3:034119. Connective tissue Regeneration Biomaterial research PDF 187 Book Motz A, Bur M, Schaefer UF, Lehr CM (2008). Instrumented in vitro approaches to assess epithelial permeability of drugs from pharmaceutical formulations. In: Drug Absorption Studies, Springer Verlag, ISBN 978-0-387-74900-6, pp. 430-455. Epithelium Lung Environmental toxicology PDF 186 Research paper Paur HR, Mülhopt S, Weiss C, Diabaté S (2008). In vitro exposure systems and bioassays for the assessment of toxicity of nanoparticles to the human lung. J Verbr. Lebensm. 3:319-329. Epithelium Lung Environmental toxicology PDF 185 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Blattmann A, Castrop H (2008). Collagen type III is an important linking molecule between generated renal tubules and an artificial interstitium. J Clinical Rehabilitative Tissue Engineering Research (CRTER) 12,32:6201-08. Epithelial tissue Kidney Stem cell research PDF 184 Research paper Volkmer E, Drosse I, Otto S, Stanglmeyer A, Stengele M, Kallukalam BC, Mutschler W, Schieker M (2008). Hypoxia in static and dynamic 3D culture systems for tissue engineering of bone. Tissue Engineering A 14,8:1331-40. Connective tissue Bone Regenerative Medicine PDF 183 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L (2008). Aldosterone-dependent generation of tubules derived from renal stem/progenitor cells. Transplantationsmedizin 20:42-47. Epithelial tissue Kidney Stem cell research PDF 182 Research paper Kaempf S, Johnen S, Salz AK, Weinberger A, Walter P, Thumann G (2008). Effects of Bevacizumab (Avastin) on retinal cells in organotypic culture. Invest Ophathalmol Vis Sci 49,7:3164-71. Neural tissue Eye Pharmacology PDF 181 Research paper Minuth WW, Blattmann A, Denk L, Castrop H (2008). Mineralocorticoid receptor, heat shock proteins and immunophilins participate in the transmission of the tubulogenic signal of aldosterone. J Epithelial Biology &amp; Pharmacology 1:24-34. Epithelial tissue Kidney Stem cell research PDF 180 Research paper Klettner AK, Roider J (2008). Comparison of Bevacizumab, Ranibizumab and Pegatanib in vitro: efficiency and possible additional pathways. Invest Opathalmol Vis Sci 49,10:4523-7. Neural tissue Eye Regenerative Medicine PDF 179 Research paper Demirci M, Hiller KA, Bosl C, Galler K, Schmalz G, Schweikl H (2008). The induction of oxidative stress, cytotoxicity, and genotoxicity by dental adhesives. Dental Materials 24:362-371. Connective tissue Dentin Biomaterial testing PDF 178 Research paper Frerich B, Zückmantel K, Winter K, Müller-Dürwald S, Hemprich A (2008). Maturation of capillary-like structures in a tube-like construct in perfusion and rotation culture. Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg 37:459-466. Connective tissue Vessel Regeneration research PDF 177 Research paper Hammer M, Richter S, Kobuch K, Mata N, Schweitzer D (2008). Intrinsic tissue fluorescence in an organotypic perfusion culture of the porcine ocular fundus exposed to blue light and free radicals. Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophtalmol Epub 246,7:979-88. Neural tissue Eye Regenerative Medicine PDF 176 Research paper Blattmann A, Denk L, Strehl R, Castrop H, Minuth WW (2008). The formation of pores in the basal lamina of regenerated renal tubules. Biomaterials 29:2749-2756. Epithelial tissue Kidney Stem cell research PDF 175 Research paper Kobuch K, Hermann WA, Framme C, Sachs HG, Gabel VP, Hillenkamp J (2008). Maintenance of adult porcine retina and retinal pigment epithelium in perfusion culture: Characterisation of an organotypic in vitro model. Exp Eye Res 86:661-668. Neural tissue Eye Regenerative Medicine PDF 174 Research paper Detsch R, Uhl F, Deisinger U, Ziegler G (2008). 3D-Cultivation of bone marrow stromal cells on hydroxyapatite scaffolds fabricated by dispens-plotting and negative mold technique. J Mater Sci: Mater Med 19,4:1491-6. Connective tissue Bone Tissue engineering PDF 173 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Castrop H (2008). Generation of tubular superstructures by piling of renal stem/progenitor cells. Tissue engineering 14,1:3-13. Stem cells Kidney Tissue engineering PDF 172 Research paper Du Y, Han R, Wen F, Ng San San S, Xia L, Wohland T, Leo HL, Yu H (2008). Synthetic sandwich culture of 3D hepatocyte monolayer. Biomaterials 29:290-301. Epithelium Liver Biomaterial research PDF 171 Research paper Bernhardt A, Lode A, Boxberger S, Pompe W, Gelinsky M (2008). Mineralised collagen – an artificial, extracellular bone matrix – improves osteogenic differentiation of bone marrow stromal cells. J Mater Sci-Mater Med: 19,1: 269-275. Connective tissue Bone Biomaterial research PDF 170 Research paper Maier KL, Alessandrini F, Beck-Speier I, Hofer TP et al. (2008). Health effects on ambient particulate matter - biological mechanisms and inflammatory responses to in vitro and in vivo particle exposures. Inhal Toxicol 20(3):319-37. Epithelial tissue Lung Environmental health PDF 169 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Hu K (2007). Kontrolliertes Environment für die Entwicklung von Stammzellen zu renalen Tubuli. Regenerative Medizin 1:22-27. Stem cells Kidney Tissue engineering PDF 168 Research paper Constantinescu R, Constanntinescu AT, Reichmann H, Janetzky B (2007). Neuronal differentiation and long-term culture of the human neuroblastoma line SH--SY5Y. J Neural Transm 72: 17-28. Neural tissue Dopaminergic cells Tissue engineering PDF 167 Research paper Minuth WW, Hu K, Denk L (2007). Kontrolliertes Environment für Stammzellen – Generierung renaler Tubuli in chemisch definiertem Kulturmedium. BIOforum 4:28-29. Epithelia Stem cell research Tissue engineering PDF 166 Research paper Röpke E, Schön I, Vogel J, Jamali J, Bloching M, Berghaus A (2007). Screening von modifizierten Polyethylenoberflächen für das Tissue engineering von Chondrozyten. Laryngo-Rhino-Otol 86:37-43. Connective tissue Biomaterial testing Tissue engineering PDF 165 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Hu K, Castrop H, Gomez-Sanchez C (2007). Tubulogenic effect of aldosterone is attributed to intact binding and intracellular response of the mineralocorticoid receptor. Central Eur J Biol  - CEJB 2(2):307-325. Epithelium Kidney Stem cell research PDF 164 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Hu K (2007). The role of polyester interstitium and aldosterone during structural development of renal tubules in serum-free medium.Biomaterials 28:4418-28. Epithelium Kidney Stem cell research PDF 163 Research paper Zheng W, Jimenez-Linan M, Rubin BS, Halvorson LM (2007). Anterior pituitary gen expression with reproductive aging in the femal rat. Biol Reprod 76:1091-1102. Epithelium Endocrinology anterior pituitary Gen research PDF 162 Research paper Hauser-Gerspach I, Kulik EM, Weiger R, Decker EM, von Ohle C, Meyer J (2007). Adhesion of Streptococcus sanguinis to dental implant and restorative materials in vitro. Dental Materials J 26(3):361-366. Connective tissue Enamel Biomaterial research PDF 161 Research paper Hu K, Denk L, deVries U, Minuth WW (2007). Chemically defined medium environment for the development of renal stem cells into tubules. Biotechnology J 2:992-995. Epithelium Kidney Stem cell research PDF 160 Research paper Seitz S, Ern K, Lamper G, Docheva D, Drosse I, Milz S, Mutschler, W, Schieker M (2007). Influence of in vitro cultivation on the integration of cell-matrix constructs after subcutaneous implantation. Tissue engineering 13,5:1059-1067. Connective tissue Stem cells Tissue engineering PDF 159 Research paper Jian GE, Jingbo L (2007). The stem cell and tissue engineering research in chinese ophthalmology. Front Med China 1(1):6-10. Nervous tissue Eye Stem cell research PDF 158 Research paper Hamilton RD, Foss AJ, Leach L (2007). Establishment of a human in vitro model of the outer blood-retinal barrier. J Anat 211(6):707-16. Nervous tissue Eye Regenerative medicine PDF 157 Research paper Minuth WW, Strehl R (2007). Technical and theoretical considerations about gradient perfusion culture for epithelia used in tissue engineering, biomaterial testing and pharmaceutical research. Biomed Mater 2:R1-R11. Epithelium Barrier Biomaterials/ Pharmacology PDF 156 Research paper Heber S, Denk L, Hu K, Minuth WW (2007). Modulating the development of renal tubules growing in serum-free culture medium at an artificial interstitium. Tissue Eng 13:2. Epithelium Kidney Stem cell research PDF 155 Research paper Schumacher K, Khong YM, Chang S, Ni J, Sun W, Yu H (2007). Perfusion culture improves the maintenance of cultured Liver Tissue slices. Tissue Eng 13:197-205. Epithelium Liver Pharmacology PDF 154 Research paper Yang SE, Cha JH, Kim ES, Kum KY, Lee CY, Jung IY (2006). Effect of smear layer and cholhexidine treatment on the adhesion of Enterococcus faecalis to bovine dentin. J Oral Endodont/JOE 32,7:663-667. Connective tissue Tooth, Dentin Biomaterial research PDF 153 Research paper Shearer H, Ellis MJ, Perera SP, Chaudhuri JB (2006). Effects of common sterilization methods on the structure and properties of poly(d,l lactic-co-glycolic acid) scaffold. Tissue Engineering 12,10:2717-27. Connective tissue Cartilage, Bone Biomaterial research PDF 152 Patent Minuth WW (2006).. Patent Nr. DE 10 2005 002 938: Verfahren zum Versorgen von Zellen oder Geweben.         151 Research paper Ng S, Han R, Chang S, Ni J, Hunziger W, Goryachev B, Ong SH, Yu H (2006). Improved hepatocyte excretory function by immediate presentation of polarity cues. Tissue Eng 12,8:2181-2191. Epithelium Liver Pharmacology PDF 150 Research paper Saikia P, Maisch T, Kobuch K, Jackson TL, Bäumler W, Szeimies RM, Gabel VP, Hillenkamp J (2006). Safety testing of Indocyanine Green in an ex vivo porcine retina model. Investigative Ophalmology &amp; Visual Science 47,11:4998-5003. Nervous tissue Eye Pharmacology PDF 149 Research paper Frerich B, Zückmantel K, Hemprich A (2006). Microvascular engineering in perfusion culture: immunohistochemistry and CLMS findings. Head &amp; Face Medicine 2:26. Microvessels Adipose tissue Vascular supply PDF 148 Research paper Minuth W, Denk L (2006). From the renal stem cell niche to functional parenchyme. 41. Congress of the European Society for surgical research in Rostock, Medimont, International Proceedings, Editor Brigitte Vollmar, ISBN 88-7587-244-9, pp 9-17. Epithelium Kidney Stem cell research PDF 147 Research paper Bitterle E, Karg E, Schroeppel A, Kreyling WG, Tippe A, Ferron GA, Schmid O, Hexder J, Maier KL, Hofer T (2006). Dose-controlled exposure of A549 epithelial cells at the air-liquid interphase to airborne ultrafine carbonaceous particles. Chemospehre 65,10:1784-1790. Epithelium Lung Test of Biomaterials PDF 146 Book Minuth WW, Strehl R (2006). 3D Kulturen - Zellen, Kultursysteme und Environment. Pabst Science Publishers, Lengerich, ISBN 10:3-89967-316-6 und ISBN 13:978-3-89967-316-6, 471 Seiten.     General PDF 145 Research paper Yamagishi K, Enomoto T, Ohmiya Y (2006). Perfusion-culture-based secreted bioluminescence reporter assay in living cells. Analytical Biochemistry 354:15-21. Nervous Tissue Circadian clock gene Reporter assay PDF 144 Patent Minuth WW (2006). Patent Nr. DE 199 52 847: Vorrichtung zum Kultivieren und/oder Differenzieren und/oder Halten von Zellen und/oder Geweben.         143 Research paper Gille J, Meisner U, Ehlers EM, Müller A, Russlies M, Behrens P (2005). Migration pattern, morphology and viability of cells suspended in or sealed with fibrin glue: a histo-morphological study. Tissue and Cell 37:339-348. Connective Tissue Cartilage Regenerative Medicine PDF 142 Research paper Leukers B, Gülkan H, Irsen SH, Milz S, Tille C, Schieker M, Seitz H (2005). Hydroxyapatite scaffold for bone tissue engineering made by 3D printing. J Materilas Scienc: Materials in Medicine 16:1121-1124. Connective Tissue Bone Biomaterial test PDF 141 Research paper Shearer H, Ellis MJ, Perera SP, Chaudhuri JB (2005). Sterilisation of PLGA flat sheet and hallow fiber tissue engineering scaffolds. Eur Cells and Materials 10,2:4. Connective Tissue Bone Biomaterial test PDF 140 Research paper Galler K, Hiller KA, Ettl T, Schmalz G (2005). Selective influence of dentin thickness upon cytotoxicity of dentin contacting materials. J Endod 31,5:396-399. Connective Tissue Dentin Toxicology PDF 139 Book Minuth WW, Strehl R, Schumacher K (2005). Microreactor optimization for functional tissue engineering. In Chapter 2 (pp 19-45) of Bioreactors for Tissue engineering, Principles, Design and Operation ed. by Chaudhuri J and Al-Rubeai M, Springer Biotechnology, ISBN 1-4020-3740-6.       PDF 138 Research paper Tiemann U, Bücher K, Pfarrer Ch, Pöhland R, Becker F, Kanitz W, Schmidt P (2005). Influence of ovarian steroid hormones or platelet-activating factor receptor in endometrial explant perfusion cultures from ovariectomized bovine. Prostaglandins &amp; other Lipid Mediators 76:35-47. Epithelium Femal Reproductive Tract Pharmacology PDF 137 Research paper Minuth WW, Denk L, Heber S (2005). Growth of embryonic renal parenchyme at the interphase of a polyester artificial interstitium. Biomaterials 26:6588-6598. Epithelium and Mesenchyme Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 136 Research paper Leukers B, Gülkan H, Irsen SH, Milz S, Tille C, Seitz H, Schieker M (2005). Biocompatibility of ceramic scaffolds for bone replacemant made by 3D printing. Mat Wiss Werkstofftechnik 36(12):781-787. Connective tissue Biomaterial testing Tissue engineering PDF 135 Research paper Steuer H, Jaworsky A, Elger B, Kaussmann M, Keldenich J, Schneider H, Stoll D, Schlosshauer B (2005). Functional characterization and comparison of the outer blood-retina barrier and the blood-brain barrier. Invest Ophtalmology &amp; Visual Science 46,3:1047-1053. Nervous Tissue Blood brain barrier Pharmacology PDF 134 Book Minuth WW, Strehl R, Schumacher K (2005). Tissue Engineering - Essentials for Daily Laboratory Work. WILEY-VCH Verlag, ISBN 3527311866, 350 pages.       PDF 133 Research paper Dimova S, Vlaeminck V, Brewster ME, Noppe M, Jorissen M, Augustijns P (2005). Stable ciliary activity in human nasal epithelial cells grown in perfusion culture. Int J Pharmaceutics 292:157-168. Epithelium Respiratory Tract Pharmacology PDF 132 Research paper Strehl R, Tallheden T, Sjögren-Jansson E, Minuth WW, Lindahl A (2005). Long-term mainteance of human articular cartilage in culture for biomaterial testing. Biomaterials 26:4540-4549. Connective Tissue Cartilage Test of Biomaterials PDF 131 Research paper Minuth WW, Schumacher K, Strehl R (2005). Renal epithelia in long term gradient culture for biomaterial testing and tissue engineering. Biomed Mater Eng. 15(1-2):51-63. Epithelium Kidney Test of Biomaterials PDF 130 Research paper Bakowsky U, Ehrhardt C, Loehbach C, Li P, Kneuer C, Jahn D, Hoekstra D, Lehr CM (2005). Adhesion molecule-modified cardivasculare prothesis: Characterization of cellular adhesion in a cell culture model and by cellular force spectroscopy. Pp 157-173, Kapitel 11 in Adhesion: Current Research and Applications ed. W. Possart, Wiley-VCH. Epithelium Vascular protheses Tissue engineering PDF 129 Technical note Bruckner H (2004). Tissue engineering: Gewebe aus der Retorte LaborPraxis 4: 62-65. All tissues Missing regeneration Tissue engineering PDF 128 Research paper Sternberg K, Selent C, Hakanßon N, Töllner J, Langer T, Seiter H, Schmiitz KP (2004). Bioartifizielle Materialien in der Urologie. Urologe 10: 1200-1207. Epithelium Urogenital tract Tissue engineering PDF 127 Research paper Rothamel D, Schwarz F, Sculean A, Herten M, Scherbaum W, Becker J (2004). Biocompatibility of various collagen membranes in cultures of human PDL fibroblast and human osteoblast-like-cells. Clin Oral Impl Res 15,4:443-9. Connective tissue Bone Biomaterial research PDF 126 Research paper Steuer H, Jaworski A, Stoll D, Schlosshauer B (2004). In vitro model of the outer blood-retina barrier. Brain Research Protocols 13:26-36. Nervous Tissue Eye Pharmacology PDF 125 Research paper Gelinsky M, König U, Sewing A, Pompe W (2004). Poröse Scaffolds aus mineralisiertem Kollagen - ein biomimetisches Knochenersatzmaterial. Mat.-wiss und Werkstofftech 35,4:229-233. Connective Tissue Bone Tissue engineering PDF 124 Research paper Duda GN, Kliche A, Kleemann R, Hoffmann JE, Sittinger M, Haisch A (2004). Does low-intensity pulsed ultrasound stimulate maturation of tissue-engineered cartilage? J Biomed Mater Res Part B: Appl Biomater 68B:21-28. Connective Tissue Cartilage Tissue engineering PDF 123 Research paper Jennings P, Koppelstaetter, C, Pfaller W, Morin JP, Hartung T, Ryan MP (2004). Assessment of a new cell culture perfusion apparatus for in vitro toxicity testing. Part 2: toxicological evaluation. ALTEX 21,2:61-66. Epithelium Kidney Pharmacology PDF 122 Research paper Koppelstaetter C, Jennings P, Ryan MP, Morin JP, Hartung T, Pfaller W (2004). Assessment of a new new cell culture perfusion apparatus for in vitro chronic toxicity testing. Part 1: technical description. ALTEX 21,2?:51-60. Epithelium Kidney Pharmacology PDF 121 Book Strehl R, Schumacher K, Minuth W (2004). The current state of engineering tissues and organ parts. In Ethical, Legal, and Social Issues in Organ Transplantation, Editors T. Gutmann, AS Daar, RA Sells, W Land, Pabst Publishers, Lengerich, ISBN 3-89967-017-5 (Europe), ISBN 1-59326-063-6 (USA), pp. 405-422.       PDF 120 Research paper Masungi C, Borremans C, Willems B, Mensch J, Dijck AV, Augustijns P, Brewster ME, Noppe M (2004). Usefulness of a novel Caco-2 cell perfusion system. I. in vitro prediction of the absorption potential of passively diffused compounds. J Pharm Sci 93,10:2507-2521. Epithelium Digestive Tract Pharmacology PDF 119 Research paper Minuth WW, Sorokin L, Schumacher K (2004). Generation of renal tubules at the interface of an artificial interstitium. Cell Physiol Biochem 14,4-6:387-394. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 118 Research paper Strehl R, Schumacher K, Minuth WW (2004). Controlled respiratory gas delivery to embryonic renal epithelial explants in perfusion culture. Tissue Engineering 10,7:1196-1202. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 117 Research paper Fiegel HC, Havers J, Kneser U, Smith MK, Moeller T, Kluth D, Mooney DJ, Rogiers X, Kaufmann P (2004). Influence of flow conditions and matrix coatings on growth and differentiation of three-dimensionally cultured rat hepatocytes. Tissue Engineering 10,1-2:165-174. Epithelium Liver Conceptual Tissue Culture PDF 116 Research paper Minuth WW, Strehl R, Schumacher R (2004). Tissue factory - Conceptual design of a modular system for the in-vitro generation of functional tissues. Tissue Engineering 10,1/2:285-294. All Tissues     PDF 115 Research paper Minuth WW, Schumacher K (2004). Tissue Engineering - Schwierigkeiten und Chancen bei der Herstellung künstlicher Gewebe. Journal DGPW 29:20-22. Tissues Regeneration Tissue engineering PDF 114 Interview Minuth WW (2003). Hat die Zukunft schon begonnen? Zellbiologie 1: 16-17. All Tissues Missing regeneration Tissue engineering PDF 113 Research paper Decker EM, Weiger R, von Ohle C, Wiech I, Brecx M (2003). Susceptibility of planktonic versus attached Streptococcus sanguinis cells to chlorhexidine. Clin Oral Invst 7:98-102. Connective Tissue Enamel Biomaterial test PDF 112 Research paper Minuth WW, Schumacher K (2003). From the renal stem cell niche to functional tubule. Med Klin 15,98 Suppl2:31-35. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 111 Research paper Wang Y, Uemura T, Dong J, Kojima H, Tanaka J, Tateishi T (2003). Application of perfusion culture system improves in vitro and in vivo osteogenesis of bone marrow-derived osteoblastic cells in porous ceramic materials. Tissue Engineering 9,6:1205-1214. Connective Tissue Cartilage and Bone Improved Tissue Culture PDF 110 Research paper Bücheler M, Haisch A (2003). Tissue engineering in Otorhinolaryngology. DNA and Cell Biology 22,9:549-564. Connective Tissue Respiratory System Improved Tissue Culture PDF 109 Research paper Schumacher K, Strehl R, Minuth WW (2003). Urea restrains aldosterone-induced development of peanut agglutinin-binding on embryonic collecting duct epithelia. J Am Soc Nephrol 14:2758-2766. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 108 Research paper Uemura T, Dong J, Wang Y, Kojima H, Saito T, Iejima D, Kikuchi M, Tanaka J, Tateishi T (2003). Transplantation of cultured bone cells using combinations of scaffolds and culture techniques. Biomaterials 24:2277-2286. Connective Tissue Cartilage and Bone Improved Tissue Culture PDF 107 Book Minuth WW, Strehl R, Schumacher K (2003). Zukunftstechnologie Tissue engineering - Von der Zellbiologie zum künstlichen Gewebe. WILEY-VCH Verlag, ISBN 3-527-30793-1.       PDF 106 Research paper Stern S, Lindenhayn K, Perka C (2003). Die Knorpeltransplantation mit bioresorbierbaren Polymeren im tierexperimentellen Modell. Kapitel 9, pp 52 - 59. Fortbildung Orthopädie - Traumatologie, Springer Verlag, edited by Jörg Jerosch. Connective tissue Cartilage Tissue engineering PDF 105 Technical note Minuth WW, Schumacher K, Strehl R, de Vries U (2002). Epithelia -Biomateriaux- Genie tissuelaire. BIOforum International Edition francaise 1: 28-30. Epithelium Kidney Tissue engineering PDF 104 Research paper Guarnizo AC, Rodriguez EV, Albaladejo JMO, Carrasquer TC, Manzano JAC, Cacha JPM, Gasso CS (2002). Autoinjerto subcutaneo de cartilago neosintetizado utilizando el polimero ETHISORB en conejos. Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp 53:631-636. Connective tissue Cartilage Biomaterial research PDF 103 Research paper von Woedtke T, Jülich WD, Alhitari N, Hanschke R, Abel PU (2002). Biosensor-controlled perfusion culture to estimate the viability of cells. Medical &amp; Biological Engineering &amp; Computing 40:704-711. Epithelium Biotest Biofilm/ Fouling PDF 102 Research paper Luppens SBI, Reij MW, van der Heijden RWL, Rombouts FM, Abee T (2002). Development of a standard test to assess the resistance of Staphylococcus aureus biofilm cells to desinfectants. Applied Environ Microbiology 68,9:4194-4200. Microorganisms Biotest Biofilm/ Fouling PDF 101 Research paper Camps J, About L, Thonneman B, Mitsiadis TA, Schmaltz G, Franquin JC (2002). Two- versus three-dimensional in vitro differentiation of human pulp cells into odontoblastic cells. Connective Tissue Res 43:396-400. Connective Tissue Dentin Test of Biomaterials PDF 100 Research paper Risbud MV, Sittinger M (2002). Tissue engineering: advances in vitro cartilage generation. Trends in Biotechnology 20,8:351-356. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 99 Research paper Schumacher K, Strehl R, De Vries U, Groene HJ, Minuth WW (2002). SBA-positive fibers between the CD ampulla, mesenchyme and renal capsule. J Am Soc Nephrol 13:2446-2453. Epithelium and Mesenchyme Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 98 Research paper Spiegel D, Schefthaler M, Kobuch K (2002). Outflow facilities through Descemet's membrane in rabbits. Graefe's Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol 240:111-113. Nervous Tissue Eye Improved Tissue Culture PDF 97 Research paper Schumacher K, Castrop H, Strehl R, de Vries U, Minuth WW (2002). Cyclooxygenases in the collecting duct of neonatal rabbit kidney. Cellular Physiol Biochem 12:63-74. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 96 Research paper Woedke T, Lindequist U, Alhitari N, Kusnick C, Jülich W-D, Abel PU (2002). The usefulness of a biosensor controlled perfusion cell culture for the investigation of new drugs demonstrated with the marine fungus Kirschsteiniothelia maritima. Pharmazie 57:270-274. Epithelium General Bioengineering PDF 95 Research paper Framme C, Kobuch K, Eckert E, Monzer J, Roider J (2002). RPE in Perfusion tissue culture and ist response to laser application. Ophthalmologica 216:320-328. Epithelium Eye Regeneration PDF 94 Research paper Haisch A, Kläring S, Gröger A, Gebert C, Sittinger M (2002). A tissue-engineered model for the manufacture of auricular-shaped cartilage implants. Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol 259:316-321. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 93 Research paper Schmalz G, Schuster U, Koch A, Schweikl H (2002). Cytotoxicity of low pH dentin-bonding agents in a dentin barrier test in vitro. J Endodontics 28,3:188-192. Connective Tissue Dentin Test of Biomaterials PDF 92 Research paper Strehl R, Schumacher K, de Vries U, Minuth WW (2002). Proliferating cells versus differentiated cells in tissue engineering. Tissue Eng. 8(1):37-42. All Tissues     PDF 91 Book Minuth WW, Strehl R, Schumacher K (2002). Von der Zellkultur zum Tissue engineering. Pabst Science Publishers ISBN 3-936142-32-7.       PDF 90 Book Minuth WW, Schumacher K, Strehl R, de Vries U (2002). Mikroreaktortechnik für Tissue engineering in Medizintechnik mit biokompatiblen Werkstoffen und Verfahren. E. Wintermantel, Suk-Woo Ha, Springer Verlag, pp 305-319.       PDF 89 Research paper Schumacher K, Strehl R, de Vries U, Minuth WW (2002). Advanced technique for long term culture of epithelia in a continuous luminal - basal medium gradient. Biomaterials 23,3:805-815. Epithelium Kidney Gradient Culture PDF 88 Research paper Tippe A, Heinzmann U, Roth C (2002). Deposition of fine and ultrafine aerosol particles during exposure at the air / cell interface. Aerosol Science 33:2007-218. Epithelial tissue Lung Environmental health PDF 87 Technical note Minuth WW, Schumacher K, Strehl R, de Vries U (2001). Epithelia - Biomaterials - Tissue engineering. BIOforum International 2: 74-76. Epithelium Kidney Tissue engineering PDF 86 Patent Minuth WW (2001). Patent Nr. US 6 187 053: Process for producing a natural implant.         85 Research paper Schmalz G, Schuster U, Thonemann B, Barth M, Esterbauer S (2001). Dentin barrier test with transfected bovine pulp-derived cells. J Endodontics 27,2:96-102. Connective Tissue Dentin Test of Biomaterials PDF 84 Research paper Kremer M, Lang E, Berger A (2001). Organotypical engineering of differentiated composite-skin equivalents of human keratinocytes in a collagen-GAG matrix (INTEGRA Artifial Skin) in a perfusion culture system. Langenbeck?s Arch Sur 386:357-363. Epithelium Skin Bioengineering PDF 83 Research paper Minuth WW, Strehl R, Schumacher K, de Vries U (2001). Long term culture of epithelia in a continuous fluid gradient for biomaterial testing and tissue engineering. J Biomater Sci Polymer Edn 12,3:353-365. Connective Tissue Kidney Gradient Culture PDF 82 Technical note Bonn E (2000). Organe aus dem Reagenzglas. Via medici 2: 48-51. All tissues Missing regeneration Tissue engineering PDF 81 Research paper Fuß M, Ehlers EM, Russlies M, Rohwedel J, Behrens P (2000). Characteristics of human chondrocytes, osteoblasts and fibroblasts seeded onto a type I/III collagen sponge under different culture conditions. Annals anatomy 182:303-310. Connective Tissue Cartilage Tissue engineering PDF 80 Research paper Duda GN, Haisch A, Endres M, Gebert C, Schroeder D, Hoffmann JE, Sittinger M (2000). Mechanical quality of tissue engineered cartilage: Results after 6 and 12 weeks in vivo. J Biomed Mat Res 53,6:673-677. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 79 Research paper Hoener MC (2000). Role played by sodium in activity-dependent secretion of neutrophins ? revisited. Eur J Neuroscience 12:3096-3106. Nervous tissue Brain Pharmacology PDF 78 Research paper Kloth S, Kobuch K, Domokos J, Wanke C, Monzer J (2000). Polar application of test substances in an organotypic environment and under continous medium flow: a new tissue-based test concept for a broad range of applications in pharmacotoxicity. Toxicology in vitro 14:265-274. Vascular System Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 77 Research paper Kloth S, Suter-Crazzolara C (2000). Modulation of renal blood vessel formation by glial cell line derived neurotrophic factor. Microvasular Res 59:190-194. Vascular System Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 76 Research paper Prem C. and  Pelster B (2000). Swimbladder gas gland cells of the European eel cultured in a superfusion system. Methods in Cell Science 22:125-132. Epithelium Barrier Gradient Culture PDF 75 Research paper Minuth WW, Schumacher K, Strehl R, Kloth S (2000). Physiological and cell biological aspects of perfusion culture technique employed to generate differentiated tissues for long term biomaterial testing and tissue engineering. J Biomater Sci Poymer Edn 11,5:495-522. Epithelium Kidney Gradient Culture PDF 74 Research paper Perka C, Schultz O, Sittinger M, Zippel H (2000). Chondrozytentransplantation in PGLA/Polydioxanon-Vliesen. Orthopäde 29:112-119. Connective Tissue Cartilage Tissue Engineering PDF 73 Research paper Kloth S, Kobuch K, Domokos J, Wanke Ch, Minuth WW (1999). Interaktive Tissue Culture Systems: Innovative Tools for Toxicity Testing. BIOforum International 3: 70-72. Epithelium Kidney Toxicity testing PDF 72 Patent Minuth WW (1999). Patent Nr. DE 196 48 876: Verfahren zum Herstellen eines natürlichen Implantates.         71 Research paper Rotter N, Aigner J, Naumann A (1999). Behaviour of tissue-engineered human cartilage after transplantation into nude mice. J Mat Sci: Materials in Medicine 10:689-693. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 70 Research paper Reischl J, Prelle K, Schol H, Neumuller C, Einspanier R, Sinowatz F, Wolf E (1999). Factors affecting proliferation and dedifferentiation of primary oviduct epithelial cells in vitro. Cell Tissue Res 296:371-383. Epithelium Female Reproductive System Improved Tissue Culture PDF 69 Research paper Griesbeck O, Canossa M, Campana G, Gärtner A, Hoener MC, Nawa H, Kolbeck R, Thoenen H (1999). Are there differences between the secretion characteristics of NGF and BDNF? Implications fort he modulatory role of neurotrophins in activity-dependent neuronal plasticity. Microscopy Res Technique 45:262-275. Nervous tissue Transmitter Pharmacology PDF 68 Research paper Schumacher K, Strehl, R, Kloth S, Tauc M, Minuth WW (1999). The influence of culture media on embryonic renal CD cell differentiation. In vitro Cell Dev Biol Animal 35:465-471. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 67 Research paper Minuth WW, Steiner P, Strehl R, Schumacher K, de Vries U, Kloth S (1999). Modulation of cell differentiation in perfusion culture. Exptl. Nephrology 7:394-406. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 66 Research paper Schmalz G, Schuster U, Nuetzel K, Schweikl H (1999). An in vitro pulp chamber with three-dimensional cell cultures. J Endodontics 24-29. Connective Tissue Dentin Test of Biomaterials PDF 65 Research paper Kreklau B, Sittinger M, Mensing MB, Voight C, Berger G, Burmester GR, Rahmanzahdeh R, Gross U (1999). Tissue engineering of biphasic joint cartilage transplants. Biomaterials 20:1743-1749. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 64 Research paper Jülich WD, Hanschke R, Alitari N (1998). Schonende Sterilisation von biologisch aktiven Implantaten. Hyg Med 23,11:465-472.       PDF 63 Research paper Kloth S, Eckert E, Klein S, Monzer J, Wanke C, Minuth WW (1998). Gastric epithelium under organotypic perfusion culture. In vitro Cell Dev Biol Animal 34:515-517. Epithelium Digestive Tract Improved Tissue Culture PDF 62 Research paper Ramsauer M, Kunz J, Krause D, Dermietzel R (1998). Regulation of blood-brain  barrier –specific enzymes expressed by cerebral pericytes (pericytic aminopeptidase N/pAPN) under cell culture conditions. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab 18(11):1270-81. Nervous tissue Blood brain barrier Pharmacology PDF 61 Research paper Kloth S, Gerdes, J, Wanke C, Minuth WW (1998). Basic fibroblast factor is a morphogenic modulator in kidney vessel development. Kidney Int 53:970-978. Vascular Tissue Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 60 Research paper Rotter N, Aigner J, Naumann A, Planck H, Hammer C, Burmester G, Sittinger M (1998). Cartilage reconstruction in head and neck surgery: comparison of resorbable polymer scaffolds for tissue engineering. J Biomed Mat Res 42:347-356. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 59 Research paper Minuth WW, Sittinger M, Kloth S (1998). Tissue engineering - Generation of differentiated artificial tissues for biomedical applications. Cell Tissue Res 291:1-11. Epithelium/ Connective Tissue/ Vascular Tissue     PDF 58 Patent Minuth WW (1998). Patent Japan Nr. 329 434/95: Kammer zur Kultivierung von   Zellen, insbesondere Mikroskopkammer.         57 Technical note Minuth WW, Strehl R, Kloth S (1997). Von der Zellkultur zum Tissue engineering. Bioscope 4/5: 19-24. All tissues Cell/ Tissue simulation Improved culture technique PDF 56 Technical note Roßteuscher J (1997). Neue Zellen fürs Labor. Aviso 2: 36-38. All tissues Cell/ Tissue simulation Tissue engineering PDF 55 Patent Minuth WW (1997). US- Patenterteilung Nr. 5 665 599: Chamber for Cultivating Cells.         54 Research paper Minuth WW, Steiner P, Strehl R, Kloth S, Tauc M (1997). Electrolyte environment modulates differentiation in embryonic renal collecting duct epithelia. Exp Nephrol 5:414-422. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 53 Research paper Schultz O, Keyszer G, Zacher J, Sittinger M, Burmester GR (1997). Development of an in vitro model system for destructive joint diseases. Arthritis and Rheumatism 40:1420-1428. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 52 Research paper Lehmann P, Kloth S, Aigner J, Dammer R, Minuth W (1997). Lebende Langzeitkonservierung von humaner Gingiva in der Perfusionskultur. Mund Kiefer GesichtsChir 1:26-30. Epithelium Gingiva Improved Tissue Culture PDF 51 Research paper Steiner P, Strehl R, Kloth S, Tauc M, Minuth WW (1997). In vitro development and preservation of specific features of collecting duct epithelial cells from embryonic rabbit kidney are regulated by the electrolyte environment. Differentiation 62:193-202. Epithelium Kidney Gradient Culture PDF 50 Research paper Strehl R, Kloth S, Aigner J, Steiner P, Minuth WW (1997). P CD Amp 1, a new antigen at the interface of the embryonic collecting duct epithelium and the nephrogenic mesenchym. Kidney Int 52:1469-1477. Epithelium and Mesenchyme Kidney Gradient Culture PDF 49 Research paper Sittinger M, Schulz O, Keyszer G, Minuth WW, Burmester GR (1997). Artificial connective tissues in perfusion culture. Int J Artificial Org 20:57-62. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 48 Research paper Minuth WW, Aigner J, Kubat B, Kloth S (1997). Improved differentiation of renal tubular epithelium in vitro: Potential for tissue engineering. Exp Nephrol 5:10-17. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 47 Research paper Minuth WW, Aigner J, Kloth S, Steiner P, Tauc M, Jennings ML (1997). Culture of embryonic renal collecting duct epithelia in a gradient container. Pediatr Nephrol 11:140-147. Epithelium Kidney Gradient Culture PDF 46 Research paper Canossa M, Griesbeck O, Berninger B, Campana G, Kolbeck R, Thoenen H (1997). Neurotrophin release by neurotrophins: Implication for activity-dependent neuronal plasticity. Proc. Natl Acad Sci 94:13279-13286. Nervous Tissue Mesencephalon Improved Tissue Culture PDF 45 Minuth WW, Kloth S, Aigner J, Röckl W (1996). Approach to an organo-typical environment for cultured cells and tissues. Biotechniques 20: 498-501. All tissues Missing regeneration Tissue engineering PDF 44 Technical note Minuth WW, Sittinger M, Kloth S (1996). Tissue engineering - Herstellung von künstlichen Geweben für die Biomedizin. Bioscope 4, 5: 36-41. All tissues Cell/ Tissue simulation Tissue engineering PDF 43 Patent Minuth WW (1996). Patent Nr. 195 30 55.6: Verfahren zur Kultivation von Zellen, insbesondere Organzellen des menschlichen und tierischen Körpers.         42 Research paper Blöchl A, Sirrenberg C (1996). Neurothrophins stimulate the release of dopamine from rat mesencephalic neurons via Trk and p75Lntr receptors. J Biological Chemistry 271,35:21100-21107. Nervous Tissue Mesencephalon Improved Tissue Culture PDF 41 Research paper Gueven N., Glatthaar B.,  Manke H.G., Haemmerle H. (1996). Co-cultivation of rat pneumocytes and bovine endothelial cells on a liquid-air interface. Eur Respir J 9:968-975. Epithelium Lung Gradient Culture PDF 40 Research paper Schmalz G, Garhammer P, Schweiki H (1996). A commercially available cell culture device modified for dentin barrier tests. J Endodontics 22,5:249-252. Connective Tissue Dentin Test of Biomaterials PDF 39 Press release XX (1995). Ohren aus der Retorte. Spiegel 17: 234-238. All tissues Cell/ Tissue simulation Tissue engineering PDF 38 Press release Kuhn L (1995). Transplantate - Kultivierte Nase. Wirtschaftswoche 18: 112-115. All tissues Cell/ Tissue simulation Tissue engineering PDF 37 Technical note Minuth WW, Kloth S, Aigner J, Steiner P (1995). MINUSHEET - Perfusionskultur: Simulierung eines gewebetypischen Milieus. Bioscope 3, 4: 20-25. All tissues Cell/ Tissue simulation Improved tissue culture technique PDF 36 Patent Minuth WW (1995). Patent Nr. P 44 43 902: Kammer zur Kultivierung von Zellen, insbesondere Mikroskopkammer.         35 Research paper Sittinger M, Buija J, Rotter N, Reitzel D, Minuth WW, Burmester GR (1996). Tissue engineering and autologous transplant formation. Biomaterials 17:237-242. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 34 Research paper Aigner J, Kloth S, Minuth WW (1995). Transitional differentiation pattern of principal and intercalated cells during renal collecting duct development. Epith Cell Biol 4:121-130. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 33 Research paper Bujia J, Rotter N, Minuth WW, Burmester GR, Hammer C, Sittinger M (1995). Züchtung menschlichen Knorpelgewebes in einer Perfusionskulturkammer. Laryngo Rhino Otol 74:559-563. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 32 Research paper Kloth S, Ebenbeck C, Kubitza M, Schmidbauer A, Weich HA, Minuth WW (1995). Stimulation of renal microvasculature development under organotypical culture conditions. FASEBJ 9:963-967. Vascular System Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 31 Research paper Kloth S, Kubitza M, Röckl W, Schmidbauer A, Gerdes J, Moll R, Minuth WW (1995). Development of renal podocytes cultured under medium perifusion. Lab Invest 73:294-301. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 30 Research paper Bujia J (1995). Die Züchtung von autologem Knorpelgewebe für die rekonstruktive chirurgie: Möglichkeiten und Grenzen. Laryngo Rhino Otol 74:205-210. Connective Tissue Cartilage Improved Tissue Culture PDF 29 Research paper Sittinger M (1995). Tissue Engineering: Künstlicher Gewebeersatz aus vitalen Komponenten. Laryngo Rhino Otol 74:695-699. Connective Tissue Cartilage Improved Tissue Culture PDF 28 Research paper Bujia J, Sittinger M, Minuth WW, Hammer C, Burmester G, Kastenbauer E (1995). Engineering of cartilage tissue using bioresorbable polymer fleeces and perfusion culture. Acta Otolaryngol 115:307-310. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 27 Book Minuth WW, Aigner J, Kubat B, Kloth S, Röckl W, Kubitza M (1995). In vitro Alternativen zum Tierversuch - Möglichkeiten und Probleme, Pabst Verlag, pp 76-87.       PDF 26 Technical note Minuth WW (1994). Kultivierte Zellen - Eine neue Technik zur Simulierung eines organspezifischen Milieus. Blick in die Wissenschaft 5:30-33. All tissues Cell/ Tissue simulation Tissue engineering PDF 25 Technical note Minuth WW (1994).  Perfusionszellkultur - eine neue Methode für organspezifische, pathologische und toxikologische Fragestellungen. MTA 9: 10-13. All tissues Cell/ Tissue simulation Improved tissue culture technique PDF 24 Research paper Bujia J, Sittinger M, Hammer C, Burmester G (1994). Züchtung menschlichen Knorpelgewebes mit Hilfe einer Perfusionskammer. Laryngo Rhino Otol 73:577-580. Connective Tissue Cartilage Improved Tissue Culture PDF 23 Patent Minuth WW (1994). US - Patent 5, 316, 945: Cell carrier arrangement.         22 Patent Minuth WW (1994). Patent Nr. P 42 00 446: Zellträgeranordnung.         21 Research paper Aigner J, Kloth S, Dermietzel R, Minuth WW (1994). Maturation of renal collecting duct cells in vivo and under perfusion culture. Epithelial Cell Biol 3:70-78. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 20 Book Minuth WW (1994). MINUSHEET - Mehr Effizienz beiZellkulturen. Fremdstoffmetabolismus und Klinische Pharmakologie - Eds. Dengler und Mutschler, Gustav Fischer Verlag, pp. 197-205.       PDF 19   Minuth WW, Kloth S, Aigner J, Sittinger M, Röckl W (1994). Organ-spezifisches Environment für kultivierte Zellen und Gewebe. BIOFORUM 17:412-416.       PDF 18 Research paper Sittinger M, Buija J, Minuth WW, Hammer C, Burmester GR (1994). Engineering of cartilage tissue using bioresorbable polymer carriers in perfusion culture. Biomaterials 15:451-456. Connective Tissue Cartilage Bioengineering PDF 17 Research paper Kloth S, Schmidbauer A, Kubitza M, Minuth WW (1994). Developing renal microvasculature can be maintained under perfusion culture conditions. Eur J Cell Biol 63:84-95. Vascular System Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 16 Research paper Minuth WW, Majer V, Kloth S, Dermietzel R (1994). Growth of MDCK cells on non-transparent supports. In vitro Cell Dev Biol 30A:12-14. Epithelium Kidney Test of Biomaterials PDF 15   Minuth WW (1993). Gebrauchsmuster G 89 08 58.3: Träger für die Zellkultivation.         14 Patent Minuth WW (1993). US-Patent 5,190,878: Apparatus for cultivating cells.         13 Book Minuth WW (1993). Die Kultur von Epithelzellen unter organtypischen Bedingungen. Alternativen zu Tierversuchen in Ausbildung, Qualitätskontrolle und Herz- Kreislaufforschung. Springer Verlag Wien - New York: pp 238-245.       PDF 12 Research paper Minuth WW, Fietzek W, Kloth S, Aigner J, Röckl W, Kubitza M, Dermietzel R (1993). Aldosterone modulates the development of PNA binding cell isoforms within renal collecting duct epithelium kept in perfusion culture. Kidney Int 44: 337-344. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 11 Research paper Herter P, Laube G, Gronczewski J, Minuth WW (1993). Silver enhanced colloidal gold labelling of rabbit kidney collecting duct cell surfaces imaged by SEM. J Microscopy 171:107-115. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 10 Patent Minuth WW, Stöckl G (1992/1995). Gebrauchsmuster und Patent Nr. G 9107 283.2 / DE 42 08 805 C2: Vorrichtung zur Behandlung, insbesondere zur Kultivierung von Biomaterial mit wenigstens einem Behandlungsmedium.         9 Research paper Minuth WW, Dermietzel R, Kloth S, Henerkes B (1992). A new method culturing renal cells under permanent perfusion and producing a luminal-basal medium gradient. Kidney Int 41:215-219. Epithelium Kidney Gradient Culture PDF 8   Minuth WW (1992). MINUSHEET - ein neuer Weg zur organspezifischen Zellkultur. Spektrum der Wissenschaften 11:15-17.       PDF 7 Research paper Minuth WW, Stöckl G, Kloth S, Dermietzel R (1992). Construction of an apparatus for cell and tissue cultures which enables in vitro experiments under organo-typical conditions. Eur J Cell Biol 57:132-137. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 6 Press release Minuth WW (1991). Erster Schritt auf dem Weg zur künstlichen Leber. Ärztliche Praxis 98:27-29. Epithelium Liver Tissue engineering PDF 5 Research paper Minuth WW (1991). Eine neue Kulturmethode für anhaftende Zellen unter natürlichen Bedingungen. ALTEX 15:18-30. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF 4   Minuth WW (1991). MINUSHEET - eine neue Methode um differenzierte Zellen unter nahezu natürlichen Bedingungen zu kultivieren. Bioengineering 5:66-69.       PDF 3 Press release Minuth WW (1990). Prof. Minuth geht neue Wege bei der Kultivation von hochspezialisierten Zellen. Regensburger Universitätszeitung 6:7-9. All tissue Cell/ Tissue simulation Tissue engineering PDF 2 Patent Minuth WW (1990). Patent Nr. DE-PS 3923279: Methode zur Kultivierung von Zellen.         1 Research paper Minuth WW, Rudolph U (1990). A compatible support system for cell culture in biomedical research. Cyto Technology 4:181-189. Epithelium Kidney Improved Tissue Culture PDF back to homepage</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Minuth/english/research.html</field>
<field name="title">Research</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Minuth/english/research.html</field>
<field name="content">Research Research back to homepage Tissue engineering 1. The Base The MINUSHEET, a cell carrier, was developed to improve the anchorage and thereby the differentiation of cultured cells and tissues. (The MINUSHEET perfusion culture system is protected by national and international patents.) The cell carrier consists of a black holder ring, in which an individually selected support material is placed by yourself. Commercially available cell supports such as glas, foils, filters, nets and stuffs with a diameter of 13 or 47 mm can be used. By the white span ring the support is fixed. The cell carrier is autoclaved and transferred to a dish to adhere the cells. a b c Fig.1 a,b,c: The cell carriers are available in different forms and functions. They area easy to handle. 2. Organo-Typical Cultures The cell carriers are placed into culture containers, which are permanently perfused with medium. This method improves the nutritional needs for the cells, eliminates the harmful metabolic products and stabilizes the level of paracrine factors. a b Fig.2a: Perfusion container for the generation of artificial tissue. Once the cells grow on a suitable matirx the cell carrier are placed into culture containers, which are permanently perfused with medium. Fig.2b: Fluid exchange in a perfusion container. With 1 ml/h a complete exchange lasts about 3h. Epithelial cells are kept in a gradient culture container. Different media can be perfused at the upper and lower side of the cells as observed under the natural environment. It helps the epithelia to polarize and to develop excellent features. a b Fig.3a: Gradient culture container. b: Complete setup. Fig. 4: In a gradient culture container different media can be perfused at the upper and lower side of the cells as observed under the natural environment. To observe the cells during perfusion culture under the inverse microscope with phase contrast optics a new container was developed. It allows the culture either on the interchangeable glas lids or on the cell carrier. Because the carrier separates the chamber into two parts, the same or different media can be perfused through the upper and lower part of the chamber. 3. The Advantages The newly developed perfusion culture system made experiments on cells and tissues possible which failed in conventional dishes. Advantages are: the selection of a variety of cell supports individual influence on the differentiation of cells perfusion of the cultures with always fresh media microscopical observation long term culture tissue engineering for surgical implantation testing of biomaterials 4, The Result Harvesting of cultured cells and tissues in an quality not observed before. Tissue Factory (PDF) Recent Literature  W.W. Minuth, R. Strehl (2007) Technical and theoretical considerations about gradient perfusion culture for epithelia used in tissue engineering, biomaterial testing and pharmaceutical research. Biomed. Mater. 2:R1-R11.(PDF) W.W. Minuth, L. Denk, A. Roessger (2009). Gradient perfusion culture - Simulating a tissue-specific environment for epithelia in biomedicine. J Epithelial Biology &amp; Pharmacology 2:1-13.(PDF) W.W. Minuth, L. Denk, A. Glashauser (2010). A modular culture system for the generation of multiple specialized tissues. Biomaterials 11:2945-2954.(PDF) Available Tools for Tissue Engineering in cooperation with BioRegio Regensburg MINUCELLS and MINUTISSUE Vertriebs GmbH Starenstrasse 2 D-93077 Bad Abbach Tel: 49 (0)9405 962440 Fax: 49 (0)9405 962441 minucells.minutissue@t-online.de back to homepage</field>
<field name="important">Research Research back to homepage Tissue engineering 1. The Base The MINUSHEET, a cell carrier, was developed to improve the anchorage and thereby the differentiation of cultured cells and tissues. (The MINUSHEET perfusion culture system is protected by national and international patents.) The cell carrier consists of a black holder ring, in which an individually selected support material is placed by yourself. Commercially available cell supports such as glas, foils, filters, nets and stuffs with a diameter of 13 or 47 mm can be used. By the white span ring the support is fixed. The cell carrier is autoclaved and transferred to a dish to adhere the cells. a b c Fig.1 a,b,c: The cell carriers are available in different forms and functions. They area easy to handle. 2. Organo-Typical Cultures The cell carriers are placed into culture containers, which are permanently perfused with medium. This method improves the nutritional needs for the cells, eliminates the harmful metabolic products and stabilizes the level of paracrine factors. a b Fig.2a: Perfusion container for the generation of artificial tissue. Once the cells grow on a suitable matirx the cell carrier are placed into culture containers, which are permanently perfused with medium. Fig.2b: Fluid exchange in a perfusion container. With 1 ml/h a complete exchange lasts about 3h. Epithelial cells are kept in a gradient culture container. Different media can be perfused at the upper and lower side of the cells as observed under the natural environment. It helps the epithelia to polarize and to develop excellent features. a b Fig.3a: Gradient culture container. b: Complete setup. Fig. 4: In a gradient culture container different media can be perfused at the upper and lower side of the cells as observed under the natural environment. To observe the cells during perfusion culture under the inverse microscope with phase contrast optics a new container was developed. It allows the culture either on the interchangeable glas lids or on the cell carrier. Because the carrier separates the chamber into two parts, the same or different media can be perfused through the upper and lower part of the chamber. 3. The Advantages The newly developed perfusion culture system made experiments on cells and tissues possible which failed in conventional dishes. Advantages are: the selection of a variety of cell supports individual influence on the differentiation of cells perfusion of the cultures with always fresh media microscopical observation long term culture tissue engineering for surgical implantation testing of biomaterials 4, The Result Harvesting of cultured cells and tissues in an quality not observed before. Tissue Factory (PDF) Recent Literature  W.W. Minuth, R. Strehl (2007) Technical and theoretical considerations about gradient perfusion culture for epithelia used in tissue engineering, biomaterial testing and pharmaceutical research. Biomed. Mater. 2:R1-R11.(PDF) W.W. Minuth, L. Denk, A. Roessger (2009). Gradient perfusion culture - Simulating a tissue-specific environment for epithelia in biomedicine. J Epithelial Biology &amp; Pharmacology 2:1-13.(PDF) W.W. Minuth, L. Denk, A. Glashauser (2010). A modular culture system for the generation of multiple specialized tissues. Biomaterials 11:2945-2954.(PDF) Available Tools for Tissue Engineering in cooperation with BioRegio Regensburg MINUCELLS and MINUTISSUE Vertriebs GmbH Starenstrasse 2 D-93077 Bad Abbach Tel: 49 (0)9405 962440 Fax: 49 (0)9405 962441 minucells.minutissue@t-online.de back to homepage</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Minuth/english/staff.html</field>
<field name="title">Staff</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Minuth/english/staff.html</field>
<field name="content">Staff Staff back to homepage Lucia Denk Room: Vkl 3.1.23 Tel.: ++49 941 943-2874 e-mail: lucia.denk@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Christian Miess Room: Vkl 3.1.25 Tel.: ++49 941 943-2879 n.n. Room: Vkl 3.1.25 Tel.: ++49 941 943-2874 back to homepage</field>
<field name="important">Staff Staff back to homepage Lucia Denk Room: Vkl 3.1.23 Tel.: ++49 941 943-2874 e-mail: lucia.denk@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Christian Miess Room: Vkl 3.1.25 Tel.: ++49 941 943-2879 n.n. Room: Vkl 3.1.25 Tel.: ++49 941 943-2874 back to homepage</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Ohlmann/index.html</field>
<field name="title">PD Dr. Andreas Ohlmann</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Ohlmann/index.html</field>
<field name="content">PD Dr. Andreas Ohlmann PD Dr. Andreas Ohlmann       Home      Staff      Research      Curriculum Vitae      Teaching      Publications      FOR 1075   AG Ohlmann / The Ohlmann Group Our group is integrated in the Institute of Human Anatomy and Embryology at the University of Regensburg.  </field>
<field name="important">PD Dr. Andreas Ohlmann PD Dr. Andreas Ohlmann       Home      Staff      Research      Curriculum Vitae      Teaching      Publications      FOR 1075   AG Ohlmann / The Ohlmann Group Our group is integrated in the Institute of Human Anatomy and Embryology at the University of Regensburg.  </field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Tamm/Galery/index.html</field>
<field name="title">Bilder Rundgang - Lehrstuhl Tamm</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Tamm/Galery/index.html</field>
<field name="content">Bilder Rundgang - Lehrstuhl Tamm Bilder Rundgang - Lehrstuhl Tamm &amp;lt;BODY&amp;gt; Viewing this page requires a browser capable of displaying frames. &amp;lt;/BODY&amp;gt;</field>
<field name="important">Bilder Rundgang - Lehrstuhl Tamm Bilder Rundgang - Lehrstuhl Tamm &amp;lt;BODY&amp;gt; Viewing this page requires a browser capable of displaying frames. &amp;lt;/BODY&amp;gt;</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Tamm/Info/index.html</field>
<field name="title">NWF III - Universität Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Tamm/Info/index.html</field>
<field name="content">NWF III - Universität Regensburg NWF III - Universität Regensburg      Staff      Research      FOR1075      Publications      Teaching      Gallery      Info      Links</field>
<field name="important">NWF III - Universität Regensburg NWF III - Universität Regensburg      Staff      Research      FOR1075      Publications      Teaching      Gallery      Info      Links</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Tamm/Publications/index.html</field>
<field name="title">NWF III - Universit?t Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Tamm/Publications/index.html</field>
<field name="content">NWF III - Universit?t Regensburg NWF III - Universit?t Regensburg      Staff      Research      FOR1075      Publications      Teaching      Gallery      Info      Links Publications Seitz R, Ohlmann A, Tamm ER. (2013) The role of M?ller glia and microglia in glaucoma. Cell Tissue Res. 2013 Jun 19. [Epub ahead of print] ( PubMed) Pollinger K, Hennig R, Ohlmann A, Fuchshofer R, Wenzel R, Breunig M, Tessmar J, Tamm ER, Goepferich A (2013) Ligand-functionalized nanoparticles target endothelial cells in retinal capillaries after systemic application. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 110:6115-20 ( PubMed) Seitz R., Tamm E.R. (2013). N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA)-mediated excitotoxic damage: A mouse model of acute retinal ganglion cell damage. Methods Mol. Biol. 935, 99-109. ( PubMed) Braunger B.M., Ohlmann A., Koch M., Tanimoto N., Volz C., Yang Y., B?sl M.R., Cvekl A., J?gle H., Seeliger M.W., Tamm E.R. (2012). Constitutive overexpression of Norrin activates Wnt/?-catenin and endothelin-2 signaling to protect photoreceptors from light damage. Neurobiol. Dis. 50, 1-12. ( PubMed) Herrnberger L., Ebner K., Junglas B., Tamm E.R. (2012). The role of plasmalemma vesicle-associated protein (PLVAP) in endothelial cells of Schlemm's canal and ocular capillaries. Exp. Eye Res. 105, 27-33 ( PubMed) Tamm E.R., Ohlmann A. (2012) Entwicklung des menschlichen Auges. [Development of the human eye]. Ophthalmologe, 109, 911-28. ( PubMed) Herrnberger L., Seitz R., Kuespert S. B?sl M.R., Fuchshofer R., Tamm E.R. (2012). Lack of endothelial diaphragms in fenestrae and caveolae of mutant Plvap-deficient mice. Histochem Cell Biol. 138,709-24. ( PubMed) Junglas B., Kuespert S., Seleem A.A., Struller T., Ullmann S., B?sl M., Bosserhoff A., K?stler J., Wagner R., Tamm E.R., Fuchshofer R. Connective tissue growth factor causes glaucoma by modifying the actin cytoskeleton of the trabecular meshwork. Am J Pathol. 2012 Jun;180(6):2386-403. Epub 2012 Apr 26. ( PubMed) Ohlmann A., Tamm E.R. (2012). Norrin: Molecular and functional properties of an angiogenic and neuroprotective growth factor. Prog Retin Eye Res., 31, 243-257. ( PubMed) Braunger B.M., Tamm E.R. (2012). The different functions of norrin. Adv. Exp. Med. Biol., 723, 679-683. ( PubMed) Fr?b F., Bremer M., Finzsch M., Kichko T., Reeh P., Tamm E.R., Charnay P., Wegner M. (2012). Establishment of myelinating schwann cells and barrier integrity between central and peripheral nervous systems depend on Sox10. Glia, 60, 806-819. ( PubMed) Fuchshofer R., Tamm E.R. (2012).The role of TGF-? in the pathogenesis of primary open-angle glaucoma. Cell Tissue Res., 347, 279-290. ( PubMed) Fuchshofer R. (2011) The pathogenic role of transforming growth factor-?2 in glaucomatous damage to the optic nerve head. Exp Eye Res. Aug, 93(2):165-9 ( PubMed) Sippl C., Bosserhoff A.K., Fischer D., Tamm E.R. Depletion of optineurin in RGC-5 cells derived from retinal neurons causes apoptosis and reduces the secretion of neurotrophins. Exp Eye Res. 2011 Aug 27. (PubMed) Fuchshofer R., Ullmann S., Zeilbeck L.F., Baumann M., Junglas B., Tamm E.R. (2011) Connective tissue growth factor modulates podocyte actin cytoskeleton and extracellular matrix synthesis and is induced in podocytes upon injury. Histochem Cell Biol., Aug 4. (PubMed) Braig S., Wallner S, Junglas B., Fuchshofer R,, Bosserhoff A.K. (2011) CTGF is overexpressed in malignant melanoma and promotes cell invasion and migration. Br J Cancer. Jul 12;105(2):231-8. (PubMed) Ohlmann A., Merkl R., Tamm E.R. (2011). Focus on Molecules: Norrin. Exp. Eye Res.,Jun 30. (PubMed) Tamm E.R. (2011). Entwicklung des Kammerwinkels und kongenitales Glaukom [Development of the iridocorneal angle and congenital glaucoma]. Ophthalmologe, 108, 610-617. (PubMed) Kritzenberger M., Junglas B., Framme C., Helbig H., Gabel V.-P., Fuchshofer R., Tamm E.R., Hillenkamp J. (2011). Different collagen types define two types of idiopathic epiretinal membranes. Histopathology, ;58, 953-965. (PubMed) Gallenberger M, Meinel DM, Kroeber M, Wegner M, Milkereit P, Boesl MR, Tamm ER. Lack of WDR36 leads to preimplantation embryonic lethality in mice and delays the formation of small subunit ribosomal RNA in human cells in vitro. Hum Mol Genet. 2011 Feb 1;20(3):422-35. Epub 2010 Nov 3. (PubMed) Fuchshofer R, Kottler UB, Ohlmann AV, Schloetzer-Schrehardt U, Juenemann A, Kruse FE, Ohlmann A. SPARC is expressed in scars of the Tenon's capsule and mediates scarring properties of human Tenon's fibroblasts in vitro. Mol Vis. 2011 Jan 19;17:177-85. (PubMed) Bohr D., Koch M., Kritzenberger M., Fuchshofer R., Tamm E.R. (2011) Increased expression of olfactomedin-1 and myocilin in podocytes during puromycin aminonucleoside nephrosis. Nephrology Dialysis Transplantation Jan;26(1):83-92 (PubMed) Karlstetter M., Walczak Y., Weigelt K., Ebert .S, Van den Brulle J., Schwer H., Fuchshofer R., Langmann T. (2010) The novel activated microglia/macrophage WAP domain protein, AMWAP, acts as a counter-regulator of proinflammatory response, J Immunol. Sep 15;185(6):3379-90. (PubMed) Kroeber M, Davis N, Holzmann S, Kritzenberger M, Shelah-Goraly M, Ofri R, Ashery-Padan R, Tamm ER. Reduced Expression of Pax6 in Lens and Cornea of Mutant Mice Leads to Failure of Chamber Angle Development and Juvenile Glaucoma. Hum Mol Genet. 2010 Jun 10. (PubMed) Finzsch M, Schreiner S, Kichko T, Reeh P, Tamm ER, B?sl MR, Meijer D, Wegner M. Sox10 is required for Schwann cell identity and progression beyond the immature Schwann cell stage. J Cell Biol. 2010 May 17;189(4):701-12. (PubMed) Seitz R, Hackl S, Seibuchner T, Tamm ER, Ohlmann A. Norrin mediates neuroprotective effects on retinal ganglion cells via activation of the Wnt/beta-catenin signaling pathway and the induction of neuroprotective growth factors in Muller cells. J Neurosci. 2010 Apr 28;30(17):5998-6010. (PubMed) Ohlmann A, Seitz R, Braunger B, Seitz D, B?sl MR, Tamm ER. (2010). Norrin promotes vascular regrowth after oxygen-induced retinal vessel loss and suppresses retinopathy in mice. J Neurosci. 2010 Jan 6;30(1):183-93.(PubMed)Dirscherl K., Karlstetter M., Ebert .S, Kraus D., Hlawatsch J., Walczak Y., Moehle C., Fuchshofer R., Langmann T. (2010) Luteolin triggers global changes in the microglial transcriptome leading to a unique anti-inflammatory and neuroprotective phenotype, J Neuroinflammation. Jan 14;7(1):3. ( PubMed) Konz DD, Fl?gel-Koch C, Ohlmann A, Tamm ER. Myocilin in the trabecular meshwork of eyes with primary open-angle glaucoma. (2009). Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol. 2009 Dec;247(12):1643-9. Epub 2009 Aug 7. (PubMed) Goldwich A, Scholz M, Tamm ER. (2009). Myocilin promotes substrate adhesion, spreading and formation of focal contacts in podocytes and mesangial cells. Histochem Cell Biol. 2009 Feb;131(2):167-80. Epub 2008 Oct 15. (PubMed) Wolf L.V., Yang Y., Wang J., Xie Q., Braunger B., Tamm E.R., Zavadil J., Cvekl A. (2009). Identification of pax6-dependent gene regulatory networks in the mouse lens. PLoS ONE 4, e4159. (PubMed) Tamm E.R., Ethier C.R. (2009). Current aspects of aqueous humor dynamics and glaucoma. Exp. Eye Res. 88. 618-9. (PubMed) Tamm E.R. (2009). The trabecular meshwork outflow pathways: structural and functional aspects. Exp Eye Res. 88, 648-55 (PubMed) Fuchshofer R., Tamm E.R. (2009). Modulation of extracellular matrix turnover in the trabecular meshwork. Exp. Eye Res. 88, 683-8 (PubMed) Fuchshofer R., Stephan D.A., Russell P., Tamm E.R. (2009). Gene expression profiling of TGF?2- and/or BMP7-treated trabecular meshwork cells: Identification of Smad7 as a critical inhibitor of TGF-?2 signaling. Exp. Eye Res. 88, 1020-32 (PubMed) Junglas B., Yu A.H.L., Welge-L?ssen U., Tamm E.R. Fuchshofer R. (2009). Connective tissue growth factor induces extracellular matrix deposition in human trabecular meshwork cells. Exp. Eye Res. 88, 1065-75 (PubMed) Davis N., Yoffe C., Raviv S., Antes R., Berger J., Holzmann S., Stoykova A., Overbeek P.A., Tamm E.R., Ashery-Padan R. (2009). Pax6 dosage requirements in iris and ciliary body differentiation. Dev Biol. 2009 Sep 1;333(1):132-42. Epub 2009 Jun 27 (PubMed) Yu A.L., Fuchshofer R., Kook D., Kampik A., Bloemendal H., Welge-L?ssen U. (2009) Subtoxic oxidative stress induces senescence in retinal pigment epithelial cells via TGF-beta release. IOVS  Feb;50(2):926-35 (PubMed) Tamm E.R. (2008). Molecular Approaches to Glaucoma: Intriguing Clues for Pathology. In: Current Topics in Membranes, The Eye?s Aqueous Humor (Ed. Civan M.M.). Elsevier Inc.  pp. 379-425. Tamm E.R. (2008). The Functional Role of Myocilin in Glaucoma. In: Ophthalmology Research: Mechanisms of the Glaucomas (Eds. Shields M.B., Tombran-Tink J., Barnstable C.J.). Humana Press, Totowa, NJ, pp. 219-231. Tamm E.R., Kellenberger A. (2008). Aqueous Humor Dynamics and Trabecular Meshwork. In: Eye, Retina, and Visual System of the Mouse. III Organization of the Adult Mouse Eye and Central Visual System (Eds. Chalupa L.M., Williams R.W.). MIT Press, p. 129-33. Paper W, Kroeber M, Heersink S, Stephan DA, Fuchshofer R, Russell P, Tamm ER. (2008). Elevated amounts of myocilin in the aqueous humor of transgenic mice cause significant changes in ocular gene expression. Exp. Eye Res. 87:257-67. (PubMed) Wurm A., Sock E., Fuchshofer R., Wegner M., Tamm E.R. (2008). Anterior segment dysgenesis in the eyes of mice deficient for the high-mobility-group transcription factor Sox11. Exp. Eye Res., 86:895-907. (PubMed) Janssen A, Hoellenriegel J, Fogarasi M, Schrewe H, Seeliger M, Tamm E, Ohlmann A, May CA, Weber BH, St?hr H. (2008). Abnormal vessel formation in the choroid of mice lacking tissue inhibitor of metalloprotease-3. Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci.;49:2812-22. (PubMed) Tamm ER, Fuchshofer R. What Increases Outflow Resistance in Primary Open-angle Glaucoma? Surv Ophthalmol. 2007 Nov;52(6 Suppl):S101-4. (PubMed) Pirity MK, Wang WL, Wolf LV, Tamm ER, Schreiber-Agus N, Cvekl A. Rybp, a polycomb complex-associated protein, is required for mouse eye development. BMC Dev Biol. 2007 Apr 30;7:39. (PubMed) Fuchshofer R, Yu AH, Welge-Lussen U, Tamm ER. Bone morphogenetic protein-7 is an antagonist of transforming growth factor-beta2 in human trabecular meshwork cells. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2007 Feb;48(2):715-26. (PubMed) Russell P, Walsh E, Chen W, Goldwich A, Tamm ER. The effect of temperature on gene silencing by siRNAs: implications for silencing in the anterior chamber of the eye. Exp Eye Res. 2006 Jun;82(6):1011-6. (PubMed) Kroeber M, Ohlmann A, Russell P, Tamm ER. Transgenic studies on the role of optineurin in the mouse eye. Exp Eye Res. 2006 Jun;82(6):1075-85. (PubMed) Hinz B, Rosch S, Ramer R, Tamm ER, Brune K. Latanoprost induces matrix metalloproteinase-1 expression in human nonpigmented ciliary epithelial cells through a cyclooxygenase-2-dependent mechanism. FASEB J. 2005 Nov;19(13):1929-31. (PubMed) Ricard CS, Tamm ER. Focus on Molecules: Myocilin/TIGR. Exp Eye Res. 2005 Nov;81(5):501-2. (PubMed) Davis-Silberman N, Kalich T, Oron-Karni V, Marquardt T, Kroeber M, Tamm ER, Ashery-Padan R. Genetic dissection of Pax6 dosage requirements in the developing mouse eye. Hum Mol Genet. 2005 Aug 1;14(15):2265-76. (PubMed) Gottanka J, Kirch W, Tamm ER. The origin of extrinsic nitrergic axons supplying the human eye. J Anat. 2005 Mar;206(3):225-9. (PubMed) Ohlmann A., Scholz M., Goldwich A., Chauhan B.K., Hudl K., Ohlmann A.V., Zrenner E., Berger W., Cvekl A., Seeliger M.W., Tamm E.R. (2005). Ectopic norrin induces growth of ocular capillaries and restores normal retinal angiogenesis in Norrie disease mutant mice. J. Neurosci. 2005 25, 1701-1710. (PubMed) Friedrich R.P., Schlierf B., Tamm E.R., Bosl M.R., Wegner M. (2005) The class III POU domain protein Brn-1 can fully replace the related Oct-6 during Schwann cell development and myelination. Mol. Cell. Biol. 25, 1821-9. (PubMed) Zillig M., Wurm A., Grehn F.J., Russell P., Tamm E.R. (2005) Overexpression and properties of wild-type and Tyr437His mutated myocilin in the eyes of transgenic mice. Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci. 46, 223-34. (PubMed) Goldwich A., Baulmann D.C., Ohlmann A., Fl?gel-Koch C., Sch?cklmann H., Tamm E.R. (2005). Myocilin is expressed in the glomerulus of the kidney and induced in mesangioproliferative glomerulonephritis. Kidney Int., 67, 140-151. (PubMed) Tamm E.R., Carassa R.G., Albert D.M., Gabelt B.T., Patel S., Rasmussen C.A., Kaufman P.L. (2004). Viscocanalostomy in rhesus monkeys. Arch. Ophthalmol., 122, 1826-1838. (PubMed) Fl?gel-Koch C., Ohlmann A., Fuchshofer R., Welge-L?ssen U., Tamm E.R. (2004). Thrombospondin-1 in the trabecular meshwork: localization in normal and glaucomatous eyes, and induction by TGF-beta1 and dexamethasone in vitro. Exp. Eye Res., 79, 649-663. (PubMed) Sock E., Rettig S.D., Enderich J., Bosl M.R., Tamm E.R., Wegner M. (2004) Gene targeting reveals a widespread role for the high-mobility-group transcription factor Sox11 in tissue remodeling. Mol. Cell Biol., 24, 6635-6644. (PubMed) Cvekl A., Tamm E.R. (2004). Anterior eye development and ocular mesenchyme: New insights from mouse models and human diseases. Bioessays, 26, 378-386. (PubMed) Knaupp, C., Fl?gel-Koch C., Goldwich A., Ohlmann, A., Tamm E.R. (2004) The expression of myocilin during murine eye development. Graefe?s Arch. Clin. Exp. Ophthalmol., 242, 339-45 . (PubMed) Santas A.J., Bahler C., Peterson J.A., Filla M.S., Kaufman P.L., Tamm E.R., Johnson D., Peters D.P. (2003). The heparin II domain of fibronectin modulates aqueous outflow in cultured anterior segments of human eyes. Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci., 44, 4796-4804. (PubMed) Rhee, D.J., Tamm, E.R., and Russell, P. (2003) Donor corneoscleral buttons: A new source of trabecular meshwork for research. Exp. Eye Res., 77, 749-756. (PubMed) Ohlmann A., Goldwich A., Fl?gel-Koch C., Fuchs A.V., Schwager K., Tamm E.R. (2003). The secreted glycoprotein myocilin is a component of the myelin sheath in peripheral nerves. Glia, 43, 128-140. (PubMed) Goldwich A., Ethier C.R., Chan D. W.-H., Tamm E.R. (2003). Perfusion with the olfactomedin domain of myocilin does not affect outflow facility. Invest. Opthalmol. Vis. Sci., 44, 1953-1961. (PubMed) Baulmann D., Ohlmann A., Fl?gel-Koch C., Goswami S., Cvekl A., Tamm E.R. (2002). Pax6 heterozygous eyes show defects in chamber angle differentiation that are associated with a wide spectrum of other anterior eye segment abnormalities. Mech. Develop. 118, 3-17. (PubMed) Fl?gel-Koch C., Ohlmann A., Piatigorsky J., Tamm E.R. (2002). Disruption of anterior segment development by TGF-beta1 overexpression in the eyes of transgenic mice. Dev. Dyn. 225, 111-125. (PubMed) Weber B.H.W., Schrewe H., Molday L.L., Gehrig A., White K.L., Seeliger M.W., Jaissle G.B., Friedburg C., Tamm E., Molday R.S. (2002). Inactivation of the murine X-linked juvenile retinoschisis gene, rs1h, suggests a role of retinoschisin in retinal cell layer organization and synaptic structure. PNAS, 99, 6222-6227. (PubMed) Rao V., Wawrousek E., Tamm E.R., Zigler S. Jr. (2002). Rho GTPase inactivation impairs lens growth and integrity. Lab. Invest. 82, 231-239. (PubMed) Borr?s T., Rowlette L.L.S., Tamm E.R., Gottanka J., Epstein D.L. (2002). Effects of elevated intraocular pressure on outflow facility and TIGR/MYOC expression in perfused human anterior segments. Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci. 43, 33-40. (PubMed) Tamm E.R. (2002). Myocilin and glaucoma. Facts and ideas. Prog. Ret. Eye Res. 21, 395-428. (PubMed) Ohlmann A., Tamm E.R. (2002). Die Rolle von Myocilin bei der Pathogenese des prim?ren Offenwinkelglaukoms. Der Ophthalmologe, 99, 672-677. (Springer) Tamm E.R., Polansky J. (2001). The TIGR/MYOC gene and glaucoma: opportunities for new understandings. J. Glaucoma, 10(Suppl 1), S9-S12. (PubMed) Brady J.P., Garland D.L., Green D.E., Tamm E.R., Giblin F., Wawrousek E.F. (2001). aB-Crystallin is not essential for development of a transparent lens but may be critical for muscle integrity. Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci., 42, 2924-2932. (PubMed) Maih?fner C., Schl?tzer-Schrehardt U., G?hring H., Zeilhofer H.U., Naumann G.O.H., Tamm E.R., Brune K. (2001). Specific loss of ciliary COX-2 expression in patients with primary open-angle glaucoma. Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci., 42, 2616-2624.  Russell P., Tamm E.R., Grehn F.J., Picht G., Johnson M. (2001). The presence and properties of myocilin in the aqueous humor. Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci., 42, 983-986. (PubMed) Tamm E.R., Russell, P. (2001) The Role of Myocilin/TIGR in Glaucoma. Results of the Glaucoma Research Foundation Catalyst Meeting in Berkeley, CA, March 2000. J. Glaucoma, 10, 329-339. (PubMed) Piatigorsky J., Kozmik Z., Horwitz J., Ding L., Carosa E., Robison W.G.Jr., Steinbach P.J., Tamm E.R. (2000). Omega-crystallin of the scallop lens. A dimeric aldehyde dehydogenase class 1/2 enzyme-crystallin. J. Biol. Chem. 275, 41064-41073. (PubMed) Kirstein L., Cvekl A., Chauhan B.K., Tamm E.R. (2000). Regulation of human myocilin/TIGR gene transcripton in trabecular meshwork cells and astrocytes: Role of upstream stimulatory factor. Genes Cells, 5, 661-676. (PubMed) Karali A., Russell P., Stefani F.H., Tamm E.R. (2000). Localization of myocilin/ trabecular meshwork inducible glucocorticoid response protein in the human eye. Invest. Opthalmol. Vis. Sci., 41, 729-740. (PubMed)</field>
<field name="important">NWF III - Universit?t Regensburg NWF III - Universit?t Regensburg      Staff      Research      FOR1075      Publications      Teaching      Gallery      Info      Links Publications Seitz R, Ohlmann A, Tamm ER. (2013) The role of M?ller glia and microglia in glaucoma. Cell Tissue Res. 2013 Jun 19. [Epub ahead of print] ( PubMed) Pollinger K, Hennig R, Ohlmann A, Fuchshofer R, Wenzel R, Breunig M, Tessmar J, Tamm ER, Goepferich A (2013) Ligand-functionalized nanoparticles target endothelial cells in retinal capillaries after systemic application. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 110:6115-20 ( PubMed) Seitz R., Tamm E.R. (2013). N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA)-mediated excitotoxic damage: A mouse model of acute retinal ganglion cell damage. Methods Mol. Biol. 935, 99-109. ( PubMed) Braunger B.M., Ohlmann A., Koch M., Tanimoto N., Volz C., Yang Y., B?sl M.R., Cvekl A., J?gle H., Seeliger M.W., Tamm E.R. (2012). Constitutive overexpression of Norrin activates Wnt/?-catenin and endothelin-2 signaling to protect photoreceptors from light damage. Neurobiol. Dis. 50, 1-12. ( PubMed) Herrnberger L., Ebner K., Junglas B., Tamm E.R. (2012). The role of plasmalemma vesicle-associated protein (PLVAP) in endothelial cells of Schlemm's canal and ocular capillaries. Exp. Eye Res. 105, 27-33 ( PubMed) Tamm E.R., Ohlmann A. (2012) Entwicklung des menschlichen Auges. [Development of the human eye]. Ophthalmologe, 109, 911-28. ( PubMed) Herrnberger L., Seitz R., Kuespert S. B?sl M.R., Fuchshofer R., Tamm E.R. (2012). Lack of endothelial diaphragms in fenestrae and caveolae of mutant Plvap-deficient mice. Histochem Cell Biol. 138,709-24. ( PubMed) Junglas B., Kuespert S., Seleem A.A., Struller T., Ullmann S., B?sl M., Bosserhoff A., K?stler J., Wagner R., Tamm E.R., Fuchshofer R. Connective tissue growth factor causes glaucoma by modifying the actin cytoskeleton of the trabecular meshwork. Am J Pathol. 2012 Jun;180(6):2386-403. Epub 2012 Apr 26. ( PubMed) Ohlmann A., Tamm E.R. (2012). Norrin: Molecular and functional properties of an angiogenic and neuroprotective growth factor. Prog Retin Eye Res., 31, 243-257. ( PubMed) Braunger B.M., Tamm E.R. (2012). The different functions of norrin. Adv. Exp. Med. Biol., 723, 679-683. ( PubMed) Fr?b F., Bremer M., Finzsch M., Kichko T., Reeh P., Tamm E.R., Charnay P., Wegner M. (2012). Establishment of myelinating schwann cells and barrier integrity between central and peripheral nervous systems depend on Sox10. Glia, 60, 806-819. ( PubMed) Fuchshofer R., Tamm E.R. (2012).The role of TGF-? in the pathogenesis of primary open-angle glaucoma. Cell Tissue Res., 347, 279-290. ( PubMed) Fuchshofer R. (2011) The pathogenic role of transforming growth factor-?2 in glaucomatous damage to the optic nerve head. Exp Eye Res. Aug, 93(2):165-9 ( PubMed) Sippl C., Bosserhoff A.K., Fischer D., Tamm E.R. Depletion of optineurin in RGC-5 cells derived from retinal neurons causes apoptosis and reduces the secretion of neurotrophins. Exp Eye Res. 2011 Aug 27. (PubMed) Fuchshofer R., Ullmann S., Zeilbeck L.F., Baumann M., Junglas B., Tamm E.R. (2011) Connective tissue growth factor modulates podocyte actin cytoskeleton and extracellular matrix synthesis and is induced in podocytes upon injury. Histochem Cell Biol., Aug 4. (PubMed) Braig S., Wallner S, Junglas B., Fuchshofer R,, Bosserhoff A.K. (2011) CTGF is overexpressed in malignant melanoma and promotes cell invasion and migration. Br J Cancer. Jul 12;105(2):231-8. (PubMed) Ohlmann A., Merkl R., Tamm E.R. (2011). Focus on Molecules: Norrin. Exp. Eye Res.,Jun 30. (PubMed) Tamm E.R. (2011). Entwicklung des Kammerwinkels und kongenitales Glaukom [Development of the iridocorneal angle and congenital glaucoma]. Ophthalmologe, 108, 610-617. (PubMed) Kritzenberger M., Junglas B., Framme C., Helbig H., Gabel V.-P., Fuchshofer R., Tamm E.R., Hillenkamp J. (2011). Different collagen types define two types of idiopathic epiretinal membranes. Histopathology, ;58, 953-965. (PubMed) Gallenberger M, Meinel DM, Kroeber M, Wegner M, Milkereit P, Boesl MR, Tamm ER. Lack of WDR36 leads to preimplantation embryonic lethality in mice and delays the formation of small subunit ribosomal RNA in human cells in vitro. Hum Mol Genet. 2011 Feb 1;20(3):422-35. Epub 2010 Nov 3. (PubMed) Fuchshofer R, Kottler UB, Ohlmann AV, Schloetzer-Schrehardt U, Juenemann A, Kruse FE, Ohlmann A. SPARC is expressed in scars of the Tenon's capsule and mediates scarring properties of human Tenon's fibroblasts in vitro. Mol Vis. 2011 Jan 19;17:177-85. (PubMed) Bohr D., Koch M., Kritzenberger M., Fuchshofer R., Tamm E.R. (2011) Increased expression of olfactomedin-1 and myocilin in podocytes during puromycin aminonucleoside nephrosis. Nephrology Dialysis Transplantation Jan;26(1):83-92 (PubMed) Karlstetter M., Walczak Y., Weigelt K., Ebert .S, Van den Brulle J., Schwer H., Fuchshofer R., Langmann T. (2010) The novel activated microglia/macrophage WAP domain protein, AMWAP, acts as a counter-regulator of proinflammatory response, J Immunol. Sep 15;185(6):3379-90. (PubMed) Kroeber M, Davis N, Holzmann S, Kritzenberger M, Shelah-Goraly M, Ofri R, Ashery-Padan R, Tamm ER. Reduced Expression of Pax6 in Lens and Cornea of Mutant Mice Leads to Failure of Chamber Angle Development and Juvenile Glaucoma. Hum Mol Genet. 2010 Jun 10. (PubMed) Finzsch M, Schreiner S, Kichko T, Reeh P, Tamm ER, B?sl MR, Meijer D, Wegner M. Sox10 is required for Schwann cell identity and progression beyond the immature Schwann cell stage. J Cell Biol. 2010 May 17;189(4):701-12. (PubMed) Seitz R, Hackl S, Seibuchner T, Tamm ER, Ohlmann A. Norrin mediates neuroprotective effects on retinal ganglion cells via activation of the Wnt/beta-catenin signaling pathway and the induction of neuroprotective growth factors in Muller cells. J Neurosci. 2010 Apr 28;30(17):5998-6010. (PubMed) Ohlmann A, Seitz R, Braunger B, Seitz D, B?sl MR, Tamm ER. (2010). Norrin promotes vascular regrowth after oxygen-induced retinal vessel loss and suppresses retinopathy in mice. J Neurosci. 2010 Jan 6;30(1):183-93.(PubMed)Dirscherl K., Karlstetter M., Ebert .S, Kraus D., Hlawatsch J., Walczak Y., Moehle C., Fuchshofer R., Langmann T. (2010) Luteolin triggers global changes in the microglial transcriptome leading to a unique anti-inflammatory and neuroprotective phenotype, J Neuroinflammation. Jan 14;7(1):3. ( PubMed) Konz DD, Fl?gel-Koch C, Ohlmann A, Tamm ER. Myocilin in the trabecular meshwork of eyes with primary open-angle glaucoma. (2009). Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol. 2009 Dec;247(12):1643-9. Epub 2009 Aug 7. (PubMed) Goldwich A, Scholz M, Tamm ER. (2009). Myocilin promotes substrate adhesion, spreading and formation of focal contacts in podocytes and mesangial cells. Histochem Cell Biol. 2009 Feb;131(2):167-80. Epub 2008 Oct 15. (PubMed) Wolf L.V., Yang Y., Wang J., Xie Q., Braunger B., Tamm E.R., Zavadil J., Cvekl A. (2009). Identification of pax6-dependent gene regulatory networks in the mouse lens. PLoS ONE 4, e4159. (PubMed) Tamm E.R., Ethier C.R. (2009). Current aspects of aqueous humor dynamics and glaucoma. Exp. Eye Res. 88. 618-9. (PubMed) Tamm E.R. (2009). The trabecular meshwork outflow pathways: structural and functional aspects. Exp Eye Res. 88, 648-55 (PubMed) Fuchshofer R., Tamm E.R. (2009). Modulation of extracellular matrix turnover in the trabecular meshwork. Exp. Eye Res. 88, 683-8 (PubMed) Fuchshofer R., Stephan D.A., Russell P., Tamm E.R. (2009). Gene expression profiling of TGF?2- and/or BMP7-treated trabecular meshwork cells: Identification of Smad7 as a critical inhibitor of TGF-?2 signaling. Exp. Eye Res. 88, 1020-32 (PubMed) Junglas B., Yu A.H.L., Welge-L?ssen U., Tamm E.R. Fuchshofer R. (2009). Connective tissue growth factor induces extracellular matrix deposition in human trabecular meshwork cells. Exp. Eye Res. 88, 1065-75 (PubMed) Davis N., Yoffe C., Raviv S., Antes R., Berger J., Holzmann S., Stoykova A., Overbeek P.A., Tamm E.R., Ashery-Padan R. (2009). Pax6 dosage requirements in iris and ciliary body differentiation. Dev Biol. 2009 Sep 1;333(1):132-42. Epub 2009 Jun 27 (PubMed) Yu A.L., Fuchshofer R., Kook D., Kampik A., Bloemendal H., Welge-L?ssen U. (2009) Subtoxic oxidative stress induces senescence in retinal pigment epithelial cells via TGF-beta release. IOVS  Feb;50(2):926-35 (PubMed) Tamm E.R. (2008). Molecular Approaches to Glaucoma: Intriguing Clues for Pathology. In: Current Topics in Membranes, The Eye?s Aqueous Humor (Ed. Civan M.M.). Elsevier Inc.  pp. 379-425. Tamm E.R. (2008). The Functional Role of Myocilin in Glaucoma. In: Ophthalmology Research: Mechanisms of the Glaucomas (Eds. Shields M.B., Tombran-Tink J., Barnstable C.J.). Humana Press, Totowa, NJ, pp. 219-231. Tamm E.R., Kellenberger A. (2008). Aqueous Humor Dynamics and Trabecular Meshwork. In: Eye, Retina, and Visual System of the Mouse. III Organization of the Adult Mouse Eye and Central Visual System (Eds. Chalupa L.M., Williams R.W.). MIT Press, p. 129-33. Paper W, Kroeber M, Heersink S, Stephan DA, Fuchshofer R, Russell P, Tamm ER. (2008). Elevated amounts of myocilin in the aqueous humor of transgenic mice cause significant changes in ocular gene expression. Exp. Eye Res. 87:257-67. (PubMed) Wurm A., Sock E., Fuchshofer R., Wegner M., Tamm E.R. (2008). Anterior segment dysgenesis in the eyes of mice deficient for the high-mobility-group transcription factor Sox11. Exp. Eye Res., 86:895-907. (PubMed) Janssen A, Hoellenriegel J, Fogarasi M, Schrewe H, Seeliger M, Tamm E, Ohlmann A, May CA, Weber BH, St?hr H. (2008). Abnormal vessel formation in the choroid of mice lacking tissue inhibitor of metalloprotease-3. Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci.;49:2812-22. (PubMed) Tamm ER, Fuchshofer R. What Increases Outflow Resistance in Primary Open-angle Glaucoma? Surv Ophthalmol. 2007 Nov;52(6 Suppl):S101-4. (PubMed) Pirity MK, Wang WL, Wolf LV, Tamm ER, Schreiber-Agus N, Cvekl A. Rybp, a polycomb complex-associated protein, is required for mouse eye development. BMC Dev Biol. 2007 Apr 30;7:39. (PubMed) Fuchshofer R, Yu AH, Welge-Lussen U, Tamm ER. Bone morphogenetic protein-7 is an antagonist of transforming growth factor-beta2 in human trabecular meshwork cells. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2007 Feb;48(2):715-26. (PubMed) Russell P, Walsh E, Chen W, Goldwich A, Tamm ER. The effect of temperature on gene silencing by siRNAs: implications for silencing in the anterior chamber of the eye. Exp Eye Res. 2006 Jun;82(6):1011-6. (PubMed) Kroeber M, Ohlmann A, Russell P, Tamm ER. Transgenic studies on the role of optineurin in the mouse eye. Exp Eye Res. 2006 Jun;82(6):1075-85. (PubMed) Hinz B, Rosch S, Ramer R, Tamm ER, Brune K. Latanoprost induces matrix metalloproteinase-1 expression in human nonpigmented ciliary epithelial cells through a cyclooxygenase-2-dependent mechanism. FASEB J. 2005 Nov;19(13):1929-31. (PubMed) Ricard CS, Tamm ER. Focus on Molecules: Myocilin/TIGR. Exp Eye Res. 2005 Nov;81(5):501-2. (PubMed) Davis-Silberman N, Kalich T, Oron-Karni V, Marquardt T, Kroeber M, Tamm ER, Ashery-Padan R. Genetic dissection of Pax6 dosage requirements in the developing mouse eye. Hum Mol Genet. 2005 Aug 1;14(15):2265-76. (PubMed) Gottanka J, Kirch W, Tamm ER. The origin of extrinsic nitrergic axons supplying the human eye. J Anat. 2005 Mar;206(3):225-9. (PubMed) Ohlmann A., Scholz M., Goldwich A., Chauhan B.K., Hudl K., Ohlmann A.V., Zrenner E., Berger W., Cvekl A., Seeliger M.W., Tamm E.R. (2005). Ectopic norrin induces growth of ocular capillaries and restores normal retinal angiogenesis in Norrie disease mutant mice. J. Neurosci. 2005 25, 1701-1710. (PubMed) Friedrich R.P., Schlierf B., Tamm E.R., Bosl M.R., Wegner M. (2005) The class III POU domain protein Brn-1 can fully replace the related Oct-6 during Schwann cell development and myelination. Mol. Cell. Biol. 25, 1821-9. (PubMed) Zillig M., Wurm A., Grehn F.J., Russell P., Tamm E.R. (2005) Overexpression and properties of wild-type and Tyr437His mutated myocilin in the eyes of transgenic mice. Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci. 46, 223-34. (PubMed) Goldwich A., Baulmann D.C., Ohlmann A., Fl?gel-Koch C., Sch?cklmann H., Tamm E.R. (2005). Myocilin is expressed in the glomerulus of the kidney and induced in mesangioproliferative glomerulonephritis. Kidney Int., 67, 140-151. (PubMed) Tamm E.R., Carassa R.G., Albert D.M., Gabelt B.T., Patel S., Rasmussen C.A., Kaufman P.L. (2004). Viscocanalostomy in rhesus monkeys. Arch. Ophthalmol., 122, 1826-1838. (PubMed) Fl?gel-Koch C., Ohlmann A., Fuchshofer R., Welge-L?ssen U., Tamm E.R. (2004). Thrombospondin-1 in the trabecular meshwork: localization in normal and glaucomatous eyes, and induction by TGF-beta1 and dexamethasone in vitro. Exp. Eye Res., 79, 649-663. (PubMed) Sock E., Rettig S.D., Enderich J., Bosl M.R., Tamm E.R., Wegner M. (2004) Gene targeting reveals a widespread role for the high-mobility-group transcription factor Sox11 in tissue remodeling. Mol. Cell Biol., 24, 6635-6644. (PubMed) Cvekl A., Tamm E.R. (2004). Anterior eye development and ocular mesenchyme: New insights from mouse models and human diseases. Bioessays, 26, 378-386. (PubMed) Knaupp, C., Fl?gel-Koch C., Goldwich A., Ohlmann, A., Tamm E.R. (2004) The expression of myocilin during murine eye development. Graefe?s Arch. Clin. Exp. Ophthalmol., 242, 339-45 . (PubMed) Santas A.J., Bahler C., Peterson J.A., Filla M.S., Kaufman P.L., Tamm E.R., Johnson D., Peters D.P. (2003). The heparin II domain of fibronectin modulates aqueous outflow in cultured anterior segments of human eyes. Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci., 44, 4796-4804. (PubMed) Rhee, D.J., Tamm, E.R., and Russell, P. (2003) Donor corneoscleral buttons: A new source of trabecular meshwork for research. Exp. Eye Res., 77, 749-756. (PubMed) Ohlmann A., Goldwich A., Fl?gel-Koch C., Fuchs A.V., Schwager K., Tamm E.R. (2003). The secreted glycoprotein myocilin is a component of the myelin sheath in peripheral nerves. Glia, 43, 128-140. (PubMed) Goldwich A., Ethier C.R., Chan D. W.-H., Tamm E.R. (2003). Perfusion with the olfactomedin domain of myocilin does not affect outflow facility. Invest. Opthalmol. Vis. Sci., 44, 1953-1961. (PubMed) Baulmann D., Ohlmann A., Fl?gel-Koch C., Goswami S., Cvekl A., Tamm E.R. (2002). Pax6 heterozygous eyes show defects in chamber angle differentiation that are associated with a wide spectrum of other anterior eye segment abnormalities. Mech. Develop. 118, 3-17. (PubMed) Fl?gel-Koch C., Ohlmann A., Piatigorsky J., Tamm E.R. (2002). Disruption of anterior segment development by TGF-beta1 overexpression in the eyes of transgenic mice. Dev. Dyn. 225, 111-125. (PubMed) Weber B.H.W., Schrewe H., Molday L.L., Gehrig A., White K.L., Seeliger M.W., Jaissle G.B., Friedburg C., Tamm E., Molday R.S. (2002). Inactivation of the murine X-linked juvenile retinoschisis gene, rs1h, suggests a role of retinoschisin in retinal cell layer organization and synaptic structure. PNAS, 99, 6222-6227. (PubMed) Rao V., Wawrousek E., Tamm E.R., Zigler S. Jr. (2002). Rho GTPase inactivation impairs lens growth and integrity. Lab. Invest. 82, 231-239. (PubMed) Borr?s T., Rowlette L.L.S., Tamm E.R., Gottanka J., Epstein D.L. (2002). Effects of elevated intraocular pressure on outflow facility and TIGR/MYOC expression in perfused human anterior segments. Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci. 43, 33-40. (PubMed) Tamm E.R. (2002). Myocilin and glaucoma. Facts and ideas. Prog. Ret. Eye Res. 21, 395-428. (PubMed) Ohlmann A., Tamm E.R. (2002). Die Rolle von Myocilin bei der Pathogenese des prim?ren Offenwinkelglaukoms. Der Ophthalmologe, 99, 672-677. (Springer) Tamm E.R., Polansky J. (2001). The TIGR/MYOC gene and glaucoma: opportunities for new understandings. J. Glaucoma, 10(Suppl 1), S9-S12. (PubMed) Brady J.P., Garland D.L., Green D.E., Tamm E.R., Giblin F., Wawrousek E.F. (2001). aB-Crystallin is not essential for development of a transparent lens but may be critical for muscle integrity. Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci., 42, 2924-2932. (PubMed) Maih?fner C., Schl?tzer-Schrehardt U., G?hring H., Zeilhofer H.U., Naumann G.O.H., Tamm E.R., Brune K. (2001). Specific loss of ciliary COX-2 expression in patients with primary open-angle glaucoma. Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci., 42, 2616-2624.  Russell P., Tamm E.R., Grehn F.J., Picht G., Johnson M. (2001). The presence and properties of myocilin in the aqueous humor. Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci., 42, 983-986. (PubMed) Tamm E.R., Russell, P. (2001) The Role of Myocilin/TIGR in Glaucoma. Results of the Glaucoma Research Foundation Catalyst Meeting in Berkeley, CA, March 2000. J. Glaucoma, 10, 329-339. (PubMed) Piatigorsky J., Kozmik Z., Horwitz J., Ding L., Carosa E., Robison W.G.Jr., Steinbach P.J., Tamm E.R. (2000). Omega-crystallin of the scallop lens. A dimeric aldehyde dehydogenase class 1/2 enzyme-crystallin. J. Biol. Chem. 275, 41064-41073. (PubMed) Kirstein L., Cvekl A., Chauhan B.K., Tamm E.R. (2000). Regulation of human myocilin/TIGR gene transcripton in trabecular meshwork cells and astrocytes: Role of upstream stimulatory factor. Genes Cells, 5, 661-676. (PubMed) Karali A., Russell P., Stefani F.H., Tamm E.R. (2000). Localization of myocilin/ trabecular meshwork inducible glucocorticoid response protein in the human eye. Invest. Opthalmol. Vis. Sci., 41, 729-740. (PubMed)</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Tamm/Research/index.html</field>
<field name="title">NWF III - Universit?t Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Tamm/Research/index.html</field>
<field name="content">NWF III - Universit?t Regensburg NWF III - Universit?t Regensburg      Staff      Research      FOR1075      Publications      Teaching      Gallery      Info      Links The research at the LAE is funded by the German Research Council (Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft) through the Research Unit (Forschergruppe) FOR 1075 ?Regulation and pathology of homeostatic systems for visual function?. The research at the Laboratory for Human Anatomy and Embryology (LAE) focuses on the molecular characterization of homeostatic systems in the mammalian eye, which are critically required for survival of retinal neurons and for visual function. Primary research interests include the regulatory processes of aqueous humor circulation, intraocular pressure maintenance, neuronal survival in the retina, and ocular angiogenesis. Molecular control mechanisms of the processes are studied in the normal eye, during embryonic development and under pathological conditions such as primary open-angle glaucoma, retinopathy of prematurity, or retinal degeneration. The primary methodological approach is the generation of genetically modified animal models and the subsequent characterization of their phenotype. In addition, cell biological aspects are investigated by studying gene expression and its control in cell culture models and/or by generating recombinant proteins.   The Tamm Laboratory moved 2004 from the Friedrich-Alexander-University of Erlangen-Nuremberg to the University of Regensburg. Teaching responsibilities of the LAE include the organization of the lectures and practical classes in gross anatomy for students of medicine and dentistry at the University of Regensburg. In addition, the LAE organizes the module Molecular Human Biology for master students in Biology, as well as internships and practical classes in cell biology and neurobiology for students of biology, biochemistry, and neurosciences at the University of Regensburg. Moreover, we supervise master theses. Workshops covering specific aspects of gross anatomy are organized for physicians and physiotherapists Projects: Genetically Modified Animal Models for Primary Open-Angle Glaucoma Primary open-angle glaucoma (POAG) is one of the most frequent causes of blindness worldwide. The project studies the molecular function of genes that have been identified to cause inherited forms of POAG using cell culture systems, anterior segment organ culture perfusion, and by the generation of transgenic animal models. Principal Investigator: Ernst Tamm Team: Martin Gallenberger, Leonie Herrnberger, Christiane Sippl, Patrick Zadravec Grant Support: Research Unit (Forschergruppe) FOR 1075 ?Regulation and pathology of homeostatic systems for visual function?, TP5 Funding period: 1.8.2011 ? 31.7.2014   The Functional Role of Norrin Norrin, a secreted polypeptide, is the gene product of the NDP-Gene that is modified in Norrie disease. Previous data indicate a role in angiogenesis during fetal development of the retina. The project studies the molecular function of norrin using cell culture systems, anterior segment organ culture perfusion, and by the generation of transgenic animal models. Principal Investigators: Andreas Ohlmann and Ernst Tamm Team: Stephanie Leopold, Birgit M?ller, Ludwig Zeilbeck Grant Support: Research Unit (Forschergruppe) FOR 1075 ?Regulation and pathology of homeostatic systems for visual function?, TP7, and Pro Retina , Germany Funding period: 1.8.2011 ? 31.7.2014   The Functional Role of CTGF, TGF-beta, and BMP-7 for Aqueous Humor Dynamics and Pathogenesis of Primary Open-Angle Glaucoma Aqueous humor outflow in the trabecular meshwork (TM) is under the influence of TM extracellular matrix turnover and cell contractility. The project studies the molecular function of the growth factors CTGF, TGF-beta, and BMP-7 for TM cell function using cell culture systems, anterior segment organ culture perfusion, and by the generation of transgenic animal models. Principal Investigator: Rudolf Fuchshofer Team: Sabrina K?spert, Sabrina Ullmann Grant Support: Research Unit (Forschergruppe) FOR 1075 ?Regulation and pathology of homeostatic systems for visual function?, TP3 Funding period: 1.8.2011 ? 31.07.2014</field>
<field name="important">NWF III - Universit?t Regensburg NWF III - Universit?t Regensburg      Staff      Research      FOR1075      Publications      Teaching      Gallery      Info      Links The research at the LAE is funded by the German Research Council (Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft) through the Research Unit (Forschergruppe) FOR 1075 ?Regulation and pathology of homeostatic systems for visual function?. The research at the Laboratory for Human Anatomy and Embryology (LAE) focuses on the molecular characterization of homeostatic systems in the mammalian eye, which are critically required for survival of retinal neurons and for visual function. Primary research interests include the regulatory processes of aqueous humor circulation, intraocular pressure maintenance, neuronal survival in the retina, and ocular angiogenesis. Molecular control mechanisms of the processes are studied in the normal eye, during embryonic development and under pathological conditions such as primary open-angle glaucoma, retinopathy of prematurity, or retinal degeneration. The primary methodological approach is the generation of genetically modified animal models and the subsequent characterization of their phenotype. In addition, cell biological aspects are investigated by studying gene expression and its control in cell culture models and/or by generating recombinant proteins.   The Tamm Laboratory moved 2004 from the Friedrich-Alexander-University of Erlangen-Nuremberg to the University of Regensburg. Teaching responsibilities of the LAE include the organization of the lectures and practical classes in gross anatomy for students of medicine and dentistry at the University of Regensburg. In addition, the LAE organizes the module Molecular Human Biology for master students in Biology, as well as internships and practical classes in cell biology and neurobiology for students of biology, biochemistry, and neurosciences at the University of Regensburg. Moreover, we supervise master theses. Workshops covering specific aspects of gross anatomy are organized for physicians and physiotherapists Projects: Genetically Modified Animal Models for Primary Open-Angle Glaucoma Primary open-angle glaucoma (POAG) is one of the most frequent causes of blindness worldwide. The project studies the molecular function of genes that have been identified to cause inherited forms of POAG using cell culture systems, anterior segment organ culture perfusion, and by the generation of transgenic animal models. Principal Investigator: Ernst Tamm Team: Martin Gallenberger, Leonie Herrnberger, Christiane Sippl, Patrick Zadravec Grant Support: Research Unit (Forschergruppe) FOR 1075 ?Regulation and pathology of homeostatic systems for visual function?, TP5 Funding period: 1.8.2011 ? 31.7.2014   The Functional Role of Norrin Norrin, a secreted polypeptide, is the gene product of the NDP-Gene that is modified in Norrie disease. Previous data indicate a role in angiogenesis during fetal development of the retina. The project studies the molecular function of norrin using cell culture systems, anterior segment organ culture perfusion, and by the generation of transgenic animal models. Principal Investigators: Andreas Ohlmann and Ernst Tamm Team: Stephanie Leopold, Birgit M?ller, Ludwig Zeilbeck Grant Support: Research Unit (Forschergruppe) FOR 1075 ?Regulation and pathology of homeostatic systems for visual function?, TP7, and Pro Retina , Germany Funding period: 1.8.2011 ? 31.7.2014   The Functional Role of CTGF, TGF-beta, and BMP-7 for Aqueous Humor Dynamics and Pathogenesis of Primary Open-Angle Glaucoma Aqueous humor outflow in the trabecular meshwork (TM) is under the influence of TM extracellular matrix turnover and cell contractility. The project studies the molecular function of the growth factors CTGF, TGF-beta, and BMP-7 for TM cell function using cell culture systems, anterior segment organ culture perfusion, and by the generation of transgenic animal models. Principal Investigator: Rudolf Fuchshofer Team: Sabrina K?spert, Sabrina Ullmann Grant Support: Research Unit (Forschergruppe) FOR 1075 ?Regulation and pathology of homeostatic systems for visual function?, TP3 Funding period: 1.8.2011 ? 31.07.2014</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Tamm/Staff/index.html</field>
<field name="title">NWF III - Universit?t Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Tamm/Staff/index.html</field>
<field name="content">NWF III - Universit?t Regensburg NWF III - Universit?t Regensburg      Staff      Research      FOR1075      Publications      Teaching      Gallery      Info      Links Anschrift: Prof. Dr. med. Ernst R. Tamm Lehrstuhl f?r Humananatomie und Embryologie Universit?t Regensburg Universit?tsstr. 31 93053 Regensburg Sekretariat: Inge K?berlein, Zi.-Nr. VKL 5.0.02A E-mail: Lehrstuhl.Tamm@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Telefon: ++49 (0) 941 943-2838 Fax: ++49 (0) 941 943-2840 Prof. Dr. med. Ernst R. Tamm Chair of the department   Phone:       (49) (0)941-943-2839 (office); -2838 (secretary)   FAX:       (49) (0)941-943-2840   E-mail: Ernst.Tamm@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Inge K?berlein Secretary   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2838   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Inge.Koeberlein@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Barbara Gareis Secretary of the Research Unit 1075   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-5588   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-5587   E-mail: Barbara.Gareis@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Rudolf Fuchshofer (PD) Group leader   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2881   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Rudolf.Fuchshofer@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Homepage Dr. Andreas Ohlmann (PD) Group leader   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2880   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Andreas.Ohlmann@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Dr. Barbara Braunger Group leader   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Barbara.Braunger@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Marcus Koch Post doc   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1658   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Marcus.Koch@vkl.uni-regensburg.de   Dr. Roswitha Seitz Post doc   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2880   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: roswitha.seitz@vkl.uni-regensburg.de   Silvia Babl Technical Assistant Molecular Biology   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1658   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: silvia.babl@vkl.uni-regensburg.de   Angelika Pach Technical Assistant Molecular and Cell Biology   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1658   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Angelika.Pach@vkl.uni-regensburg.de   Margit Schimmel Technical Assistant Electron Microscopy   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2841   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Margit.Schimmel@vkl.uni-regensburg.de   Elke Stauber Technical Assistant Immunohistochemistry, Histology   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2844   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Elke.Stauber@vkl.uni-regensburg.de     Eva Zitzelsperger Technical Assistant Molecular and Cell Biology   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1658   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: eva.zitzelsperger@vkl.uni-regensburg.de       Richard Niedermeier Anatomists? Assistant   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2910   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2891   E-mail: Richard.niedermeier@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Andreas Rieger Anatomists? Assistant   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2910   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2891   Markus Sch?pperl Anatomists? Assistant   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2910   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2891 Natalie Abramov Graduate Student (med.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840 E-Mail: AbramovN@web.de Bahar Ademoglu Graduate Student (med.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840 E-Mail: bahar.ademoglu@hotmail.de Stefaniya Boneva Graduate Student (med.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840 E-Mail: Stefaniya.Boneva@stud.uni-regensburg.de Andrea Dillinger Graduate Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Andrea.Dillinger@stud.uni-regensburg.de   Konstantin Drexler Graduate Student (med.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840 E-Mail: konstantin_drexler@web.de Silke Eggerstorfer Graduate Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Silke.Eggerstorfer@stud.uni-regensburg.de   Christian Eimer Graduate Student (med.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840 E-Mail: christian.eimer@stud.uni-regensburg.de   Markus G?tz Graduate Student (med)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: markusgoetz3@gmx.de Tatjana Gross Graduate Student (med)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Gross.Tatjana@stud.uni-regensburg.de Leonie Herrnberger Graduate Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: leonie.herrnberger@vkl.uni-regensburg.de       Daniela Kawall Graduate Student (med.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: daniela.kawall@stud.uni-regensburg.de Christian Komandzik Graduate Student (med.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Christian.Komandzik@stud.uni-regensburg.de Sebastian Koschade Graduate Student (med.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840 E-Mail: Sebastian.Koschade@stud.uni-regensburg.de   Sabrina K?spert Graduate Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Sabrina.Kuespert@vkl.uni-regensburg.de   Stephanie Leopold Graduate Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Stephanie.Leopold@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Birgit M?ller Graduate Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1658   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: birgit1.mueller@stud.uni-regensburg.de Anja Schlecht Graduate Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840 E-Mail: Anja.Schlecht@vkl.uni-regensburg.de     Magdalena Schneider Graduate Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Magdalena.Schneider@vkl.uni-regensburg.de   Christiane Sippl Graduate Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: christiane.sippl@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Gregor Weber Graduate Student (med.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Gregor.Weber@stud.uni-regensburg.de Daniel W?hl Graduate Student (med.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Daniel_Simon.Woehl@stud.uni-regensburg.de Patrick Zadravec Graduate Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1658   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: patrick.zadravec@vkl.uni-regensburg.de   Sandra F?rtsch Master Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Sandra.Foertsch@stud.uni-regensburg.de   Lena Jaschkowitz Master Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2914   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: lena.jaschkowitz@stud.uni-regensburg.de   Sabrina Schmitt Master Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2914   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: sabrina.schmitt@stud.uni-regensburg.de   Sandra Theobald Master Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2914   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Sandra.Theobald@stud.uni-regensburg.de   Alumni</field>
<field name="important">NWF III - Universit?t Regensburg NWF III - Universit?t Regensburg      Staff      Research      FOR1075      Publications      Teaching      Gallery      Info      Links Anschrift: Prof. Dr. med. Ernst R. Tamm Lehrstuhl f?r Humananatomie und Embryologie Universit?t Regensburg Universit?tsstr. 31 93053 Regensburg Sekretariat: Inge K?berlein, Zi.-Nr. VKL 5.0.02A E-mail: Lehrstuhl.Tamm@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Telefon: ++49 (0) 941 943-2838 Fax: ++49 (0) 941 943-2840 Prof. Dr. med. Ernst R. Tamm Chair of the department   Phone:       (49) (0)941-943-2839 (office); -2838 (secretary)   FAX:       (49) (0)941-943-2840   E-mail: Ernst.Tamm@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Inge K?berlein Secretary   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2838   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Inge.Koeberlein@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Barbara Gareis Secretary of the Research Unit 1075   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-5588   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-5587   E-mail: Barbara.Gareis@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Rudolf Fuchshofer (PD) Group leader   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2881   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Rudolf.Fuchshofer@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Homepage Dr. Andreas Ohlmann (PD) Group leader   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2880   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Andreas.Ohlmann@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Dr. Barbara Braunger Group leader   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Barbara.Braunger@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Marcus Koch Post doc   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1658   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Marcus.Koch@vkl.uni-regensburg.de   Dr. Roswitha Seitz Post doc   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2880   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: roswitha.seitz@vkl.uni-regensburg.de   Silvia Babl Technical Assistant Molecular Biology   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1658   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: silvia.babl@vkl.uni-regensburg.de   Angelika Pach Technical Assistant Molecular and Cell Biology   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1658   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Angelika.Pach@vkl.uni-regensburg.de   Margit Schimmel Technical Assistant Electron Microscopy   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2841   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Margit.Schimmel@vkl.uni-regensburg.de   Elke Stauber Technical Assistant Immunohistochemistry, Histology   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2844   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Elke.Stauber@vkl.uni-regensburg.de     Eva Zitzelsperger Technical Assistant Molecular and Cell Biology   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1658   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: eva.zitzelsperger@vkl.uni-regensburg.de       Richard Niedermeier Anatomists? Assistant   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2910   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2891   E-mail: Richard.niedermeier@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Andreas Rieger Anatomists? Assistant   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2910   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2891   Markus Sch?pperl Anatomists? Assistant   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2910   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2891 Natalie Abramov Graduate Student (med.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840 E-Mail: AbramovN@web.de Bahar Ademoglu Graduate Student (med.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840 E-Mail: bahar.ademoglu@hotmail.de Stefaniya Boneva Graduate Student (med.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840 E-Mail: Stefaniya.Boneva@stud.uni-regensburg.de Andrea Dillinger Graduate Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Andrea.Dillinger@stud.uni-regensburg.de   Konstantin Drexler Graduate Student (med.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840 E-Mail: konstantin_drexler@web.de Silke Eggerstorfer Graduate Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Silke.Eggerstorfer@stud.uni-regensburg.de   Christian Eimer Graduate Student (med.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840 E-Mail: christian.eimer@stud.uni-regensburg.de   Markus G?tz Graduate Student (med)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: markusgoetz3@gmx.de Tatjana Gross Graduate Student (med)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Gross.Tatjana@stud.uni-regensburg.de Leonie Herrnberger Graduate Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: leonie.herrnberger@vkl.uni-regensburg.de       Daniela Kawall Graduate Student (med.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: daniela.kawall@stud.uni-regensburg.de Christian Komandzik Graduate Student (med.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Christian.Komandzik@stud.uni-regensburg.de Sebastian Koschade Graduate Student (med.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840 E-Mail: Sebastian.Koschade@stud.uni-regensburg.de   Sabrina K?spert Graduate Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Sabrina.Kuespert@vkl.uni-regensburg.de   Stephanie Leopold Graduate Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Stephanie.Leopold@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Birgit M?ller Graduate Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1658   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: birgit1.mueller@stud.uni-regensburg.de Anja Schlecht Graduate Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840 E-Mail: Anja.Schlecht@vkl.uni-regensburg.de     Magdalena Schneider Graduate Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Magdalena.Schneider@vkl.uni-regensburg.de   Christiane Sippl Graduate Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: christiane.sippl@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Gregor Weber Graduate Student (med.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Gregor.Weber@stud.uni-regensburg.de Daniel W?hl Graduate Student (med.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Daniel_Simon.Woehl@stud.uni-regensburg.de Patrick Zadravec Graduate Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1658   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: patrick.zadravec@vkl.uni-regensburg.de   Sandra F?rtsch Master Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-1660   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Sandra.Foertsch@stud.uni-regensburg.de   Lena Jaschkowitz Master Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2914   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: lena.jaschkowitz@stud.uni-regensburg.de   Sabrina Schmitt Master Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2914   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: sabrina.schmitt@stud.uni-regensburg.de   Sandra Theobald Master Student (biol.)   Phone:       (49) (0)941 943-2914   Fax:      (49) (0)941 943-2840   E-mail: Sandra.Theobald@stud.uni-regensburg.de   Alumni</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Tamm/Teaching/index.html</field>
<field name="title">NWF III - Universit?t Regensburg</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Tamm/Teaching/index.html</field>
<field name="content">NWF III - Universit?t Regensburg NWF III - Universit?t Regensburg      Staff      Research      FOR1075      Publications      Teaching      Gallery      Info      Links In der Lehrt?tigkeit erfolgt eine Beteiligung an den Unterrichtsveranstaltungen des Anatomischen Instituts. Lehrveranstaltungen: Die Lehrveranstaltungen sind dem aktuellem Vorlesungsverzeichnis zu entnehmen. Scripte: Vorlesungsscripte finden Sie bei den jeweiligen Vorlesungen. Hier finden Sie die Fotos vom Pr?parierkurs 2014. Pressestimmen: Merkur Online vom 28.10.2013 Mittelbayerische Zeitung vom 29.6.2009. Donaupost vom 31.10.2008. Mittelbayerische Zeitung vom 17.7.2008. Donaupost vom 8.7.2008. Pr?parationsteam 2012 Pr?parationsteam 2011 Pr?parationsteam 2010 Pr?parationsteam 2009   Pr?parationsteam 2008 Pr?parationsteam 2007 Pr?parationsteam 2006</field>
<field name="important">NWF III - Universit?t Regensburg NWF III - Universit?t Regensburg      Staff      Research      FOR1075      Publications      Teaching      Gallery      Info      Links In der Lehrt?tigkeit erfolgt eine Beteiligung an den Unterrichtsveranstaltungen des Anatomischen Instituts. Lehrveranstaltungen: Die Lehrveranstaltungen sind dem aktuellem Vorlesungsverzeichnis zu entnehmen. Scripte: Vorlesungsscripte finden Sie bei den jeweiligen Vorlesungen. Hier finden Sie die Fotos vom Pr?parierkurs 2014. Pressestimmen: Merkur Online vom 28.10.2013 Mittelbayerische Zeitung vom 29.6.2009. Donaupost vom 31.10.2008. Mittelbayerische Zeitung vom 17.7.2008. Donaupost vom 8.7.2008. Pr?parationsteam 2012 Pr?parationsteam 2011 Pr?parationsteam 2010 Pr?parationsteam 2009   Pr?parationsteam 2008 Pr?parationsteam 2007 Pr?parationsteam 2006</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Witzgall/English/links_eng.html</field>
<field name="title">Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Links</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Witzgall/English/links_eng.html</field>
<field name="content">? Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Links Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Fakultäten &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Institute &amp;gt; Anatomie &amp;gt; LS Witzgall &amp;gt; Links Research   Staff   Ralph Witzgall   Publications   For Students   Links   Map Links SFB 699: "Strukturelle, physiologische und molekulare Grundlagen der Nierenfunktion" DFG-Forschergruppe: "Mechanismen der Progression des chronischen  Nierenversagens" Register der Mutationen im PKD1 Gen Register der Mutationen im PKD2 Gen Mutationen im PKHD1 Gen PKD Mutation Database PKD Foundation (USA) PKD Charity (UK) Zystennieren.de Deutsche Gesellschaft für Nephrologie Erbkrankheiten im Internet Literatursuche im Internet Kidney development database Nail Patella Syndrome Worldwide Veranstaltungskalender der Universität Regensburg Fachschaft Medizin Internetseite der Stadt Regensburg Bayerische Eliteakademie Impressum</field>
<field name="important">? Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Links Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Fakultäten &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Institute &amp;gt; Anatomie &amp;gt; LS Witzgall &amp;gt; Links Research   Staff   Ralph Witzgall   Publications   For Students   Links   Map Links SFB 699: "Strukturelle, physiologische und molekulare Grundlagen der Nierenfunktion" DFG-Forschergruppe: "Mechanismen der Progression des chronischen  Nierenversagens" Register der Mutationen im PKD1 Gen Register der Mutationen im PKD2 Gen Mutationen im PKHD1 Gen PKD Mutation Database PKD Foundation (USA) PKD Charity (UK) Zystennieren.de Deutsche Gesellschaft für Nephrologie Erbkrankheiten im Internet Literatursuche im Internet Kidney development database Nail Patella Syndrome Worldwide Veranstaltungskalender der Universität Regensburg Fachschaft Medizin Internetseite der Stadt Regensburg Bayerische Eliteakademie Impressum</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Witzgall/English/map.html</field>
<field name="title">Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Map</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Witzgall/English/map.html</field>
<field name="content">? Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Map Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Fakultäten &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Institute &amp;gt; Anatomie &amp;gt; LS Witzgall &amp;gt; Map Research   Staff   Ralph Witzgall   Publications   For Students   Links   Map How to find the University of Regensburg By train to Regensburg Hbf, then by taxi or bus number 6 (Klinikum) or 11 (Burgweinting) to busstop Mensa. With a car use the A3 (via "Autobahnkreuz Regensburg") to exit 100a: Universität &amp; Klinikum. Impressum</field>
<field name="important">? Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Map Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Fakultäten &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Institute &amp;gt; Anatomie &amp;gt; LS Witzgall &amp;gt; Map Research   Staff   Ralph Witzgall   Publications   For Students   Links   Map How to find the University of Regensburg By train to Regensburg Hbf, then by taxi or bus number 6 (Klinikum) or 11 (Burgweinting) to busstop Mensa. With a car use the A3 (via "Autobahnkreuz Regensburg") to exit 100a: Universität &amp; Klinikum. Impressum</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Witzgall/English/publications.html</field>
<field name="title">Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Publications</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Witzgall/English/publications.html</field>
<field name="content">Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Publications Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Publications Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Fakultäten &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Institute &amp;gt; Anatomie &amp;gt; LS Witzgall &amp;gt; Publications Research   Staff   Ralph Witzgall   Publications   For Students   Links   Map List of publications Original publications: (1) Dummer R., G. Posseckert, F. Nestle, R. Witzgall, M. Burger, J. C. Becker, E. Schäfer, J. Wiede, W. Sebald, G. Burg.  Soluble interleukin-2 receptors inhibit interleukin 2-dependent proliferation and cytotoxicity: Explanation for diminished natural killer cell activity in cutaneous T-cell lymphomas in vivo?  J. Invest. Dermatology 98: 50-54 (1992).   PDF (2) Witzgall R., E. O´Leary, R. Gessner, A. J. Ouellette, J.V. Bonventre.  Kid-1, a putative renal transcription factor: Regulation during ontogeny, and in response to ischemia and toxic injury.  Mol. Cell. Biol. 13: 1933-1942 (1993).   PDF (3) Witzgall R., D. Brown, C. Schwarz, J.V. Bonventre.  Localization of proliferating cell nuclear antigen, vimentin, c-Fos, and clusterin in the post-ischemic kidney. Evidence for a heterogeneous genetic response among nephron segments, and a large pool of mitotically active and dedifferentiated cells.  J. Clin. Invest. 93: 2175-2188 (1994).   PDF (4) Witzgall R., R. Volk, R. Yeung, J.V. Bonventre.  Genomic structure and chromosomal location of the rat gene encoding the zinc finger transcription factor Kid-1.  Genomics 20: 203-209 (1994).   PDF (5) Witzgall R., E. O´Leary, A. Leaf, D. Önaldi, J.V. Bonventre.  The Krüppel-associated box-A (KRAB-A) domain of zinc finger proteins mediates transcriptional repression.  Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 91: 4514-4518 (1994).   PDF (6) Witzgall R., E. O´Leary, J.V. Bonventre.  A mammalian expression vector for the expression of GAL4 fusion proteins with an epitope tag and histidine tail.  Anal. Biochem. 223: 291-298 (1994).   PDF (7) Sapirstein A., R. A. Spech, R. Witzgall, J. V. Bonventre.  Cytosolic phospholipase A2 (PLA2), but not secretory PLA2, potentiates hydrogen peroxide cytotoxicity in kidney epithelial cells. J. Biol. Chem. 271: 21505-21513 (1996).   PDF (8) Kim S.-S., Y.-M. Chen, E. O?Leary, R. Witzgall, M. Vidal, J. V. Bonventre.  A novel member of the RING finger family, KRIP-1, associates with the KRAB-A transcriptional repressor domain of zinc finger proteins.  Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 93: 15299-15304 (1996).   PDF (9) Bonventre J. V., J. M. Kyriakis, R. Spech, R. Witzgall, T. Force.  Phospholipase A2 and lipids as potential modulators of c-Raf-1 kinase.  Am. J. Ther. 3, 287-293 (1996).   PDF (10) Obermüller N., N. Gretz, W. Kriz, F. J. van der Woude, R. F. Reilly, H. Murer, J. Biber, R. Witzgall.  Differentiation and cell polarity during renal cyst formation in the Han:SPRD (cy/+) rat, a model for ADPKD.  Am. J. Physiol. 273: F357-F371 (1997).   PDF (11) Schaub T. P., J. Kartenbeck, J. König, O. Vogel, R. Witzgall, W. Kriz, D. Keppler.  Expression of the conjugate export pump encoded by the mrp2 gene in the apical membrane of kidney proximal tubules.  J. Am. Soc. Nephrol.  8: 1213-1221 (1997).   PDF (12) Obermüller N., B. Kränzlin, R. Verma, N. Gretz, W. Kriz, R. Witzgall.  Renal osmotic stress induced cotransporter:  Expression in the newborn, adult and post-ischemic rat kidney.  Kidney Int.  52: 1584-1592 (1997).   PDF (13) Elser B., W. Kriz, J. V. Bonventre, C. Englert, R. Witzgall.  The Krüppel-associated box (KRAB)-zinc finger protein Kid-1 and the Wilms? tumor protein WT1, two transcriptional repressor proteins, bind to heteroduplex DNA.  J. Biol. Chem.  272: 27908-27912 (1997).   PDF (14) Obermüller N., N. Gretz, W. Kriz, R. F. Reilly, R. Witzgall.  The swelling -activated chloride channel ClC-2, the chloride channel ClC-3, and ClC-5, a chloride channel mutated in kidney stone disease, are expressed in distinct subpopulations of renal epithelial cells.  J. Clin. Invest. 101: 635-642 (1998).   PDF (15) Witzgall R., N. Obermüller, U. Bölitz, J. P. Calvet, B. D. Cowley Jr., C. Walker, W. Kriz, N. Gretz, J. V. Bonventre.  Kid-1 expression is high in differentiated renal proximal tubule cells and suppressed in cyst epithelia.  Am. J. Physiol. 275: F928-F937 (1998).   PDF (16) Huang Z., B. Philippin, E. O?Leary, J. V. Bonventre, W. Kriz, R. Witzgall.  Expression of the transcriptional repressor protein Kid-1 leads to the disintegration of the nucleolus.  J. Biol. Chem. 274, 7640-7648 (1999).   PDF (17) Cai Y., Y. Maeda, A. Cedzich, V. E. Torres, G. Wu, T. Hayashi, T. Mochizuki, J. H. Park, R. Witzgall, S. Somlo.  Identification and characterization of polycystin-2, the PKD2 gene product.  J. Biol. Chem. 274, 28557-28565 (1999).   PDF (18) Obermüller N., A. R. Gallagher, Y. Cai, N. Gassler, N. Gretz, S. Somlo, R. Witzgall.  The rat Pkd2 protein assumes distinct subcellular distributions in different organs.  Am. J. Physiol. 277, F914-F925 (1999).   PDF (19) Gallagher A. R., A. Cedzich, N. Gretz, S. Somlo, R. Witzgall.  The polycystic kidney disease protein PKD2 interacts with Hax-1, a protein associated with the actin cytoskeleton.  Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 97, 4017-4022 (2000).   PDF (20) Obermüller N., B. Kränzlin, W. F. Blum, N. Gretz, R. Witzgall.  An endocytosis defect as a possible cause of proteinuria in polycystic kidney disease.  Am. J. Physiol. Renal Physiol. 280, F244-F253 (2001).   PDF (21) Obermüller N., N. Morente, B. Kränzlin, N. Gretz, R. Witzgall.  A possible role for metalloproteinases in renal cyst development.  Am. J. Physiol. Renal Physiol. 280, F540-F550 (2001).   PDF (22) Gassler, N., F. Autschbach, G. Heuschen, R. Witzgall, H. F. Otto, N. Obermüller.  Expression of clusterin in Crohn?s disease of terminal ileum.  Histol. Histopathol. 16, 755-762 (2001).   PDF (23) Klimaschewski, L., N. Obermüller, R. Witzgall.  Regulation of clusterin expression following spinal cord injury.  Cell Tissue Res. 306, 209-216 (2001).   PDF (24) Koulen P., Y. Cai, L. Geng, Y. Maeda, S. Nishimura, R. Witzgall, B. E. Ehrlich, S. Somlo.  Polycystin-2 is an intracellular calcium release channel.  Nat. Cell Biol. 4, 191-197 (2002).  PDF (25) Wärntges S., B. Friedrich, G. Henke, C. Duranton, P. A. Lang, S. Waldegger, R. Meyermann, D. Kuhl, E. J. Speckmann, N. Obermüller, R. Witzgall, A. F. Mack, H. J. Wagner, C. A. Wagner, S. Bröer, F. Lang.  Cerebral localization and regulation of the cell volume-sensitive serum- and glucocorticoid-dependent kinase SGK1.  Pflügers Arch. - Eur. J. Physiol. 443, 617-624 (2002). PDF (26) Rohr C., J. Prestel, L. Heidet, H. Hosser, W. Kriz, R. L. Johnson, C. Antignac, R. Witzgall.  The LIM-homeodomain transcription factor Lmx1b plays a crucial role in podocytes.  J. Clin. Invest. 109, 1073-1082 (2002).   PDF (27) Obermüller N., Y. Cai, B. Kränzlin, R. B. Thomson, N. Gretz, W. Kriz, S. Somlo, R. Witzgall.  Altered expression pattern of polycystin-2 in acute and chronic renal tubular diseases.  J. Am. Soc. Nephrol. 13, 1855-1864 (2002).   PDF (28) Friedrich B., S. Wärntges, K. Klingel, M. Sauter, R. Kandolf, T. Risler, G. A. Müller, R. Witzgall, W. Kriz, H. J. Gröne, F. Lang. Up-regulation of the human serum and glucocorticoid-dependent kinase 1 in glomerulonephritis. Kidney Blood Press. Res. 25, 303-307 (2002).  PDF (29) Hidaka S., B. Kränzlin, N. Gretz, R. Witzgall. Urinary clusterin levels in the rat correlate with the severity of tubular damage and may help to differentiate between glomerular and tubular injuries. Cell Tissue Res. 310: 289-296 (2002).   PDF (30) Gallagher A. R., K. Schönig, N. Brown, H. Bujard, R. Witzgall. Use of the tetracycline system for inducible protein synthesis in the kidney. J. Am. Soc. Nephrol. 14: 2042-2051 (2003).   PDF (31) Wolf M. T. F., B. E. Mucha, M. Attanasio, I. Zalewski, S. M. Karle, H. P. H. Neumann, N. Rahman, B. Bader, C. A. Baldamus, E. Otto, R. Witzgall, A. Fuchshuber, F. Hildebrandt. Mutations of the Uromodulin gene in MCKD type 2 patients cluster in exon 4, which encodes three EGF-like domains. Kidney Int. 64: 1580-1587 (2003).   PDF (32) Cai Y., G. Anyatonwu, D. Okuhara, K.-B. Lee, Z. Yu, T. Onoe, C.-L. Mei, Q. Qian, L. Geng, R. Witzgall, B. E. Ehrlich, S. Somlo. Calcium dependence of polycystin-2 channel activity is modulated by phosphorylation at Ser812. J. Biol. Chem. 279: 19987-19995 (2004).   PDF (33) Hidaka S., V. Könecke, L. Osten, R. Witzgall. PIGEA-14, a novel coiled-coil protein affecting the intracellular distribution of polycystin-2. J. Biol. Chem. 279, 35009-35016 (2004). PDF (34) Karcher C., A. Fischer, A. Schweickert, E. Bitzer, S. Horie, R. Witzgall, M. Blum. Lack of a laterality phenotype in Pkd1 knock-out embryos correlates with absence of polycystin-1 in primarycilia. Differentiation 73, 425-432 (2005).   PDF (35) Brown J. H., M.-T. Bihoreau, S. Hoffmann, B. Kränzlin, I. Tychinskaya, N. Obermüller, D. Podlich, S. N. Boehn, P. J. Kaisaki, N. Megel, P. Danoy, R. R. Copley, J. Broxholme, R. Witzgall, M. Lathrop, N. Gretz, D. Gauguier. Missense mutation in sterile a motif of novel protein SamCystin is associated with polycystic kidney disease in (cy/+) rat. J. Am. Soc. Nephrol. 16, 3517-3526 (2005).   PDF (36) Pelucchi B., G. Aguiari, A. Pignatelli, E. Manzati, R. Witzgall, L. del Senno, O. Belluzzi. Nonspecific cation current associated with native polycystin-2 in HEK-293 cells. J. Am. Soc. Nephrol. 17, 388-397 (2006).   PDF (37) Gallagher, A. R., S. Hoffmann, N. Brown, A. Cedzich, S.Meruvu, D. Podlich, Y. Feng, V. Könecke, U. de Vries, H.-P. Hammes, N. Gretz, R. Witzgall. A truncated polycystin-2 protein causes polycystic kidney disease and retinal degeneration in transgenic rats. J. Am. Soc. Nephrol. 17, 2719-2730 (2006).   PDF (38) Banzi M., G. Aguiari, V. Trimi, A. Mangolini, P. Pinton, R. Witzgall, R. Rizzuto, L. del Senno.  Polycystin-1 promotes PKCa-mediated NF-kB activation in kidney cells.  Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 350, 257-262 (2006).   PDF (39) Kurtz L., F. Schweda, C. de Wit, W. Kriz, R. Witzgall, R. Warth, A. Sauter, A. Kurtz, C. Wagner. Lack of connexin 40 causes displacement of renin-producing cells from afferent arterioles to the extraglomerular mesangium. J. Am. Soc. Nephrol. 18, 1103-1111 (2007).  PDF (40) Suleiman H., D. Heudobler, A.-S. Raschta, Y. Zhao, Q. Zhao, I. Hertting, H. Vitzthum, M. J. Moeller, L. B. Holzman, R. Rachel, R. Johnson, H. Westphal, A. Rascle, R. Witzgall. The podocyte-specific inactivation of Lmx1b, Ldb1 and E2a yields new insight into a transcriptional network in podocytes. Dev. Biol. 304, 701-712 (2007).   PDF (41) Endele, S., S. Klein, S. Richter, T. Molter, K. Amann, B. Klanke, R. Witzgall, R. L. Johnson, K. F. Hilgers, A. Winterpacht. Renal phenotype in heterozygous Lmx1b knockout mice (Lmx1b+/-) after unilateral nephrectomy. Transgenic Res. 16, 723-729 (2007).   PDF (42) Aguiari G., V. Trimi, M. Bogo, A. Mangolini, G. Szabadkai, P. Pinton, R. Witzgall, P. C. Harris, P. A. Borea, R. Rizzuto, L. del Senno. Novel role for polycystin-1 in modulating cell proliferation through calcium oscillations in kidney cells. Cell Prolif. 41: 554-573 (2008).   PDF (43) Felekkis K. N., P. Koupepidou, E. Kastanos, R. Witzgall, C.-X. Bai, L. Li, L. Tsiokas, N. Gretz, C. Deltas. Mutant polycystin-2 induces proliferation in primary rat tubular epithelial cells in a STAT-1/p21-independent fashion accompanied instead by alterations in expression of p57KIP2 and Cdk2. BMC Nephrol. 9: 10 (2008).   PDF (44) Rascle A., T. Neumann, A.-S. Raschta, A. Neumann, E. Heining, J. Kastner, R. Witzgall. The LIM-homeodomain transcription factor LMX1B regulates expression of NF-kappa B target genes. Exp. Cell Res. 315: 76-96 (2009).   PDF (45) Schumann, F. H., H. Hoffmeister, M. Schmidt, R. Bader, E. Besl, R. Witzgall, H. R. Kalbitzer. NMR-assignments of a cytosolic domain of the C-terminus of polycystin-2. Biomol. NMR Assign. 3: 141-144 (2009).   PDF (46) Osten L., M. Kubitza, A. R. Gallagher, J. Kastner, H. Olbrich, U. de Vries, F. Kees, B. Lelongt, S. Somlo, H. Omran, R. Witzgall. Doxycycline accelerates renal cyst growth and fibrosis in the pcy/pcy mouse model of type 3 nephronophthisis, a form of recessive polycystic kidney disease. Histochem. Cell Biol. 132: 199-210 (2009).   PDF (47) Schumann F., H. Hoffmeister, R. Bader, M. Schmidt, R. Witzgall, H. R. Kalbitzer.  Ca2+-dependent conformational changes in a C-terminal cytosolic domain of polycystin-2.  J. Biol. Chem. 284: 24372-24383 (2009).   PDF (48) Barro-Soria R., F. Aldehni, J. Almaça, R. Witzgall, R. Schreiber, K. Kunzelmann.  ER-localized bestrophin 1 activates Ca2+-dependent ion channels TMEM16A and SK4 possibly by acting as a counterion channel.  Pflügers Arch. - Eur. J. Physiol. 459: 485-497 (2010).   PDF (49) Behn D., S. Bosk, H. Hoffmeister, A. Janshoff, R. Witzgall, C. Steinem.  Quantifying the interaction of the C-terminal regions of polycystin-2 and polycystin-1 attached to a lipid bilayer by means of QCM.  Biophys. Chem. 150: 47-53 (2010).   PDF (50) Reichold M., A. A. Zdebik, E. Lieberer, M. Rapedius, K. Schmidt, S. Bandulik, C. Sterner, I. Tegtmeier, D. Penton, T. Baukrowitz, S.-A. Hulton, R. Witzgall, B. Ben-Zeev, A. J. Howie, R. Kleta, D. Bockenhauer, R. Warth.  KCNJ10 gene mutations causing EAST syndrome (epilepsy, ataxia, sensorineural deafness, and tubulopathy) disrupt channel function.  Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 107: 14490-14495 (2010).   PDF (51) Hoffmeister H., A.-R. Gallagher, A. Rascle, R. Witzgall.  The human polycystin-2 protein represents an integral membrane protein with six membrane-spanning domains and intracellular N- and C-termini.  Biochem. J. 433: 285-294 (2011).   PDF (52) Tian Y., P. Kongsuphol, M. Hug, J. Ousingsawat, R. Witzgall, R. Schreiber, K. Kunzelmann.  Calmodulin-dependent activation of the epithelial calcium-dependent chloride channel TMEM16A.  FASEB J. 25: 1058-1068 (2011).   PDF  (53) Hoffmeister H., K. Babinger, S. Gürster, A. Cedzich, C. Meese, K. Schadendorf, L. Osten, U. de Vries, A. Rascle, R. Witzgall.  Polycystin-2 takes different routes to the somatic and ciliary plasma membrane.  J. Cell Biol. 192: 631-645 (2011).   PDF  (54) Pollinger K., R. Hennig, M. Breunig, J. Tessmar, A. Ohlmann, E.R. Tamm, R. Witzgall, A. Goepferich. Kidney podocytes as specific targets for cyclo(RGDfC)-modified nanoparticles. Small 8: 3368-3375 (2012).   PDF  (55)    Burghardt T., J. Kastner, H. Suleiman, E. Rivera-Milla, N. Stepanova, C. Lottaz, M. Kubitza, C. A. Böger, S. Schmidt, M. Gorski, U. de Vries, H. Schmidt, I. Hertting, J. Kopp, A. Rascle, M. Moser, I. M. Heid, R. Warth, R. Spang, J. Wegener, C. T. Mierke, C. Englert, R. Witzgall.  LMX1B is essential for the maintenance of differentiated podocytes in adult kidneys.  J. Am. Soc. Nephrol. 24, 1830-1848 (2013).   PDF (56)    Klootwijk, E. D., M. Reichold, A. Helip-Wooley, A. Tolaymat, C. Broeker, S. L. Robinette, J. Reinders, D. Peindl, K. Renner, K. Eberhart, N. Assmann, P. J. Oefner, K. Dettmer, C. Sterner, J. Schroeder, N. Zorger, R. Witzgall, S. W. Reinhold, H. C. Stanescu, D. Bockenhauer, G. Jaureguiberry, H. Courtneidge, A. M. Hall, A. D. Wijeyesekera, E. Holmes, J. K. Nicholson, K. O?Brien, I. Bernardini, D. M. Krasnewich, M. Arcos-Burgos, Y. Izumi, H. Nonoguchi, Y. Jia, J. K. Reddy, M. Ilyas, R. J. Unwin, W. A. Gahl, R. Warth, R. Kleta.  N. Engl. J. Med. 370, 129-138 (2014). PDF Reviews: (1) Bonventre J.V., R. Witzgall.  Kid-1, a kidney transcription factor.  Exp. Nephrol. 3: 159-164 (1995).   PDF (2) Witzgall R.  The proximal tubule phenotype and its disruption in acute renal failure and polycystic kidney disease.  Exp. Nephrol. 7: 15-19 (1999).   PDF (3) Gallagher A. R., N. Obermüller, A. Cedzich, N. Gretz, R. Witzgall.  An ever-expanding story of cyst formation.  Cell Tissue Res. 300: 361-371 (2000).   PDF (4) Gretz N., R. Witzgall, B. Dworniczak.  Tiermodelle mit Zystennieren:  Beispiel für die Bedeutung von Tiermodellen in der Nephrologischen Forschung.  medgen 12: 187-192 (2000). (5) Endlich K., W. Kriz, R. Witzgall.  Update in podocyte biology.  Curr. Opin. Nephrol. Hypertens. 10: 331-340 (2001).   PDF (6) Gallagher A. R., S. Hidaka, N. Gretz, R. Witzgall.  Molecular basis of autosomal-dominant polycystic kidney disease.  Cell. Mol. Life Sci. 59: 682-693 (2002).   PDF (7) Witzgall R. New developments in the field of cystic kidney diseases. Curr. Mol. Med. 5: 455-465 (2005).   PDF (8) Rascle A., H. Suleiman, T. Neumann, R. Witzgall. Role of transcription factors in podocytes. Nephron Exp. Nephrol. 106: e60-e66 (2007).   PDF (9) Babinger, K., R. Witzgall.  Primary cilia and polycystic kidney disease.  Zellbiologie aktuell 36: 8-13 (2010).   PDF  (10) Kunzelmann K., P. Konsuphol, K. Chootip, C. Toledo, J. R. Martins, J. Almaca, Y. Tian, R. Witzgall, J. Ousingsawat, R. Schreiber.  Role of the Ca2+-activated Cl- channels bestrophin and anoctamin in epithelial cells.  Biol. Chem. 392: 125-134 (2011)   PDF  Book chapters: (1) Bonventre J. V., R. Witzgall.  Cellular and molecular mechanisms of ischemic acute renal failure and repair.  Kapitel 2, pp. 15-42.  In: Mechanisms of injury in renal disease and toxicity.  By R. S. Goldstein (ed.).  CRC Press (1994).   PDF (2) Witzgall R., J. V. Bonventre.  Transcription factors in kidney development and renal injury.  Kapitel 37, pp. 535-550.  In: Molecular Nephrology.  By J. V. Bonventre, D. Schlöndorff (ed.).  Marcel-Dekker (1995).   PDF (3) Witzgall R., J. V. Bonventre.  Molecular responses to oxygen deprivation and ischemia.  Kapitel 22, pp. 429-447.  In:  Comprehensive Toxicology. Renal Toxicology.  By R. S. Goldstein (ed.).  Pergamon Press (1997). (4) Witzgall R., TRPP2 channel regulation. Pp. 363-375. In: Handbook of Experimental Pharmacology (vol. 179): Transient receptor potential (TRP) channels. By V. Flockerzi, B. Nilius (ed.). Springer (2007).   PDF (5) Witzgall R. Nail-patella syndrome. Chapter 11, pp. 173-178. In: Molecular and Genetic Basis of Renal Disease. By D. B. Mount, M. R. Pollak (ed.). Saunders Elsevier (2008).   PDF Conference proceedings and published lectures: (1) Witzgall R.  Polycystic kidney disease:  A tale of calcium channels and the actin cytoskeleton.  Ann. Anat.  183: 391-392 (2001).   PDF (2) Witzgall R., B. Kränzlin, N. Gretz, N. Obermüller.  Impaired endocytosis may represent an obstacle to gene therapy in polycystic kidney disease.  Kidney Int.  61 (suppl. 1): S132-S137 (2002).   PDF (3) Witzgall R. Polycystin-2 - an intracellular or plasma membrane channel? Naunyn-Schmiedeberg's Arch. Pharmacol. 371: 342-347 (2005).   PDF Commentaries and editorials: (1) Witzgall R. Are renal proximal tubular epithelial cells constantly prepared for an emergency? Focus on "The proliferation capacity of the renal proximal tubule involves the bulk of differentiated epithelial cells". Am. J. Physiol. Cell Physiol. 294: C1-C3 (2008).   PDF (2) Witzgall R. How are podocytes affected in nail-patella syndrome? Pediatr. Nephrol. 23: 1017-1020 (2008).   PDF Impressum</field>
<field name="important">Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Publications Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Publications Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Fakultäten &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Institute &amp;gt; Anatomie &amp;gt; LS Witzgall &amp;gt; Publications Research   Staff   Ralph Witzgall   Publications   For Students   Links   Map List of publications Original publications: (1) Dummer R., G. Posseckert, F. Nestle, R. Witzgall, M. Burger, J. C. Becker, E. Schäfer, J. Wiede, W. Sebald, G. Burg.  Soluble interleukin-2 receptors inhibit interleukin 2-dependent proliferation and cytotoxicity: Explanation for diminished natural killer cell activity in cutaneous T-cell lymphomas in vivo?  J. Invest. Dermatology 98: 50-54 (1992).   PDF (2) Witzgall R., E. O´Leary, R. Gessner, A. J. Ouellette, J.V. Bonventre.  Kid-1, a putative renal transcription factor: Regulation during ontogeny, and in response to ischemia and toxic injury.  Mol. Cell. Biol. 13: 1933-1942 (1993).   PDF (3) Witzgall R., D. Brown, C. Schwarz, J.V. Bonventre.  Localization of proliferating cell nuclear antigen, vimentin, c-Fos, and clusterin in the post-ischemic kidney. Evidence for a heterogeneous genetic response among nephron segments, and a large pool of mitotically active and dedifferentiated cells.  J. Clin. Invest. 93: 2175-2188 (1994).   PDF (4) Witzgall R., R. Volk, R. Yeung, J.V. Bonventre.  Genomic structure and chromosomal location of the rat gene encoding the zinc finger transcription factor Kid-1.  Genomics 20: 203-209 (1994).   PDF (5) Witzgall R., E. O´Leary, A. Leaf, D. Önaldi, J.V. Bonventre.  The Krüppel-associated box-A (KRAB-A) domain of zinc finger proteins mediates transcriptional repression.  Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 91: 4514-4518 (1994).   PDF (6) Witzgall R., E. O´Leary, J.V. Bonventre.  A mammalian expression vector for the expression of GAL4 fusion proteins with an epitope tag and histidine tail.  Anal. Biochem. 223: 291-298 (1994).   PDF (7) Sapirstein A., R. A. Spech, R. Witzgall, J. V. Bonventre.  Cytosolic phospholipase A2 (PLA2), but not secretory PLA2, potentiates hydrogen peroxide cytotoxicity in kidney epithelial cells. J. Biol. Chem. 271: 21505-21513 (1996).   PDF (8) Kim S.-S., Y.-M. Chen, E. O?Leary, R. Witzgall, M. Vidal, J. V. Bonventre.  A novel member of the RING finger family, KRIP-1, associates with the KRAB-A transcriptional repressor domain of zinc finger proteins.  Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 93: 15299-15304 (1996).   PDF (9) Bonventre J. V., J. M. Kyriakis, R. Spech, R. Witzgall, T. Force.  Phospholipase A2 and lipids as potential modulators of c-Raf-1 kinase.  Am. J. Ther. 3, 287-293 (1996).   PDF (10) Obermüller N., N. Gretz, W. Kriz, F. J. van der Woude, R. F. Reilly, H. Murer, J. Biber, R. Witzgall.  Differentiation and cell polarity during renal cyst formation in the Han:SPRD (cy/+) rat, a model for ADPKD.  Am. J. Physiol. 273: F357-F371 (1997).   PDF (11) Schaub T. P., J. Kartenbeck, J. König, O. Vogel, R. Witzgall, W. Kriz, D. Keppler.  Expression of the conjugate export pump encoded by the mrp2 gene in the apical membrane of kidney proximal tubules.  J. Am. Soc. Nephrol.  8: 1213-1221 (1997).   PDF (12) Obermüller N., B. Kränzlin, R. Verma, N. Gretz, W. Kriz, R. Witzgall.  Renal osmotic stress induced cotransporter:  Expression in the newborn, adult and post-ischemic rat kidney.  Kidney Int.  52: 1584-1592 (1997).   PDF (13) Elser B., W. Kriz, J. V. Bonventre, C. Englert, R. Witzgall.  The Krüppel-associated box (KRAB)-zinc finger protein Kid-1 and the Wilms? tumor protein WT1, two transcriptional repressor proteins, bind to heteroduplex DNA.  J. Biol. Chem.  272: 27908-27912 (1997).   PDF (14) Obermüller N., N. Gretz, W. Kriz, R. F. Reilly, R. Witzgall.  The swelling -activated chloride channel ClC-2, the chloride channel ClC-3, and ClC-5, a chloride channel mutated in kidney stone disease, are expressed in distinct subpopulations of renal epithelial cells.  J. Clin. Invest. 101: 635-642 (1998).   PDF (15) Witzgall R., N. Obermüller, U. Bölitz, J. P. Calvet, B. D. Cowley Jr., C. Walker, W. Kriz, N. Gretz, J. V. Bonventre.  Kid-1 expression is high in differentiated renal proximal tubule cells and suppressed in cyst epithelia.  Am. J. Physiol. 275: F928-F937 (1998).   PDF (16) Huang Z., B. Philippin, E. O?Leary, J. V. Bonventre, W. Kriz, R. Witzgall.  Expression of the transcriptional repressor protein Kid-1 leads to the disintegration of the nucleolus.  J. Biol. Chem. 274, 7640-7648 (1999).   PDF (17) Cai Y., Y. Maeda, A. Cedzich, V. E. Torres, G. Wu, T. Hayashi, T. Mochizuki, J. H. Park, R. Witzgall, S. Somlo.  Identification and characterization of polycystin-2, the PKD2 gene product.  J. Biol. Chem. 274, 28557-28565 (1999).   PDF (18) Obermüller N., A. R. Gallagher, Y. Cai, N. Gassler, N. Gretz, S. Somlo, R. Witzgall.  The rat Pkd2 protein assumes distinct subcellular distributions in different organs.  Am. J. Physiol. 277, F914-F925 (1999).   PDF (19) Gallagher A. R., A. Cedzich, N. Gretz, S. Somlo, R. Witzgall.  The polycystic kidney disease protein PKD2 interacts with Hax-1, a protein associated with the actin cytoskeleton.  Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 97, 4017-4022 (2000).   PDF (20) Obermüller N., B. Kränzlin, W. F. Blum, N. Gretz, R. Witzgall.  An endocytosis defect as a possible cause of proteinuria in polycystic kidney disease.  Am. J. Physiol. Renal Physiol. 280, F244-F253 (2001).   PDF (21) Obermüller N., N. Morente, B. Kränzlin, N. Gretz, R. Witzgall.  A possible role for metalloproteinases in renal cyst development.  Am. J. Physiol. Renal Physiol. 280, F540-F550 (2001).   PDF (22) Gassler, N., F. Autschbach, G. Heuschen, R. Witzgall, H. F. Otto, N. Obermüller.  Expression of clusterin in Crohn?s disease of terminal ileum.  Histol. Histopathol. 16, 755-762 (2001).   PDF (23) Klimaschewski, L., N. Obermüller, R. Witzgall.  Regulation of clusterin expression following spinal cord injury.  Cell Tissue Res. 306, 209-216 (2001).   PDF (24) Koulen P., Y. Cai, L. Geng, Y. Maeda, S. Nishimura, R. Witzgall, B. E. Ehrlich, S. Somlo.  Polycystin-2 is an intracellular calcium release channel.  Nat. Cell Biol. 4, 191-197 (2002).  PDF (25) Wärntges S., B. Friedrich, G. Henke, C. Duranton, P. A. Lang, S. Waldegger, R. Meyermann, D. Kuhl, E. J. Speckmann, N. Obermüller, R. Witzgall, A. F. Mack, H. J. Wagner, C. A. Wagner, S. Bröer, F. Lang.  Cerebral localization and regulation of the cell volume-sensitive serum- and glucocorticoid-dependent kinase SGK1.  Pflügers Arch. - Eur. J. Physiol. 443, 617-624 (2002). PDF (26) Rohr C., J. Prestel, L. Heidet, H. Hosser, W. Kriz, R. L. Johnson, C. Antignac, R. Witzgall.  The LIM-homeodomain transcription factor Lmx1b plays a crucial role in podocytes.  J. Clin. Invest. 109, 1073-1082 (2002).   PDF (27) Obermüller N., Y. Cai, B. Kränzlin, R. B. Thomson, N. Gretz, W. Kriz, S. Somlo, R. Witzgall.  Altered expression pattern of polycystin-2 in acute and chronic renal tubular diseases.  J. Am. Soc. Nephrol. 13, 1855-1864 (2002).   PDF (28) Friedrich B., S. Wärntges, K. Klingel, M. Sauter, R. Kandolf, T. Risler, G. A. Müller, R. Witzgall, W. Kriz, H. J. Gröne, F. Lang. Up-regulation of the human serum and glucocorticoid-dependent kinase 1 in glomerulonephritis. Kidney Blood Press. Res. 25, 303-307 (2002).  PDF (29) Hidaka S., B. Kränzlin, N. Gretz, R. Witzgall. Urinary clusterin levels in the rat correlate with the severity of tubular damage and may help to differentiate between glomerular and tubular injuries. Cell Tissue Res. 310: 289-296 (2002).   PDF (30) Gallagher A. R., K. Schönig, N. Brown, H. Bujard, R. Witzgall. Use of the tetracycline system for inducible protein synthesis in the kidney. J. Am. Soc. Nephrol. 14: 2042-2051 (2003).   PDF (31) Wolf M. T. F., B. E. Mucha, M. Attanasio, I. Zalewski, S. M. Karle, H. P. H. Neumann, N. Rahman, B. Bader, C. A. Baldamus, E. Otto, R. Witzgall, A. Fuchshuber, F. Hildebrandt. Mutations of the Uromodulin gene in MCKD type 2 patients cluster in exon 4, which encodes three EGF-like domains. Kidney Int. 64: 1580-1587 (2003).   PDF (32) Cai Y., G. Anyatonwu, D. Okuhara, K.-B. Lee, Z. Yu, T. Onoe, C.-L. Mei, Q. Qian, L. Geng, R. Witzgall, B. E. Ehrlich, S. Somlo. Calcium dependence of polycystin-2 channel activity is modulated by phosphorylation at Ser812. J. Biol. Chem. 279: 19987-19995 (2004).   PDF (33) Hidaka S., V. Könecke, L. Osten, R. Witzgall. PIGEA-14, a novel coiled-coil protein affecting the intracellular distribution of polycystin-2. J. Biol. Chem. 279, 35009-35016 (2004). PDF (34) Karcher C., A. Fischer, A. Schweickert, E. Bitzer, S. Horie, R. Witzgall, M. Blum. Lack of a laterality phenotype in Pkd1 knock-out embryos correlates with absence of polycystin-1 in primarycilia. Differentiation 73, 425-432 (2005).   PDF (35) Brown J. H., M.-T. Bihoreau, S. Hoffmann, B. Kränzlin, I. Tychinskaya, N. Obermüller, D. Podlich, S. N. Boehn, P. J. Kaisaki, N. Megel, P. Danoy, R. R. Copley, J. Broxholme, R. Witzgall, M. Lathrop, N. Gretz, D. Gauguier. Missense mutation in sterile a motif of novel protein SamCystin is associated with polycystic kidney disease in (cy/+) rat. J. Am. Soc. Nephrol. 16, 3517-3526 (2005).   PDF (36) Pelucchi B., G. Aguiari, A. Pignatelli, E. Manzati, R. Witzgall, L. del Senno, O. Belluzzi. Nonspecific cation current associated with native polycystin-2 in HEK-293 cells. J. Am. Soc. Nephrol. 17, 388-397 (2006).   PDF (37) Gallagher, A. R., S. Hoffmann, N. Brown, A. Cedzich, S.Meruvu, D. Podlich, Y. Feng, V. Könecke, U. de Vries, H.-P. Hammes, N. Gretz, R. Witzgall. A truncated polycystin-2 protein causes polycystic kidney disease and retinal degeneration in transgenic rats. J. Am. Soc. Nephrol. 17, 2719-2730 (2006).   PDF (38) Banzi M., G. Aguiari, V. Trimi, A. Mangolini, P. Pinton, R. Witzgall, R. Rizzuto, L. del Senno.  Polycystin-1 promotes PKCa-mediated NF-kB activation in kidney cells.  Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 350, 257-262 (2006).   PDF (39) Kurtz L., F. Schweda, C. de Wit, W. Kriz, R. Witzgall, R. Warth, A. Sauter, A. Kurtz, C. Wagner. Lack of connexin 40 causes displacement of renin-producing cells from afferent arterioles to the extraglomerular mesangium. J. Am. Soc. Nephrol. 18, 1103-1111 (2007).  PDF (40) Suleiman H., D. Heudobler, A.-S. Raschta, Y. Zhao, Q. Zhao, I. Hertting, H. Vitzthum, M. J. Moeller, L. B. Holzman, R. Rachel, R. Johnson, H. Westphal, A. Rascle, R. Witzgall. The podocyte-specific inactivation of Lmx1b, Ldb1 and E2a yields new insight into a transcriptional network in podocytes. Dev. Biol. 304, 701-712 (2007).   PDF (41) Endele, S., S. Klein, S. Richter, T. Molter, K. Amann, B. Klanke, R. Witzgall, R. L. Johnson, K. F. Hilgers, A. Winterpacht. Renal phenotype in heterozygous Lmx1b knockout mice (Lmx1b+/-) after unilateral nephrectomy. Transgenic Res. 16, 723-729 (2007).   PDF (42) Aguiari G., V. Trimi, M. Bogo, A. Mangolini, G. Szabadkai, P. Pinton, R. Witzgall, P. C. Harris, P. A. Borea, R. Rizzuto, L. del Senno. Novel role for polycystin-1 in modulating cell proliferation through calcium oscillations in kidney cells. Cell Prolif. 41: 554-573 (2008).   PDF (43) Felekkis K. N., P. Koupepidou, E. Kastanos, R. Witzgall, C.-X. Bai, L. Li, L. Tsiokas, N. Gretz, C. Deltas. Mutant polycystin-2 induces proliferation in primary rat tubular epithelial cells in a STAT-1/p21-independent fashion accompanied instead by alterations in expression of p57KIP2 and Cdk2. BMC Nephrol. 9: 10 (2008).   PDF (44) Rascle A., T. Neumann, A.-S. Raschta, A. Neumann, E. Heining, J. Kastner, R. Witzgall. The LIM-homeodomain transcription factor LMX1B regulates expression of NF-kappa B target genes. Exp. Cell Res. 315: 76-96 (2009).   PDF (45) Schumann, F. H., H. Hoffmeister, M. Schmidt, R. Bader, E. Besl, R. Witzgall, H. R. Kalbitzer. NMR-assignments of a cytosolic domain of the C-terminus of polycystin-2. Biomol. NMR Assign. 3: 141-144 (2009).   PDF (46) Osten L., M. Kubitza, A. R. Gallagher, J. Kastner, H. Olbrich, U. de Vries, F. Kees, B. Lelongt, S. Somlo, H. Omran, R. Witzgall. Doxycycline accelerates renal cyst growth and fibrosis in the pcy/pcy mouse model of type 3 nephronophthisis, a form of recessive polycystic kidney disease. Histochem. Cell Biol. 132: 199-210 (2009).   PDF (47) Schumann F., H. Hoffmeister, R. Bader, M. Schmidt, R. Witzgall, H. R. Kalbitzer.  Ca2+-dependent conformational changes in a C-terminal cytosolic domain of polycystin-2.  J. Biol. Chem. 284: 24372-24383 (2009).   PDF (48) Barro-Soria R., F. Aldehni, J. Almaça, R. Witzgall, R. Schreiber, K. Kunzelmann.  ER-localized bestrophin 1 activates Ca2+-dependent ion channels TMEM16A and SK4 possibly by acting as a counterion channel.  Pflügers Arch. - Eur. J. Physiol. 459: 485-497 (2010).   PDF (49) Behn D., S. Bosk, H. Hoffmeister, A. Janshoff, R. Witzgall, C. Steinem.  Quantifying the interaction of the C-terminal regions of polycystin-2 and polycystin-1 attached to a lipid bilayer by means of QCM.  Biophys. Chem. 150: 47-53 (2010).   PDF (50) Reichold M., A. A. Zdebik, E. Lieberer, M. Rapedius, K. Schmidt, S. Bandulik, C. Sterner, I. Tegtmeier, D. Penton, T. Baukrowitz, S.-A. Hulton, R. Witzgall, B. Ben-Zeev, A. J. Howie, R. Kleta, D. Bockenhauer, R. Warth.  KCNJ10 gene mutations causing EAST syndrome (epilepsy, ataxia, sensorineural deafness, and tubulopathy) disrupt channel function.  Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 107: 14490-14495 (2010).   PDF (51) Hoffmeister H., A.-R. Gallagher, A. Rascle, R. Witzgall.  The human polycystin-2 protein represents an integral membrane protein with six membrane-spanning domains and intracellular N- and C-termini.  Biochem. J. 433: 285-294 (2011).   PDF (52) Tian Y., P. Kongsuphol, M. Hug, J. Ousingsawat, R. Witzgall, R. Schreiber, K. Kunzelmann.  Calmodulin-dependent activation of the epithelial calcium-dependent chloride channel TMEM16A.  FASEB J. 25: 1058-1068 (2011).   PDF  (53) Hoffmeister H., K. Babinger, S. Gürster, A. Cedzich, C. Meese, K. Schadendorf, L. Osten, U. de Vries, A. Rascle, R. Witzgall.  Polycystin-2 takes different routes to the somatic and ciliary plasma membrane.  J. Cell Biol. 192: 631-645 (2011).   PDF  (54) Pollinger K., R. Hennig, M. Breunig, J. Tessmar, A. Ohlmann, E.R. Tamm, R. Witzgall, A. Goepferich. Kidney podocytes as specific targets for cyclo(RGDfC)-modified nanoparticles. Small 8: 3368-3375 (2012).   PDF  (55)    Burghardt T., J. Kastner, H. Suleiman, E. Rivera-Milla, N. Stepanova, C. Lottaz, M. Kubitza, C. A. Böger, S. Schmidt, M. Gorski, U. de Vries, H. Schmidt, I. Hertting, J. Kopp, A. Rascle, M. Moser, I. M. Heid, R. Warth, R. Spang, J. Wegener, C. T. Mierke, C. Englert, R. Witzgall.  LMX1B is essential for the maintenance of differentiated podocytes in adult kidneys.  J. Am. Soc. Nephrol. 24, 1830-1848 (2013).   PDF (56)    Klootwijk, E. D., M. Reichold, A. Helip-Wooley, A. Tolaymat, C. Broeker, S. L. Robinette, J. Reinders, D. Peindl, K. Renner, K. Eberhart, N. Assmann, P. J. Oefner, K. Dettmer, C. Sterner, J. Schroeder, N. Zorger, R. Witzgall, S. W. Reinhold, H. C. Stanescu, D. Bockenhauer, G. Jaureguiberry, H. Courtneidge, A. M. Hall, A. D. Wijeyesekera, E. Holmes, J. K. Nicholson, K. O?Brien, I. Bernardini, D. M. Krasnewich, M. Arcos-Burgos, Y. Izumi, H. Nonoguchi, Y. Jia, J. K. Reddy, M. Ilyas, R. J. Unwin, W. A. Gahl, R. Warth, R. Kleta.  N. Engl. J. Med. 370, 129-138 (2014). PDF Reviews: (1) Bonventre J.V., R. Witzgall.  Kid-1, a kidney transcription factor.  Exp. Nephrol. 3: 159-164 (1995).   PDF (2) Witzgall R.  The proximal tubule phenotype and its disruption in acute renal failure and polycystic kidney disease.  Exp. Nephrol. 7: 15-19 (1999).   PDF (3) Gallagher A. R., N. Obermüller, A. Cedzich, N. Gretz, R. Witzgall.  An ever-expanding story of cyst formation.  Cell Tissue Res. 300: 361-371 (2000).   PDF (4) Gretz N., R. Witzgall, B. Dworniczak.  Tiermodelle mit Zystennieren:  Beispiel für die Bedeutung von Tiermodellen in der Nephrologischen Forschung.  medgen 12: 187-192 (2000). (5) Endlich K., W. Kriz, R. Witzgall.  Update in podocyte biology.  Curr. Opin. Nephrol. Hypertens. 10: 331-340 (2001).   PDF (6) Gallagher A. R., S. Hidaka, N. Gretz, R. Witzgall.  Molecular basis of autosomal-dominant polycystic kidney disease.  Cell. Mol. Life Sci. 59: 682-693 (2002).   PDF (7) Witzgall R. New developments in the field of cystic kidney diseases. Curr. Mol. Med. 5: 455-465 (2005).   PDF (8) Rascle A., H. Suleiman, T. Neumann, R. Witzgall. Role of transcription factors in podocytes. Nephron Exp. Nephrol. 106: e60-e66 (2007).   PDF (9) Babinger, K., R. Witzgall.  Primary cilia and polycystic kidney disease.  Zellbiologie aktuell 36: 8-13 (2010).   PDF  (10) Kunzelmann K., P. Konsuphol, K. Chootip, C. Toledo, J. R. Martins, J. Almaca, Y. Tian, R. Witzgall, J. Ousingsawat, R. Schreiber.  Role of the Ca2+-activated Cl- channels bestrophin and anoctamin in epithelial cells.  Biol. Chem. 392: 125-134 (2011)   PDF  Book chapters: (1) Bonventre J. V., R. Witzgall.  Cellular and molecular mechanisms of ischemic acute renal failure and repair.  Kapitel 2, pp. 15-42.  In: Mechanisms of injury in renal disease and toxicity.  By R. S. Goldstein (ed.).  CRC Press (1994).   PDF (2) Witzgall R., J. V. Bonventre.  Transcription factors in kidney development and renal injury.  Kapitel 37, pp. 535-550.  In: Molecular Nephrology.  By J. V. Bonventre, D. Schlöndorff (ed.).  Marcel-Dekker (1995).   PDF (3) Witzgall R., J. V. Bonventre.  Molecular responses to oxygen deprivation and ischemia.  Kapitel 22, pp. 429-447.  In:  Comprehensive Toxicology. Renal Toxicology.  By R. S. Goldstein (ed.).  Pergamon Press (1997). (4) Witzgall R., TRPP2 channel regulation. Pp. 363-375. In: Handbook of Experimental Pharmacology (vol. 179): Transient receptor potential (TRP) channels. By V. Flockerzi, B. Nilius (ed.). Springer (2007).   PDF (5) Witzgall R. Nail-patella syndrome. Chapter 11, pp. 173-178. In: Molecular and Genetic Basis of Renal Disease. By D. B. Mount, M. R. Pollak (ed.). Saunders Elsevier (2008).   PDF Conference proceedings and published lectures: (1) Witzgall R.  Polycystic kidney disease:  A tale of calcium channels and the actin cytoskeleton.  Ann. Anat.  183: 391-392 (2001).   PDF (2) Witzgall R., B. Kränzlin, N. Gretz, N. Obermüller.  Impaired endocytosis may represent an obstacle to gene therapy in polycystic kidney disease.  Kidney Int.  61 (suppl. 1): S132-S137 (2002).   PDF (3) Witzgall R. Polycystin-2 - an intracellular or plasma membrane channel? Naunyn-Schmiedeberg's Arch. Pharmacol. 371: 342-347 (2005).   PDF Commentaries and editorials: (1) Witzgall R. Are renal proximal tubular epithelial cells constantly prepared for an emergency? Focus on "The proliferation capacity of the renal proximal tubule involves the bulk of differentiated epithelial cells". Am. J. Physiol. Cell Physiol. 294: C1-C3 (2008).   PDF (2) Witzgall R. How are podocytes affected in nail-patella syndrome? Pediatr. Nephrol. 23: 1017-1020 (2008).   PDF Impressum</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Witzgall/English/staff.html</field>
<field name="title">Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Staff</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Witzgall/English/staff.html</field>
<field name="content">? Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Staff Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Fakultäten &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Institute &amp;gt; Anatomie &amp;gt; LS Witzgall &amp;gt; Staff Research   Staff   Ralph Witzgall   Publications   For Students   Links   Map Members of the laboratory Dr. Karin Babinger Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2873 Vkl 3.1.05 Karin.Babinger@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Susanne Baumgarten Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2878 Vkl 3.1.06 Susanne.Baumgarten@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Tillmann Burghardt Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2873 Vkl 3.1.05 Tillmann.Burghardt@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Melanie Grosch Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2878 Vkl 3.1.08 Melanie.Grosch@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Kerstin Herrmann Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2882 Vkl 3.1.28 Kerstin.Herrmann@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Marion Kubitza Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2882 Vkl 3.1.28 Marion.Kubitza@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Edeltraud Lautenschlager Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2820 Vkl 3.1.04 Sekretariat.Witzgall@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Olga Maier Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2882 Vkl 3.1.28 Olga.Maier@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Christine Meese Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2857 Vkl 3.1.01 Christine.Meese@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Larissa Osten Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2861 Vkl 3.1.02 Larissa.Osten@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Benjamin Salecker Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2837 Vkl 3.1.29 Benjamin.Salecker@biologie.uni-regensburg.de Karin Schadendorf Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2882 Vkl 3.1.28 Karin.Schadendorf@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Kerstin Schmidt Tel. Raum E-mail ++49 941-943 2882 Vkl 3.1.28 Kerstin1.Schmidt@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Helga Schmidt Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2882 Vkl 3.1.28 Helga.Schmidt@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Denise Schmied Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2878 Vkl 3.1.06 Denise.Schmied@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Markus Setzer Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2882 Vkl 3.1.28 Markus.Setzer@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Natalya Stepanova Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2878 Vkl 3.1.06 Natalya.Stepanova@vkl.uni-regensburg.de PD Dr. Kálmán Szabó Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2864 Vkl 3.1.08 Kalman.Szabo@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Uwe de Vries Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2864 Vkl 3.1.08 Uwe.Devries@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Melanie Zaparty Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2873 Vkl 3.1.05 Melanie.Zaparty@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Yulia Zaytseva Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2882 Vkl 3.1.28 Yulia.Zaytseva@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Photography and graphic design Anita Hecht Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2884 Vkl 3.1.07 Anita.Hecht@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Ton Maurer Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2884 Vkl 3.1.07 Anthonie.Maurer@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Antje Zenker Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2884 Vkl 3.1.07 Antje.Zenker@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Prosectors Richard Niedermeier Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2910 Vkl 3.1.04 Richard.Niedermeier@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Andreas Rieger Tel. Room ++49 941-943 2910 Vkl 3.1.04 Markus Schöpperl Tel. Room ++49 941-943 2910 Vkl 3.1.04 General services (glassware, autoclaves) Ludwig Utz Tel. Room ++49 941-943 2897 Vkl 5.1.13 Cäcilia Vitzthum Tel. Room ++49 941-943 2897 Vkl 5.1.13 Impressum</field>
<field name="important">? Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Staff Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Fakultäten &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Institute &amp;gt; Anatomie &amp;gt; LS Witzgall &amp;gt; Staff Research   Staff   Ralph Witzgall   Publications   For Students   Links   Map Members of the laboratory Dr. Karin Babinger Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2873 Vkl 3.1.05 Karin.Babinger@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Susanne Baumgarten Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2878 Vkl 3.1.06 Susanne.Baumgarten@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Tillmann Burghardt Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2873 Vkl 3.1.05 Tillmann.Burghardt@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Melanie Grosch Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2878 Vkl 3.1.08 Melanie.Grosch@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Kerstin Herrmann Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2882 Vkl 3.1.28 Kerstin.Herrmann@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Marion Kubitza Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2882 Vkl 3.1.28 Marion.Kubitza@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Edeltraud Lautenschlager Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2820 Vkl 3.1.04 Sekretariat.Witzgall@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Olga Maier Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2882 Vkl 3.1.28 Olga.Maier@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Christine Meese Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2857 Vkl 3.1.01 Christine.Meese@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Larissa Osten Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2861 Vkl 3.1.02 Larissa.Osten@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Benjamin Salecker Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2837 Vkl 3.1.29 Benjamin.Salecker@biologie.uni-regensburg.de Karin Schadendorf Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2882 Vkl 3.1.28 Karin.Schadendorf@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Kerstin Schmidt Tel. Raum E-mail ++49 941-943 2882 Vkl 3.1.28 Kerstin1.Schmidt@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Helga Schmidt Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2882 Vkl 3.1.28 Helga.Schmidt@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Denise Schmied Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2878 Vkl 3.1.06 Denise.Schmied@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Markus Setzer Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2882 Vkl 3.1.28 Markus.Setzer@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Natalya Stepanova Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2878 Vkl 3.1.06 Natalya.Stepanova@vkl.uni-regensburg.de PD Dr. Kálmán Szabó Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2864 Vkl 3.1.08 Kalman.Szabo@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Uwe de Vries Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2864 Vkl 3.1.08 Uwe.Devries@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Dr. Melanie Zaparty Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2873 Vkl 3.1.05 Melanie.Zaparty@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Yulia Zaytseva Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2882 Vkl 3.1.28 Yulia.Zaytseva@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Photography and graphic design Anita Hecht Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2884 Vkl 3.1.07 Anita.Hecht@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Ton Maurer Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2884 Vkl 3.1.07 Anthonie.Maurer@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Antje Zenker Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2884 Vkl 3.1.07 Antje.Zenker@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Prosectors Richard Niedermeier Tel. Room E-mail ++49 941-943 2910 Vkl 3.1.04 Richard.Niedermeier@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Andreas Rieger Tel. Room ++49 941-943 2910 Vkl 3.1.04 Markus Schöpperl Tel. Room ++49 941-943 2910 Vkl 3.1.04 General services (glassware, autoclaves) Ludwig Utz Tel. Room ++49 941-943 2897 Vkl 5.1.13 Cäcilia Vitzthum Tel. Room ++49 941-943 2897 Vkl 5.1.13 Impressum</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Witzgall/English/students.html</field>
<field name="title">Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Students</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Witzgall/English/students.html</field>
<field name="content">Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Students Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Students Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Fakultäten &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Institute &amp;gt; Anatomie &amp;gt; LS Witzgall &amp;gt; Students Research   Staff   Ralph Witzgall   Publications   For Students   Links   Map Information for students Lecture notes (pdf-files) Sommersemester 2014 Wintersemester 2013/14 2. Semester, Histologie 4. Semester, Neuroanatomie - Zellbiologie - Epithel - Bindegewebe - Muskulatur - Auge - Ohr - Geruch - Poster (Prof. Krahn) - Letzte Fragen - Immunologie - Respirationstrakt - Verdauungstrakt Lectures - courses - exams Histological textbooks These remarks are intended to serve as a guidline for students taking a histology class, in particular I want to discuss the topic of textbooks. It is only natural that every teacher will recommend different textbooks and that every student (rightfully so) will develop its own  preferences. Therefore the textbooks listed below should only be understood as a rough guide. I also want to emphasize that the frequent and attentive (drawings!) work at the microscope cannot be replaced by any textbook. The final exam at the microscope not only deals with recognizing structures and describing them, but it also requires a functional understanding.  Both aspects of the exam are intimately connected with each other. Please keep in mind the saying attributed to Louis Pasteur "Chance favours only the prepared mind?, so anticipating what to expect does help! To look something up Because they contain so many facts, the following textbooks are mostly recommended for selective reading. ? Alberts/Bray/Lewis/Raff/Roberts/Watson: Molecular biology of the cell. Excellent but very extensive textbook for molecular and cell biology. ? Alberts/Bray/Johnson/Lewis/Raff/Roberts/Walter: Textbook of molecular biology. Somewhat slimmed-down version of the textbook just mentioned. ? Benninghoff: Anatomie (in 2 volumes). A large textbook on gross anatomy and histology as well as on those aspects of molecular and cell biology, which are relevant in this context.  A new edition of the first volume has appeared at the end of 2002, a new edition of the second volume at the end of 2003. Textbooks to work through ? Bucher/Wartenberg: Cytologie, Histologie und mikroskopische Anatomie des Menschen. ? Hees/Sinowatz: Histologie. Kurzlehrbuch für die Zellbiologie und Histologie. ? Junqueira/Carneiro: Histologie. In my opinion at least so far the standard textbook in histology. Recently a new edition with a new concept has come out, which has received a mixed reception. ? Schmidt/Unsicker: Lehrbuch Vorklinik.  A textbook in four volumes following a novel philosophy insofar as anatomy (gross anatomy, histology and neuroanatomy), biochemistry and physiology are discussed together in one chapter.  The first edition has come out in 2003, therefore only very limited experience is available. ? Stevens/Lowe: Histologie des Menschen. A combination of atlas and textbook with clinical aspects, but somewhat limited basic facts. ? Welsch:  Lehrbuch Histologie.  This new textbook has come out at the end of 2002.  Well written with many excellent histological pictures and diagrams! Atlas ? Kühnel: Taschenatlas der Zytologie, Histologie und mikroskopischen Anatomie. Contains text on one page and figures on the facing page. Compact and well-liked when working at the microscope. ? Ross/Rohen/Lütjen-Drecoll/Kaye: Atlas der Histologie. Simular concept to that of the Kühnel. Gross anatomy ? Benninghoff:  A large textbook on gross anatomy and histology as well as on those aspects of molecular and cell biology, which are relevant in this context.  A new edition of the first volume has appeared at the end of 2002, a new edition of the second volume at the end of 2003. ? Feneis:  Great to look something up, but not suitable for studying. ? Kahle/Leonhardt/Platzer:  Good concept with text on one page and schematic diagrams on the facing page.  Convenient for qick repetitions and also as a start. ? Netter:  Competing atlas to the Sobotta - it is almost a matter of taste whether the Netter or Sobotta are better. ? Rohen:  Photographic atlas; limited own experience. ? Schiebler:  No own experience. ? Schmidt/Unsicker: Lehrbuch Vorklinik.  A textbook in four volumes following a novel philosophy insofar as anatomy (gross anatomy, histology and neuroanatomy), biochemistry and physiology are discussed together in one chapter.  The first edition has come out in 2003, therefore only very limited experience is available. ? Sobotta:  Perhaps still the best atlas. ? Waldeyer:  A well-rounded textbook, not as voluminous as the Benninghoff and therefore easier to handle. Impressum</field>
<field name="important">Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Students Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Students Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Fakultäten &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Institute &amp;gt; Anatomie &amp;gt; LS Witzgall &amp;gt; Students Research   Staff   Ralph Witzgall   Publications   For Students   Links   Map Information for students Lecture notes (pdf-files) Sommersemester 2014 Wintersemester 2013/14 2. Semester, Histologie 4. Semester, Neuroanatomie - Zellbiologie - Epithel - Bindegewebe - Muskulatur - Auge - Ohr - Geruch - Poster (Prof. Krahn) - Letzte Fragen - Immunologie - Respirationstrakt - Verdauungstrakt Lectures - courses - exams Histological textbooks These remarks are intended to serve as a guidline for students taking a histology class, in particular I want to discuss the topic of textbooks. It is only natural that every teacher will recommend different textbooks and that every student (rightfully so) will develop its own  preferences. Therefore the textbooks listed below should only be understood as a rough guide. I also want to emphasize that the frequent and attentive (drawings!) work at the microscope cannot be replaced by any textbook. The final exam at the microscope not only deals with recognizing structures and describing them, but it also requires a functional understanding.  Both aspects of the exam are intimately connected with each other. Please keep in mind the saying attributed to Louis Pasteur "Chance favours only the prepared mind?, so anticipating what to expect does help! To look something up Because they contain so many facts, the following textbooks are mostly recommended for selective reading. ? Alberts/Bray/Lewis/Raff/Roberts/Watson: Molecular biology of the cell. Excellent but very extensive textbook for molecular and cell biology. ? Alberts/Bray/Johnson/Lewis/Raff/Roberts/Walter: Textbook of molecular biology. Somewhat slimmed-down version of the textbook just mentioned. ? Benninghoff: Anatomie (in 2 volumes). A large textbook on gross anatomy and histology as well as on those aspects of molecular and cell biology, which are relevant in this context.  A new edition of the first volume has appeared at the end of 2002, a new edition of the second volume at the end of 2003. Textbooks to work through ? Bucher/Wartenberg: Cytologie, Histologie und mikroskopische Anatomie des Menschen. ? Hees/Sinowatz: Histologie. Kurzlehrbuch für die Zellbiologie und Histologie. ? Junqueira/Carneiro: Histologie. In my opinion at least so far the standard textbook in histology. Recently a new edition with a new concept has come out, which has received a mixed reception. ? Schmidt/Unsicker: Lehrbuch Vorklinik.  A textbook in four volumes following a novel philosophy insofar as anatomy (gross anatomy, histology and neuroanatomy), biochemistry and physiology are discussed together in one chapter.  The first edition has come out in 2003, therefore only very limited experience is available. ? Stevens/Lowe: Histologie des Menschen. A combination of atlas and textbook with clinical aspects, but somewhat limited basic facts. ? Welsch:  Lehrbuch Histologie.  This new textbook has come out at the end of 2002.  Well written with many excellent histological pictures and diagrams! Atlas ? Kühnel: Taschenatlas der Zytologie, Histologie und mikroskopischen Anatomie. Contains text on one page and figures on the facing page. Compact and well-liked when working at the microscope. ? Ross/Rohen/Lütjen-Drecoll/Kaye: Atlas der Histologie. Simular concept to that of the Kühnel. Gross anatomy ? Benninghoff:  A large textbook on gross anatomy and histology as well as on those aspects of molecular and cell biology, which are relevant in this context.  A new edition of the first volume has appeared at the end of 2002, a new edition of the second volume at the end of 2003. ? Feneis:  Great to look something up, but not suitable for studying. ? Kahle/Leonhardt/Platzer:  Good concept with text on one page and schematic diagrams on the facing page.  Convenient for qick repetitions and also as a start. ? Netter:  Competing atlas to the Sobotta - it is almost a matter of taste whether the Netter or Sobotta are better. ? Rohen:  Photographic atlas; limited own experience. ? Schiebler:  No own experience. ? Schmidt/Unsicker: Lehrbuch Vorklinik.  A textbook in four volumes following a novel philosophy insofar as anatomy (gross anatomy, histology and neuroanatomy), biochemistry and physiology are discussed together in one chapter.  The first edition has come out in 2003, therefore only very limited experience is available. ? Sobotta:  Perhaps still the best atlas. ? Waldeyer:  A well-rounded textbook, not as voluminous as the Benninghoff and therefore easier to handle. Impressum</field>
</doc>
<doc>
<field name="id">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Witzgall/English/witzgall_eng.html</field>
<field name="title">Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Curriculum vitae</field>
<field name="url">http://www.biologie.uni-regensburg.de/Anatomie/Witzgall/English/witzgall_eng.html</field>
<field name="content">? Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Curriculum vitae Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Fakultäten &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Institute &amp;gt; Anatomie &amp;gt; LS Witzgall &amp;gt; Curriculum vitae Research   Staff   Ralph Witzgall   Publications   For Students   Links   Map Prof. Dr. Ralph Witzgall Institute for Molecular and Cellular Anatomy University of Regensburg Universitätsstr. 31 93053 Regensburg Germany Telephone Office ++49 (0)941 943-2820 Telephone Prof. Witzgall ++49 (0)941 943-2821 Fax ++49 (0)941 943-2868 e-mail Office Sekretariat.Witzgall@vkl.uni-regensburg.de e-mail Prof. Witzgall Ralph.Witzgall@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Curriculum vitae 1983 - 1985 Attending Medical School at the University of Regensburg 1985 - 1990 Attending Medical School at the University of Würzburg 1989 Visiting student at the University of Wisconsin in Madison, at the Medical College of Virginia in Richmond and the Massachusetts General Hospital of the Harvard Medical School in Boston, USA  1990 Completion of the MD thesis at the Institute for Physiological Chemistry, University of Würzburg 1990 - 1994 Fellowship at the Massachusetts General Hospital, Harvard Medical School in the laboratory of Prof. Dr. Joseph Bonventre 1994 Appointment as ?Instructor in Medicine? at the Harvard Medical School 1994 - 2002 Group leader at the Institute for Anatomy and Cell Biology, University of Heidelberg 1999 Appointment as Assistant Professor 2002 - Chairman and Full Professor at the Institute for Molecular and Cellular Anatomy,  University of Regensburg Impressum</field>
<field name="important">? Prof. Dr. Witzgall - Curriculum vitae Universität Regensburg &amp;gt; Fakultäten &amp;gt; Biologie und Vkl &amp;gt; Institute &amp;gt; Anatomie &amp;gt; LS Witzgall &amp;gt; Curriculum vitae Research   Staff   Ralph Witzgall   Publications   For Students   Links   Map Prof. Dr. Ralph Witzgall Institute for Molecular and Cellular Anatomy University of Regensburg Universitätsstr. 31 93053 Regensburg Germany Telephone Office ++49 (0)941 943-2820 Telephone Prof. Witzgall ++49 (0)941 943-2821 Fax ++49 (0)941 943-2868 e-mail Office Sekretariat.Witzgall@vkl.uni-regensburg.de e-mail Prof. Witzgall Ralph.Witzgall@vkl.uni-regensburg.de Curriculum vitae 1983 - 1985 Attending Medical School at the University of Regensburg 1985 - 1990 Attending Medical School at the University of Würzburg 1989 Visiting student at the University of Wisconsin in Madison, at the Medical College of Virginia in Richmond and the Massachusetts General Hospital of the Harvard Medical School in Boston, USA  1990 Completion of the MD thesis at the Institute for Physiological Chemistry, University of Würzburg 1990 - 1994 Fellowship at the Massachusetts General Hospital, Harvard Medical School in the laboratory of Prof. Dr. Joseph Bonventre 1994 Appointment as ?Instructor in Medicine? at the Harvard Medical School 1994 - 2002 Group leader at the Institute for Anatomy and Cell Biology, University of Heidelberg 1999 Appointment as Assistant Professor 2002 - Chairman and Full Professor at the Institute for Molecular and Cellular Anatomy,  University of Regensburg Impressum</field>
</doc>

</add>